<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="1KI" style="id">The First Book of the Kings</book>
    <para style="mt">The First Book of the Kings</para>
    <chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Adonijah Presumes to Be King</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now King David was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:1</char></note>old, advanced in years; and they put covers on him, but he could not get warm. <verse number="2" style="v" />Therefore his servants said to him, “Let a young woman, a virgin, be sought for our lord the king, and let her stand before the king, and let her care for him; and let her lie in your bosom, that our lord the king may be warm.” <verse number="3" style="v" />So they sought for a lovely young woman throughout all the territory of Israel, and found <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:17</char></note>Abishag the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:18; 1 Sam. 28:4</char></note>Shunammite, and brought her to the king. <verse number="4" style="v" />The young woman <char style="it">was</char> very lovely; and she cared for the king, and served him; but the king did not know her.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 3:4</char></note>Adonijah the son of Haggith exalted himself, saying, “I will be king”; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 15:1</char></note>he prepared for himself chariots and horsemen, and fifty men to run before him. <verse number="6" style="v" />(And his father had not rebuked him at any time by saying, “Why have you done so?” He <char style="it">was</char> also very good-looking. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 3:3, 4; 1 Chr. 3:2</char></note><char style="it">His</char> <char style="it">mother</char> had borne him after Absalom.) <verse number="7" style="v" />Then he conferred with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 11:6</char></note>Joab the son of Zeruiah and with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:25</char></note>Abiathar the priest, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:22, 28</char></note>they followed and helped Adonijah. <verse number="8" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:35</char></note>Zadok the priest, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:25; 2 Sam. 8:18</char></note>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 12:1</char></note>Nathan the prophet, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:18</char></note>Shimei, Rei, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 23:8</char></note>the mighty men who <char style="it">belonged</char> to David were not with Adonijah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And Adonijah sacrificed sheep and oxen and fattened cattle by the stone of Zoheleth, which <char style="it">is</char> by <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:7; 18:16; 2 Sam. 17:17</char></note>En Rogel; he also invited all his brothers, the king’s sons, and all the men of Judah, the king’s servants. <verse number="10" style="v" />But he did not invite Nathan the prophet, Benaiah, the mighty men, or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 12:24</char></note>Solomon his brother.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So Nathan spoke to Bathsheba the mother of Solomon, saying, “Have you not heard that Adonijah the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 3:4</char></note>Haggith has become king, and David our lord does not know <char style="it">it?</char> <verse number="12" style="v" />Come, please, let me now give you advice, that you may save your own life and the life of your son Solomon. <verse number="13" style="v" />Go immediately to King David and say to him, ‘Did you not, my lord, O king, swear to your maidservant, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:30; 1 Chr. 22:9–13</char></note>“Assuredly your son Solomon shall reign after me, and he shall sit on my throne“? Why then has Adonijah become king?’ <verse number="14" style="v" />Then, while you are still talking there with the king, I also will come in after you and confirm your words.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />So Bathsheba went into the chamber to the king. (Now the king was very old, and Abishag the Shunammite was serving the king.) <verse number="16" style="v" />And Bathsheba bowed and did homage to the king. Then the king said, “What is your wish?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then she said to him, “My lord, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:13, 30</char></note>you swore by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God to your maidservant, <char style="it">saying,</char> ‘Assuredly Solomon your son shall reign after me, and he shall sit on my throne.’ <verse number="18" style="v" />So now, look! Adonijah has become king; and now, my lord the king, you do not know about <char style="it">it.</char> <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:7–9, 25</char></note>He has sacrificed oxen and fattened cattle and sheep in abundance, and has invited all the sons of the king, Abiathar the priest, and Joab the commander of the army; but Solomon your servant he has not invited. <verse number="20" style="v" />And as for you, my lord, O king, the eyes of all Israel <char style="it">are</char> on you, that you should tell them who will sit on the throne of my lord the king after him. <verse number="21" style="v" />Otherwise it will happen, when my lord the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:16; 2 Sam. 7:12; 1 Kin. 2:10</char></note>rests with his fathers, that I and my son Solomon will be counted as offenders.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And just then, while she was still talking with the king, Nathan the prophet also came in. <verse number="23" style="v" />So they told the king, saying, “Here is Nathan the prophet.” And when he came in before the king, he bowed down before the king with his face to the ground. <verse number="24" style="v" />And Nathan said, “My lord, O king, have you said, ‘Adonijah shall reign after me, and he shall sit on my throne’? <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:9, 19</char></note>For he has gone down today, and has sacrificed oxen and fattened cattle and sheep in abundance, and has invited all the king’s sons, and the commanders of the army, and Abiathar the priest; and look! They are eating and drinking before him; and they say, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 10:24</char></note>‘<char style="it">Long</char> live King Adonijah!’ <verse number="26" style="v" />But he has not invited me—me your servant—nor Zadok the priest, nor Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, nor your servant Solomon. <verse number="27" style="v" />Has this thing been done by my lord the king, and you have not told your servant who should sit on the throne of my lord the king after him?”</para>
	<para style="s">David Proclaims Solomon King</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Then King David answered and said, “Call Bathsheba to me.” So she came into the king’s presence and stood before the king. <verse number="29" style="v" />And the king took an oath and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 4:9; 12:5</char></note>“<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, who has redeemed my life from every distress, <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:13, 17</char></note>just as I swore to you by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, saying, ‘Assuredly Solomon your son shall be king after me, and he shall sit on my throne in my place,’ so I certainly will do this day.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Then Bathsheba bowed with <char style="it">her</char> face to the earth, and paid homage to the king, and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 2:3; Dan. 2:4; 3:9</char></note>“Let my lord King David live forever!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />And King David said, “Call to me Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada.” So they came before the king. <verse number="33" style="v" />The king also said to them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:6</char></note>“Take with you the servants of your lord, and have Solomon my son ride on my own <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 6:8</char></note>mule, and take him down to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:30; 33:14</char></note>Gihon. <verse number="34" style="v" />There let Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 10:1; 16:3, 12; 2 Sam. 2:4; 5:3; 1 Kin. 19:16; 2 Kin. 9:3; 11:12; 1 Chr. 29:22</char></note>anoint him king over Israel; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 15:10; 2 Kin. 9:13; 11:14</char></note>blow the horn, and say, ‘<char style="it">Long</char> live King Solomon!’ <verse number="35" style="v" />Then you shall come up after him, and he shall come and sit on my throne, and he shall be king in my place. For I have appointed him to be ruler over Israel and Judah.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />Benaiah the son of Jehoiada answered the king and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 28:6</char></note>“Amen! May the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of my lord the king say so <char style="it">too.</char> <verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:5, 17; 1 Sam. 20:13</char></note>As the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has been with my lord the king, even so may He be with Solomon, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:47</char></note>make his throne greater than the throne of my lord King David.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />So Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:18; 23:20–23</char></note>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:7; 1 Chr. 18:17</char></note>Cherethites, and the Pelethites went down and had Solomon ride on King David’s mule, and took him to Gihon. <verse number="39" style="v" />Then Zadok the priest took a horn of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:23, 25, 32; Ps. 89:20</char></note>oil from the tabernacle and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 29:22</char></note>anointed Solomon. And they blew the horn, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 10:24</char></note>and all the people said, <char style="it">“Long</char> live King Solomon!” <verse number="40" style="v" />And all the people went up after him; and the people played the flutes and rejoiced with great joy, so that the earth <char style="it">seemed</char> <char style="it">to</char> split with their sound.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />Now Adonijah and all the guests who <char style="it">were</char> with him heard <char style="it">it</char> as they finished eating. And when Joab heard the sound of the horn, he said, “Why <char style="it">is</char> the city in such a noisy uproar?” <verse number="42" style="v" />While he was still speaking, there came <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 17:17, 20</char></note>Jonathan, the son of Abiathar the priest. And Adonijah said to him, “Come in, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 18:27</char></note>you <char style="it">are</char> a prominent man, and bring good news.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" />Then Jonathan answered and said to Adonijah, “No! Our lord King David has made Solomon king. <verse number="44" style="v" />The king has sent with him Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the Cherethites, and the Pelethites; and they have made him ride on the king’s mule. <verse number="45" style="v" />So Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet have anointed him king at Gihon; and they have gone up from there rejoicing, so that the city is in an uproar. This <char style="it">is</char> the noise that you have heard. <verse number="46" style="v" />Also Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:12; 1 Chr. 29:23</char></note>sits on the throne of the kingdom. <verse number="47" style="v" />And moreover the king’s servants have gone to bless our lord King David, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:37</char></note>‘May God make the name of Solomon better than your name, and may He make his throne greater than your throne.’ <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 47:31</char></note>Then the king bowed himself on the bed. <verse number="48" style="v" />Also the king said thus, ‘Blessed <char style="it">be</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, who has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:6; (Ps. 132:11, 12)</char></note>given <char style="it">one</char> to sit on my throne this day, while my eyes see <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12</char></note><char style="it">it!</char>’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" />So all the guests who were with Adonijah were afraid, and arose, and each one went his way.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" />Now Adonijah was afraid of Solomon; so he arose, and went and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:2; 30:10; 1 Kin. 2:28</char></note>took hold of the horns of the altar. <verse number="51" style="v" />And it was told Solomon, saying, “Indeed Adonijah is afraid of King Solomon; for look, he has taken hold of the horns of the altar, saying, ‘Let King Solomon swear to me today that he will not put his servant to death with the sword.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v" />Then Solomon said, “If he proves himself a worthy man, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 14:45; 2 Sam. 14:11; Acts 27:34</char></note>not one hair of him shall fall to the earth; but if wickedness is found in him, he shall die.” <verse number="53" style="v" />So King Solomon sent them to bring him down from the altar. And he came and fell down before King Solomon; and Solomon said to him, “Go to your house.”</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="s">David’s Instructions to Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 47:29; Deut. 31:14</char></note>the days of David drew near that he should die, and he charged Solomon his son, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 23:14</char></note>“I go the way of all the earth; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:7, 23; 1 Chr. 22:13</char></note>be strong, therefore, and prove yourself a man. <verse number="3" style="v" />And keep the charge of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God: to walk in His ways, to keep His statutes, His commandments, His judgments, and His testimonies, as it is written in the Law of Moses, that you may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 29:9; Josh. 1:7); 1 Chr. 22:12, 13</char></note>prosper in all that you do and wherever you turn; <verse number="4" style="v" />that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:25</char></note>fulfill His word which He spoke concerning me, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 132:12)</char></note>‘If your sons take heed to their way, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:3</char></note>walk before Me in truth with all their heart and with all their soul,’ He said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12, 13; 1 Kin. 8:25</char></note>‘you shall not lack a man on the throne of Israel.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />“Moreover you know also what Joab the son of Zeruiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 3:39; 18:5, 12, 14</char></note>did to me, <char style="it">and</char> what he did to the two commanders of the armies of Israel, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 3:27; 1 Kin. 2:32</char></note>Abner the son of Ner and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:10</char></note>Amasa the son of Jether, whom he killed. And he shed the blood of war in peacetime, and put the blood of war on his belt that <char style="it">was</char> around his waist, and on his sandals that <char style="it">were</char> on his feet. <verse number="6" style="v" />Therefore do <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:9; Prov. 20:26</char></note>according to your wisdom, and do not let his gray hair go down to the grave in peace.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />“But show kindness to the sons of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 19:31–39</char></note>Barzillai the Gileadite, and let them be among those who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 9:7, 10; 19:28</char></note>eat at your table, for so <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 17:17–29</char></note>they came to me when I fled from Absalom your brother.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />“And see, <char style="it">you</char> <char style="it">have</char> with you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 16:5–13</char></note>Shimei the son of Gera, a Benjamite from Bahurim, who cursed me with a malicious curse in the day when I went to Mahanaim. But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 19:18</char></note>he came down to meet me at the Jordan, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 19:23</char></note>I swore to him by the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, ‘I will not put you to death with the sword.’ <verse number="9" style="v" />Now therefore, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:7; Job 9:28</char></note>do not hold him guiltless, for you <char style="it">are</char> a wise man and know what you ought to do to him; but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 42:38; 44:31</char></note>bring his gray hair down to the grave with blood.”</para>
	<para style="s">Death of David</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:21; Acts 2:29; 13:36</char></note>David rested with his fathers, and was buried in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:7; 1 Kin. 3:1</char></note>the City of David. <verse number="11" style="v" />The period that David <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:4, 5; 1 Chr. 3:4; 29:26, 27</char></note>reigned over Israel <char style="it">was</char> forty years; seven years he reigned in Hebron, and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty-three years. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:46; 1 Chr. 29:23</char></note>Then Solomon sat on the throne of his father David; and his kingdom was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:46; 2 Chr. 1:1</char></note>firmly established.</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon Executes Adonijah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Now Adonijah the son of Haggith came to Bathsheba the mother of Solomon. So she said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 16:4, 5</char></note>“Do you come peaceably?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “Peaceably.” <verse number="14" style="v" />Moreover he said, “I have something <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">say</char> to you.”</para>
	<para style="p">And she said, “Say it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then he said, “You know that the kingdom was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:11, 18</char></note>mine, and all Israel had set their expectations on me, that I should reign. However, the kingdom has been turned over, and has become my brother’s; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:9, 10; 28:5–7; (Dan. 2:21)</char></note>it was his from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="16" style="v" />Now I ask one petition of you; do not deny me.”</para>
	<para style="p">And she said to him, “Say it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then he said, “Please speak to King Solomon, for he will not refuse you, that he may give me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:3, 4</char></note>Abishag the Shunammite as wife.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />So Bathsheba said, “Very well, I will speak for you to the king.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Bathsheba therefore went to King Solomon, to speak to him for Adonijah. And the king rose up to meet her and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 20:12)</char></note>bowed down to her, and sat down on his throne and had a throne set for the king’s mother; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 45:9</char></note>so she sat at his right hand. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then she said, “I desire one small petition of you; do not refuse me.”</para>
	<para style="p">And the king said to her, “Ask it, my mother, for I will not refuse you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />So she said, “Let Abishag the Shunammite be given to Adonijah your brother as wife.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And King Solomon answered and said to his mother, “Now why do you ask Abishag the Shunammite for Adonijah? Ask for him the kingdom also—for he <char style="it">is</char> my <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:6; 2:15; 1 Chr. 3:2, 5</char></note>older brother—for him, and for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:7</char></note>Abiathar the priest, and for Joab the son of Zeruiah.” <verse number="23" style="v" />Then King Solomon swore by the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ruth 1:17</char></note>“May God do so to me, and more also, if Adonijah has not spoken this word against his own life! <verse number="24" style="v" />Now therefore, <char style="it">as</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, who has confirmed me and set me on the throne of David my father, and who has established a house for me, as He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:11, 13; 1 Chr. 22:10</char></note>promised, Adonijah shall be put to death today!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />So King Solomon sent by the hand of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:18; 1 Kin. 4:4</char></note>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; and he struck him down, and he died.</para>
	<para style="s">Abiathar Exiled, Joab Executed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />And to Abiathar the priest the king said, “Go to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:18; Jer. 1:1</char></note>Anathoth, to your own fields, for you <char style="it">are</char> deserving of death; but I will not put you to death at this time, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 22:23; 23:6; 2 Sam. 15:14, 29</char></note>because you carried the ark of the Lord <char style="sc">God</char> before my father David, and because you were afflicted every time my father was afflicted.” <verse number="27" style="v" />So Solomon removed Abiathar from being priest to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that he might <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:31–35</char></note>fulfill the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He spoke concerning the house of Eli at Shiloh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Then news came to Joab, for Joab <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:7</char></note>had defected to Adonijah, though he had not defected to Absalom. So Joab fled to the tabernacle of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:50</char></note>took hold of the horns of the altar. <verse number="29" style="v" />And King Solomon was told, “Joab has fled to the tabernacle of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; there <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">is,</char> by the altar.” Then Solomon sent Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, saying, “Go, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:5, 6</char></note>strike him down.” <verse number="30" style="v" />So Benaiah went to the tabernacle of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said to him, “Thus says the king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 21:14)</char></note>‘Come out!’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “No, but I will die here.” And Benaiah brought back word to the king, saying, “Thus said Joab, and thus he answered me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Then the king said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 21:14)</char></note>“Do as he has said, and strike him down and bury him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Num. 35:33; Deut. 19:13; 21:8, 9)</char></note>that you may take away from me and from the house of my father the innocent blood which Joab shed. <verse number="32" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Gen. 9:6); Judg. 9:24, 57</char></note>will return his blood on his head, because he struck down two men more righteous <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:13, 14</char></note>and better than he, and killed them with the sword—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 3:27</char></note>Abner the son of Ner, the commander of the army of Israel, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:9, 10</char></note>Amasa the son of Jether, the commander of the army of Judah—though my father David did not know <char style="it">it.</char> <verse number="33" style="v" />Their blood shall therefore return upon the head of Joab and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 3:29</char></note>upon the head of his descendants forever. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 25:5)</char></note>But upon David and his descendants, upon his house and his throne, there shall be peace forever from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />So Benaiah the son of Jehoiada went up and struck and killed him; and he was buried in his own house in the wilderness. <verse number="35" style="v" />The king put Benaiah the son of Jehoiada in his place over the army, and the king put <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:35; 1 Kin. 4:4; 1 Chr. 6:53; 24:3; 29:22</char></note>Zadok the priest in the place of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:27</char></note>Abiathar.</para>
	<para style="s">Shimei Executed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />Then the king sent and called for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 16:5–13; 1 Kin. 2:8</char></note>Shimei, and said to him, “Build yourself a house in Jerusalem and dwell there, and do not go out from there anywhere. <verse number="37" style="v" />For it shall be, on the day you go out and cross <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 15:23; 2 Kin. 23:6; John 18:1</char></note>the Brook Kidron, know for certain you shall surely die; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:9; Josh. 2:19; 2 Sam. 1:16; Ezek. 18:13</char></note>your blood shall be on your own head.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />And Shimei said to the king, “The saying <char style="it">is</char> good. As my lord the king has said, so your servant will do.” So Shimei dwelt in Jerusalem many days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />Now it happened at the end of three years, that two slaves of Shimei ran away to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 27:2</char></note>Achish the son of Maachah, king of Gath. And they told Shimei, saying, “Look, your slaves <char style="it">are</char> in Gath!” <verse number="40" style="v" />So Shimei arose, saddled his donkey, and went to Achish at Gath to seek his slaves. And Shimei went and brought his slaves from Gath. <verse number="41" style="v" />And Solomon was told that Shimei had gone from Jerusalem to Gath and had come back. <verse number="42" style="v" />Then the king sent and called for Shimei, and said to him, “Did I not make you swear by the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and warn you, saying, ‘Know for certain that on the day you go out and travel anywhere, you shall surely die’? And you said to me, ‘The word I have heard <char style="it">is</char> good.’ <verse number="43" style="v" />Why then have you not kept the oath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the commandment that I gave you?” <verse number="44" style="v" />The king said moreover to Shimei, “You know, as your heart acknowledges, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 16:5–13</char></note>all the wickedness that you did to my father David; therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:39; 2 Kin. 11:1, 12–16; Ps. 7:16; Ezek. 17:19</char></note>return your wickedness on your own head. <verse number="45" style="v" />But King Solomon <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> blessed, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:13; (Prov. 25:5)</char></note>the throne of David shall be established before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> forever.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" />So the king commanded Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; and he went out and struck him down, and he died. Thus the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:12; 2 Chr. 1:1</char></note>kingdom was established in the hand of Solomon.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon Requests Wisdom</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:8; 9:24</char></note>Solomon made a treaty with Pharaoh king of Egypt, and married Pharaoh’s daughter; then he brought her <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:7</char></note>to the City of David until he had finished building his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:1</char></note>own house, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6</char></note>the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:15, 19</char></note>the wall all around Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 12:2–5, 13, 14); 1 Kin. 11:7; 22:43</char></note>Meanwhile the people sacrificed at the high places, because there was no house built for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> until those days. <verse number="3" style="v" />And Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rom. 8:28)</char></note>loved the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Kin. 3:6, 14)</char></note>walking in the statutes of his father David, except that he sacrificed and burned incense at the high places.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:2; 2 Chr. 1:3</char></note>the king went to Gibeon to sacrifice there, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 16:39; 21:29</char></note>for that <char style="it">was</char> the great high place: Solomon offered a thousand burnt offerings on that altar. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:2; 11:9; 2 Chr. 1:7</char></note>At Gibeon the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared to Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 12:6; Matt. 1:20; 2:13</char></note>in a dream by night; and God said, “Ask! What shall I give you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 1:8</char></note>And Solomon said: “You have shown great mercy to Your servant David my father, because he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:4; 9:4; 2 Kin. 20:3</char></note>walked before You in truth, in righteousness, and in uprightness of heart with You; You have continued this great kindness for him, and You <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:8–17; 1 Kin. 1:48</char></note>have given him a son to sit on his throne, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> this day. <verse number="7" style="v" />Now, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, You have made Your servant king instead of my father David, but I <char style="it">am</char> a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:5; Jer. 1:6, 7</char></note>little child; I do not know <char style="it">how</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:17; 2 Sam. 5:2</char></note>to go out or come in. <verse number="8" style="v" />And Your servant <char style="it">is</char> in the midst of Your people whom You <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 19:6; Deut. 7:6)</char></note>have chosen, a great people, too <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 13:6; 15:5; 22:17</char></note>numerous to be numbered or counted. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 1:10; (James 1:5)</char></note>Therefore give to Your servant an understanding heart <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 72:1, 2</char></note>to judge Your people, that I may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 14:17; Is. 7:15; (Heb. 5:14)</char></note>discern between good and evil. For who is able to judge this great people of Yours?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />The speech pleased the Lord, that Solomon had asked this thing. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then God said to him: “Because you have asked this thing, and have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(James 4:3)</char></note>not asked long life for yourself, nor have asked riches for yourself, nor have asked the life of your enemies, but have asked for yourself understanding to discern justice, <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 John 5:14, 15)</char></note>behold, I have done according to your words; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:29–31; 5:12; 10:24; Eccl. 1:16</char></note>see, I have given you a wise and understanding heart, so that there has not been anyone like you before you, nor shall any like you arise after you. <verse number="13" style="v" />And I have also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 6:33; Eph. 3:20)</char></note>given you what you have not asked: both <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:21, 24; 10:23; 1 Chr. 29:12</char></note>riches and honor, so that there shall not be anyone like you among the kings all your days. <verse number="14" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Kin. 6:12)</char></note>if you walk in My ways, to keep My statutes and My commandments, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:5</char></note>as your father David walked, then I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 91:16; Prov. 3:2</char></note>lengthen your days.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:7</char></note>awoke; and indeed it had been a dream. And he came to Jerusalem and stood before the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, offered up burnt offerings, offered peace offerings, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 40:20; 1 Kin. 8:65;  Esth. 1:3; Dan. 5:1; Mark 6:21</char></note>made a feast for all his servants.</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Wise Judgment</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Now two women <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> harlots came to the king, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:2</char></note>stood before him. <verse number="17" style="v" />And one woman said, “O my lord, this woman and I dwell in the same house; and I gave birth while she <char style="it">was</char> in the house. <verse number="18" style="v" />Then it happened, the third day after I had given birth, that this woman also gave birth. And we <char style="it">were</char> together; no one <char style="it">was</char> with us in the house, except the two of us in the house. <verse number="19" style="v" />And this woman’s son died in the night, because she lay on him. <verse number="20" style="v" />So she arose in the middle of the night and took my son from my side, while your maidservant slept, and laid him in her bosom, and laid her dead child in my bosom. <verse number="21" style="v" />And when I rose in the morning to nurse my son, there he was, dead. But when I had examined him in the morning, indeed, he was not my son whom I had borne.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then the other woman said, “No! But the living one <char style="it">is</char> my son, and the dead one <char style="it">is</char> your son.”</para>
	<para style="p">And the first woman said, “No! But the dead one <char style="it">is</char> your son, and the living one <char style="it">is</char> my son.”</para>
	<para style="p">Thus they spoke before the king.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And the king said, “The one says, ‘This <char style="it">is</char> my son, who lives, and your son <char style="it">is</char> the dead one’; and the other says, ‘No! But your son <char style="it">is</char> the dead one, and my son <char style="it">is</char> the living one.’ ” <verse number="24" style="v" />Then the king said, “Bring me a sword.” So they brought a sword before the king. <verse number="25" style="v" />And the king said, “Divide the living child in two, and give half to one, and half to the other.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then the woman whose son <char style="it">was</char> living spoke to the king, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 43:30; Is. 49:15; Jer. 31:20; Hos. 11:8</char></note>she yearned with compassion for her son; and she said, “O my lord, give her the living child, and by no means kill him!”</para>
	<para style="p">But the other said, “Let him be neither mine nor yours, <char style="it">but</char> divide <char style="it">him.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />So the king answered and said, “Give the first woman the living child, and by no means kill him; she <char style="it">is</char> his mother.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And all Israel heard of the judgment which the king had rendered; and they feared the king, for they saw that the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:9, 11, 12; 2 Chr. 1:12; Dan. 1:17; (Col. 2:2, 3)</char></note>wisdom of God <char style="it">was</char> in him to administer justice.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Administration</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />So King Solomon was king over all Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />And these <char style="it">were</char> his officials: Azariah the son of Zadok, the priest; <verse number="3" style="v" />Elihoreph and Ahijah, the sons of Shisha, scribes; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:16; 20:24</char></note>Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud, the recorder; <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:35</char></note>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, over the army; Zadok and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:27</char></note>Abiathar, the priests; <verse number="5" style="v" />Azariah the son of Nathan, over <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:7</char></note>the officers; Zabud the son of Nathan, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:18; 20:26</char></note>a priest <char style="it">and</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 15:37; 16:16; 1 Chr. 27:33</char></note>the king’s friend; <verse number="6" style="v" />Ahishar, over the household; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:14</char></note>Adoniram the son of Abda, over the labor force.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And Solomon had twelve governors over all Israel, who provided food for the king and his household; each one made provision for one month of the year. <verse number="8" style="v" />These <char style="it">are</char> their names: Ben-Hur, in the mountains of Ephraim; <verse number="9" style="v" />Ben-Deker, in Makaz, Shaalbim, Beth Shemesh, and Elon Beth Hanan; <verse number="10" style="v" />Ben-Hesed, in Arubboth; to him <char style="it">belonged</char> Sochoh and all the land of Hepher; <verse number="11" style="v" />Ben-Abinadab, <char style="it">in</char> all the regions of Dor; he had Taphath the daughter of Solomon as wife; <verse number="12" style="v" />Baana the son of Ahilud, <char style="it">in</char> Taanach, Megiddo, and all Beth Shean, which <char style="it">is</char> beside Zaretan below Jezreel, from Beth Shean to Abel Meholah, as far as the other side of Jokneam; <verse number="13" style="v" />Ben-Geber, in Ramoth Gilead; to him <char style="it">belonged</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:41; 1 Chr. 2:22</char></note>the towns of Jair the son of Manasseh, in Gilead; to him <char style="it">also</char> <char style="it">belonged</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:4</char></note>the region of Argob in Bashan—sixty large cities with walls and bronze gate-bars; <verse number="14" style="v" />Ahinadab the son of Iddo, <char style="it">in</char> Mahanaim; <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 15:27</char></note>Ahimaaz, in Naphtali; he also took Basemath the daughter of Solomon as wife; <verse number="16" style="v" />Baanah the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 15:32; 1 Chr. 27:33</char></note>Hushai, in Asher and Aloth; <verse number="17" style="v" />Jehoshaphat the son of Paruah, in Issachar; <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:8</char></note>Shimei the son of Elah, in Benjamin; <verse number="19" style="v" />Geber the son of Uri, in the land of Gilead, <char style="it">in</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:8–10</char></note>the country of Sihon king of the Amorites, and of Og king of Bashan. <char style="it">He</char> <char style="it">was</char> the only governor who <char style="it">was</char> in the land.</para>
	<para style="s">Prosperity and Wisdom of Solomon’s Reign</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Judah and Israel <char style="it">were</char> as numerous <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 22:17; 32:12; 1 Kin. 3:8; (Prov. 14:28)</char></note>as the sand by the sea in multitude, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 72:3, 7; Mic. 4:4</char></note>eating and drinking and rejoicing. <verse number="21" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:24; 2 Chr. 9:26; Ps. 72:8</char></note>Solomon reigned over all kingdoms from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:18; Josh. 1:4</char></note>the River <char style="it">to</char> the land of the Philistines, as far as the border of Egypt. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 68:29</char></note><char style="it">They</char> brought tribute and served Solomon all the days of his life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 5:18</char></note>Now Solomon’s provision for one day was thirty kors of fine flour, sixty kors of meal, <verse number="23" style="v" />ten fatted oxen, twenty oxen from the pastures, and one hundred sheep, besides deer, gazelles, roebucks, and fatted fowl.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />For he had dominion over all <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">region</char> on this side of the River from Tiphsah even to Gaza, namely over <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 72:11</char></note>all the kings on this side of the River; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:4; 1 Chr. 22:9</char></note>he had peace on every side all around him. <verse number="25" style="v" />And Judah and Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 23:6)</char></note>dwelt safely, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Mic. 4:4; Zech. 3:10)</char></note>each man under his vine and his fig tree, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:1</char></note>from Dan as far as Beersheba, all the days of Solomon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:26; 2 Chr. 1:14</char></note>Solomon had forty thousand stalls of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 17:16)</char></note>horses for his chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen. <verse number="27" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:7</char></note>these governors, each man in his month, provided food for King Solomon and for all who came to King Solomon’s table. There was no lack in their supply. <verse number="28" style="v" />They also brought barley and straw to the proper place, for the horses and steeds, each man according to his charge.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:12</char></note>God gave Solomon wisdom and exceedingly great understanding, and largeness of heart like the sand on the seashore. <verse number="30" style="v" />Thus Solomon’s wisdom excelled the wisdom of all the men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 25:6</char></note>of the East and all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 19:11, 12; Acts 7:22</char></note>the wisdom of Egypt. <verse number="31" style="v" />For he was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:12</char></note>wiser than all men—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 15:19; Ps. 89:title</char></note>than Ethan the Ezrahite, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 2:6; Ps. 88:title</char></note>and Heman, Chalcol, and Darda, the sons of Mahol; and his fame was in all the surrounding nations. <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 1:1; 10:1; 25:1; Eccl. 12:9</char></note>He spoke three thousand proverbs, and his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Song 1:1</char></note>songs were one thousand and five. <verse number="33" style="v" />Also he spoke of trees, from the cedar tree of Lebanon even to the hyssop that springs out of the wall; he spoke also of animals, of birds, of creeping things, and of fish. <verse number="34" style="v" />And men of all nations, from all the kings of the earth who had heard of his wisdom, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:1; 2 Chr. 9:1, 23</char></note>came to hear the wisdom of Solomon.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon Prepares to Build the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:10, 18; 2 Chr. 2:3</char></note>Hiram king of Tyre sent his servants to Solomon, because he heard that they had anointed him king in place of his father, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:11; 1 Chr. 14:1</char></note>for Hiram had always loved David. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:3</char></note>Solomon sent to Hiram, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:2, 3</char></note>You know how my father David could not build a house for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:8; 28:3</char></note>because of the wars which were fought against him on every side, until the <char style="sc">Lord</char> put <char style="it">his</char> <char style="it">foes</char> under the soles of his feet.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="4" style="v" />But now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God has given me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:24; 1 Chr. 22:9</char></note>rest on every side; <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> neither adversary nor evil occurrence.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:4</char></note>And behold, I propose to build a house for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12, 13; 1 Kin. 6:38; 1 Chr. 17:12; 22:10; 28:6; 2 Chr. 6:2</char></note>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to my father David, saying, “Your son, whom I will set on your throne in your place, he shall build the house for My name.”</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="6" style="v" />Now therefore, command that they cut down <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:8, 10</char></note>cedars for me from Lebanon; and my servants will be with your servants, and I will pay you wages for your servants according to whatever you say. For you know <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> none among us who has skill to cut timber like the Sidonians.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So it was, when Hiram heard the words of Solomon, that he rejoiced greatly and said,</para>
	<para style="q1">Blessed <char style="it">be</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> this day, for He has given David a wise son over this great people!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then Hiram sent to Solomon, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1">I have considered <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">message</char> which you sent me, <char style="it">and</char> I will do all you desire concerning the cedar and cypress logs.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="9" style="v" />My servants shall bring <char style="it">them</char> down <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 3:7</char></note>from Lebanon to the sea; I will float them in rafts by sea to the place you indicate to me, and will have them broken apart there; then you can take <char style="it">them</char> away. And you shall fulfill my desire <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 27:17; Acts 12:20</char></note>by giving food for my household.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Then Hiram gave Solomon cedar and cypress logs <char style="it">according</char> <char style="it">to</char> all his desire. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:10</char></note>And Solomon gave Hiram twenty thousand kors of wheat <char style="it">as</char> food for his household, and twenty kors of pressed oil. Thus Solomon gave to Hiram year by year.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave Solomon wisdom, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:12</char></note>as He had promised him; and there was peace between Hiram and Solomon, and the two of them made a treaty together.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then King Solomon raised up a labor force out of all Israel; and the labor force was thirty thousand men. <verse number="14" style="v" />And he sent them to Lebanon, ten thousand a month in shifts: they were one month in Lebanon <char style="it">and</char> two months at home; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:18</char></note>Adoniram <char style="it">was</char> in charge of the labor force. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:20–22; 2 Chr. 2:17, 18</char></note>Solomon had seventy thousand who carried burdens, and eighty thousand who quarried <char style="it">stone</char> in the mountains, <verse number="16" style="v" />besides three thousand three hundred from the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:23</char></note>chiefs of Solomon’s deputies, who supervised the people who labored in the work. <verse number="17" style="v" />And the king commanded them to quarry large stones, costly stones, <char style="it">and</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:7; 1 Chr. 22:2</char></note>hewn stones, to lay the foundation of the temple. <verse number="18" style="v" />So Solomon’s builders, Hiram’s builders, and the Gebalites quarried <char style="it">them;</char> and they prepared timber and stones to build the temple.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon Builds the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 3:1, 2</char></note>it came to pass in the four hundred and eightieth year after the children of Israel had come out of the land of Egypt, in the fourth year of Solomon’s reign over Israel, in the month of Ziv, which <char style="it">is</char> the second month, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 7:47</char></note>that he began to build the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="2" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 41:1</char></note>the house which King Solomon built for the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, its length <char style="it">was</char> sixty cubits, its width twenty, and its height thirty cubits. <verse number="3" style="v" />The vestibule in front of the sanctuary of the house <char style="it">was</char> twenty cubits long across the width of the house, <char style="it">and</char> the width of <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">vestibule</char> <char style="it">extended</char> ten cubits from the front of the house. <verse number="4" style="v" />And he made for the house <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 40:16; 41:16</char></note>windows with beveled frames.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Against the wall of the temple he built <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 41:6</char></note>chambers all around, <char style="it">against</char> the walls of the temple, all around the sanctuary <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:16, 19–21, 31</char></note>and the inner sanctuary. Thus he made side chambers all around it. <verse number="6" style="v" />The lowest chamber <char style="it">was</char> five cubits wide, the middle <char style="it">was</char> six cubits wide, and the third <char style="it">was</char> seven cubits wide; for he made narrow ledges around the outside of the temple, so that <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">support</char> <char style="it">beams</char> would not be fastened into the walls of the temple. <verse number="7" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:25; Deut. 27:5, 6</char></note>the temple, when it was being built, was built with stone finished at the quarry, so that no hammer or chisel <char style="it">or</char> any iron tool was heard in the temple while it was being built. <verse number="8" style="v" />The doorway for the middle story <char style="it">was</char> on the right side of the temple. They went up by stairs to the middle <char style="it">story,</char> and from the middle to the third.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:14, 38</char></note>So he built the temple and finished it, and he paneled the temple with beams and boards of cedar. <verse number="10" style="v" />And he built side chambers against the entire temple, each five cubits high; they were attached to the temple with cedar beams.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to Solomon, saying: <verse number="12" style="v" />“<char style="it">Concerning</char> this temple which you are building, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:4; 9:4</char></note>if you walk in My statutes, execute My judgments, keep all My commandments, and walk in them, then I will perform My word with you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Sam. 7:13; 1 Chr. 22:10)</char></note>which I spoke to your father David. <verse number="13" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:8; Lev. 26:11; (2 Cor. 6:16; Rev. 21:3)</char></note>I will dwell among the children of Israel, and will not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 31:6)</char></note>forsake My people Israel.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So Solomon built the temple and finished it. <verse number="15" style="v" />And he built the inside walls of the temple with cedar boards; from the floor of the temple to the ceiling he paneled the inside with wood; and he covered the floor of the temple with planks of cypress. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then he built the twenty-cubit room at the rear of the temple, from floor to ceiling, with cedar boards; he built <char style="it">it</char> inside as the inner sanctuary, as the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 26:33; Lev. 16:2; 1 Kin. 8:6; 2 Chr. 3:8; Ezek. 45:3; Heb. 9:3</char></note>Most Holy <char style="it">Place.</char> <verse number="17" style="v" />And in front of it the temple sanctuary was forty cubits <char style="it">long.</char> <verse number="18" style="v" />The inside of the temple was cedar, carved with ornamental buds and open flowers. All <char style="it">was</char> cedar; there was no stone <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">be</char> seen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And he prepared the inner sanctuary inside the temple, to set the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> there. <verse number="20" style="v" />The inner sanctuary <char style="it">was</char> twenty cubits long, twenty cubits wide, and twenty cubits high. He overlaid it with pure gold, and overlaid the altar of cedar. <verse number="21" style="v" />So Solomon overlaid the inside of the temple with pure gold. He stretched gold chains across the front of the inner sanctuary, and overlaid it with gold. <verse number="22" style="v" />The whole temple he overlaid with gold, until he had finished all the temple; also he overlaid with gold <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:1, 3, 6</char></note>the entire altar that <char style="it">was</char> by the inner sanctuary.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Inside the inner sanctuary <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 37:7–9; 2 Chr. 3:10–12</char></note>he made two cherubim <char style="it">of</char> olive wood, <char style="it">each</char> ten cubits high. <verse number="24" style="v" />One wing of the cherub <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, and the other wing of the cherub five cubits: ten cubits from the tip of one wing to the tip of the other. <verse number="25" style="v" />And the other cherub <char style="it">was</char> ten cubits; both cherubim <char style="it">were</char> of the same size and shape. <verse number="26" style="v" />The height of one cherub <char style="it">was</char> ten cubits, and so <char style="it">was</char> the other cherub. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then he set the cherubim inside the inner room; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:20; 37:9; 1 Kin. 8:7; 2 Chr. 5:8</char></note>they stretched out the wings of the cherubim so that the wing of the one touched <char style="it">one</char> wall, and the wing of the other cherub touched the other wall. And their wings touched each other in the middle of the room. <verse number="28" style="v" />Also he overlaid the cherubim with gold.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Then he carved all the walls of the temple all around, both the inner and outer <char style="it">sanctuaries,</char> with carved <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 36:8, 35</char></note>figures of cherubim, palm trees, and open flowers. <verse number="30" style="v" />And the floor of the temple he overlaid with gold, both the inner and outer <char style="it">sanctuaries.</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />For the entrance of the inner sanctuary he made doors <char style="it">of</char> olive wood; the lintel <char style="it">and</char> doorposts <char style="it">were</char> one-fifth <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">wall.</char> <verse number="32" style="v" />The two doors <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">of</char> olive wood; and he carved on them figures of cherubim, palm trees, and open flowers, and overlaid <char style="it">them</char> with gold; and he spread gold on the cherubim and on the palm trees. <verse number="33" style="v" />So for the door of the sanctuary he also made doorposts <char style="it">of</char> olive wood, one-fourth <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">wall.</char> <verse number="34" style="v" />And the two doors <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">of</char> cypress wood; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 41:23–25</char></note>two panels <char style="it">comprised</char> one folding door, and two panels <char style="it">comprised</char> the other folding door. <verse number="35" style="v" />Then he carved cherubim, palm trees, and open flowers <char style="it">on</char> <char style="it">them,</char> and overlaid <char style="it">them</char> with gold applied evenly on the carved work.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />And he built the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:12; Jer. 36:10</char></note>inner court with three rows of hewn stone and a row of cedar beams.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:1</char></note>In the fourth year the foundation of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was laid, in the month of Ziv. <verse number="38" style="v" />And in the eleventh year, in the month of Bul, which is the eighth month, the house was finished in all its details and according to all its plans. So he was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:13; 1 Kin. 5:5; 6:1; 8:19</char></note>seven years in building it.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Other Buildings</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />But Solomon took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:1; 9:10; 2 Chr. 8:1</char></note>thirteen years to build his own house; so he finished all his house.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />He also built the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:17, 21; 2 Chr. 9:16</char></note>House of the Forest of Lebanon; its length <char style="it">was</char> one hundred cubits, its width fifty cubits, and its height thirty cubits, with four rows of cedar pillars, and cedar beams on the pillars. <verse number="3" style="v" />And <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> paneled with cedar above the beams that <char style="it">were</char> on forty-five pillars, fifteen <char style="it">to</char> a row. <verse number="4" style="v" /><char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">were</char> windows <char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">beveled</char> <char style="it">frames</char> <char style="it">in</char> three rows, and window <char style="it">was</char> opposite window <char style="it">in</char> three tiers. <verse number="5" style="v" />And all the doorways and doorposts <char style="it">had</char> rectangular frames; and window <char style="it">was</char> opposite window <char style="it">in</char> three tiers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />He also made the Hall of Pillars: its length <char style="it">was</char> fifty cubits, and its width thirty cubits; and in front of them <char style="it">was</char> a portico with pillars, and a canopy <char style="it">was</char> in front of them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then he made a hall for the throne, the Hall of Judgment, where he might judge; and <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> paneled with cedar from floor to ceiling.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And the house where he dwelt <char style="it">had</char> another court inside the hall, of like workmanship. Solomon also made a house like this hall for Pharaoh’s daughter, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:1; 9:24; 11:1; 2 Chr. 8:11</char></note>whom he had taken <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">wife.</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />All these <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">of</char> costly stones cut to size, trimmed with saws, inside and out, from the foundation to the eaves, and also on the outside to the great court. <verse number="10" style="v" />The foundation <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">of</char> costly stones, large stones, some ten cubits and some eight cubits. <verse number="11" style="v" />And above <char style="it">were</char> costly stones, hewn to size, and cedar wood. <verse number="12" style="v" />The great court <char style="it">was</char> enclosed with three rows of hewn stones and a row of cedar beams. So were the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:36</char></note>inner court of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">John 10:23; Acts 3:11</char></note>and the vestibule of the temple.</para>
	<para style="s">Hiram the Craftsman</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Now King Solomon sent and brought Huram from Tyre. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:14</char></note>He <char style="it">was</char> the son of a widow from the tribe of Naphtali, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:16</char></note>his father <char style="it">was</char> a man of Tyre, a bronze worker; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 31:3; 36:1</char></note>he was filled with wisdom and understanding and skill in working with all kinds of bronze work. So he came to King Solomon and did all his work.</para>
	<para style="s">The Bronze Pillars for the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And he cast <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:17; 2 Chr. 3:15; 4:12; Jer. 52:21</char></note>two pillars of bronze, each one eighteen cubits high, and a line of twelve cubits measured the circumference of each. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then he made two capitals <char style="it">of</char> cast bronze, to set on the tops of the pillars. The height of one capital <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, and the height of the other capital <char style="it">was</char> five cubits. <verse number="17" style="v" /><char style="it">He</char> <char style="it">made</char> a lattice network, with wreaths of chainwork, for the capitals which <char style="it">were</char> on top of the pillars: seven chains for one capital and seven for the other capital. <verse number="18" style="v" />So he made the pillars, and two rows of pomegranates above the network all around to cover the capitals that <char style="it">were</char> on top; and thus he did for the other capital.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />The capitals which <char style="it">were</char> on top of the pillars in the hall <char style="it">were</char> in the shape of lilies, four cubits. <verse number="20" style="v" />The capitals on the two pillars also <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">pomegranates</char> above, by the convex surface which <char style="it">was</char> next to the network; and there <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 3:16; 4:13; Jer. 52:23</char></note>two hundred such pomegranates in rows on each of the capitals all around.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 3:17</char></note>Then he set up the pillars by the vestibule of the temple; he set up the pillar on the right and called its name Jachin, and he set up the pillar on the left and called its name Boaz. <verse number="22" style="v" />The tops of the pillars were in the shape of lilies. So the work of the pillars was finished.</para>
	<para style="s">The Sea and the Oxen</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And he made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:13; 2 Chr. 4:2; Jer. 52:17</char></note>the Sea of cast bronze, ten cubits from one brim to the other; <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> completely round. Its height <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, and a line of thirty cubits measured its circumference.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Below its brim <char style="it">were</char> ornamental buds encircling it all around, ten to a cubit, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:3</char></note>all the way around the Sea. The ornamental buds <char style="it">were</char> cast in two rows when it was cast. <verse number="25" style="v" />It stood on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:4, 5; Jer. 52:20</char></note>twelve oxen: three looking toward the north, three looking toward the west, three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east; the Sea <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">set</char> upon them, and all their back parts <char style="it">pointed</char> inward. <verse number="26" style="v" />It <char style="it">was</char> a handbreadth thick; and its brim was shaped like the brim of a cup, <char style="it">like</char> a lily blossom. It contained two thousand baths.</para>
	<para style="s">The Carts and the Lavers</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />He also made ten carts of bronze; four cubits <char style="it">was</char> the length of each cart, four cubits its width, and three cubits its height. <verse number="28" style="v" />And this <char style="it">was</char> the design of the carts: They had panels, and the panels <char style="it">were</char> between frames; <verse number="29" style="v" />on the panels that <char style="it">were</char> between the frames <char style="it">were</char> lions, oxen, and cherubim. And on the frames <char style="it">was</char> a pedestal on top. Below the lions and oxen <char style="it">were</char> wreaths of plaited work. <verse number="30" style="v" />Every cart had four bronze wheels and axles of bronze, and its four feet had supports. Under the laver <char style="it">were</char> supports of cast <char style="it">bronze</char> beside each wreath. <verse number="31" style="v" />Its opening inside the crown at the top <char style="it">was</char> one cubit in diameter; and the opening <char style="it">was</char> round, shaped <char style="it">like</char> a pedestal, one and a half cubits in outside diameter; and also on the opening <char style="it">were</char> engravings, but the panels were square, not round. <verse number="32" style="v" />Under the panels <char style="it">were</char> the four wheels, and the axles of the wheels <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">joined</char> to the cart. The height of a wheel <char style="it">was</char> one and a half cubits. <verse number="33" style="v" />The workmanship of the wheels <char style="it">was</char> like the workmanship of a chariot wheel; their axle pins, their rims, their spokes, and their hubs <char style="it">were</char> all of cast <char style="it">bronze.</char> <verse number="34" style="v" />And <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">were</char> four supports at the four corners of each cart; its supports <char style="it">were</char> part of the cart itself. <verse number="35" style="v" />On the top of the cart, at the height of half a cubit, <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> perfectly round. And on the top of the cart, its flanges and its panels <char style="it">were</char> of the same casting. <verse number="36" style="v" />On the plates of its flanges and on its panels he engraved cherubim, lions, and palm trees, wherever there was a clear space on each, with wreaths all around. <verse number="37" style="v" />Thus he made the ten carts. All of them were of the same mold, one measure, <char style="it">and</char> one shape.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:18; 2 Chr. 4:6</char></note>he made ten lavers of bronze; each laver contained forty baths, <char style="it">and</char> each laver <char style="it">was</char> four cubits. On each of the ten carts <char style="it">was</char> a laver. <verse number="39" style="v" />And he put five carts on the right side of the house, and five on the left side of the house. He set the Sea on the right side of the house, toward the southeast.</para>
	<para style="s">Furnishings of the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:11—5:1</char></note>Huram made the lavers and the shovels and the bowls. So Huram finished doing all the work that he was to do for King Solomon <char style="it">for</char> the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <verse number="41" style="v" />the two pillars, the <char style="it">two</char> bowl-shaped capitals that <char style="it">were</char> on top of the two pillars; the two <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:17, 18</char></note>networks covering the two bowl-shaped capitals which <char style="it">were</char> on top of the pillars; <verse number="42" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:20</char></note>four hundred pomegranates for the two networks (two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that <char style="it">were</char> on top of the pillars); <verse number="43" style="v" />the ten carts, and ten lavers on the carts; <verse number="44" style="v" />one Sea, and twelve oxen under the Sea; <verse number="45" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:3; 2 Chr. 4:16</char></note>the pots, the shovels, and the bowls.</para>
	<para style="p">All these articles which Huram made for King Solomon <char style="it">for</char> the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">of</char> burnished bronze. <verse number="46" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:17</char></note>In the plain of Jordan the king had them cast in clay molds, between <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 33:17; Josh. 13:27</char></note>Succoth and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:16</char></note>Zaretan. <verse number="47" style="v" />And Solomon did not weigh all the articles, because <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">were</char> so many; the weight of the bronze was not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:3, 14</char></note>determined.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" />Thus Solomon had all the furnishings made for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 37:25, 26; 2 Chr. 4:8</char></note>the altar of gold, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 37:10, 11</char></note>the table of gold on which <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 24:5–8</char></note>the showbread; <verse number="49" style="v" />the lampstands of pure gold, five on the right <char style="it">side</char> and five on the left in front of the inner sanctuary, with the flowers and the lamps and the wick-trimmers of gold; <verse number="50" style="v" />the basins, the trimmers, the bowls, the ladles, and the censers of pure gold; and the hinges of gold, <char style="it">both</char> for the doors of the inner room (the Most Holy <char style="it">Place</char>) <char style="it">and</char> for the doors of the main hall of the temple.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" />So all the work that King Solomon had done for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was finished; and Solomon brought in the things <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:11; 1 Chr. 18:11; 2 Chr. 5:1</char></note>which his father David had dedicated: the silver and the gold and the furnishings. He put them in the treasuries of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Ark Brought into the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 1:4; 7:2; 2 Chr. 5:2–14</char></note>Solomon assembled the elders of Israel and all the heads of the tribes, the chief fathers of the children of Israel, to King Solomon in Jerusalem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 6:12–17; 1 Chr. 15:25–29</char></note>that they might bring <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:7; 6:12, 16</char></note>up the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> from the City of David, which <char style="it">is</char> Zion. <verse number="2" style="v" />Therefore all the men of Israel assembled with King Solomon at the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:34; 1 Kin. 8:65; 2 Chr. 7:8–10</char></note>feast in the month of Ethanim, which <char style="it">is</char> the seventh month. <verse number="3" style="v" />So all the elders of Israel came, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 4:15; 7:9; Deut. 31:9; Josh. 3:3, 6</char></note>and the priests took up the ark. <verse number="4" style="v" />Then they brought up the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:4; 2 Chr. 1:3</char></note>the tabernacle of meeting, and all the holy furnishings that <char style="it">were</char> in the tabernacle. The priests and the Levites brought them up. <verse number="5" style="v" />Also King Solomon, and all the congregation of Israel who were assembled with him, <char style="it">were</char> with him before the ark, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 6:13; 2 Chr. 1:6</char></note>sacrificing sheep and oxen that could not be counted or numbered for multitude. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then the priests <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 6:17</char></note>brought in the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 26:33, 34; 1 Kin. 6:19</char></note>its place, into the inner sanctuary of the temple, to the Most Holy <char style="it">Place,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:27</char></note>under the wings of the cherubim. <verse number="7" style="v" />For the cherubim spread <char style="it">their</char> two wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubim overshadowed the ark and its poles. <verse number="8" style="v" />The poles <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:13–15; 37:4, 5</char></note>extended so that the ends of the poles could be seen from the holy <char style="it">place,</char> in front of the inner sanctuary; but they could not be seen from outside. And they are there to this day. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:21; Deut. 10:2</char></note>Nothing <char style="it">was</char> in the ark <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:16; Deut. 10:5; Heb. 9:4</char></note>except the two tablets of stone which Moses <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 24:7, 8; 40:20; Deut. 4:13</char></note>put there at Horeb, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:27, 28</char></note>when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">covenant</char> with the children of Israel, when they came out of the land of Egypt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And it came to pass, when the priests came out of the holy <char style="it">place,</char> that the cloud <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:34, 35; 2 Chr. 7:1, 2</char></note>filled the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse number="11" style="v" />so that the priests could not continue ministering because of the cloud; for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:1, 2</char></note>glory of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> filled the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:1</char></note>Then Solomon spoke:</para>
	<para style="q1">“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said He would dwell <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:2; Ps. 18:11; 97:2</char></note>in the dark cloud.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:13</char></note>I have surely built You an exalted house,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 15:17); Ps. 132:14</char></note>And a place for You to dwell in forever.”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Speech at Completion of the Work</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then the king turned around and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 6:18; 1 Kin. 8:55</char></note>blessed the whole assembly of Israel, while all the assembly of Israel was standing. <verse number="15" style="v" />And he said: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 29:10, 20; Neh. 9:5; Luke 1:68</char></note>“Blessed <char style="it">be</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:2, 12, 13, 25; 1 Chr. 22:10</char></note>spoke with His mouth to my father David, and with His hand has fulfilled <char style="it">it,</char> saying, <verse number="16" style="v" />‘Since the day that I brought My people Israel out of Egypt, I have chosen no city from any tribe of Israel <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">which</char> to build a house, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5; 1 Kin. 8:29</char></note>My name might be there; but I chose <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 16:1; 2 Sam. 7:8; 1 Chr. 28:4</char></note>David to be over My people Israel.’ <verse number="17" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:2, 3; 1 Chr. 17:1, 2</char></note>it was in the heart of my father David to build a temple for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:8, 9</char></note>But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to my father David, ‘Whereas it was in your heart to build a temple for My name, you did well that it was in your heart. <verse number="19" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:5, 12, 13; 1 Kin. 5:3, 5; 6:38; 1 Chr. 17:11, 12; 22:8–10; 2 Chr. 6:2</char></note>you shall not build the temple, but your son who will come from your body, he shall build the temple for My name.’ <verse number="20" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has fulfilled His word which He spoke; and I have filled the position of my father David, and sit on the throne of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:5, 6</char></note>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> promised; and I have built a temple for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="21" style="v" />And there I have made a place for the ark, in which <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:26; 1 Kin. 8:9</char></note>the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He made with our fathers, when He brought them out of the land of Egypt.”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Prayer of Dedication</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then Solomon stood before <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:54; 2 Chr. 6:12</char></note>the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in the presence of all the assembly of Israel, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 9:33; Ezra 9:5</char></note>spread out his hands toward heaven; <verse number="23" style="v" />and he said: “<char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:11; 2 Sam. 7:22</char></note><char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no God in heaven above or on earth below like You, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 7:9; Neh. 1:5; Dan. 9:4)</char></note>who keep <char style="it">Your</char> covenant and mercy with Your servants who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Gen. 17:1; 1 Kin. 3:6); 2 Kin. 20:3</char></note>walk before You with all their hearts. <verse number="24" style="v" />You have kept what You promised Your servant David my father; You have both spoken with Your mouth and fulfilled <char style="it">it</char> with Your hand, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> this day. <verse number="25" style="v" />Therefore, <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, now keep what You promised Your servant David my father, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12, 16; 1 Kin. 2:4; 9:5</char></note>‘You shall not fail to have a man sit before Me on the throne of Israel, only if your sons take heed to their way, that they walk before Me as you have walked before Me.’ <verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:25</char></note>And now I pray, O God of Israel, let Your word come true, which You have spoken to Your servant David my father.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />“But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 2:6; Is. 66:1; Acts 7:49; 17:24)</char></note>will God indeed dwell on the earth? Behold, heaven and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Cor. 12:2</char></note>heaven of heavens cannot contain You. How much less this temple which I have built! <verse number="28" style="v" />Yet regard the prayer of Your servant and his supplication, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, and listen to the cry and the prayer which Your servant is praying before You today: <verse number="29" style="v" />that Your eyes may be open toward this temple night and day, toward the place of which You said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:11</char></note>‘My name shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:3; 2 Chr. 7:15</char></note>there,’ that You may hear the prayer which Your servant makes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:10</char></note>toward this place. <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 1:6</char></note>And may You hear the supplication of Your servant and of Your people Israel, when they pray toward this place. Hear in heaven Your dwelling place; and when You hear, forgive.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />“When anyone sins against his neighbor, and is forced to take <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:8–11</char></note>an oath, and comes <char style="it">and</char> takes an oath before Your altar in this temple, <verse number="32" style="v" />then hear in heaven, and act, and judge Your servants, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 25:1</char></note>condemning the wicked, bringing his way on his head, and justifying the righteous by giving him according to his righteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:17; Deut. 28:25</char></note>“When Your people Israel are defeated before an enemy because they have sinned against You, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:39, 40</char></note>when they turn back to You and confess Your name, and pray and make supplication to You in this temple, <verse number="34" style="v" />then hear in heaven, and forgive the sin of Your people Israel, and bring them back to the land which You gave to their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 26:40–42; Deut. 30:1–3)</char></note>fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:19; Deut. 28:23</char></note>“When the heavens are shut up and there is no rain because they have sinned against You, when they pray toward this place and confess Your name, and turn from their sin because You afflict them, <verse number="36" style="v" />then hear in heaven, and forgive the sin of Your servants, Your people Israel, that You may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 25:4; 27:11; 94:12</char></note>teach them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 12:23</char></note>the good way in which they should walk; and send rain on Your land which You have given to Your people as an inheritance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:16, 25, 26; Deut. 28:21, 22, 27, 38, 42, 52</char></note>“When there is famine in the land, pestilence <char style="it">or</char> blight <char style="it">or</char> mildew, locusts <char style="it">or</char> grasshoppers; when their enemy besieges them in the land of their cities; whatever plague or whatever sickness <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is;</char> <verse number="38" style="v" />whatever prayer, whatever supplication is made by anyone, <char style="it">or</char> by all Your people Israel, when each one knows the plague of his own heart, and spreads out his hands toward this temple: <verse number="39" style="v" />then hear in heaven Your dwelling place, and forgive, and act, and give to everyone according to all his ways, whose heart You know (for You alone <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Sam. 16:7; 1 Chr. 28:9; Jer. 17:10); Acts 1:24</char></note>know the hearts of all the sons of men), <verse number="40" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 130:4)</char></note>that they may fear You all the days that they live in the land which You gave to our fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />“Moreover, concerning a foreigner, who <char style="it">is</char> not of Your people Israel, but has come from a far country for Your name’s sake <verse number="42" style="v" />(for they will hear of Your great name and Your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 13:3; Deut. 3:24</char></note>strong hand and Your outstretched arm), when he comes and prays toward this temple, <verse number="43" style="v" />hear in heaven Your dwelling place, and do according to all for which the foreigner calls to You, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 9:16; 1 Sam. 17:46; 2 Kin. 19:19)</char></note>that all peoples of the earth may know Your name and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 102:15</char></note>fear You, as <char style="it">do</char> Your people Israel, and that they may know that this temple which I have built is called by Your name.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" />“When Your people go out to battle against their enemy, wherever You send them, and when they pray to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> toward the city which You have chosen and the temple which I have built for Your name, <verse number="45" style="v" />then hear in heaven their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" />“When they sin against You <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:36; Ps. 130:3; Prov. 20:9; Eccl. 7:20; (Rom. 3:23; 1 John 1:8, 10)</char></note>(for <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no one who does not sin), and You become angry with them and deliver them to the enemy, and they take them captive <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:34, 44; Deut. 28:36, 64; 2 Kin. 17:6, 18; 25:21</char></note>to the land of the enemy, far or near; <verse number="47" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 26:40–42); Neh. 9:2</char></note><char style="it">yet</char> when they come to themselves in the land where they were carried captive, and repent, and make supplication to You in the land of those who took them captive, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 9:6, 7; Neh. 1:6; Ps. 106:6; Dan. 9:5</char></note>saying, ‘We have sinned and done wrong, we have committed wickedness’; <verse number="48" style="v" />and <char style="it">when</char> they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 29:12–14</char></note>return to You with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their enemies who led them away captive, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:10; Jon. 2:4</char></note>pray to You toward their land which You gave to their fathers, the city which You have chosen and the temple which I have built for Your name: <verse number="49" style="v" />then hear in heaven Your dwelling place their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause, <verse number="50" style="v" />and forgive Your people who have sinned against You, and all their transgressions which they have transgressed against You; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 30:9); Ezra 7:6; Ps. 106:46; Acts 7:10</char></note>grant them compassion before those who took them captive, that they may have compassion on them <verse number="51" style="v" />(for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:11, 12; Deut. 9:26–29; Neh. 1:10; (Rom. 11:28, 29)</char></note>they <char style="it">are</char> Your people and Your inheritance, whom You brought out of Egypt, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:20; Jer. 11:4</char></note>out of the iron furnace), <verse number="52" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:29</char></note>that Your eyes may be open to the supplication of Your servant and the supplication of Your people Israel, to listen to them whenever they call to You. <verse number="53" style="v" />For You separated them from among all the peoples of the earth <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">be</char> Your inheritance, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:5, 6</char></note>as You spoke by Your servant Moses, when You brought our fathers out of Egypt, O Lord <char style="sc">God</char>.”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon Blesses the Assembly</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:1</char></note>And so it was, when Solomon had finished praying all this prayer and supplication to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that he arose from before the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, from kneeling on his knees with his hands spread up to heaven. <verse number="55" style="v" />Then he stood <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:23–26; 2 Sam. 6:18; 1 Kin. 8:14</char></note>and blessed all the assembly of Israel with a loud voice, saying: <verse number="56" style="v" />“Blessed <char style="it">be</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, who has given <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:18</char></note>rest to His people Israel, according to all that He promised. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:10; Josh. 21:45; 23:14</char></note>There has not failed one word of all His good promise, which He promised through His servant Moses. <verse number="57" style="v" />May the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God be with us, as He was with our fathers. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:6; Josh. 1:5; 1 Sam. 12:22; (Rom. 8:31–37); Heb. 13:5</char></note>May He not leave us nor forsake us, <verse number="58" style="v" />that He may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 119:36; Jer. 31:33</char></note>incline our hearts to Himself, to walk in all His ways, and to keep His commandments and His statutes and His judgments, which He commanded our fathers. <verse number="59" style="v" />And may these words of mine, with which I have made supplication before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, be near the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God day and night, that He may maintain the cause of His servant and the cause of His people Israel, as each day may require, <verse number="60" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:24; 1 Sam. 17:46; 1 Kin. 8:43; 2 Kin. 19:19</char></note>that all the peoples of the earth may know that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:35, 39; 1 Kin. 18:39; (Jer. 10:10–12)</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> God; <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no other. <verse number="61" style="v" />Let your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 18:13; 1 Kin. 11:4; 15:3, 14; 2 Kin. 20:3</char></note>heart therefore be loyal to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, to walk in His statutes and keep His commandments, as at this day.”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon Dedicates the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="62" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:4–10</char></note>the king and all Israel with him offered sacrifices before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="63" style="v" />And Solomon offered a sacrifice of peace offerings, which he offered to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, twenty-two thousand bulls and one hundred and twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the children of Israel dedicated the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="64" style="v" />On <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:7</char></note>the same day the king consecrated the middle of the court that <char style="it">was</char> in front of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; for there he offered burnt offerings, grain offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings, because the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:1</char></note>bronze altar that <char style="it">was</char> before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">was</char> too small to receive the burnt offerings, the grain offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="65" style="v" />At that time Solomon held <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:34; 1 Kin. 8:2</char></note>a feast, and all Israel with him, a great assembly from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:8; Josh. 13:5; Judg. 3:3; 2 Kin. 14:25</char></note>the entrance of Hamath to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:18; Ex. 23:31; Num. 34:5</char></note>the Brook of Egypt, before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:8</char></note>seven days and seven <char style="it">more</char> days—fourteen days. <verse number="66" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:9</char></note>On the eighth day he sent the people away; and they blessed the king, and went to their tents joyful and glad of heart for all the good that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had done for His servant David, and for Israel His people.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="s">God’s Second Appearance to Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:11</char></note>it came to pass, when Solomon had finished building the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:1</char></note>and the king’s house, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:6</char></note>all Solomon’s desire which he wanted to do, <verse number="2" style="v" />that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared to Solomon the second time, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:5; 11:9; 2 Chr. 1:7</char></note>as He had appeared to him at Gibeon. <verse number="3" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:5; Ps. 10:17</char></note>“I have heard your prayer and your supplication that you have made before Me; I have consecrated this house which you have built <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:29</char></note>to put My name there forever, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 11:12</char></note>My eyes and My heart will be there perpetually. <verse number="4" style="v" />Now if you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:1</char></note>walk before Me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:4, 6; 15:5</char></note>as your father David walked, in integrity of heart and in uprightness, to do according to all that I have commanded you, <char style="it">and</char> if you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:61</char></note>keep My statutes and My judgments, <verse number="5" style="v" />then I will establish the throne of your kingdom over Israel forever, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12, 16; 1 Kin. 2:4; 6:12; 8:25; 1 Chr. 22:10; Matt. 1:6; 25:31</char></note>as I promised David your father, saying, ‘You shall not fail to have a man on the throne of Israel.’ <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:14–16; 2 Chr. 7:19, 20; Ps. 89:30</char></note><char style="it">But</char> if you or your sons at all turn from following Me, and do not keep My commandments <char style="it">and</char> My statutes which I have set before you, but go and serve other gods and worship them, <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:24–29); Deut. 4:26; 2 Kin. 17:23; 25:21</char></note>then I will cut off Israel from the land which I have given them; and this house which I have consecrated <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 7:4–14)</char></note>for My name I will cast out of My sight. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:37; Ps. 44:14; Jer. 24:9</char></note>Israel will be a proverb and a byword among all peoples. <verse number="8" style="v" />And <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">for</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:21</char></note>this house, <char style="it">which</char> is exalted, everyone who passes by it will be astonished and will hiss, and say, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 29:24–26); Jer. 22:8, 9</char></note>‘Why has the <char style="sc">Lord</char> done thus to this land and to this house?’ <verse number="9" style="v" />Then they will answer, ‘Because they forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, who brought their fathers out of the land of Egypt, and have embraced other gods, and worshiped them and served them; therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has brought all this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 29:25–28)</char></note>calamity on them.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon and Hiram Exchange Gifts</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:37, 38; 7:1; 2 Chr. 8:1</char></note>it happened at the end of twenty years, when Solomon had built the two houses, the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the king’s house <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:1</char></note>(Hiram the king of Tyre had supplied Solomon with cedar and cypress and gold, as much as he desired), <char style="it">that</char> King Solomon then gave Hiram twenty cities in the land of Galilee. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then Hiram went from Tyre to see the cities which Solomon had given him, but they did not please him. <verse number="13" style="v" />So he said, “What <char style="it">kind</char> <char style="it">of</char> cities <char style="it">are</char> these which you have given me, my brother?” <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:27</char></note>And he called them the land of Cabul, as they are to this day. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then Hiram sent the king one hundred and twenty talents of gold.</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Additional Achievements</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And this <char style="it">is</char> the reason for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:13</char></note>the labor force which King Solomon raised: to build the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, his own house, the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:9; 1 Kin. 9:24</char></note>Millo, the wall of Jerusalem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:1; 19:36</char></note>Hazor, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:11</char></note>Megiddo, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:10</char></note>Gezer. <verse number="16" style="v" />(Pharaoh king of Egypt had gone up and taken Gezer and burned it with fire, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:10; Judg. 1:29</char></note>had killed the Canaanites who dwelt in the city, and had given it <char style="it">as</char> a dowry to his daughter, Solomon’s wife.) <verse number="17" style="v" />And Solomon built Gezer, Lower <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:10; 16:3; 21:22; 2 Chr. 8:5</char></note>Beth Horon, <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:44; 2 Chr. 8:4</char></note>Baalath, and Tadmor in the wilderness, in the land <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">Judah,</char> <verse number="19" style="v" />all the storage cities that Solomon had, cities for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:26; 2 Chr. 1:14</char></note>his chariots and cities for his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:26</char></note>cavalry, and whatever Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:1</char></note>desired to build in Jerusalem, in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:7</char></note>All the people <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> left of the Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites, who <char style="it">were</char> not of the children of Israel— <verse number="21" style="v" />that is, their descendants <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:21–36; 3:1</char></note>who were left in the land after them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:63; 17:12, 13</char></note>whom the children of Israel had not been able to destroy completely—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:28, 35</char></note>from these Solomon raised <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 2:55, 58; Neh. 7:57</char></note>forced labor, as it is to this day. <verse number="22" style="v" />But of the children of Israel Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 25:39)</char></note>made no forced laborers, because they <char style="it">were</char> men of war and his servants: his officers, his captains, commanders of his chariots, and his cavalry.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Others <char style="it">were</char> chiefs of the officials who <char style="it">were</char> over Solomon’s work: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:10</char></note>five hundred and fifty, who ruled over the people who did the work.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:1</char></note>Pharaoh’s daughter came up from the City of David to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:8</char></note>her house which <char style="it">Solomon</char> had built for her. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:9; 1 Kin. 11:27; 2 Chr. 32:5</char></note>Then he built the Millo.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:14–17; Deut. 16:16; 2 Chr. 8:12, 13</char></note>Now three times a year Solomon offered burnt offerings and peace offerings on the altar which he had built for the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and he burned incense with them <char style="it">on</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">altar</char> that <char style="it">was</char> before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. So he finished the temple.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:17, 18</char></note>King Solomon also built a fleet of ships at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:35; Deut. 2:8; 1 Kin. 22:48</char></note>Ezion Geber, which <char style="it">is</char> near Elath on the shore of the Red Sea, in the land of Edom. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:6, 9; 10:11</char></note>Then Hiram sent his servants with the fleet, seamen who knew the sea, to work with the servants of Solomon. <verse number="28" style="v" />And they went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 22:24</char></note>Ophir, and acquired four hundred and twenty talents of gold from there, and brought <char style="it">it</char> to King Solomon.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Queen of Sheba’s Praise of Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now when the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:1; Matt. 12:42; Luke 11:31</char></note>queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon concerning the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, she came <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 14:12; Ps. 49:4; Prov. 1:6</char></note>to test him with hard questions. <verse number="2" style="v" />She came to Jerusalem with a very great retinue, with camels that bore spices, very much gold, and precious stones; and when she came to Solomon, she spoke with him about all that was in her heart. <verse number="3" style="v" />So Solomon answered all her questions; there was nothing so difficult for the king that he could not explain <char style="it">it</char> to her. <verse number="4" style="v" />And when the queen of Sheba had seen all the wisdom of Solomon, the house that he had built, <verse number="5" style="v" />the food on his table, the seating of his servants, the service of his waiters and their apparel, his cupbearers, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 26:16; 2 Chr. 9:4</char></note>and his entryway by which he went up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, there was no more spirit in her. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then she said to the king: “It was a true report which I heard in my own land about your words and your wisdom. <verse number="7" style="v" />However I did not believe the words until I came and saw with my own eyes; and indeed the half was not told me. Your wisdom and prosperity exceed the fame of which I heard. <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 8:34</char></note>Happy <char style="it">are</char> your men and happy <char style="it">are</char> these your servants, who stand continually before you <char style="it">and</char> hear your wisdom! <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:7</char></note>Blessed be the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 22:20</char></note>delighted in you, setting you on the throne of Israel! Because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has loved Israel forever, therefore He made you king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:15; Ps. 72:2; (Prov. 8:15)</char></note>to do justice and righteousness.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Then she <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 72:10, 15</char></note>gave the king one hundred and twenty talents of gold, spices in great quantity, and precious stones. There never again came such abundance of spices as the queen of Sheba gave to King Solomon. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:27, 28; Job 22:24</char></note>Also, the ships of Hiram, which brought gold from Ophir, brought great quantities of almug wood and precious stones from Ophir. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:11</char></note>And the king made steps of the almug wood for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and for the king’s house, also harps and stringed instruments for singers. There never again came such <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:10</char></note>almug wood, nor has the like been seen to this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Now King Solomon gave the queen of Sheba all she desired, whatever she asked, besides what Solomon had given her according to the royal generosity. So she turned and went to her own country, she and her servants.</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Great Wealth</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />The weight of gold that came to Solomon yearly was six hundred and sixty-six talents of gold, <verse number="15" style="v" />besides <char style="it">that</char> from the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 1:16</char></note>traveling merchants, from the income of traders, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:24; Ps. 72:10</char></note>from all the kings of Arabia, and from the governors of the country.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And King Solomon made two hundred large shields <char style="it">of</char> hammered gold; six hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of gold went into each shield. <verse number="17" style="v" />He also <char style="it">made</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:26</char></note>three hundred shields <char style="it">of</char> hammered gold; three minas of gold went into each shield. The king put them in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:2</char></note>House of the Forest of Lebanon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:22; 2 Chr. 9:17; Ps. 45:8</char></note>Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with pure gold. <verse number="19" style="v" />The throne had six steps, and the top of the throne <char style="it">was</char> round at the back; <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">were</char> armrests on either side of the place of the seat, and two lions stood beside the armrests. <verse number="20" style="v" />Twelve lions stood there, one on each side of the six steps; nothing like <char style="it">this</char> had been made for any <char style="it">other</char> kingdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:20</char></note>All King Solomon’s drinking vessels <char style="it">were</char> gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Lebanon <char style="it">were</char> pure gold. Not <char style="it">one</char> <char style="it">was</char> silver, for this was accounted as nothing in the days of Solomon. <verse number="22" style="v" />For the king had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 10:4; 2 Chr. 20:36</char></note>merchant ships at sea with the fleet of Hiram. Once every three years the merchant <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:26–28; 22:48; Ps. 72:10</char></note>ships came bringing gold, silver, ivory, apes, and monkeys. <verse number="23" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:12, 13; 4:30; 2 Chr. 1:12</char></note>King Solomon surpassed all the kings of the earth in riches and wisdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Now all the earth sought the presence of Solomon to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. <verse number="25" style="v" />Each man brought his present: articles of silver and gold, garments, armor, spices, horses, and mules, at a set rate year by year.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:26; 2 Chr. 1:14; 9:25</char></note>And Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 17:16); 1 Kin. 9:19</char></note>gathered chariots and horsemen; he had one thousand four hundred chariots and twelve thousand horsemen, whom he stationed in the chariot cities and with the king at Jerusalem. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 17:17); 2 Chr. 1:15–17</char></note>The king made silver <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">common</char> in Jerusalem as stones, and he made cedar trees as abundant as the sycamores which <char style="it">are</char> in the lowland.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 17:16); 2 Chr. 1:16; 9:28</char></note>Also Solomon had horses imported from Egypt and Keveh; the king’s merchants bought them in Keveh at the <char style="it">current</char> price. <verse number="29" style="v" />Now a chariot that was imported from Egypt cost six hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver, and a horse one hundred and fifty; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:4; 2 Kin. 7:6, 7</char></note>and thus, through their agents, they exported <char style="it">them</char> to all the kings of the Hittites and the kings of Syria.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Heart Turns from the <char style="sc">Lord</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Neh. 13:26)</char></note>King Solomon loved <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 17:17); 1 Kin. 3:1</char></note>many foreign women, as well as the daughter of Pharaoh: women of the Moabites, Ammonites, Edomites, Sidonians, <char style="it">and</char> Hittites— <verse number="2" style="v" />from the nations of whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said to the children of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:16; (Deut. 7:3, 4)</char></note>“You shall not intermarry with them, nor they with you. Surely they will turn away your hearts after their gods.” Solomon clung to these in love. <verse number="3" style="v" />And he had seven hundred wives, princesses, and three hundred concubines; and his wives turned away his heart. <verse number="4" style="v" />For it was so, when Solomon was old, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 17:17; Neh. 13:26)</char></note>that his wives turned his heart after other gods; and his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:61</char></note>heart was not loyal to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:4</char></note>as <char style="it">was</char> the heart of his father David. <verse number="5" style="v" />For Solomon went after <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:13; 1 Kin. 11:33</char></note>Ashtoreth the goddess of the Sidonians, and after <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 20:2–5)</char></note>Milcom the abomination of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:13</char></note>Ammonites. <verse number="6" style="v" />Solomon did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and did not fully follow the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as <char style="it">did</char> his father David. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:52</char></note>Then Solomon built a high place for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:29; Judg. 11:24</char></note>Chemosh the abomination of Moab, on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:13</char></note>the hill that <char style="it">is</char> east of Jerusalem, and for Molech the abomination of the people of Ammon. <verse number="8" style="v" />And he did likewise for all his foreign wives, who burned incense and sacrificed to their gods.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> became angry with Solomon, because his heart had turned from the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:5; 9:2</char></note>who had appeared to him twice, <verse number="10" style="v" />and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:12; 9:6, 7</char></note>had commanded him concerning this thing, that he should not go after other gods; but he did not keep what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded. <verse number="11" style="v" />Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Solomon, “Because you have done this, and have not kept My covenant and My statutes, which I have commanded you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:31; 12:15, 16</char></note>I will surely tear the kingdom away from you and give it to your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:31, 37</char></note>servant. <verse number="12" style="v" />Nevertheless I will not do it in your days, for the sake of your father David; I will tear it out of the hand of your son. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:15; 1 Chr. 17:13; Ps. 89:33</char></note>However I will not tear away the whole kingdom; I will give <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:20</char></note>one tribe to your son <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:15, 16</char></note>for the sake of My servant David, and for the sake of Jerusalem <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:11; 1 Kin. 9:3; 14:21</char></note>which I have chosen.”</para>
	<para style="s">Adversaries of Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 5:26</char></note>raised up an adversary against Solomon, Hadad the Edomite; he <char style="it">was</char> a descendant of the king in Edom. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:14; 1 Chr. 18:12, 13</char></note>For it happened, when David was in Edom, and Joab the commander of the army had gone up to bury the slain, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 24:18, 19; (Deut. 20:13)</char></note>after he had killed every male in Edom <verse number="16" style="v" />(because for six months Joab remained there with all Israel, until he had cut down every male in Edom), <verse number="17" style="v" />that Hadad fled to go to Egypt, he and certain Edomites of his father’s servants with him. Hadad <char style="it">was</char> still a little child. <verse number="18" style="v" />Then they arose from Midian and came to Paran; and they took men with them from Paran and came to Egypt, to Pharaoh king of Egypt, who gave him a house, apportioned food for him, and gave him land. <verse number="19" style="v" />And Hadad found great favor in the sight of Pharaoh, so that he gave him as wife the sister of his own wife, that is, the sister of Queen Tahpenes. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then the sister of Tahpenes bore him Genubath his son, whom Tahpenes weaned in Pharaoh’s house. And Genubath was in Pharaoh’s household among the sons of Pharaoh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:10, 34</char></note>So when Hadad heard in Egypt that David rested with his fathers, and that Joab the commander of the army was dead, Hadad said to Pharaoh, “Let me depart, that I may go to my own country.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then Pharaoh said to him, “But what have you lacked with me, that suddenly you seek to go to your own country?”</para>
	<para style="p">So he answered, “Nothing, but do let me go anyway.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And God raised up <char style="it">another</char> adversary against him, Rezon the son of Eliadah, who had fled from his lord, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:3; 10:16</char></note>Hadadezer king of Zobah. <verse number="24" style="v" />So he gathered men to him and became captain over a band <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">raiders,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:3; 10:8, 18</char></note>when David killed those <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">Zobah.</char> And they went to Damascus and dwelt there, and reigned in Damascus. <verse number="25" style="v" />He was an adversary of Israel all the days of Solomon (besides the trouble that Hadad <char style="it">caused</char>); and he abhorred Israel, and reigned over Syria.</para>
	<para style="s">Jeroboam’s Rebellion</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then Solomon’s servant, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:2</char></note>Jeroboam the son of Nebat, an Ephraimite from Zereda, whose mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Zeruah, a widow, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:11; 2 Chr. 13:6</char></note>also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:21</char></note>rebelled against the king.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />And this <char style="it">is</char> what caused him to rebel against the king: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:15, 24</char></note>Solomon had built the Millo <char style="it">and</char> repaired the damages to the City of David his father. <verse number="28" style="v" />The man Jeroboam <char style="it">was</char> a mighty man of valor; and Solomon, seeing that the young man was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 22:29)</char></note>industrious, made him the officer over all the labor force of the house of Joseph.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Now it happened at that time, when Jeroboam went out of Jerusalem, that the prophet <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:15; 14:2; 2 Chr. 9:29</char></note>Ahijah the Shilonite met him on the way; and he had clothed himself with a new garment, and the two <char style="it">were</char> alone in the field. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then Ahijah took hold of the new garment that <char style="it">was</char> on him, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 15:27, 28; 24:5</char></note>tore it <char style="it">into</char> twelve pieces. <verse number="31" style="v" />And he said to Jeroboam, “Take for yourself ten pieces, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:11, 13</char></note>thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel: ‘Behold, I will tear the kingdom out of the hand of Solomon and will give ten tribes to you <verse number="32" style="v" />(but he shall have one tribe for the sake of My servant David, and for the sake of Jerusalem, the city which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel), <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 7:3; 1 Kin. 11:5–8</char></note>because they have forsaken Me, and worshiped Ashtoreth the goddess of the Sidonians, Chemosh the god of the Moabites, and Milcom the god of the people of Ammon, and have not walked in My ways to do <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">is</char> right in My eyes and <char style="it">keep</char> My statutes and My judgments, as <char style="it">did</char> his father David. <verse number="34" style="v" />However I will not take the whole kingdom out of his hand, because I have made him ruler all the days of his life for the sake of My servant David, whom I chose because he kept My commandments and My statutes. <verse number="35" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:16, 17</char></note>I will take the kingdom out of his son’s hand and give it to you—ten tribes. <verse number="36" style="v" />And to his son I will give one tribe, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Kin. 15:4; 2 Kin. 8:19)</char></note>My servant David may always have a lamp before Me in Jerusalem, the city which I have chosen for Myself, to put My name there. <verse number="37" style="v" />So I will take you, and you shall reign over all your heart desires, and you shall be king over Israel. <verse number="38" style="v" />Then it shall be, if you heed all that I command you, walk in My ways, and do <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">is</char> right in My sight, to keep My statutes and My commandments, as My servant David did, then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:8; Josh. 1:5</char></note>I will be with you and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:11, 27</char></note>build for you an enduring house, as I built for David, and will give Israel to you. <verse number="39" style="v" />And I will afflict the descendants of David because of this, but not forever.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" />Solomon therefore sought to kill Jeroboam. But Jeroboam arose and fled to Egypt, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:17; 14:25; 2 Chr. 12:2–9</char></note>Shishak king of Egypt, and was in Egypt until the death of Solomon.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:29</char></note>the rest of the acts of Solomon, all that he did, and his wisdom, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the acts of Solomon? <verse number="42" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:30</char></note>And the period that Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel <char style="it">was</char> forty years. <verse number="43" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:10; 2 Chr. 9:31</char></note>Then Solomon rested with his fathers, and was buried in the City of David his father. And Rehoboam his son reigned in his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:21; 2 Chr. 10:1</char></note>place.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Revolt Against Rehoboam</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 10:1</char></note>Rehoboam went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:6</char></note>Shechem, for all Israel had gone to Shechem to make him king. <verse number="2" style="v" />So it happened, when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:26</char></note>Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard <char style="it">it</char> (he was still in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:40</char></note>Egypt, for he had fled from the presence of King Solomon and had been dwelling in Egypt ), <verse number="3" style="v" />that they sent and called him. Then Jeroboam and the whole assembly of Israel came and spoke to Rehoboam, saying, <verse number="4" style="v" />“Your father made our <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 8:11–18; 1 Kin. 4:7; 5:13–15</char></note>yoke heavy; now therefore, lighten the burdensome service of your father, and his heavy yoke which he put on us, and we will serve you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So he said to them, “Depart <char style="it">for</char> three days, then come back to me.” And the people departed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then King Rehoboam consulted the elders who stood before his father Solomon while he still lived, and he said, “How do you advise <char style="it">me</char> to answer these people?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And they spoke to him, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 10:7; (Prov. 15:1)</char></note>“If you will be a servant to these people today, and serve them, and answer them, and speak good words to them, then they will be your servants forever.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />But he rejected the advice which the elders had given him, and consulted the young men who had grown up with him, who stood before him. <verse number="9" style="v" />And he said to them, “What advice do you give? How should we answer this people who have spoken to me, saying, ‘Lighten the yoke which your father put on us’?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Then the young men who had grown up with him spoke to him, saying, “Thus you should speak to this people who have spoken to you, saying, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, but you make <char style="it">it</char> lighter on us’—thus you shall say to them: ‘My little <char style="it">finger</char> shall be thicker than my father’s waist! <verse number="11" style="v" />And now, whereas my father put a heavy yoke on you, I will add to your yoke; my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scourges!’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king had directed, saying, “Come back to me the third day.” <verse number="13" style="v" />Then the king answered the people roughly, and rejected the advice which the elders had given him; <verse number="14" style="v" />and he spoke to them according to the advice of the young men, saying, “My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to your yoke; my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scourges!” <verse number="15" style="v" />So the king did not listen to the people; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:30; Judg. 14:4; 1 Kin. 12:24; 2 Chr. 10:15</char></note>the turn <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">events</char> was from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that He might fulfill His word, which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:11, 29, 31</char></note>spoken by Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Now when all Israel saw that the king did not listen to them, the people answered the king, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:1</char></note>“What share have we in David?</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">We</char> <char style="it">have</char> no inheritance in the son of Jesse.</para>
	<para style="q2">To your tents, O Israel!</para>
	<para style="q2">Now, see to your own house, O David!”</para>
	<para style="p">So Israel departed to their tents. <verse number="17" style="v" />But Rehoboam reigned over <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:13, 36; 2 Chr. 11:14–17</char></note>the children of Israel who dwelt in the cities of Judah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then King Rehoboam <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:6; 5:14</char></note>sent Adoram, who <char style="it">was</char> in charge of the revenue; but all Israel stoned him with stones, and he died. Therefore King Rehoboam mounted his chariot in haste to flee to Jerusalem. <verse number="19" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:21</char></note>Israel has been in rebellion against the house of David to this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Now it came to pass when all Israel heard that Jeroboam had come back, they sent for him and called him to the congregation, and made him king over all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:21</char></note>Israel. There was none who followed the house of David, but the tribe of Judah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:13, 32, 36</char></note>only.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:1–4</char></note>Rehoboam came to Jerusalem, he assembled all the house of Judah with the tribe of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 19:17</char></note>Benjamin, one hundred and eighty thousand chosen <char style="it">men</char> who were warriors, to fight against the house of Israel, that he might restore the kingdom to Rehoboam the son of Solomon. <verse number="22" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:2; 12:5–7</char></note>the word of God came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying, <verse number="23" style="v" />“Speak to Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, to all the house of Judah and Benjamin, and to the rest of the people, saying, <verse number="24" style="v" />‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: “You shall not go up nor fight against your brethren the children of Israel. Let every man return to his house, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:15</char></note>for this thing is from Me.” ’ ” Therefore they obeyed the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and turned back, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="s">Jeroboam’s Gold Calves</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Then Jeroboam <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 12:6; Judg. 9:45–49; 1 Kin. 12:1</char></note>built Shechem in the mountains of Ephraim, and dwelt there. Also he went out from there and built <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:30, 31; Judg. 8:8, 17</char></note>Penuel. <verse number="26" style="v" />And Jeroboam said in his heart, “Now the kingdom may return to the house of David: <verse number="27" style="v" />If these people <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 12:5–7, 14)</char></note>go up to offer sacrifices in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at Jerusalem, then the heart of this people will turn back to their lord, Rehoboam king of Judah, and they will kill me and go back to Rehoboam king of Judah.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Therefore the king asked advice, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:29; 17:16; (Hos. 8:4–7)</char></note>made two calves of gold, and said to the people, “It is too much for you to go up to Jerusalem. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:4, 8</char></note>Here are your gods, O Israel, which brought you up from the land of Egypt!” <verse number="29" style="v" />And he set up one in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 28:19</char></note>Bethel, and the other he put in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:26–31</char></note>Dan. <verse number="30" style="v" />Now this thing became <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:34; 2 Kin. 17:21</char></note>a sin, for the people went <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">worship</char> before the one as far as Dan. <verse number="31" style="v" />He made shrines on the high places, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Num. 3:10; 17:1–11); Judg. 17:5; 1 Kin. 13:33; 2 Kin. 17:32; 2 Chr. 11:14, 15</char></note>and made priests from every class of people, who were not of the sons of Levi.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />Jeroboam ordained a feast on the fifteenth day of the eighth month, like <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:33, 34; Num. 29:12; 1 Kin. 8:2, 5</char></note>the feast that <char style="it">was</char> in Judah, and offered sacrifices on the altar. So he did at Bethel, sacrificing to the calves that he had made. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Amos 7:10–13</char></note>And at Bethel he installed the priests of the high places which he had made. <verse number="33" style="v" />So he made offerings on the altar which he had made at Bethel on the fifteenth day of the eighth month, in the month which he had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:39</char></note>devised in his own heart. And he ordained a feast for the children of Israel, and offered sacrifices on the altar and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:1</char></note>burned incense.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Message of the Man of God</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:17</char></note>a man of God went from Judah to Bethel by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:32, 33</char></note>and Jeroboam stood by the altar to burn incense. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then he cried out against the altar by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said, “O altar, altar! Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Behold, a child, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:15, 16</char></note>Josiah by name, shall be born to the house of David; and on you he shall sacrifice the priests of the high places who burn incense on you, and men’s bones shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 26:30)</char></note>burned on you.’ ” <verse number="3" style="v" />And he gave <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 4:1–5; Judg. 6:17; Is. 7:14; 38:7; John 2:18; 1 Cor. 1:22</char></note>a sign the same day, saying, “This <char style="it">is</char> the sign which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has spoken: Surely the altar shall split apart, and the ashes on it shall be poured out.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So it came to pass when King Jeroboam heard the saying of the man of God, who cried out against the altar in Bethel, that he stretched out his hand from the altar, saying, “Arrest him!” Then his hand, which he stretched out toward him, withered, so that he could not pull it back to himself. <verse number="5" style="v" />The altar also was split apart, and the ashes poured out from the altar, according to the sign which the man of God had given by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then the king answered and said to the man of God, “Please <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 8:8; 9:28; 10:17; Num. 21:7; Jer. 37:3; Acts 8:24; (James 5:16)</char></note>entreat the favor of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, and pray for me, that my hand may be restored to me.”</para>
	<para style="p">So the man of God entreated the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and the king’s hand was restored to him, and became as before. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then the king said to the man of God, “Come home with me and refresh yourself, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:7; 2 Kin. 5:15</char></note>I will give you a reward.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />But the man of God said to the king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:18; 24:13; 1 Kin. 13:16, 17</char></note>“If you were to give me half your house, I would not go in with you; nor would I eat bread nor drink water in this place. <verse number="9" style="v" />For so it was commanded me by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Cor. 5:11)</char></note>‘You shall not eat bread, nor drink water, nor return by the same way you came.’ ” <verse number="10" style="v" />So he went another way and did not return by the way he came to Bethel.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of the Man of God</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Now an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:25</char></note>old prophet dwelt in Bethel, and his sons came and told him all the works that the man of God had done that day in Bethel; they also told their father the words which he had spoken to the king. <verse number="12" style="v" />And their father said to them, “Which way did he go?” For his sons had seen which way the man of God went who came from Judah. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then he said to his sons, “Saddle the donkey for me.” So they saddled the donkey for him; and he rode on it, <verse number="14" style="v" />and went after the man of God, and found him sitting under an oak. Then he said to him, “<char style="it">Are</char> you the man of God who came from Judah?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “I <char style="it">am.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then he said to him, “Come home with me and eat bread.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And he said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:8, 9</char></note>“I cannot return with you nor go in with you; neither can I eat bread nor drink water with you in this place. <verse number="17" style="v" />For I have been told <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:35; 1 Thess. 4:15</char></note>by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘You shall not eat bread nor drink water there, nor return by going the way you came.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />He said to him, “I too <char style="it">am</char> a prophet as you <char style="it">are,</char> and an angel spoke to me by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, ‘Bring him back with you to your house, that he may eat bread and drink water.’ ” (He was lying to him.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />So he went back with him, and ate bread in his house, and drank water.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Now it happened, as they sat at the table, that the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to the prophet who had brought him back; <verse number="21" style="v" />and he cried out to the man of God who came from Judah, saying, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Because you have disobeyed the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and have not kept the commandment which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God commanded you, <verse number="22" style="v" />but you came back, ate bread, and drank water in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:9</char></note>place of which <char style="it">the</char> <char style="sc"><char style="it">Lord</char></char> said to you, “Eat no bread and drink no water,” your corpse shall not come to the tomb of your fathers.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />So it was, after he had eaten bread and after he had drunk, that he saddled the donkey for him, the prophet whom he had brought back. <verse number="24" style="v" />When he was gone, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:36</char></note>a lion met him on the road and killed him. And his corpse was thrown on the road, and the donkey stood by it. The lion also stood by the corpse. <verse number="25" style="v" />And there, men passed by and saw the corpse thrown on the road, and the lion standing by the corpse. Then they went and told <char style="it">it</char> in the city where the old prophet dwelt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Now when the prophet who had brought him back from the way heard <char style="it">it,</char> he said, “It <char style="it">is</char> the man of God who was disobedient to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has delivered him to the lion, which has torn him and killed him, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He spoke to him.” <verse number="27" style="v" />And he spoke to his sons, saying, “Saddle the donkey for me.” So they saddled <char style="it">it.</char> <verse number="28" style="v" />Then he went and found his corpse thrown on the road, and the donkey and the lion standing by the corpse. The lion had not eaten the corpse nor torn the donkey. <verse number="29" style="v" />And the prophet took up the corpse of the man of God, laid it on the donkey, and brought it back. So the old prophet came to the city to mourn, and to bury him. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then he laid the corpse in his own tomb; and they mourned over him, <char style="it">saying,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 22:18</char></note>“Alas, my brother!” <verse number="31" style="v" />So it was, after he had buried him, that he spoke to his sons, saying, “When I am dead, then bury me in the tomb where the man of God <char style="it">is</char> buried; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ruth 1:17; 2 Kin. 23:17, 18</char></note>lay my bones beside his bones. <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:2; 2 Kin. 23:16, 19</char></note>For the saying which he cried out by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> against the altar in Bethel, and against all the shrines on the high places which <char style="it">are</char> in the cities of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:24; John 4:5; Acts 8:14</char></note>Samaria, will surely come to pass.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:31, 32; 2 Chr. 11:15; 13:9</char></note>After this event Jeroboam did not turn from his evil way, but again he made priests from every class of people for the high places; whoever wished, he consecrated him, and he became <char style="it">one</char> of the priests of the high places. <verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:30; 2 Kin. 17:21</char></note>And this thing was the sin of the house of Jeroboam, so as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Kin. 14:10; 15:29, 30)</char></note>to exterminate and destroy <char style="it">it</char> from the face of the earth.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Judgment on the House of Jeroboam</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />At that time Abijah the son of Jeroboam became sick. <verse number="2" style="v" />And Jeroboam said to his wife, “Please arise, and disguise yourself, that they may not recognize you as the wife of Jeroboam, and go to Shiloh. Indeed, Ahijah the prophet <char style="it">is</char> there, who told me that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:29–31</char></note><char style="it">I</char> <char style="it">would</char> <char style="it">be</char> king over this people. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:7, 8; 1 Kin. 13:7; 2 Kin. 4:42</char></note>Also take with you ten loaves, <char style="it">some</char> cakes, and a jar of honey, and go to him; he will tell you what will become of the child.” <verse number="4" style="v" />And Jeroboam’s wife did so; she arose <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:29</char></note>and went to Shiloh, and came to the house of Ahijah. But Ahijah could not see, for his eyes were glazed by reason of his age.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said to Ahijah, “Here is the wife of Jeroboam, coming to ask you something about her son, for he <char style="it">is</char> sick. Thus and thus you shall say to her; for it will be, when she comes in, that she will pretend <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">be</char> another <char style="it">woman.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And so it was, when Ahijah heard the sound of her footsteps as she came through the door, he said, “Come in, wife of Jeroboam. Why do you pretend <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">be</char> another <char style="it">person?</char> For I <char style="it">have</char> <char style="it">been</char> sent to you <char style="it">with</char> bad <char style="it">news.</char> <verse number="7" style="v" />Go, tell Jeroboam, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 12:7, 8; 1 Kin. 16:2</char></note>“Because I exalted you from among the people, and made you ruler over My people Israel, <verse number="8" style="v" />and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:31</char></note>tore the kingdom away from the house of David, and gave it to you; and <char style="it">yet</char> you have not been as My servant David, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:33, 38; 15:5</char></note>who kept My commandments and who followed Me with all his heart, to do only <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in My eyes; <verse number="9" style="v" />but you have done more evil than all who were before you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28; 2 Chr. 11:15</char></note>for you have gone and made for yourself other gods and molded images to provoke Me to anger, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:6; Neh. 9:26; Ps. 50:17</char></note>have cast Me behind your back— <verse number="10" style="v" />therefore behold! <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:29</char></note>I will bring disaster on the house of Jeroboam, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:21; 2 Kin. 9:8</char></note>will cut off from Jeroboam every male in Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:36; 2 Kin. 14:26</char></note>bond and free; I will take away the remnant of the house of Jeroboam, as one takes away refuse until it is all gone. <verse number="11" style="v" />The dogs shall eat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:4; 21:24</char></note>whoever belongs to Jeroboam and dies in the city, and the birds of the air shall eat whoever dies in the field; for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has spoken!” ’ <verse number="12" style="v" />Arise therefore, go to your own house. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:17</char></note>When your feet enter the city, the child shall die. <verse number="13" style="v" />And all Israel shall mourn for him and bury him, for he is the only one of Jeroboam who shall come to the grave, because in him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:12; 19:3</char></note>there is found something good toward the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel in the house of Jeroboam.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:27–29</char></note>“Moreover the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will raise up for Himself a king over Israel who shall cut off the house of Jeroboam; this is the day. What? Even now! <verse number="15" style="v" />For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will strike Israel, as a reed is shaken in the water. He will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 29:28; 2 Kin. 17:6; Ps. 52:5</char></note>uproot Israel from this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Josh. 23:15, 16)</char></note>good land which He gave to their fathers, and will scatter them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:29</char></note>beyond the River, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 34:13, 14; Deut. 12:3)</char></note>because they have made their wooden images, provoking the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to anger. <verse number="16" style="v" />And He will give Israel up because of the sins of Jeroboam, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:30; 13:34; 15:30, 34; 16:2</char></note>who sinned and who made Israel sin.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then Jeroboam’s wife arose and departed, and came to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:21, 33; 16:6, 8, 15, 23; Song 6:4</char></note>Tirzah. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:12</char></note>When she came to the threshold of the house, the child died. <verse number="18" style="v" />And they buried him; and all Israel mourned for him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:13</char></note>according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He spoke through His servant Ahijah the prophet.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Jeroboam</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jeroboam, how he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:30; 2 Chr. 13:2–20</char></note>made war and how he reigned, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel. <verse number="20" style="v" />The period that Jeroboam reigned <char style="it">was</char> twenty-two years. So he rested with his fathers. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:25</char></note>Then Nadab his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Rehoboam Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And Rehoboam the son of Solomon reigned in Judah. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:13</char></note>Rehoboam <char style="it">was</char> forty-one years old when he became king. He reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:32, 36</char></note>which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put His name there. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:31</char></note>His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Naamah, an Ammonitess. <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:1, 14</char></note>Now Judah did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:21; Ps. 78:58; 1 Cor. 10:22</char></note>provoked Him to jealousy with their sins which they committed, more than all that their fathers had done. <verse number="23" style="v" />For they also built for themselves <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:2; Ezek. 16:24, 25</char></note>high places, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 16:22)</char></note><char style="it">sacred</char> pillars, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Kin. 17:9, 10)</char></note>wooden images on every high hill and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 57:5; Jer. 2:20</char></note>under every green tree. <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:5; Deut. 23:17; 1 Kin. 15:12; 22:46; 2 Kin. 23:7</char></note>And there were also perverted persons in the land. They did according to all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:18</char></note>abominations of the nations which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had cast out before the children of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 9:4, 5)</char></note>Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:40; 2 Chr. 12:2</char></note>It happened in the fifth year of King Rehoboam <char style="it">that</char> Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem. <verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:18; 2 Chr. 12:9–11</char></note>And he took away the treasures of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the treasures of the king’s house; he took away everything. He also took away all the gold shields <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:17</char></note>which Solomon had made. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then King Rehoboam made bronze shields in their place, and committed <char style="it">them</char> to the hands of the captains of the guard, who guarded the doorway of the king’s house. <verse number="28" style="v" />And whenever the king entered the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the guards carried them, then brought them back into the guardroom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:15, 16</char></note>Now the rest of the acts of Rehoboam, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="30" style="v" />And there was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:21–24; 15:6</char></note>war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all <char style="it">their</char> days. <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:16</char></note>So Rehoboam rested with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the City of David. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:21</char></note>His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Naamah, an Ammonitess. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:16</char></note>Abijam his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Abijam Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:1</char></note>In the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam the son of Nebat, Abijam became king over Judah. <verse number="2" style="v" />He reigned three years in Jerusalem. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:20–22</char></note>His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:2</char></note>Maachah the granddaughter of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:21</char></note>Abishalom. <verse number="3" style="v" />And he walked in all the sins of his father, which he had done before him; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:4; Ps. 119:80</char></note>his heart was not loyal to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, as was the heart of his father David. <verse number="4" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 21:17; 1 Kin. 11:32, 36; 2 Chr. 21:7</char></note>for David’s sake the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God gave him a lamp in Jerusalem, by setting up his son after him and by establishing Jerusalem; <verse number="5" style="v" />because David <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:4; 14:8; Luke 1:6</char></note>did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and had not turned aside from anything that He commanded him all the days of his life, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 11:3, 15–17; 12:9, 10</char></note>except in the matter of Uriah the Hittite. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:30; 2 Chr. 12:15—13:20</char></note>And there was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all the days of his life. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:2–22</char></note>Now the rest of the acts of Abijam, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? And there was war between Abijam and Jeroboam.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:1</char></note>So Abijam rested with his fathers, and they buried him in the City of David. Then Asa his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Asa Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />In the twentieth year of Jeroboam king of Israel, Asa became king over Judah. <verse number="10" style="v" />And he reigned forty-one years in Jerusalem. His grandmother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Maachah the granddaughter of Abishalom. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:2</char></note>Asa did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as <char style="it">did</char> his father David. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 23:17; 1 Kin. 14:24; 22:46</char></note>And he banished the perverted persons from the land, and removed all the idols that his fathers had made. <verse number="13" style="v" />Also he removed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:16–18</char></note>Maachah his grandmother from <char style="it">being</char> queen mother, because she had made an obscene image of Asherah. And Asa cut down her obscene image and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:20</char></note>burned <char style="it">it</char> by the Brook Kidron. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:2; 22:43; 2 Kin. 12:3; 2 Chr. 15:17, 18</char></note>But the high places were not removed. Nevertheless Asa’s <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Sam. 16:7); 1 Kin. 8:61; 15:3</char></note>heart was loyal to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all his days. <verse number="15" style="v" />He also brought into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> the things which his father <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:51</char></note>had dedicated, and the things which he himself had dedicated: silver and gold and utensils.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Now there was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days. <verse number="17" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:1–6</char></note>Baasha king of Israel came up against Judah, and built <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:25; 1 Kin. 15:21, 22</char></note>Ramah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:26–29</char></note>that he might let none go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. <verse number="18" style="v" />Then Asa took all the silver and gold <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">was</char> left in the treasuries of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the treasuries of the king’s house, and delivered them into the hand of his servants. And King Asa sent them to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:17, 18; 2 Chr. 16:2</char></note>Ben-Hadad the son of Tabrimmon, the son of Hezion, king of Syria, who dwelt in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 14:15; 1 Kin. 11:23, 24</char></note>Damascus, saying, <verse number="19" style="v" />“<char style="it">Let</char> <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">be</char> a treaty between you and me, as there was between my father and your father. See, I have sent you a present of silver and gold. Come and break your treaty with Baasha king of Israel, so that he will withdraw from me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So Ben-Hadad heeded King Asa, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:1</char></note>sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel. He attacked <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:29</char></note>Ijon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:29; 1 Kin. 12:29</char></note>Dan, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 20:14, 15</char></note>Abel Beth Maachah, and all Chinneroth, with all the land of Naphtali. <verse number="21" style="v" />Now it happened, when Baasha heard <char style="it">it,</char> that he stopped building Ramah, and remained in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:17; 16:15–18</char></note>Tirzah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:6</char></note>Then King Asa made a proclamation throughout all Judah; none <char style="it">was</char> exempted. And they took away the stones and timber of Ramah, which Baasha had used for building; and with them King Asa built <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:17</char></note>Geba of Benjamin, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:26</char></note>Mizpah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />The rest of all the acts of Asa, all his might, all that he did, and the cities which he built, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:11–14</char></note>in the time of his old age he was diseased in his feet. <verse number="24" style="v" />So Asa rested with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the City of David his father. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:1</char></note>Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:41–44; Matt. 1:8</char></note>Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Nadab Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:20</char></note>Nadab the son of Jeroboam became king over Israel in the second year of Asa king of Judah, and he reigned over Israel two years. <verse number="26" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and walked in the way of his father, and in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28–33; 14:16</char></note>his sin by which he had made Israel sin.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:14</char></note>Then Baasha the son of Ahijah, of the house of Issachar, conspired against him. And Baasha killed him at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:44; 21:23; 1 Kin. 16:15</char></note>Gibbethon, which <char style="it">belonged</char> to the Philistines, while Nadab and all Israel laid siege to Gibbethon. <verse number="28" style="v" />Baasha killed him in the third year of Asa king of Judah, and reigned in his place. <verse number="29" style="v" />And it was so, when he became king, <char style="it">that</char> he killed all the house of Jeroboam. He did not leave to Jeroboam anyone that breathed, until he had destroyed him, according to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:10–14</char></note>the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He had spoken by His servant Ahijah the Shilonite, <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:9, 16</char></note>because of the sins of Jeroboam, which he had sinned and by which he had made Israel sin, because of his provocation with which he had provoked the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel to anger.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Nadab, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:16</char></note>And there was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days.</para>
	<para style="s">Baasha Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />In the third year of Asa king of Judah, Baasha the son of Ahijah became king over all Israel in Tirzah, and <char style="it">reigned</char> twenty-four years. <verse number="34" style="v" />He did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and walked in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:33; 14:16</char></note>the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin by which he had made Israel sin.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:7; 2 Chr. 19:2; 20:34</char></note>Jehu the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:7–10</char></note>Hanani, against <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:27</char></note>Baasha, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:8; 1 Kin. 14:7</char></note>“Inasmuch as I lifted you out of the dust and made you ruler over My people Israel, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:25–33; 15:34</char></note>you have walked in the way of Jeroboam, and have made My people Israel sin, to provoke Me to anger with their sins, <verse number="3" style="v" />surely I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:11; 21:21</char></note>take away the posterity of Baasha and the posterity of his house, and I will make your house like <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:10; 15:29</char></note>the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat. <verse number="4" style="v" />The dogs shall eat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:11; 21:24</char></note>whoever belongs to Baasha and dies in the city, and the birds of the air shall eat whoever dies in the fields.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Baasha, what he did, and his might, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:11</char></note><char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="6" style="v" />So Baasha rested with his fathers and was buried in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:17; 15:21</char></note>Tirzah. Then Elah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And also the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came by the prophet <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:1</char></note>Jehu the son of Hanani against Baasha and his house, because of all the evil that he did in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in provoking Him to anger with the work of his hands, in being like the house of Jeroboam, and because <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:27, 29</char></note>he killed them.</para>
	<para style="s">Elah Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />In the twenty-sixth year of Asa king of Judah, Elah the son of Baasha became king over Israel, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> two years in Tirzah. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:30–33</char></note>Now his servant Zimri, commander of half <char style="it">his</char> chariots, conspired against him as he was in Tirzah drinking himself drunk in the house of Arza, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 24:2; 39:4; 1 Kin. 18:3</char></note>steward of <char style="it">his</char> house in Tirzah. <verse number="10" style="v" />And Zimri went in and struck him and killed him in the twenty-seventh year of Asa king of Judah, and reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then it came to pass, when he began to reign, as soon as he was seated on his throne, <char style="it">that</char> he killed all the household of Baasha; he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:22</char></note>did not leave him one male, neither of his relatives nor of his friends. <verse number="12" style="v" />Thus Zimri destroyed all the household of Baasha, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:3</char></note>according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which He spoke against Baasha by Jehu the prophet, <verse number="13" style="v" />for all the sins of Baasha and the sins of Elah his son, by which they had sinned and by which they had made Israel sin, in provoking the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel to anger <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:21; 1 Sam. 12:21; (Is. 41:29; Jon. 2:8; 1 Cor. 8:4; 10:19)</char></note>with their idols.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Elah, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</para>
	<para style="s">Zimri Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />In the twenty-seventh year of Asa king of Judah, Zimri had reigned in Tirzah seven days. And the people <char style="it">were</char> encamped <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:27</char></note>against Gibbethon, which <char style="it">belonged</char> to the Philistines. <verse number="16" style="v" />Now the people <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> encamped heard it said, “Zimri has conspired and also has killed the king.” So all Israel made Omri, the commander of the army, king over Israel that day in the camp. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then Omri and all Israel with him went up from Gibbethon, and they besieged Tirzah. <verse number="18" style="v" />And it happened, when Zimri saw that the city was taken, that he went into the citadel of the king’s house and burned the king’s house down upon himself with fire, and died, <verse number="19" style="v" />because of the sins which he had committed in doing evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:26, 34</char></note>in walking in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:25–33</char></note>way of Jeroboam, and in his sin which he had committed to make Israel sin.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Zimri, and the treason he committed, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</para>
	<para style="s">Omri Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then the people of Israel were divided into two parts: half of the people followed Tibni the son of Ginath, to make him king, and half followed Omri. <verse number="22" style="v" />But the people who followed Omri prevailed over the people who followed Tibni the son of Ginath. So Tibni died and Omri reigned. <verse number="23" style="v" />In the thirty-first year of Asa king of Judah, Omri became king over Israel, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> twelve years. Six years he reigned in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:21; 2 Kin. 15:14</char></note>Tirzah. <verse number="24" style="v" />And he bought the hill of Samaria from Shemer for two talents of silver; then he built on the hill, and called the name of the city which he built, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:32; 2 Kin. 17:24; John 4:4</char></note>Samaria, after the name of Shemer, owner of the hill. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Mic. 6:16</char></note>Omri did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and did worse than all who <char style="it">were</char> before him. <verse number="26" style="v" />For he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:19</char></note>walked in all the ways of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and in his sin by which he had made Israel sin, provoking the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel to anger with their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:13</char></note>idols.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Omri which he did, and the might that he showed, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />So Omri rested with his fathers and was buried in Samaria. Then Ahab his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Ahab Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />In the thirty-eighth year of Asa king of Judah, Ahab the son of Omri became king over Israel; and Ahab the son of Omri reigned over Israel in Samaria twenty-two years. <verse number="30" style="v" />Now Ahab the son of Omri did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, more than all who <char style="it">were</char> before him. <verse number="31" style="v" />And it came to pass, as though it had been a trivial thing for him to walk in the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:3</char></note>that he took as wife Jezebel the daughter of Ethbaal, king of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:7; 1 Kin. 11:1–5</char></note>Sidonians; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:25, 26; 2 Kin. 10:18; 17:16</char></note>and he went and served Baal and worshiped him. <verse number="32" style="v" />Then he set up an altar for Baal in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:21, 26, 27</char></note>the temple of Baal, which he had built in Samaria. <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:6</char></note>And Ahab made a wooden image. Ahab <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:9; 16:29, 30; 21:25</char></note>did more to provoke the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel to anger than all the kings of Israel who were before him. <verse number="34" style="v" />In his days Hiel of Bethel built Jericho. He laid its foundation with Abiram his firstborn, and with his youngest <char style="it">son</char> Segub he set up its gates, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:26</char></note>according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which He had spoken through Joshua the son of Nun.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Elijah Proclaims a Drought</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Elijah the Tishbite, of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 12:4</char></note>inhabitants of Gilead, said to Ahab, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:10; 22:14; 2 Kin. 3:14; 5:20</char></note>“<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel lives, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 10:8</char></note>before whom I stand, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:1; James 5:17</char></note>there shall not be dew nor rain <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 4:25</char></note>these years, except at my word.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Then the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to him, saying, <verse number="3" style="v" />“Get away from here and turn eastward, and hide by the Brook Cherith, which flows into the Jordan. <verse number="4" style="v" />And it will be <char style="it">that</char> you shall drink from the brook, and I have commanded the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 38:41</char></note>ravens to feed you there.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So he went and did according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, for he went and stayed by the Brook Cherith, which flows into the Jordan. <verse number="6" style="v" />The ravens brought him bread and meat in the morning, and bread and meat in the evening; and he drank from the brook. <verse number="7" style="v" />And it happened after a while that the brook dried up, because there had been no rain in the land.</para>
	<para style="s">Elijah and the Widow</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to him, saying, <verse number="9" style="v" />“Arise, go to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Obad. 20; Luke 4:25, 26</char></note>Zarephath, which <char style="it">belongs</char> to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 24:6</char></note>Sidon, and dwell there. See, I have commanded a widow there to provide for you.” <verse number="10" style="v" />So he arose and went to Zarephath. And when he came to the gate of the city, indeed a widow <char style="it">was</char> there gathering sticks. And he called to her and said, “Please bring me a little water in a cup, that I may drink.” <verse number="11" style="v" />And as she was going to get <char style="it">it,</char> he called to her and said, “Please bring me a morsel of bread in your hand.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So she said, “As the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God lives, I do not have bread, only a handful of flour in a bin, and a little oil in a jar; and see, I <char style="it">am</char> gathering a couple of sticks that I may go in and prepare it for myself and my son, that we may eat it, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:23, 24</char></note>die.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And Elijah said to her, “Do not fear; go <char style="it">and</char> do as you have said, but make me a small cake from it first, and bring <char style="it">it</char> to me; and afterward make <char style="it">some</char> for yourself and your son. <verse number="14" style="v" />For thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: ‘The bin of flour shall not be used up, nor shall the jar of oil run dry, until the day the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sends rain on the earth.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />So she went away and did according to the word of Elijah; and she and he and her household ate for <char style="it">many</char> days. <verse number="16" style="v" />The bin of flour was not used up, nor did the jar of oil run dry, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He spoke by Elijah.</para>
	<para style="s">Elijah Revives the Widow’s Son</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Now it happened after these things <char style="it">that</char> the son of the woman who owned the house became sick. And his sickness was so serious that there was no breath left in him. <verse number="18" style="v" />So she said to Elijah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 5:8</char></note>“What have I to do with you, O man of God? Have you come to me to bring my sin to remembrance, and to kill my son?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And he said to her, “Give me your son.” So he took him out of her arms and carried him to the upper room where he was staying, and laid him on his own bed. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then he cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and said, “O <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, have You also brought tragedy on the widow with whom I lodge, by killing her son?” <verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:34, 35; Acts 20:10</char></note>And he stretched himself out on the child three times, and cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and said, “O <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, I pray, let this child’s soul come back to him.” <verse number="22" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> heard the voice of Elijah; and the soul of the child came back to him, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 7:14, 15; Heb. 11:35</char></note>revived.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And Elijah took the child and brought him down from the upper room into the house, and gave him to his mother. And Elijah said, “See, your son lives!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Then the woman said to Elijah, “Now by this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">John 2:11; 3:2; 16:30</char></note>I know that you <char style="it">are</char> a man of God, <char style="it">and</char> that the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in your mouth <char style="it">is</char> the truth.”</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Elijah’s Message to Ahab</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass <char style="it">after</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 17:1; Luke 4:25; James 5:17</char></note>many days that the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to Elijah, in the third year, saying, “Go, present yourself to Ahab, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:12</char></note>I will send rain on the earth.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />So Elijah went to present himself to Ahab; and <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> a severe famine in Samaria. <verse number="3" style="v" />And Ahab had called Obadiah, who <char style="it">was</char> in charge of <char style="it">his</char> house. (Now Obadiah feared the <char style="sc">Lord</char> greatly. <verse number="4" style="v" />For so it was, while Jezebel massacred the prophets of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that Obadiah had taken one hundred prophets and hidden them, fifty to a cave, and had fed them with bread and water.) <verse number="5" style="v" />And Ahab had said to Obadiah, “Go into the land to all the springs of water and to all the brooks; perhaps we may find grass to keep the horses and mules alive, so that we will not have to kill any livestock.” <verse number="6" style="v" />So they divided the land between them to explore it; Ahab went one way by himself, and Obadiah went another way by himself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Now as Obadiah was on his way, suddenly Elijah met him; and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 1:6–8</char></note>recognized him, and fell on his face, and said, “<char style="it">Is</char> that you, my lord Elijah?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And he answered him, “<char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> I. Go, tell your master, ‘Elijah <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">here.</char>’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So he said, “How have I sinned, that you are delivering your servant into the hand of Ahab, to kill me? <verse number="10" style="v" /><char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God lives, there is no nation or kingdom where my master has not sent someone to hunt for you; and when they said, ‘<char style="it">He</char> <char style="it">is</char> not <char style="it">here,</char>’ he took an oath from the kingdom or nation that they could not find you. <verse number="11" style="v" />And now you say, ‘Go, tell your master, “Elijah <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">here</char>” ’! <verse number="12" style="v" />And it shall come to pass, <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">soon</char> <char style="it">as</char> I am gone from you, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:16; Ezek. 3:12, 14; Matt. 4:1; Acts 8:39</char></note>the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will carry you to a place I do not know; so when I go and tell Ahab, and he cannot find you, he will kill me. But I your servant have feared the <char style="sc">Lord</char> from my youth. <verse number="13" style="v" />Was it not reported to my lord what I did when Jezebel killed the prophets of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, how I hid one hundred men of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s prophets, fifty to a cave, and fed them with bread and water? <verse number="14" style="v" />And now you say, ‘Go, tell your master, “Elijah <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">here.</char>” ’ He will kill me!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then Elijah said, “<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> of hosts lives, before whom I stand, I will surely present myself to him today.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So Obadiah went to meet Ahab, and told him; and Ahab went to meet Elijah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then it happened, when Ahab saw Elijah, that Ahab said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:20</char></note>“<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">that</char> you, O <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:25; Acts 16:20</char></note>troubler of Israel?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And he answered, “I have not troubled Israel, but you and your father’s house <char style="it">have,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:30–33; (2 Chr. 15:2)</char></note>in that you have forsaken the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and have followed the Baals. <verse number="19" style="v" />Now therefore, send <char style="it">and</char> gather all Israel to me on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:26; 2 Kin. 2:25</char></note>Mount Carmel, the four hundred and fifty prophets of Baal, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:33</char></note>and the four hundred prophets of Asherah, who eat at Jezebel’s table.”</para>
	<para style="s">Elijah’s Mount Carmel Victory</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So Ahab sent for all the children of Israel, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:6</char></note>gathered the prophets together on Mount Carmel. <verse number="21" style="v" />And Elijah came to all the people, and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:41; (Matt. 6:24)</char></note>“How long will you falter between two opinions? If the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> God, follow Him; but if Baal, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:15</char></note>follow him.” But the people answered him not a word. <verse number="22" style="v" />Then Elijah said to the people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:10, 14</char></note>“I alone am left a prophet of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:19</char></note>but Baal’s prophets <char style="it">are</char> four hundred and fifty men. <verse number="23" style="v" />Therefore let them give us two bulls; and let them choose one bull for themselves, cut it in pieces, and lay <char style="it">it</char> on the wood, but put no fire <char style="it">under</char> <char style="it">it;</char> and I will prepare the other bull, and lay <char style="it">it</char> on the wood, but put no fire <char style="it">under</char> <char style="it">it.</char> <verse number="24" style="v" />Then you call on the name of your gods, and I will call on the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and the God who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:38; 1 Chr. 21:26</char></note>answers by fire, He is God.”</para>
	<para style="p">So all the people answered and said, “It is well spoken.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Now Elijah said to the prophets of Baal, “Choose one bull for yourselves and prepare <char style="it">it</char> first, for you <char style="it">are</char> many; and call on the name of your god, but put no fire <char style="it">under</char> <char style="it">it.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />So they took the bull which was given them, and they prepared <char style="it">it,</char> and called on the name of Baal from morning even till noon, saying, “O Baal, hear us!” But <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 115:5; Jer. 10:5; (1 Cor. 8:4)</char></note>no voice; no one answered. Then they leaped about the altar which they had made.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />And so it was, at noon, that Elijah mocked them and said, “Cry aloud, for he <char style="it">is</char> a god; either he is meditating, or he is busy, or he is on a journey, <char style="it">or</char> perhaps he is sleeping and must be awakened.” <verse number="28" style="v" />So they cried aloud, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 19:28; Deut. 14:1)</char></note>cut themselves, as was their custom, with knives and lances, until the blood gushed out on them. <verse number="29" style="v" />And when midday was past, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:39, 41</char></note>they prophesied until the <char style="it">time</char> of the offering of the <char style="it">evening</char> sacrifice. But <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:26</char></note>no voice; no one answered, no one paid attention.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Then Elijah said to all the people, “Come near to me.” So all the people came near to him. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:10, 14; 2 Chr. 33:16</char></note>And he repaired the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">was</char> broken down. <verse number="31" style="v" />And Elijah took twelve stones, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, to whom the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had come, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:28; 35:10; 2 Kin. 17:34</char></note>“Israel shall be your name.” <verse number="32" style="v" />Then with the stones he built an altar <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 20:25; Col. 3:17)</char></note>in the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and he made a trench around the altar large enough to hold two seahs of seed. <verse number="33" style="v" />And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 22:9; Lev. 1:6–8</char></note>put the wood in order, cut the bull in pieces, and laid <char style="it">it</char> on the wood, and said, “Fill four waterpots with water, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:20</char></note>pour <char style="it">it</char> on the burnt sacrifice and on the wood.” <verse number="34" style="v" />Then he said, “Do <char style="it">it</char> a second time,” and they did <char style="it">it</char> a second time; and he said, “Do <char style="it">it</char> a third time,” and they did <char style="it">it</char> a third time. <verse number="35" style="v" />So the water ran all around the altar; and he also filled <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:32, 38</char></note>the trench with water.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />And it came to pass, at <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">time</char> <char style="it">of</char> the offering of the <char style="it">evening</char> sacrifice, that Elijah the prophet came near and said, “<char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 28:13; Ex. 3:6; 4:5; (Matt. 22:32)</char></note>God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:43; 2 Kin. 19:19</char></note>let it be known this day that You <char style="it">are</char> God in Israel and I <char style="it">am</char> Your servant, and <char style="it">that</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 16:28</char></note>I have done all these things at Your word. <verse number="37" style="v" />Hear me, O <char style="sc">Lord</char>, hear me, that this people may know that You <char style="it">are</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God, and <char style="it">that</char> You have turned their hearts back <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">You</char> again.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:17; Lev. 9:24; 10:1, 2; Judg. 6:21; 2 Kin. 1:12; 1 Chr. 21:26; 2 Chr. 7:1; Job 1:16</char></note>the fire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> fell and consumed the burnt sacrifice, and the wood and the stones and the dust, and it licked up the water that <char style="it">was</char> in the trench. <verse number="39" style="v" />Now when all the people saw <char style="it">it,</char> they fell on their faces; and they said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:21, 24</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char>, He <char style="it">is</char> God! The <char style="sc">Lord</char>, He <char style="it">is</char> God!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" />And Elijah said to them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:25</char></note>“Seize the prophets of Baal! Do not let one of them escape!” So they seized them; and Elijah brought them down to the Brook <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:7; 5:21</char></note>Kishon and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 13:5; 18:20)</char></note>executed them there.</para>
	<para style="s">The Drought Ends</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />Then Elijah said to Ahab, “Go up, eat and drink; for <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> the sound of abundance of rain.” <verse number="42" style="v" />So Ahab went up to eat and drink. And Elijah went up to the top of Carmel; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">James 5:17, 18</char></note>then he bowed down on the ground, and put his face between his knees, <verse number="43" style="v" />and said to his servant, “Go up now, look toward the sea.”</para>
	<para style="p">So he went up and looked, and said, “<char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">is</char> nothing.” And seven times he said, “Go again.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" />Then it came to pass the seventh <char style="it">time,</char> that he said, “There is a cloud, as small as a man’s hand, rising out of the sea!” So he said, “Go up, say to Ahab, ‘Prepare <char style="it">your</char> <char style="it">chariot,</char> and go down before the rain stops you.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" />Now it happened in the meantime that the sky became black with clouds and wind, and there was a heavy rain. So Ahab rode away and went to Jezreel. <verse number="46" style="v" />Then the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:15; Is. 8:11; Ezek. 3:14</char></note>hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon Elijah; and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:29; 9:1; Jer. 1:17; 1 Pet. 1:13</char></note>girded up his loins and ran ahead of Ahab to the entrance of Jezreel.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Elijah Escapes from Jezebel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Ahab told Jezebel all that Elijah had done, also how he had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:40</char></note>executed all the prophets with the sword. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then Jezebel sent a messenger to Elijah, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ruth 1:17; 1 Kin. 20:10; 2 Kin. 6:31</char></note>“So let the gods do <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">me,</char> and more also, if I do not make your life as the life of one of them by tomorrow about this time.” <verse number="3" style="v" />And when he saw <char style="it">that,</char> he arose and ran for his life, and went to Beersheba, which <char style="it">belongs</char> to Judah, and left his servant there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />But he himself went a day’s journey into the wilderness, and came and sat down under a broom tree. And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 11:15; Jer. 20:14–18; Jon. 4:3, 8</char></note>prayed that he might die, and said, “It is enough! Now, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, take my life, for I <char style="it">am</char> no better than my fathers!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then as he lay and slept under a broom tree, suddenly an angel touched him, and said to him, “Arise <char style="it">and</char> eat.” <verse number="6" style="v" />Then he looked, and there by his head <char style="it">was</char> a cake baked on coals, and a jar of water. So he ate and drank, and lay down again. <verse number="7" style="v" />And the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came back the second time, and touched him, and said, “Arise <char style="it">and</char> eat, because the journey <char style="it">is</char> too great for you.” <verse number="8" style="v" />So he arose, and ate and drank; and he went in the strength of that food forty days and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 24:18; 34:28; Deut. 9:9–11, 18; Matt. 4:2</char></note>forty nights as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:1; 4:27</char></note>Horeb, the mountain of God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And there he went into a cave, and spent the night in that place; and behold, the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">came</char> to him, and He said to him, “What are you doing here, Elijah?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So he said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rom. 11:3</char></note>“I have been very <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 25:11, 13; Ps. 69:9</char></note>zealous for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of hosts; for the children of Israel have forsaken Your covenant, torn down Your altars, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:4</char></note>killed Your prophets with the sword. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:22; Rom. 11:3</char></note>I alone am left; and they seek to take my life.”</para>
	<para style="s">God’s Revelation to Elijah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then He said, “Go out, and stand <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:20; 24:12, 18</char></note>on the mountain before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” And behold, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 33:21, 22</char></note>passed by, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 1:4; 37:7</char></note>a great and strong wind tore into the mountains and broke the rocks in pieces before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <char style="it">but</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">was</char> not in the wind; and after the wind an earthquake, <char style="it">but</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">was</char> not in the earthquake; <verse number="12" style="v" />and after the earthquake a fire, <char style="it">but</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">was</char> not in the fire; and after the fire a still small voice.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So it was, when Elijah heard <char style="it">it,</char> that he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:6; Is. 6:2</char></note>wrapped his face in his mantle and went out and stood in the entrance of the cave. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:9</char></note>Suddenly a voice <char style="it">came</char> to him, and said, “What are you doing here, Elijah?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:10</char></note>And he said, “I have been very zealous for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of hosts; because the children of Israel have forsaken Your covenant, torn down Your altars, and killed Your prophets with the sword. I alone am left; and they seek to take my life.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him: “Go, return on your way to the Wilderness of Damascus; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:8–15</char></note>and when you arrive, anoint Hazael <char style="it">as</char> king over Syria. <verse number="16" style="v" />Also you shall anoint <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:1–10</char></note>Jehu the son of Nimshi <char style="it">as</char> king over Israel. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:19–21; 2 Kin. 2:9–15</char></note>Elisha the son of Shaphat of Abel Meholah you shall anoint <char style="it">as</char> prophet in your place. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:12; 13:3, 22</char></note>It shall be <char style="it">that</char> whoever escapes the sword of Hazael, Jehu will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:14—10:28</char></note>kill; and whoever escapes the sword of Jehu, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Hos. 6:5)</char></note>Elisha will kill. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rom. 11:4</char></note>Yet I have reserved seven thousand in Israel, all whose knees have not bowed to Baal, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Hos. 13:2</char></note>and every mouth that has not kissed him.”</para>
	<para style="s">Elisha Follows Elijah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />So he departed from there, and found Elisha the son of Shaphat, who <char style="it">was</char> plowing <char style="it">with</char> twelve yoke <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">oxen</char> before him, and he was with the twelfth. Then Elijah passed by him and threw his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 28:14; 2 Kin. 2:8, 13, 14</char></note>mantle on him. <verse number="20" style="v" />And he left the oxen and ran after Elijah, and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 8:21, 22; Luke 9:61, 62); Acts 20:37</char></note>“Please let me kiss my father and my mother, and <char style="it">then</char> I will follow you.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said to him, “Go back again, for what have I done to you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />So <char style="it">Elisha</char> turned back from him, and took a yoke of oxen and slaughtered them and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 24:22</char></note>boiled their flesh, using the oxen’s equipment, and gave it to the people, and they ate. Then he arose and followed Elijah, and became his servant.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Ahab Defeats the Syrians</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:18, 20; 2 Kin. 6:24</char></note>Ben-Hadad the king of Syria gathered all his forces together; thirty-two kings <char style="it">were</char> with him, with horses and chariots. And he went up and besieged <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:24; 2 Kin. 6:24</char></note>Samaria, and made war against it. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then he sent messengers into the city to Ahab king of Israel, and said to him, “Thus says Ben-Hadad: <verse number="3" style="v" />‘Your silver and your gold <char style="it">are</char> mine; your loveliest wives and children are mine.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And the king of Israel answered and said, “My lord, O king, just as you say, I and all that I have <char style="it">are</char> yours.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then the messengers came back and said, “Thus speaks Ben-Hadad, saying, ‘Indeed I have sent to you, saying, “You shall deliver to me your silver and your gold, your wives and your children”; <verse number="6" style="v" />but I will send my servants to you tomorrow about this time, and they shall search your house and the houses of your servants. And it shall be, <char style="it">that</char> whatever is pleasant in your eyes, they will put <char style="it">it</char> in their hands and take <char style="it">it.</char>’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So the king of Israel called all the elders of the land, and said, “Notice, please, and see how this <char style="it">man</char> seeks trouble, for he sent to me for my wives, my children, my silver, and my gold; and I did not deny him.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And all the elders and all the people said to him, “Do not listen or consent.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Therefore he said to the messengers of Ben-Hadad, “Tell my lord the king, ‘All that you sent for to your servant the first time I will do, but this thing I cannot do.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">And the messengers departed and brought back word to him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Then Ben-Hadad sent to him and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:2; 2 Kin. 6:31</char></note>“The gods do so to me, and more also, if enough dust is left of Samaria for a handful for each of the people who follow me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So the king of Israel answered and said, “Tell <char style="it">him,</char> ‘Let not the one who puts on <char style="it">his</char> <char style="it">armor</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 27:1; (Eccl. 7:8)</char></note>boast like the one who takes <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">off.</char>’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And it happened when <char style="it">Ben-Hadad</char> heard this message, as he and the kings <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:16</char></note>drinking at the command post, that he said to his servants, “Get ready.” And they got ready to attack the city.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Suddenly a prophet approached Ahab king of Israel, saying, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Have you seen all this great multitude? Behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:28</char></note>I will deliver it into your hand today, and you shall know that I <char style="it">am</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So Ahab said, “By whom?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘By the young leaders of the provinces.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">Then he said, “Who will set the battle in order?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he answered, “You.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then he mustered the young leaders of the provinces, and there were two hundred and thirty-two; and after them he mustered all the people, all the children of Israel—seven thousand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So they went out at noon. Meanwhile Ben-Hadad and the thirty-two kings helping him were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:9; 20:12; (Prov. 20:1)</char></note>getting drunk at the command post. <verse number="17" style="v" />The young leaders of the provinces went out first. And Ben-Hadad sent out <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">patrol,</char> and they told him, saying, “Men are coming out of Samaria!” <verse number="18" style="v" />So he said, “If they have come out for peace, take them alive; and if they have come out for war, take them alive.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then these young leaders of the provinces went out of the city with the army which followed them. <verse number="20" style="v" />And each one killed his man; so the Syrians fled, and Israel pursued them; and Ben-Hadad the king of Syria escaped on a horse with the cavalry. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then the king of Israel went out and attacked the horses and chariots, and killed the Syrians with a great slaughter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And the prophet came to the king of Israel and said to him, “Go, strengthen yourself; take note, and see what you should do, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 11:1; 1 Kin. 20:26</char></note>for in the spring of the year the king of Syria will come up against you.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Syrians Again Defeated</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then the servants of the king of Syria said to him, “Their gods <char style="it">are</char> gods of the hills. Therefore they were stronger than we; but if we fight against them in the plain, surely we will be stronger than they. <verse number="24" style="v" />So do this thing: Dismiss the kings, each from his position, and put captains in their places; <verse number="25" style="v" />and you shall muster an army like the army that you have lost, horse for horse and chariot for chariot. Then we will fight against them in the plain; surely we will be stronger than they.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he listened to their voice and did so.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />So it was, in the spring of the year, that Ben-Hadad mustered the Syrians and went up to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:4; 2 Kin. 13:17</char></note>Aphek to fight against Israel. <verse number="27" style="v" />And the children of Israel were mustered and given provisions, and they went against them. Now the children of Israel encamped before them like two little flocks of goats, while the Syrians filled the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:3–5; 1 Sam. 13:5–8</char></note>countryside.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Then a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 17:18</char></note>man of God came and spoke to the king of Israel, and said, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Because the Syrians have said, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> God of the hills, but He <char style="it">is</char> not God of the valleys,” therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:13</char></note>I will deliver all this great multitude into your hand, and you shall know that I <char style="it">am</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ ” <verse number="29" style="v" />And they encamped opposite each other for seven days. So it was that on the seventh day the battle was joined; and the children of Israel killed one hundred thousand foot soldiers <char style="it">of</char> the Syrians in one day. <verse number="30" style="v" />But the rest fled to Aphek, into the city; then a wall fell on twenty-seven thousand of the men <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> left.</para>
	<para style="p">And Ben-Hadad fled and went into the city, into an inner chamber.</para>
	<para style="s">Ahab’s Treaty with Ben-Hadad</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Then his servants said to him, “Look now, we have heard that the kings of the house of Israel <char style="it">are</char> merciful kings. Please, let us <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 37:34; 2 Sam. 3:31</char></note>put sackcloth around our waists and ropes around our heads, and go out to the king of Israel; perhaps he will spare your life.” <verse number="32" style="v" />So they wore sackcloth around their waists and <char style="it">put</char> ropes around their heads, and came to the king of Israel and said, “Your servant Ben-Hadad says, ‘Please let me live.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “<char style="it">Is</char> he still alive? He <char style="it">is</char> my brother.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />Now the men were watching closely to see whether <char style="it">any</char> <char style="it">sign</char> <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">mercy</char> <char style="it">would</char> <char style="it">come</char> from him; and they quickly grasped <char style="it">at</char> <char style="it">this</char> <char style="it">word</char> and said, “Your brother Ben-Hadad.”</para>
	<para style="p">So he said, “Go, bring him.” Then Ben-Hadad came out to him; and he had him come up into the chariot.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />So <char style="it">Ben-Hadad</char> said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:20</char></note>“The cities which my father took from your father I will restore; and you may set up marketplaces for yourself in Damascus, as my father did in Samaria.”</para>
	<para style="p">Then <char style="it">Ahab</char> <char style="it">said,</char> “I will send you away with this treaty.” So he made a treaty with him and sent him away.</para>
	<para style="s">Ahab Condemned</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />Now a certain man of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:3, 5, 7, 15</char></note>the sons of the prophets said to his neighbor <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:17, 18</char></note>by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, “Strike me, please.” And the man refused to strike him. <verse number="36" style="v" />Then he said to him, “Because you have not obeyed the voice of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, surely, as soon as you depart from me, a lion shall kill you.” And as soon as he left him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:24</char></note>a lion found him and killed him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" />And he found another man, and said, “Strike me, please.” So the man struck him, inflicting a wound. <verse number="38" style="v" />Then the prophet departed and waited for the king by the road, and disguised himself with a bandage over his eyes. <verse number="39" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 12:1</char></note>as the king passed by, he cried out to the king and said, “Your servant went out into the midst of the battle; and there, a man came over and brought a man to me, and said, ‘Guard this man; if by any means he is missing, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:24</char></note>your life shall be for his life, or else you shall pay a talent of silver.’ <verse number="40" style="v" />While your servant was busy here and there, he was gone.”</para>
	<para style="p">Then the king of Israel said to him, “So <char style="it">shall</char> your judgment <char style="it">be;</char> you yourself have decided <char style="it">it.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />And he hastened to take the bandage away from his eyes; and the king of Israel recognized him as one of the prophets. <verse number="42" style="v" />Then he said to him, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:31–37</char></note>‘Because you have let slip out of <char style="it">your</char> hand a man whom I appointed to utter destruction, therefore your life shall go for his life, and your people for his people.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" />So the king of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:4</char></note>went to his house sullen and displeased, and came to Samaria.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Naboth Is Murdered for His Vineyard</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass after these things <char style="it">that</char> Naboth the Jezreelite had a vineyard which <char style="it">was</char> in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:33; 1 Kin. 18:45, 46</char></note>Jezreel, next to the palace of Ahab king of Samaria. <verse number="2" style="v" />So Ahab spoke to Naboth, saying, “Give me your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 8:14</char></note>vineyard, that I may have it for a vegetable garden, because it <char style="it">is</char> near, next to my house; and for it I will give you a vineyard better than it. <char style="it">Or,</char> if it seems good to you, I will give you its worth in money.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />But Naboth said to Ahab, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> forbid <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 25:23; Num. 36:7; Ezek. 46:18)</char></note>that I should give the inheritance of my fathers to you!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So Ahab went into his house sullen and displeased because of the word which Naboth the Jezreelite had spoken to him; for he had said, “I will not give you the inheritance of my fathers.” And he lay down on his bed, and turned away his face, and would eat no food. <verse number="5" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:1, 2</char></note>Jezebel his wife came to him, and said to him, “Why is your spirit so sullen that you eat no food?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />He said to her, “Because I spoke to Naboth the Jezreelite, and said to him, ‘Give me your vineyard for money; or else, if it pleases you, I will give you <char style="it">another</char> vineyard for it.’ And he answered, ‘I will not give you my vineyard.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then Jezebel his wife said to him, “You now exercise authority over Israel! Arise, eat food, and let your heart be cheerful; I will give you the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And she wrote letters in Ahab’s name, sealed <char style="it">them</char> with his seal, and sent the letters to the elders and the nobles who <char style="it">were</char> dwelling in the city with Naboth. <verse number="9" style="v" />She wrote in the letters, saying,</para>
	<para style="q1">Proclaim a fast, and seat Naboth with high honor among the people; <verse number="10" style="v" />and seat two men, scoundrels, before him to bear witness against him, saying, “You have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 22:28; Lev. 24:15, 16); Acts 6:11</char></note>blasphemed God and the king.” <char style="it">Then</char> take him out, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 24:14)</char></note>stone him, that he may die.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So the men of his city, the elders and nobles who were inhabitants of his city, did as Jezebel had sent to them, as it <char style="it">was</char> written in the letters which she had sent to them. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 58:4</char></note>They proclaimed a fast, and seated Naboth with high honor among the people. <verse number="13" style="v" />And two men, scoundrels, came in and sat before him; and the scoundrels <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 20:16; 23:1, 7)</char></note>witnessed against him, against Naboth, in the presence of the people, saying, “Naboth has blasphemed God and the king!” <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:26; 2 Chr. 24:21; Acts 7:58, 59; Heb. 11:37</char></note>Then they took him outside the city and stoned him with stones, so that he died. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then they sent to Jezebel, saying, “Naboth has been stoned and is dead.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And it came to pass, when Jezebel heard that Naboth had been stoned and was dead, that Jezebel said to Ahab, “Arise, take possession of the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite, which he refused to give you for money; for Naboth is not alive, but dead.” <verse number="16" style="v" />So it was, when Ahab heard that Naboth was dead, that Ahab got up and went down to take possession of the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite.</para>
	<para style="s">The <char style="sc">Lord</char> Condemns Ahab</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 9:12)</char></note>Then the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:1</char></note>Elijah the Tishbite, saying, <verse number="18" style="v" />“Arise, go down to meet Ahab king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:32; 2 Chr. 22:9</char></note>who <char style="it">lives</char> in Samaria. There <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">is,</char> in the vineyard of Naboth, where he has gone down to take possession of it. <verse number="19" style="v" />You shall speak to him, saying, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: “Have you murdered and also taken possession?” ’ And you shall speak to him, saying, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:38; 2 Kin. 9:26</char></note>“In the place where dogs licked the blood of Naboth, dogs shall lick your blood, even yours.” ’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So Ahab said to Elijah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:17</char></note>“Have you found me, O my enemy?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he answered, “I have found <char style="it">you,</char> because <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:25; 2 Kin. 17:17; (Rom. 7:14)</char></note>you have sold yourself to do evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <verse number="21" style="v" />‘Behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:10; 2 Kin. 9:8</char></note>I will bring calamity on you. I will take away your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:10</char></note>posterity, and will cut off from Ahab <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:22</char></note>every male in Israel, both <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:10</char></note>bond and free. <verse number="22" style="v" />I will make your house like the house of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:29</char></note>Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:3, 11</char></note>Baasha the son of Ahijah, because of the provocation with which you have provoked <char style="it">Me</char> to anger, and made Israel sin.’ <verse number="23" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:10, 30–37</char></note>concerning Jezebel the <char style="sc">Lord</char> also spoke, saying, ‘The dogs shall eat Jezebel by the wall of Jezreel.’ <verse number="24" style="v" />The dogs shall eat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:11; 16:4</char></note>whoever belongs to Ahab and dies in the city, and the birds of the air shall eat whoever dies in the field.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:30–33; 21:20</char></note>there was no one like Ahab who sold himself to do wickedness in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:31</char></note>because Jezebel his wife stirred him up. <verse number="26" style="v" />And he behaved very abominably in following idols, according to all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:16; (Lev. 18:25–30); 2 Kin. 21:11</char></note><char style="it">that</char> the Amorites had done, whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had cast out before the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />So it was, when Ahab heard those words, that he tore his clothes and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 37:34; 2 Sam. 3:31; 2 Kin. 6:30</char></note>put sackcloth on his body, and fasted and lay in sackcloth, and went about mourning.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to Elijah the Tishbite, saying, <verse number="29" style="v" />“See how Ahab has humbled himself before Me? Because he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Kin. 22:19)</char></note>has humbled himself before Me, I will not bring the calamity in his days. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:25; 10:11, 17</char></note>In the days of his son I will bring the calamity on his house.”</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Micaiah Warns Ahab</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now three years passed without war between Syria and Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then it came to pass, in the third year, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:24; 2 Chr. 18:2</char></note>Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went down to <char style="it">visit</char> the king of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />And the king of Israel said to his servants, “Do you know that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:43; Josh. 21:38; 1 Kin. 4:13</char></note>Ramoth in Gilead <char style="it">is</char> ours, but we hesitate to take it out of the hand of the king of Syria?” <verse number="4" style="v" />So he said to Jehoshaphat, “Will you go with me to fight at Ramoth Gilead?”</para>
	<para style="p">Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:7</char></note>“I <char style="it">am</char> as you <char style="it">are,</char> my people as your people, my horses as your horses.” <verse number="5" style="v" />Also Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:11</char></note>“Please inquire for the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> today.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then the king of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:19</char></note>gathered the prophets together, about four hundred men, and said to them, “Shall I go against Ramoth Gilead to fight, or shall I refrain?”</para>
	<para style="p">So they said, “Go up, for the Lord will deliver <char style="it">it</char> into the hand of the king.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:11</char></note>Jehoshaphat said, “<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">there</char> not still a prophet of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> here, that we may inquire of Him?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “<char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">is</char> still one man, Micaiah the son of Imlah, by whom we may inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; but I hate him, because he does not prophesy good concerning me, but evil.”</para>
	<para style="p">And Jehoshaphat said, “Let not the king say such things!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then the king of Israel called an officer and said, “Bring Micaiah the son of Imlah quickly!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />The king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah, having put on <char style="it">their</char> robes, sat each on his throne, at a threshing floor at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets prophesied before them. <verse number="11" style="v" />Now Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah had made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Zech. 1:18–21</char></note>horns of iron for himself; and he said, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘With these you shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 33:17</char></note>gore the Syrians until they are destroyed.’ ” <verse number="12" style="v" />And all the prophets prophesied so, saying, “Go up to Ramoth Gilead and prosper, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will deliver <char style="it">it</char> into the king’s hand.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then the messenger who had gone to call Micaiah spoke to him, saying, “Now listen, the words of the prophets with one accord encourage the king. Please, let your word be like the word of one of them, and speak encouragement.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And Micaiah said, “<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:38; 24:13</char></note>whatever the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says to me, that I will speak.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then he came to the king; and the king said to him, “Micaiah, shall we go to war against Ramoth Gilead, or shall we refrain?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he answered him, “Go and prosper, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will deliver <char style="it">it</char> into the hand of the king!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So the king said to him, “How many times shall I make you swear that you tell me nothing but the truth in the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then he said, “I saw all Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:17; 1 Kin. 22:34–36; 2 Chr. 18:16; Matt. 9:36; Mark 6:34</char></note>scattered on the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd. And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, ‘These have no master. Let each return to his house in peace.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “Did I not tell you he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then <char style="it">Micaiah</char> said, “Therefore hear the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 6:1; Ezek. 1:26–28; Dan. 7:9</char></note>I saw the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sitting on His throne, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 1:6; 2:1; Ps. 103:20; Dan. 7:10; Zech. 1:10; (Matt. 18:10; Heb. 1:7, 14)</char></note>and all the host of heaven standing by, on His right hand and on His left. <verse number="20" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, ‘Who will persuade Ahab to go up, that he may fall at Ramoth Gilead?’ So one spoke in this manner, and another spoke in that manner. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then a spirit came forward and stood before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said, ‘I will persuade him.’ <verse number="22" style="v" />The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, ‘In what way?’ So he said, ‘I will go out and be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’ And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:23; 1 Sam. 16:14; 18:10; 19:9; Job 12:16; (Ezek. 14:9; 2 Thess. 2:11)</char></note>‘You shall persuade <char style="it">him,</char> and also prevail. Go out and do so.’ <verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ezek. 14:9)</char></note>Therefore look! The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has put a lying spirit in the mouth of all these prophets of yours, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has declared disaster against you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Now Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah went near and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 20:2</char></note>struck Micaiah on the cheek, and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:23</char></note>“Which way did the spirit from the <char style="sc">Lord</char> go from me to speak to you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />And Micaiah said, “Indeed, you shall see on that day when you go into an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:30</char></note>inner chamber to hide!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />So the king of Israel said, “Take Micaiah, and return him to Amon the governor of the city and to Joash the king’s son; <verse number="27" style="v" />and say, ‘Thus says the king: “Put this <char style="it">fellow</char> in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:10; 18:25–27</char></note>prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and water of affliction, until I come in peace.” ’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />But Micaiah said, “If you ever return in peace, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 16:29; Deut. 18:20–22</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has not spoken by me.” And he said, “Take heed, all you people!”</para>
	<para style="s">Ahab Dies in Battle</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth Gilead. <verse number="30" style="v" />And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “I will disguise myself and go into battle; but you put on your robes.” So the king of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:22</char></note>disguised himself and went into battle.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Now the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:1</char></note>king of Syria had commanded the thirty-two <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:24; 2 Chr. 18:30</char></note>captains of his chariots, saying, “Fight with no one small or great, but only with the king of Israel.” <verse number="32" style="v" />So it was, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, “Surely it <char style="it">is</char> the king of Israel!” Therefore they turned aside to fight against him, and Jehoshaphat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:31</char></note>cried out. <verse number="33" style="v" />And it happened, when the captains of the chariots saw that it <char style="it">was</char> not the king of Israel, that they turned back from pursuing him. <verse number="34" style="v" />Now a <char style="it">certain</char> man drew a bow at random, and struck the king of Israel between the joints of his armor. So he said to the driver of his chariot, “Turn around and take me out of the battle, for I am wounded.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />The battle increased that day; and the king was propped up in his chariot, facing the Syrians, and died at evening. The blood ran out from the wound onto the floor of the chariot. <verse number="36" style="v" />Then, as the sun was going down, a shout went throughout the army, saying, “Every man to his city, and every man to his own country!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" />So the king died, and was brought to Samaria. And they buried the king in Samaria. <verse number="38" style="v" />Then <char style="it">someone</char> washed the chariot at a pool in Samaria, and the dogs licked up his blood while the harlots bathed, according <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:19</char></note>to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He had spoken.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Ahab, and all that he did, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 45:8; Amos 3:15</char></note>the ivory house which he built and all the cities that he built, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="40" style="v" />So Ahab rested with his fathers. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 1:2, 18</char></note>Ahaziah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Jehoshaphat Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:31</char></note>Jehoshaphat the son of Asa had become king over Judah in the fourth year of Ahab king of Israel. <verse number="42" style="v" />Jehoshaphat <char style="it">was</char> thirty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned twenty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. <verse number="43" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:3; 20:32, 33</char></note>he walked in all the ways of his father Asa. He did not turn aside from them, doing <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:23; 15:14; 2 Kin. 12:3</char></note>the high places were not taken away, <char style="it">for</char> the people offered sacrifices and burned incense on the high places. <verse number="44" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 19:2</char></note>Jehoshaphat made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:1</char></note>peace with the king of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, the might that he showed, and how he made war, <char style="it">are</char> they not written <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:34</char></note>in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="46" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:5; Deut. 23:17; 1 Kin. 14:24; 15:12; 2 Kin. 23:7; Jude 7</char></note>And the rest of the perverted persons, who remained in the days of his father Asa, he banished from the land. <verse number="47" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:14; 2 Kin. 3:9; 8:20</char></note><char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">was</char> then no king in Edom, only a deputy of the king.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:35–37</char></note>Jehoshaphat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:22</char></note>made merchant ships to go to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:28</char></note>Ophir for gold; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:37</char></note>but they never sailed, for the ships were wrecked at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:26</char></note>Ezion Geber. <verse number="49" style="v" />Then Ahaziah the son of Ahab said to Jehoshaphat, “Let my servants go with your servants in the ships.” But Jehoshaphat would not.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:1</char></note>Jehoshaphat rested with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the City of David his father. Then Jehoram his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Ahaziah Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:40</char></note>Ahaziah the son of Ahab became king over Israel in Samaria in the seventeenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and reigned two years over Israel. <verse number="52" style="v" />He did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:26; 21:25</char></note>walked in the way of his father and in the way of his mother and in the way of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin; <verse number="53" style="v" />for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:11</char></note>he served Baal and worshiped him, and provoked the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel to anger, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:30–32</char></note>according to all that his father had done.</para>
	
</usx>