<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="2CH" style="id">The Second Book of the Chronicles</book>
    <para style="mt">The Second Book of the Chronicles</para>
    <chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon Requests Wisdom</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:46</char></note>Solomon the son of David was strengthened in his kingdom, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 39:2</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God <char style="it">was</char> with him and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 29:25</char></note>exalted him exceedingly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And Solomon spoke to all Israel, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 27:1–34</char></note>the captains of thousands and of hundreds, to the judges, and to every leader in all Israel, the heads of the fathers’ <char style="it">houses.</char> <verse number="3" style="v" />Then Solomon, and all the assembly with him, went to the high place that <char style="it">was</char> at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:4; 1 Chr. 16:39; 21:29</char></note>Gibeon; for the tabernacle of meeting with God was there, which Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25—27; 35:4—36:38</char></note>made in the wilderness. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:10–22; 2 Sam. 6:2–17; 1 Chr. 15:25—16:1</char></note>But David had brought up the ark of God from Kirjath Jearim to <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">place</char> David had prepared for it, for he had pitched a tent for it at Jerusalem. <verse number="5" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:1, 2; 38:1, 2</char></note>the bronze altar that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 31:2</char></note>Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, had made, he put before the tabernacle of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; Solomon and the assembly sought Him <char style="it">there.</char> <verse number="6" style="v" />And Solomon went up there to the bronze altar before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which <char style="it">was</char> at the tabernacle of meeting, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:4</char></note>offered a thousand burnt offerings on it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:5–14; 9:2</char></note>On that night God appeared to Solomon, and said to him, “Ask! What shall I give you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And Solomon said to God: “You have shown great <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 18:50</char></note>mercy to David my father, and have made me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:5</char></note>king in his place. <verse number="9" style="v" />Now, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God, let Your promise to David my father be established, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:8–16; 1 Kin. 3:7, 8</char></note>for You have made me king over a people like the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 13:16; Num. 23:10</char></note>dust of the earth in multitude. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:9</char></note>Now give me wisdom and knowledge, that I may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:17; Deut. 31:2</char></note>go out and come in before this people; for who can judge this great people of Yours?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:11–13</char></note>Then God said to Solomon: “Because this was in your heart, and you have not asked riches or wealth or honor or the life of your enemies, nor have you asked long life—but have asked wisdom and knowledge for yourself, that you may judge My people over whom I have made you king— <verse number="12" style="v" />wisdom and knowledge <char style="it">are</char> granted to you; and I will give you riches and wealth and honor, such as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:23; 1 Chr. 29:25; 2 Chr. 9:22; Eccl. 2:9</char></note>none of the kings have had who <char style="it">were</char> before you, nor shall any after you have the like.”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Military and Economic Power</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So Solomon came to Jerusalem from the high place that <char style="it">was</char> at Gibeon, from before the tabernacle of meeting, and reigned over Israel. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:26; 2 Chr. 9:25</char></note>And Solomon gathered chariots and horsemen; he had one thousand four hundred chariots and twelve thousand horsemen, whom he stationed in the chariot cities and with the king in Jerusalem. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:27; 2 Chr. 9:27; Job 22:24</char></note>Also the king made silver and gold as common in Jerusalem as stones, and he made cedars as abundant as the sycamores which <char style="it">are</char> in the lowland. <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:28; 22:36; 2 Chr. 9:28</char></note>And Solomon had horses imported from Egypt and Keveh; the king’s merchants bought them in Keveh at the <char style="it">current</char> price. <verse number="17" style="v" />They also acquired and imported from Egypt a chariot for six hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver, and a horse for one hundred and fifty; thus, through their agents, they exported them to all the kings of the Hittites and the kings of Syria.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon Prepares to Build the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:5</char></note>determined to build a temple for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and a royal house for himself. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:15, 16; 2 Chr. 2:18</char></note>Solomon selected seventy thousand men to bear burdens, eighty thousand to quarry <char style="it">stone</char> in the mountains, and three thousand six hundred to oversee them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then Solomon sent to Hiram king of Tyre, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 14:1</char></note>As you have dealt with David my father, and sent him cedars to build himself a house to dwell in, <char style="it">so</char> <char style="it">deal</char> <char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">me.</char> <verse number="4" style="v" />Behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:1</char></note>I am building a temple for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, to dedicate <char style="it">it</char> to Him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:7</char></note>to burn before Him sweet incense, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:30; Lev. 24:8</char></note>the continual showbread, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:38–42</char></note>the burnt offerings morning and evening, on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 28:3, 9–11</char></note>Sabbaths, on the New Moons, and on the set feasts of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God. This <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">an</char> <char style="it">ordinance</char> forever to Israel.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="5" style="v" />And the temple which I build <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> great, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 135:5; (1 Cor. 8:5, 6)</char></note>our God is greater than all gods. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:27; 2 Chr. 6:18; Is. 66:1</char></note>But who is able to build Him a temple, since heaven and the heaven of heavens cannot contain Him? Who <char style="it">am</char> I then, that I should build Him a temple, except to burn sacrifice before Him?</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="7" style="v" />Therefore send me at once a man skillful to work in gold and silver, in bronze and iron, in purple and crimson and blue, who has skill to engrave with the skillful men who are with me in Judah and Jerusalem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:15</char></note>whom David my father provided. <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:6</char></note>Also send me cedar and cypress and algum logs from Lebanon, for I know that your servants have skill to cut timber in Lebanon; and indeed my servants <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> with your servants, <verse number="9" style="v" />to prepare timber for me in abundance, for the temple which I am about to build <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> great and wonderful.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:11</char></note>And indeed I will give to your servants, the woodsmen who cut timber, twenty thousand kors of ground wheat, twenty thousand kors of barley, twenty thousand baths of wine, and twenty thousand baths of oil.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then Hiram king of Tyre answered in writing, which he sent to Solomon:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:9; 2 Chr. 9:8</char></note>Because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> loves His people, He has made you king over them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Hiram also said:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:7</char></note>Blessed <char style="it">be</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 1; 2; Acts 4:24; 14:15; Rev. 10:6</char></note>who made heaven and earth, for He has given King David a wise son, endowed with prudence and understanding, who will build a temple for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and a royal house for himself!</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="13" style="v" />And now I have sent a skillful man, endowed with understanding, Huram my master <char style="it">craftsman</char><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:13, 14</char></note>(the son of a woman of the daughters of Dan, and his father was a man of Tyre), skilled to work in gold and silver, bronze and iron, stone and wood, purple and blue, fine linen and crimson, and to make any engraving and to accomplish any plan which may be given to him, with your skillful men and with the skillful men of my lord David your father.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="15" style="v" />Now therefore, the wheat, the barley, the oil, and the wine which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:10</char></note>my lord has spoken of, let him send to his servants.<verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:8, 9</char></note>And we will cut wood from Lebanon, as much as you need; we will bring it to you in rafts by sea to Joppa, and you will carry it up to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:13; 2 Chr. 8:7, 8</char></note>Then Solomon numbered all the aliens who <char style="it">were</char> in the land of Israel, after the census in which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:2</char></note>David his father had numbered them; and there were found to be one hundred and fifty-three thousand six hundred. <verse number="18" style="v" />And he made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 2:2</char></note>seventy thousand of them bearers of burdens, eighty thousand stonecutters in the mountain, and three thousand six hundred overseers to make the people work.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon Builds the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:1</char></note>Solomon began to build the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 22:2–14</char></note>Jerusalem on Mount Moriah, where <char style="it">the</char> <char style="sc"><char style="it">Lord</char></char> had appeared to his father David, at the place that David had prepared on the threshing floor of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 21:18; 22:1</char></note>Ornan the Jebusite. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he began to build on the second <char style="it">day</char> of the second month in the fourth year of his reign.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />This is the foundation <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:2; 1 Chr. 28:11–19</char></note>which Solomon laid for building the house of God: The length <char style="it">was</char> sixty cubits (by cubits according to the former measure) and the width twenty cubits. <verse number="4" style="v" />And the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:3; 1 Chr. 28:11</char></note>vestibule that <char style="it">was</char> in front <char style="it">of</char> the sanctuary was twenty cubits long across the width of the house, and the height <char style="it">was</char> one hundred and twenty. He overlaid the inside with pure gold. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:17</char></note>The larger room he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:15; Jer. 22:14</char></note>paneled with cypress which he overlaid with fine gold, and he carved palm trees and chainwork on it. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he decorated the house with precious stones for beauty, and the gold <char style="it">was</char> gold from Parvaim. <verse number="7" style="v" />He also overlaid the house—the beams and doorposts, its walls and doors—with gold; and he carved cherubim on the walls.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And he made the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 26:33; 1 Kin. 6:16</char></note>Most Holy Place. Its length was according to the width of the house, twenty cubits, and its width twenty cubits. He overlaid it with six hundred talents of fine gold. <verse number="9" style="v" />The weight of the nails <char style="it">was</char> fifty shekels of gold; and he overlaid the upper <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:11</char></note>area with gold. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:18–20; 1 Kin. 6:23–28</char></note>In the Most Holy Place he made two cherubim, fashioned by carving, and overlaid them with gold. <verse number="11" style="v" />The wings of the cherubim <char style="it">were</char> twenty cubits in <char style="it">overall</char> length: one wing <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">one</char> <char style="it">cherub</char> <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, touching the wall of the room, and the other wing <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, touching the wing of the other cherub; <verse number="12" style="v" /><char style="it">one</char> wing of the other cherub <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, touching the wall of the room, and the other wing <char style="it">also</char> <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, touching the wing of the other cherub. <verse number="13" style="v" />The wings of these cherubim spanned twenty cubits overall. They stood on their feet, and they faced inward. <verse number="14" style="v" />And he made the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 26:31; Matt. 27:51; Heb. 9:3</char></note>veil of blue, purple, crimson, and fine linen, and wove cherubim into it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Also he made in front of the temple <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:15–20; Jer. 52:21</char></note>two pillars thirty-five cubits high, and the capital that <char style="it">was</char> on the top of each of <char style="it">them</char> was five cubits. <verse number="16" style="v" />He made wreaths of chainwork, as in the inner sanctuary, and put <char style="it">them</char> on top of the pillars; and he made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:20</char></note>one hundred pomegranates, and put <char style="it">them</char> on the wreaths of chainwork. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:21</char></note>set up the pillars before the temple, one on the right hand and the other on the left; he called the name of the one on the right hand Jachin, and the name of the one on the left Boaz.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Furnishings of the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Moreover he made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:1, 2; 2 Kin. 16:14; Ezek. 43:13, 16</char></note>a bronze altar: twenty cubits was its length, twenty cubits its width, and ten cubits its height.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:17–21; 1 Kin. 7:23–26</char></note>Then he made the Sea of cast <char style="it">bronze,</char> ten cubits from one brim to the other; <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> completely round. Its height <char style="it">was</char> five cubits, and a line of thirty cubits measured its circumference. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:24–26</char></note>And under it <char style="it">was</char> the likeness of oxen encircling it all around, ten to a cubit, all the way around the Sea. The oxen <char style="it">were</char> cast in two rows, when it was cast. <verse number="4" style="v" />It stood on twelve <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:25</char></note>oxen: three looking toward the north, three looking toward the west, three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east; the Sea <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">set</char> upon them, and all their back parts <char style="it">pointed</char> inward. <verse number="5" style="v" />It <char style="it">was</char> a handbreadth thick; and its brim was shaped like the brim of a cup, <char style="it">like</char> a lily blossom. It contained three thousand baths.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />He also made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:38, 40</char></note>ten lavers, and put five on the right side and five on the left, to wash in them; such things as they offered for the burnt offering they would wash in them, but the Sea <char style="it">was</char> for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:19–21</char></note>priests to wash in. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:49</char></note>And he made ten lampstands of gold <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:31; 1 Chr. 28:12, 19</char></note>according to their design, and set <char style="it">them</char> in the temple, five on the right side and five on the left. <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:48</char></note>He also made ten tables, and placed <char style="it">them</char> in the temple, five on the right side and five on the left. And he made one hundred <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:17</char></note>bowls of gold.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Furthermore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:36</char></note>he made the court of the priests, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:5</char></note>great court and doors for the court; and he overlaid these doors with bronze. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:39</char></note>He set the Sea on the right side, toward the southeast.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:40–51</char></note>Huram made the pots and the shovels and the bowls. So Huram finished doing the work that he was to do for King Solomon for the house of God: <verse number="12" style="v" />the two pillars and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:41</char></note>the bowl-shaped capitals <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">were</char> on top of the two pillars; the two networks covering the two bowl-shaped capitals which <char style="it">were</char> on top of the pillars; <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:20</char></note>four hundred pomegranates for the two networks (two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that <char style="it">were</char> on the pillars); <verse number="14" style="v" />he also made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:27, 43</char></note>carts and the lavers on the carts; <verse number="15" style="v" />one Sea and twelve oxen under it; <verse number="16" style="v" />also the pots, the shovels, the forks—and all their articles <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:45; 2 Chr. 2:13</char></note>Huram his master <char style="it">craftsman</char> made of burnished bronze for King Solomon for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />In the plain of Jordan the king had them cast in clay molds, between Succoth and Zeredah. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:47</char></note>And Solomon had all these articles made in such great abundance that the weight of the bronze was not determined.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Thus <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:48–50</char></note>Solomon had all the furnishings made for the house of God: the altar of gold and the tables on which <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:30</char></note>the showbread; <verse number="20" style="v" />the lampstands with their lamps of pure gold, to burn <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:20, 21</char></note>in the prescribed manner in front of the inner sanctuary, <verse number="21" style="v" />with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:31</char></note>the flowers and the lamps and the wick-trimmers of gold, of purest gold; <verse number="22" style="v" />the trimmers, the bowls, the ladles, and the censers of pure gold. As for the entry of the sanctuary, its inner doors to the Most Holy <char style="it">Place,</char> and the doors of the main hall of the temple, <char style="it">were</char> gold.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:51</char></note>all the work that Solomon had done for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was finished; and Solomon brought in the things which his father David had dedicated: the silver and the gold and all the furnishings. And he put <char style="it">them</char> in the treasuries of the house of God.</para>
	<para style="s">The Ark Brought into the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:1–9; Ps. 47:9</char></note>Now Solomon assembled the elders of Israel and all the heads of the tribes, the chief fathers of the children of Israel, in Jerusalem, that they might bring the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> up <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 6:12</char></note>from the City of David, which <char style="it">is</char> Zion. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:2</char></note>Therefore all the men of Israel assembled with the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:34; 2 Chr. 7:8–10</char></note>at the feast, which <char style="it">was</char> in the seventh month. <verse number="4" style="v" />So all the elders of Israel came, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 15:2, 15</char></note>Levites took up the ark. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then they brought up the ark, the tabernacle of meeting, and all the holy furnishings that <char style="it">were</char> in the tabernacle. The priests and the Levites brought them up. <verse number="6" style="v" />Also King Solomon, and all the congregation of Israel who were assembled with him before the ark, were sacrificing sheep and oxen that could not be counted or numbered for multitude. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then the priests brought in the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to its place, into the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:20</char></note>inner sanctuary of the temple, to the Most Holy <char style="it">Place,</char> under the wings of the cherubim. <verse number="8" style="v" />For the cherubim spread <char style="it">their</char> wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubim overshadowed the ark and its poles. <verse number="9" style="v" />The poles extended so that the ends of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:13–15</char></note>poles of the ark could be seen from <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">holy</char> <char style="it">place,</char> in front of the inner sanctuary; but they could not be seen from outside. And they are there to this day. <verse number="10" style="v" />Nothing was in the ark except the two tablets which Moses <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:16; Deut. 10:2, 5; 2 Chr. 6:11; Heb. 9:4</char></note>put <char style="it">there</char> at Horeb, when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">covenant</char> with the children of Israel, when they had come out of Egypt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And it came to pass when the priests came out of the <char style="it">Most</char> Holy <char style="it">Place</char> (for all the priests who <char style="it">were</char> present had sanctified themselves, without keeping to their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 24:1–5</char></note>divisions), <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:26; 1 Chr. 25:1–7</char></note>and the Levites <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> the singers, all those of Asaph and Heman and Jeduthun, with their sons and their brethren, stood at the east end of the altar, clothed in white linen, having cymbals, stringed instruments and harps, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 13:8; 15:16, 24</char></note>and with them one hundred and twenty priests sounding with trumpets— <verse number="13" style="v" />indeed it came to pass, when the trumpeters and singers <char style="it">were</char> as one, to make one sound to be heard in praising and thanking the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and when they lifted up their voice with the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of music, and praised the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <char style="it">saying:</char></para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 16:34, 41; 2 Chr. 7:3; Ezra 3:11; Ps. 100:5; 106:1; Ps. 136; Jer. 33:11</char></note><char style="it">“For He is</char> good,</para>
	<para style="q2">For His mercy <char style="it">endures</char> forever,”</para>
	<para style="p">that the house, the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, was filled with a cloud, <verse number="14" style="v" />so that the priests could not continue ministering because of the cloud; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:35; 1 Kin. 8:11; 2 Chr. 7:2; Ezek. 43:5</char></note>for the glory of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> filled the house of God.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:9; 20:21; 1 Kin. 8:12–21</char></note>Solomon spoke:</para>
	<para style="q1">“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said He would dwell in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 16:2); Ps. 97:2</char></note>dark cloud.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="2" style="v" />I have surely built You an exalted house,</para>
	<para style="q2">And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:13; 1 Chr. 17:12; 2 Chr. 7:12</char></note>a place for You to dwell in forever.”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Speech upon Completion of the Work</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then the king turned around and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 6:18</char></note>blessed the whole assembly of Israel, while all the assembly of Israel was standing. <verse number="4" style="v" />And he said: “Blessed <char style="it">be</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, who has fulfilled with His hands <char style="it">what</char> He spoke with His mouth to my father David, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 17:5</char></note>saying, <verse number="5" style="v" />‘Since the day that I brought My people out of the land of Egypt, I have chosen no city from any tribe of Israel <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">which</char> to build a house, that My name might be there, nor did I choose any man to be a ruler over My people Israel. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5–7; 2 Chr. 12:13; Zech. 2:12</char></note>Yet I have chosen Jerusalem, that My name may be there, and I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 16:7–13; 1 Chr. 28:4</char></note>have chosen David to be over My people Israel.’ <verse number="7" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:2; 1 Chr. 17:1; 28:2; Ps. 132:1–5</char></note>it was in the heart of my father David to build a temple for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="8" style="v" />But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to my father David, ‘Whereas it was in your heart to build a temple for My name, you did well in that it was in your heart. <verse number="9" style="v" />Nevertheless you shall not build the temple, but your son who will come from your body, he shall build the temple for My <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:3–6</char></note>name.’ <verse number="10" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has fulfilled His word which He spoke, and I have filled the position of my father David, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:12; 10:9</char></note>sit on the throne of Israel, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> promised; and I have built the temple for the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="11" style="v" />And there I have put the ark, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 5:7–10</char></note>in which <char style="it">is</char> the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He made with the children of Israel.”</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Prayer of Dedication</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:22; 2 Chr. 7:7–9</char></note>Then <char style="it">Solomon</char> stood before the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in the presence of all the assembly of Israel, and spread out his hands <verse number="13" style="v" />(for Solomon had made a bronze platform five cubits long, five cubits wide, and three cubits high, and had set it in the midst of the court; and he stood on it, knelt down on his knees before all the assembly of Israel, and spread out his hands toward heaven); <verse number="14" style="v" />and he said: “<char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 15:11; Deut. 4:39)</char></note><char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no God in heaven or on earth like You, who keep <char style="it">Your</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 7:9)</char></note>covenant and mercy with Your servants who walk before You with all their hearts. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 22:9, 10</char></note>You have kept what You promised Your servant David my father; You have both spoken with Your mouth and fulfilled <char style="it">it</char> with Your hand, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> this day. <verse number="16" style="v" />Therefore, <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, now keep what You promised Your servant David my father, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12, 16; 1 Kin. 2:4; 6:12; 2 Chr. 7:18</char></note>‘You shall not fail to have a man sit before Me on the throne of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 132:12</char></note>only if your sons take heed to their way, that they walk in My law as you have walked before Me.’ <verse number="17" style="v" />And now, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, let Your word come true, which You have spoken to Your servant David.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />“But will God indeed dwell with men on the earth? <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 2:6; Is. 66:1; Acts 7:49)</char></note>Behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens cannot contain You. How much less this temple which I have built! <verse number="19" style="v" />Yet regard the prayer of Your servant and his supplication, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, and listen to the cry and the prayer which Your servant is praying before You: <verse number="20" style="v" />that Your eyes may be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:15</char></note>open toward this temple day and night, toward the place where <char style="it">You</char> said <char style="it">You</char> <char style="it">would</char> put Your name, that You may hear the prayer which Your servant makes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 5:7; Dan. 6:10</char></note>toward this place. <verse number="21" style="v" />And may You hear the supplications of Your servant and of Your people Israel, when they pray toward this place. Hear from heaven Your dwelling place, and when You hear, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 43:25; 44:22; Mic. 7:18)</char></note>forgive.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />“If anyone sins against his neighbor, and is forced to take an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:8–11</char></note>oath, and comes <char style="it">and</char> takes an oath before Your altar in this temple, <verse number="23" style="v" />then hear from heaven, and act, and judge Your servants, bringing retribution on the wicked by bringing his way on his own head, and justifying the righteous by giving him according to his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Job 34:11)</char></note>righteousness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />“Or if Your people Israel are defeated before an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:14, 15</char></note>enemy because they have sinned against You, and return and confess Your name, and pray and make supplication before You in this temple, <verse number="25" style="v" />then hear from heaven and forgive the sin of Your people Israel, and bring them back to the land which You gave to them and their fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />“When the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:23, 24; 1 Kin. 17:1</char></note>heavens are shut up and there is no rain because they have sinned against You, when they pray toward this place and confess Your name, and turn from their sin because You afflict them, <verse number="27" style="v" />then hear <char style="it">in</char> heaven, and forgive the sin of Your servants, Your people Israel, that You may teach them the good way in which they should walk; and send rain on Your land which You have given to Your people as an inheritance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />“When there <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:9</char></note>is famine in the land, pestilence or blight or mildew, locusts or grasshoppers; when their enemies besiege them in the land of their cities; whatever plague or whatever <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Mic. 6:13)</char></note>sickness <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is;</char> <verse number="29" style="v" />whatever prayer, whatever supplication is <char style="it">made</char> by anyone, or by all Your people Israel, when each one knows his own burden and his own grief, and spreads out his hands to this temple: <verse number="30" style="v" />then hear from heaven Your dwelling place, and forgive, and give to everyone according to all his ways, whose heart You know (for You alone <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Chr. 28:9; Prov. 21:2; 24:12)</char></note>know the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Sam. 16:7)</char></note>hearts of the sons of men), <verse number="31" style="v" />that they may fear You, to walk in Your ways as long as they live in the land which You gave to our fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />“Moreover, concerning a foreigner, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">John 12:20; Acts 8:27</char></note>who is not of Your people Israel, but has come from a far country for the sake of Your great name and Your mighty hand and Your outstretched arm, when they come and pray in this temple; <verse number="33" style="v" />then hear from heaven Your dwelling place, and do according to all for which the foreigner calls to You, that all peoples of the earth may know Your name and fear You, as <char style="it">do</char> Your people Israel, and that they may know that this temple which I have built is called by Your name.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />“When Your people go out to battle against their enemies, wherever You send them, and when they pray to You toward this city which You have chosen and the temple which I have built for Your name, <verse number="35" style="v" />then hear from heaven their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />“When they sin against You (for <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 20:9; Eccl. 7:20; (Rom. 3:9, 19; 5:12; Gal. 3:10); James 3:2; 1 John 1:8</char></note>no one who does not sin), and You become angry with them and deliver them to the enemy, and they take them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:63–68</char></note>captive to a land far or near; <verse number="37" style="v" /><char style="it">yet</char> when they come to themselves in the land where they were carried captive, and repent, and make supplication to You in the land of their captivity, saying, ‘We have sinned, we have done wrong, and have committed wickedness’; <verse number="38" style="v" />and <char style="it">when</char> they return to You with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their captivity, where they have been carried captive, and pray toward their land which You gave to their fathers, the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:10</char></note>city which You have chosen, and toward the temple which I have built for Your name: <verse number="39" style="v" />then hear from heaven Your dwelling place their prayer and their supplications, and maintain their cause, and forgive Your people who have sinned against You. <verse number="40" style="v" />Now, my God, I pray, let Your eyes be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:20</char></note>open and <char style="it">let</char> Your ears <char style="it">be</char> attentive to the prayer <char style="it">made</char> in this place.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="41" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 132:8–10, 16</char></note>“Now therefore,</para>
	<para style="q2">Arise, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God, to Your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:2</char></note>resting place,</para>
	<para style="q2">You and the ark of Your strength.</para>
	<para style="q2">Let Your priests, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God, be clothed with salvation,</para>
	<para style="q2">And let Your saints <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 9:25</char></note>rejoice in goodness.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="42" style="v" />“O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God, do not turn away the face of Your Anointed;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:15; Ps. 89:49; 132:1, 8–10; Is. 55:3</char></note>Remember the mercies of Your servant David.”</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon Dedicates the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />When <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:54</char></note>Solomon had finished praying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 9:24; Judg. 6:21; 1 Kin. 18:38; 1 Chr. 21:26</char></note>fire came down from heaven and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:10, 11</char></note>the glory of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> filled the temple. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 5:14</char></note>And the priests could not enter the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, because the glory of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had filled the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s house. <verse number="3" style="v" />When all the children of Israel saw how the fire came down, and the glory of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> on the temple, they bowed their faces to the ground on the pavement, and worshiped and praised the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <char style="it">saying:</char></para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 5:13; Ps. 106:1; 136:1</char></note>“For <char style="it">He</char> <char style="it">is</char> good,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 16:41; 2 Chr. 20:21</char></note>For His mercy <char style="it">endures</char> forever.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:62, 63</char></note>Then the king and all the people offered sacrifices before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="5" style="v" />King Solomon offered a sacrifice of twenty-two thousand bulls and one hundred and twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the people dedicated the house of God. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 15:16</char></note>And the priests attended to their services; the Levites also with instruments of the music of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which King David had made to praise the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, “For His mercy <char style="it">endures</char> forever,” whenever David offered praise by their ministry. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 5:12</char></note>The priests sounded trumpets opposite them, while all Israel stood.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Furthermore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:64–66; 9:3</char></note>Solomon consecrated the middle of the court that <char style="it">was</char> in front of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; for there he offered burnt offerings and the fat of the peace offerings, because the bronze altar which Solomon had made was not able to receive the burnt offerings, the grain offerings, and the fat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:65</char></note>At that time Solomon kept the feast seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great assembly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:21, 24; 2 Kin. 14:25</char></note>from the entrance of Hamath to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:3</char></note>the Brook of Egypt. <verse number="9" style="v" />And on the eighth day they held a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:36</char></note>sacred assembly, for they observed the dedication of the altar seven days, and the feast seven days. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:66</char></note>On the twenty-third day of the seventh month he sent the people away to their tents, joyful and glad of heart for the good that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had done for David, for Solomon, and for His people Israel. <verse number="11" style="v" />Thus <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:1</char></note>Solomon finished the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the king’s house; and Solomon successfully accomplished all that came into his heart to make in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in his own house.</para>
	<para style="s">God’s Second Appearance to Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:5; 11:9</char></note>appeared to Solomon by night, and said to him: “I have heard your prayer, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5, 11</char></note>and have chosen this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:20</char></note>place for Myself as a house of sacrifice. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:23, 24; 1 Kin. 17:1; 2 Chr. 6:26–28</char></note>When I shut up heaven and there is no rain, or command the locusts to devour the land, or send pestilence among My people, <verse number="14" style="v" />if My people who are <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:10; (Is. 43:7)</char></note>called by My name will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:6, 7; (James 4:10)</char></note>humble themselves, and pray and seek My face, and turn from their wicked ways, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:27, 30</char></note>then I will hear from heaven, and will forgive their sin and heal their land. <verse number="15" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:20, 40</char></note>My eyes will be open and My ears attentive to prayer <char style="it">made</char> in this place. <verse number="16" style="v" />For now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:3; 2 Chr. 6:6</char></note>I have chosen and sanctified this house, that My name may be there forever; and My eyes and My heart will be there perpetually. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:4</char></note>As for you, if you walk before Me as your father David walked, and do according to all that I have commanded you, and if you keep My statutes and My judgments, <verse number="18" style="v" />then I will establish the throne of your kingdom, as I covenanted with David your father, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12–16; 1 Kin. 2:4; 2 Chr. 6:16</char></note>‘You shall not fail <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">have</char> a man as ruler in Israel.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:14, 33; (Deut. 28:15, 36)</char></note>“But if you turn away and forsake My statutes and My commandments which I have set before you, and go and serve other gods, and worship them, <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:63–68; 2 Kin. 25:1–7</char></note>then I will uproot them from My land which I have given them; and this house which I have sanctified for My name I will cast out of My sight, and will make it a proverb and a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 44:14</char></note>byword among all peoples.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />“And <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">for</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:9</char></note>this house, which is exalted, everyone who passes by it will be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:8</char></note>astonished and say, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 29:24, 25; Jer. 22:8, 9)</char></note>‘Why has the <char style="sc">Lord</char> done thus to this land and this house?’ <verse number="22" style="v" />Then they will answer, ‘Because they forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers, who brought them out of the land of Egypt, and embraced other gods, and worshiped them and served them; therefore He has brought all this calamity on them.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Additional Achievements</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />It <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:10–14</char></note>came to pass at the end of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:38—7:1</char></note>twenty years, when Solomon had built the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and his own house, <verse number="2" style="v" />that the cities which Hiram had given to Solomon, Solomon built them; and he settled the children of Israel there. <verse number="3" style="v" />And Solomon went to Hamath Zobah and seized it. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:17, 18</char></note>He also built Tadmor in the wilderness, and all the storage cities which he built in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 18:3, 9</char></note>Hamath. <verse number="5" style="v" />He built Upper Beth Horon and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 7:24</char></note>Lower Beth Horon, fortified cities <char style="it">with</char> walls, gates, and bars, <verse number="6" style="v" />also Baalath and all the storage cities that Solomon had, and all the chariot cities and the cities of the cavalry, and all that Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:11</char></note>desired to build in Jerusalem, in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:18–21; 1 Kin. 9:20</char></note>All the people <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> left of the Hittites, Amorites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites, who <char style="it">were</char> not of Israel— <verse number="8" style="v" />that is, their descendants who were left in the land after them, whom the children of Israel did not destroy—from these Solomon raised forced labor, as it is to this day. <verse number="9" style="v" />But Solomon did not make the children of Israel servants for his work. Some <char style="it">were</char> men of war, captains of his officers, captains of his chariots, and his cavalry. <verse number="10" style="v" />And others <char style="it">were</char> chiefs of the officials of King Solomon: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:23</char></note>two hundred and fifty, who ruled over the people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Now Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:1; 7:8; 9:24; 11:1</char></note>brought the daughter of Pharaoh up from the City of David to the house he had built for her, for he said, “My wife shall not dwell in the house of David king of Israel, because <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">places</char> to which the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has come are holy.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then Solomon offered burnt offerings to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> on the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which he had built before the vestibule, <verse number="13" style="v" />according to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:38–42; Num. 28:3, 9, 11, 26; 29:1</char></note>daily rate, offering according to the commandment of Moses, for the Sabbaths, the New Moons, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:14–17; 34:22, 23; Deut. 16:16</char></note>three appointed yearly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:1–44</char></note>feasts—the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the Feast of Weeks, and the Feast of Tabernacles. <verse number="14" style="v" />And, according to the order of David his father, he appointed the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 24:3</char></note>divisions of the priests for their service, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 25:1</char></note>the Levites for their duties (to praise and serve before the priests) as the duty of each day required, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 9:17; 26:1</char></note>gatekeepers by their divisions at each gate; for so David the man of God had commanded. <verse number="15" style="v" />They did not depart from the command of the king to the priests and Levites concerning any matter or concerning the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 26:20–28</char></note>treasuries.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Now all the work of Solomon was well-ordered from the day of the foundation of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> until it was finished. So the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was completed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then Solomon went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:26; 2 Chr. 20:36</char></note>Ezion Geber and Elath on the seacoast, in the land of Edom. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:27; 2 Chr. 9:10, 13</char></note>And Hiram sent him ships by the hand of his servants, and servants who knew the sea. They went with the servants of Solomon to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 29:4</char></note>Ophir, and acquired four hundred and fifty talents of gold from there, and brought it to King Solomon.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Queen of Sheba’s Praise of Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:1; Ps. 72:10; (Matt. 12:42; Luke 11:31)</char></note>when the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, she came to Jerusalem to test Solomon with hard questions, <char style="it">having</char> a very great retinue, camels that bore spices, gold in abundance, and precious stones; and when she came to Solomon, she spoke with him about all that was in her heart. <verse number="2" style="v" />So Solomon answered all her questions; there was nothing so difficult for Solomon that he could not explain it to her. <verse number="3" style="v" />And when the queen of Sheba had seen the wisdom of Solomon, the house that he had built, <verse number="4" style="v" />the food on his table, the seating of his servants, the service of his waiters and their apparel, his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 1:11</char></note>cupbearers and their apparel, and his entryway by which he went up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, there was no more spirit in her.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then she said to the king: “<char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">was</char> a true report which I heard in my own land about your words and your wisdom. <verse number="6" style="v" />However I did not believe their words until I came and saw with my own eyes; and indeed the half of the greatness of your wisdom was not told me. You exceed the fame of which I heard. <verse number="7" style="v" />Happy <char style="it">are</char> your men and happy <char style="it">are</char> these your servants, who stand continually before you and hear your wisdom! <verse number="8" style="v" />Blessed be the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, who delighted in you, setting you on His throne <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">be</char> king for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God! Because your God has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:8; 2 Chr. 2:11; (Ps. 44:3)</char></note>loved Israel, to establish them forever, therefore He made you king over them, to do justice and righteousness.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And she gave the king one hundred and twenty talents of gold, spices in great abundance, and precious stones; there never were any spices such as those the queen of Sheba gave to King Solomon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Also, the servants of Hiram and the servants of Solomon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:18</char></note>who brought gold from Ophir, brought algum wood and precious stones. <verse number="11" style="v" />And the king made walkways <char style="it">of</char> the algum wood for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and for the king’s house, also harps and stringed instruments for singers; and there were none such <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">these</char> seen before in the land of Judah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Now King Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all she desired, whatever she asked, <char style="it">much</char> <char style="it">more</char> than she had brought to the king. So she turned and went to her own country, she and her servants.</para>
	<para style="s">Solomon’s Great Wealth</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:14–29</char></note>The weight of gold that came to Solomon yearly was six hundred and sixty-six talents of gold, <verse number="14" style="v" />besides <char style="it">what</char> the traveling merchants and traders brought. And all the kings of Arabia and governors of the country brought gold and silver to Solomon. <verse number="15" style="v" />And King Solomon made two hundred large shields of hammered gold; six hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of hammered gold went into each shield. <verse number="16" style="v" /><char style="it">He</char> also <char style="it">made</char> three hundred shields of hammered gold; three hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of gold went into each shield. The king put them in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:2</char></note>House of the Forest of Lebanon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with pure gold. <verse number="18" style="v" />The throne <char style="it">had</char> six steps, with a footstool of gold, <char style="it">which</char> <char style="it">were</char> fastened to the throne; there were armrests on either side of the place of the seat, and two lions stood beside the armrests. <verse number="19" style="v" />Twelve lions stood there, one on each side of the six steps; nothing like <char style="it">this</char> had been made for any <char style="it">other</char> kingdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />All King Solomon’s drinking vessels <char style="it">were</char> gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Lebanon <char style="it">were</char> pure gold. Not <char style="it">one</char> <char style="it">was</char> silver, for this was accounted as nothing in the days of Solomon. <verse number="21" style="v" />For the king’s ships went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:36, 37; Ps. 72:10</char></note>Tarshish with the servants of Hiram. Once every three years the merchant ships came, bringing gold, silver, ivory, apes, and monkeys.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />So King Solomon surpassed all the kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. <verse number="23" style="v" />And all the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. <verse number="24" style="v" />Each man brought his present: articles of silver and gold, garments, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:11</char></note>armor, spices, horses, and mules, at a set rate year by year.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Solomon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:16; 1 Kin. 4:26; 10:26; 2 Chr. 1:14; Is. 2:7</char></note>had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen whom he stationed in the chariot cities and with the king at Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:21</char></note>So he reigned over all the kings <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:18; Ps. 72:8</char></note>from the River to the land of the Philistines, as far as the border of Egypt. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:27</char></note>The king made silver <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">common</char> in Jerusalem as stones, and he made cedar trees <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 1:15–17</char></note>as abundant as the sycamores which <char style="it">are</char> in the lowland. <verse number="28" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:28; 2 Chr. 1:16</char></note>And they brought horses to Solomon from Egypt and from all lands.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Solomon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:41</char></note>Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, first and last, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of Nathan the prophet, in the prophecy of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:29</char></note>Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:15; 13:22</char></note>Iddo the seer concerning Jeroboam the son of Nebat? <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:21; 11:42, 43; 1 Chr. 29:28</char></note>Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years. <verse number="31" style="v" />Then Solomon rested with his fathers, and was buried in the City of David his father. And Rehoboam his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Revolt Against Rehoboam</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:1–20</char></note>Rehoboam went to Shechem, for all Israel had gone to Shechem to make him king. <verse number="2" style="v" />So it happened, when Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard <char style="it">it</char> (he was in Egypt, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:40</char></note>where he had fled from the presence of King Solomon), that Jeroboam returned from Egypt. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then they sent for him and called him. And Jeroboam and all Israel came and spoke to Rehoboam, saying, <verse number="4" style="v" />“Your father made our yoke heavy; now therefore, lighten the burdensome service of your father and his heavy yoke which he put on us, and we will serve you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So he said to them, “Come back to me after three days.” And the people departed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then King Rehoboam consulted the elders who stood before his father Solomon while he still lived, saying, “How do you advise <char style="it">me</char> to answer these people?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And they spoke to him, saying, “If you are kind to these people, and please them, and speak good words to them, they will be your servants forever.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:8–11</char></note>But he rejected the advice which the elders had given him, and consulted the young men who had grown up with him, who stood before him. <verse number="9" style="v" />And he said to them, “What advice do you give? How should we answer this people who have spoken to me, saying, ‘Lighten the yoke which your father put on us’?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Then the young men who had grown up with him spoke to him, saying, “Thus you should speak to the people who have spoken to you, saying, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, but you make <char style="it">it</char> lighter on us’—thus you shall say to them: ‘My little <char style="it">finger</char> shall be thicker than my father’s waist! <verse number="11" style="v" />And now, whereas my father put a heavy yoke on you, I will add to your yoke; my father chastised you with whips, but I <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">chastise</char> <char style="it">you</char> with scourges!’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:12–14</char></note>Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam on the third day, as the king had directed, saying, “Come back to me the third day.” <verse number="13" style="v" />Then the king answered them roughly. King Rehoboam rejected the advice of the elders, <verse number="14" style="v" />and he spoke to them according to the advice of the young men, saying, “My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to it; my father chastised you with whips, but I <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">chastise</char> <char style="it">you</char> with scourges!” <verse number="15" style="v" />So the king did not listen to the people; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 14:4; 1 Chr. 5:22; 2 Chr. 11:4; 22:7</char></note>for the turn <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">events</char> was from God, that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> might fulfill His <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:29–39</char></note>word, which He had spoken by the hand of Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Now when all Israel <char style="it">saw</char> that the king did not listen to them, the people answered the king, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1">“What share have we in David?</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">We</char> <char style="it">have</char> no inheritance in the son of Jesse.</para>
	<para style="q2">Every man to your tents, O Israel!</para>
	<para style="q2">Now see to your own house, O David!”</para>
	<para style="p">So all Israel departed to their tents. <verse number="17" style="v" />But Rehoboam reigned over the children of Israel who dwelt in the cities of Judah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then King Rehoboam sent Hadoram, who <char style="it">was</char> in charge of revenue; but the children of Israel stoned him with stones, and he died. Therefore King Rehoboam mounted <char style="it">his</char> chariot in haste to flee to Jerusalem. <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:19</char></note>So Israel has been in rebellion against the house of David to this day.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:21–24</char></note>when Rehoboam came to Jerusalem, he assembled from the house of Judah and Benjamin one hundred and eighty thousand chosen <char style="it">men</char> who were warriors, to fight against Israel, that he might restore the kingdom to Rehoboam.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />But the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 12:5; 2 Chr. 12:15</char></note>to Shemaiah the man of God, saying, <verse number="3" style="v" />“Speak to Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying, <verse number="4" style="v" />‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: “You shall not go up or fight against your brethren! Let every man return to his house, for this thing is from Me.” ’ ” Therefore they obeyed the words of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and turned back from attacking Jeroboam.</para>
	<para style="s">Rehoboam Fortifies the Cities</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So Rehoboam dwelt in Jerusalem, and built cities for defense in Judah. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he built Bethlehem, Etam, Tekoa, <verse number="7" style="v" />Beth Zur, Sochoh, Adullam, <verse number="8" style="v" />Gath, Mareshah, Ziph, <verse number="9" style="v" />Adoraim, Lachish, Azekah, <verse number="10" style="v" />Zorah, Aijalon, and Hebron, which are in Judah and Benjamin, fortified cities. <verse number="11" style="v" />And he fortified the strongholds, and put captains in them, and stores of food, oil, and wine. <verse number="12" style="v" />Also in every city <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">put</char> shields and spears, and made them very strong, having Judah and Benjamin on his side.</para>
	<para style="s">Priests and Levites Move to Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And from all their territories the priests and the Levites who <char style="it">were</char> in all Israel took their stand with him. <verse number="14" style="v" />For the Levites left <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:2–5</char></note>their common-lands and their possessions and came to Judah and Jerusalem, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28–33; 2 Chr. 13:9</char></note>Jeroboam and his sons had rejected them from serving as priests to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:31; 13:33; 14:9; (Hos. 13:2)</char></note>Then he appointed for himself priests for the high places, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 17:7; 1 Cor. 10:20)</char></note>the demons, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28</char></note>the calf idols which he had made. <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:7</char></note>And after <char style="it">the</char> Levites <char style="it">left,</char> those from all the tribes of Israel, such as set their heart to seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:9, 10; 30:11, 18</char></note>came to Jerusalem to sacrifice to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers. <verse number="17" style="v" />So they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:1, 13</char></note>strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and made Rehoboam the son of Solomon strong for three years, because they walked in the way of David and Solomon for three years.</para>
	<para style="s">The Family of Rehoboam</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then Rehoboam took for himself as wife Mahalath the daughter of Jerimoth the son of David, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">of</char> Abihail the daughter of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 16:6</char></note>Eliah the son of Jesse. <verse number="19" style="v" />And she bore him children: Jeush, Shamariah, and Zaham. <verse number="20" style="v" />After her he took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:2</char></note>Maachah the granddaughter of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:2</char></note>Absalom; and she bore him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:31</char></note>Abijah, Attai, Ziza, and Shelomith. <verse number="21" style="v" />Now Rehoboam loved Maachah the granddaughter of Absalom more than all his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:17</char></note>wives and his concubines; for he took eighteen wives and sixty concubines, and begot twenty-eight sons and sixty daughters. <verse number="22" style="v" />And Rehoboam <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 21:15–17</char></note>appointed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:1</char></note>Abijah the son of Maachah as chief, <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">be</char> leader among his brothers; for he <char style="it">intended</char> to make him king. <verse number="23" style="v" />He dealt wisely, and dispersed some of his sons throughout all the territories of Judah and Benjamin, to every <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:5</char></note>fortified city; and he gave them provisions in abundance. He also sought many wives <char style="it">for</char> <char style="it">them.</char></para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Egypt Attacks Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:17</char></note>it came to pass, when Rehoboam had established the kingdom and had strengthened himself, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:22–24</char></note>he forsook the law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and all Israel along with him. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:40; 14:25</char></note>And it happened in the fifth year of King Rehoboam <char style="it">that</char> Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, because they had transgressed against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse number="3" style="v" />with twelve hundred chariots, sixty thousand horsemen, and people without number who came with him out of Egypt—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:8; Nah. 3:9</char></note>the Lubim and the Sukkiim and the Ethiopians. <verse number="4" style="v" />And he took the fortified cities of Judah and came to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:2</char></note>Shemaiah the prophet came to Rehoboam and the leaders of Judah, who were gathered together in Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said to them, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘You have forsaken Me, and therefore I also have left you in the hand of Shishak.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So the leaders of Israel and the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(James 4:10)</char></note>humbled themselves; and they said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 9:27; (Dan. 9:14)</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> righteous.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Now when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> saw that they humbled themselves, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:28, 29</char></note>the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to Shemaiah, saying, “They have humbled themselves; <char style="it">therefore</char> I will not destroy them, but I will grant them some deliverance. My wrath shall not be poured out on Jerusalem by the hand of Shishak. <verse number="8" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 26:13</char></note>they will be his servants, that they may distinguish <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 28:47, 48)</char></note>My service from the service of the kingdoms of the nations.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:25, 26</char></note>So Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, and took away the treasures of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the treasures of the king’s house; he took everything. He also carried away the gold shields which Solomon had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:16, 17; 2 Chr. 9:15, 16</char></note>made. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then King Rehoboam made bronze shields in their place, and committed <char style="it">them</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:27</char></note>to the hands of the captains of the guard, who guarded the doorway of the king’s house. <verse number="11" style="v" />And whenever the king entered the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the guard would go and bring them out; then they would take them back into the guardroom. <verse number="12" style="v" />When he humbled himself, the wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> turned from him, so as not to destroy <char style="it">him</char> completely; and things also went well in Judah.</para>
	<para style="s">The End of Rehoboam’s Reign</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Thus King Rehoboam strengthened himself in Jerusalem and reigned. Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:21</char></note>Rehoboam <char style="it">was</char> forty-one years old when he became king; and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:6</char></note>the city which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put His name there. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Naamah, an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:1, 5</char></note>Ammonitess. <verse number="14" style="v" />And he did evil, because he did not prepare his heart to seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />The acts of Rehoboam, first and last, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of Shemaiah the prophet, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:29; 13:22</char></note>and of Iddo the seer concerning genealogies? <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:30</char></note>And <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">were</char> wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all their days. <verse number="16" style="v" />So Rehoboam rested with his fathers, and was buried in the City of David. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:20–22</char></note>Abijah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Abijah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:1</char></note>the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam, Abijah became king over <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:17</char></note>Judah. <verse number="2" style="v" />He reigned three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Michaiah the daughter of Uriel of Gibeah.</para>
	<para style="p">And there was war between Abijah and Jeroboam. <verse number="3" style="v" />Abijah set the battle in order with an army of valiant warriors, four hundred thousand choice men. Jeroboam also drew up in battle formation against him with eight hundred thousand choice men, mighty men of valor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Then Abijah stood on Mount <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:22</char></note>Zemaraim, which <char style="it">is</char> in the mountains of Ephraim, and said, “Hear me, Jeroboam and all Israel: <verse number="5" style="v" />Should you not know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:8–16</char></note>gave the dominion over Israel to David forever, to him and his sons, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:13; Num. 18:19</char></note>by a covenant of salt? <verse number="6" style="v" />Yet Jeroboam the son of Nebat, the servant of Solomon the son of David, rose up and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:28; 12:20</char></note>rebelled against his lord. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:4</char></note>worthless rogues gathered to him, and strengthened themselves against Rehoboam the son of Solomon, when Rehoboam was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:13</char></note>young and inexperienced and could not withstand them. <verse number="8" style="v" />And now you think to withstand the kingdom of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which is in the hand of the sons of David; and you <char style="it">are</char> a great multitude, and with you are the gold calves which Jeroboam <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28; 14:9; 2 Chr. 11:15; (Hos. 8:4–6)</char></note>made for you as gods. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:13–15</char></note>Have you not cast out the priests of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and made for yourselves priests, like the peoples of <char style="it">other</char> lands, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:29–33</char></note>so that whoever comes to consecrate himself with a young bull and seven rams may be a priest of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 2:11; 5:7</char></note><char style="it">things</char> <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">are</char> not gods? <verse number="10" style="v" />But as for us, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> our <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:15</char></note>God, and we have not forsaken Him; and the priests who minister to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">are</char> the sons of Aaron, and the Levites <char style="it">attend</char> to <char style="it">their</char> duties. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:38; 2 Chr. 2:4</char></note>And they burn to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> every morning and every evening burnt sacrifices and sweet incense; <char style="it">they</char> also <char style="it">set</char> the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:30; Lev. 24:5–9</char></note>showbread <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">order</char> <char style="it">on</char> the pure <char style="it">gold</char> table, and the lampstand of gold with its lamps <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:20, 21; Lev. 24:2, 3</char></note>to burn every evening; for we keep the command of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, but you have forsaken Him. <verse number="12" style="v" />Now look, God Himself is with us as <char style="it">our</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:13–15; (Heb. 2:10)</char></note>head, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Num. 10:8–10)</char></note>and His priests with sounding trumpets to sound the alarm against you. O children of Israel, do not fight against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of your fathers, for you shall not prosper!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />But Jeroboam caused an ambush to go around behind them; so they were in front of Judah, and the ambush <char style="it">was</char> behind them. <verse number="14" style="v" />And when Judah looked around, to their surprise the battle line <char style="it">was</char> at both front and rear; and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:7; 2 Chr. 6:34, 35; 14:11</char></note>cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and the priests sounded the trumpets. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then the men of Judah gave a shout; and as the men of Judah shouted, it happened that God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:14; 2 Chr. 14:12</char></note>struck Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah. <verse number="16" style="v" />And the children of Israel fled before Judah, and God delivered them into their hand. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then Abijah and his people struck them with a great slaughter; so five hundred thousand choice men of Israel fell slain. <verse number="18" style="v" />Thus the children of Israel were subdued at that time; and the children of Judah prevailed, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 5:20; 2 Chr. 14:11; (Ps. 22:5)</char></note>because they relied on the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And Abijah pursued Jeroboam and took cities from him: Bethel with its villages, Jeshanah with its villages, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:9</char></note>Ephrain with its villages. <verse number="20" style="v" />So Jeroboam did not recover strength again in the days of Abijah; and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:6; 25:38; Acts 12:23</char></note>struck him, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:20</char></note>he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />But Abijah grew mighty, married fourteen wives, and begot twenty-two sons and sixteen daughters. <verse number="22" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Abijah, his ways, and his sayings <char style="it">are</char> written in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:29</char></note>the annals of the prophet Iddo.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />So Abijah rested with his fathers, and they buried him in the City of David. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:8</char></note>Asa his son reigned in his place. In his days the land was quiet for ten years.</para>
	<para style="s">Asa Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Asa did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> good and right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, <verse number="3" style="v" />for he removed the altars of the foreign <char style="it">gods</char> and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:14; 2 Chr. 15:17</char></note>the high places, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 34:13)</char></note>broke down the <char style="it">sacred</char> pillars <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:7</char></note>and cut down the wooden images. <verse number="4" style="v" />He commanded Judah to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 7:14)</char></note>seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers, and to observe the law and the commandment. <verse number="5" style="v" />He also removed the high places and the incense altars from all the cities of Judah, and the kingdom was quiet under him. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he built fortified cities in Judah, for the land had rest; he had no war in those years, because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had given him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:15</char></note>rest. <verse number="7" style="v" />Therefore he said to Judah, “Let us build these cities and make walls around <char style="it">them,</char> and towers, gates, and bars, <char style="it">while</char> the land <char style="it">is</char> yet before us, because we have sought the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God; we have sought <char style="it">Him,</char> and He has given us rest on every side.” So they built and prospered. <verse number="8" style="v" />And Asa had an army of three hundred thousand from Judah who carried shields and spears, and from Benjamin two hundred and eighty thousand men who carried shields and drew <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 12:2</char></note>bows; all these <char style="it">were</char> mighty men of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:3</char></note>valor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:2, 3; 16:8</char></note>Then Zerah the Ethiopian came out against them with an army of a million men and three hundred chariots, and he came to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:44</char></note>Mareshah. <verse number="10" style="v" />So Asa went out against him, and they set the troops in battle array in the Valley of Zephathah at Mareshah. <verse number="11" style="v" />And Asa <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:10; 2 Chr. 13:14; (Ps. 22:5)</char></note>cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, and said, “<char style="sc">Lord</char>, <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Sam. 14:6)</char></note>nothing for You to help, whether with many or with those who have no power; help us, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, for we rest on You, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 17:45; (Prov. 18:10)</char></note>in Your name we go against this multitude. O <char style="sc">Lord</char>, You <char style="it">are</char> our God; do not let man prevail against You!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:15</char></note>struck the Ethiopians before Asa and Judah, and the Ethiopians fled. <verse number="13" style="v" />And Asa and the people who <char style="it">were</char> with him pursued them to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 10:19; 20:1</char></note>Gerar. So the Ethiopians were overthrown, and they could not recover, for they were broken before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and His army. And they carried away very much spoil. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then they defeated all the cities around Gerar, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:5; Deut. 11:25; Josh. 2:9; 2 Chr. 17:10</char></note>the fear of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon them; and they plundered all the cities, for there was exceedingly much spoil in them. <verse number="15" style="v" />They also attacked the livestock enclosures, and carried off sheep and camels in abundance, and returned to Jerusalem.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Reforms of Asa</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 24:2; Judg. 3:10; 2 Chr. 20:14; 24:20</char></note>the Spirit of God came upon Azariah the son of Oded. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he went out to meet Asa, and said to him: “Hear me, Asa, and all Judah and Benjamin. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(James 4:8)</char></note>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> with you while you are with Him. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Chr. 28:9); 2 Chr. 14:4; 33:12, 13; (Jer. 29:13; Matt. 7:7)</char></note>If you seek Him, He will be found by you; but if <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:20</char></note>you forsake Him, He will forsake you. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Hos. 3:4</char></note>For a long time Israel <char style="it">has</char> <char style="it">been</char> without the true God, without a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:2</char></note>teaching priest, and without <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:11; 2 Chr. 17:8, 9</char></note>law; <verse number="4" style="v" />but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 4:29)</char></note>when in their trouble they turned to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, and sought Him, He was found by them. <verse number="5" style="v" />And in those times <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> no peace to the one who went out, nor to the one who came in, but great turmoil <char style="it">was</char> on all the inhabitants of the lands. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 24:7</char></note>So nation was destroyed by nation, and city by city, for God troubled them with every adversity. <verse number="7" style="v" />But you, be strong and do not let your hands be weak, for your work shall be rewarded!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And when Asa heard these words and the prophecy of Oded the prophet, he took courage, and removed the abominable idols from all the land of Judah and Benjamin and from the cities <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:19</char></note>which he had taken in the mountains of Ephraim; and he restored the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that <char style="it">was</char> before the vestibule of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then he gathered all Judah and Benjamin, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:16</char></note>those who dwelt with them from Ephraim, Manasseh, and Simeon, for they came over to him in great numbers from Israel when they saw that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God was with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So they gathered together at Jerusalem in the third month, in the fifteenth year of the reign of Asa. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:13–15</char></note>And they offered to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at that time seven hundred bulls and seven thousand sheep from the spoil they had brought. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:3; 2 Chr. 23:16; 34:31; Neh. 10:29</char></note>entered into a covenant to seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers with all their heart and with all their soul; <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:20</char></note>and whoever would not seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:5–15</char></note>was to be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then they took an oath before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with a loud voice, with shouting and trumpets and rams’ horns. <verse number="15" style="v" />And all Judah rejoiced at the oath, for they had sworn with all their heart and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:2</char></note>sought Him with all their soul; and He was found by them, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:7</char></note>rest all around.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Also he removed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:2, 10, 13</char></note>Maachah, the mother of Asa the king, from <char style="it">being</char> queen mother, because she had made an obscene image of Asherah; and Asa cut down her obscene image, then crushed and burned <char style="it">it</char> by the Brook Kidron. <verse number="17" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:14; 2 Chr. 14:3, 5</char></note>the high places were not removed from Israel. Nevertheless the heart of Asa was loyal all his days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />He also brought into the house of God the things that his father had dedicated and that he himself had dedicated: silver and gold and utensils. <verse number="19" style="v" />And there was no war until the thirty-fifth year of the reign of Asa.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Asa’s Treaty with Syria</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the thirty-sixth year of the reign of Asa, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:17–22</char></note>Baasha king of Israel came up against Judah and built Ramah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:9</char></note>that he might let none go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then Asa brought silver and gold from the treasuries of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and of the king’s house, and sent to Ben-Hadad king of Syria, who dwelt in Damascus, saying, <verse number="3" style="v" />“<char style="it">Let</char> <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">be</char> a treaty between you and me, as there was between my father and your father. See, I have sent you silver and gold; come, break your treaty with Baasha king of Israel, so that he will withdraw from me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So Ben-Hadad heeded King Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel. They attacked Ijon, Dan, Abel Maim, and all the storage cities of Naphtali. <verse number="5" style="v" />Now it happened, when Baasha heard <char style="it">it,</char> that he stopped building Ramah and ceased his work. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then King Asa took all Judah, and they carried away the stones and timber of Ramah, which Baasha had used for building; and with them he built Geba and Mizpah.</para>
	<para style="s">Hanani’s Message to Asa</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And at that time <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:1; 2 Chr. 19:2</char></note>Hanani the seer came to Asa king of Judah, and said to him: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:8–10; Ps. 118:9; (Is. 31:1; Jer. 17:5)</char></note>“Because you have relied on the king of Syria, and have not relied on the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, therefore the army of the king of Syria has escaped from your hand. <verse number="8" style="v" />Were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:9</char></note>the Ethiopians and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:3</char></note>the Lubim not a huge army with very many chariots and horsemen? Yet, because you relied on the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, He delivered them into your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:16, 18</char></note>hand. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 34:21; (Prov. 5:21; 15:3; Jer. 16:17; 32:19); Zech. 4:10</char></note>For the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to show Himself strong on behalf of <char style="it">those</char> whose heart <char style="it">is</char> loyal to Him. In this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 13:13</char></note>you have done foolishly; therefore from now on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:32</char></note>you shall have wars.” <verse number="10" style="v" />Then Asa was angry with the seer, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:26; Jer. 20:2; Matt. 14:3</char></note>put him in prison, for <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">was</char> enraged at him because of this. And Asa oppressed <char style="it">some</char> of the people at that time.</para>
	<para style="s">Illness and Death of Asa</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:23, 24; 2 Chr. 14:2</char></note>Note that the acts of Asa, first and last, are indeed written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse number="12" style="v" />And in the thirty-ninth year of his reign, Asa became diseased in his feet, and his malady was severe; yet in his disease he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 17:5)</char></note>did not seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but the physicians.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:24</char></note>So Asa rested with his fathers; he died in the forty-first year of his reign. <verse number="14" style="v" />They buried him in his own tomb, which he had made for himself in the City of David; and they laid him in the bed which was filled <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 50:2; Mark 16:1; John 19:39, 40</char></note>with spices and various ingredients prepared in a mixture of ointments. They made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:19; Jer. 34:5</char></note>a very great burning for him.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jehoshaphat Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:24; 2 Chr. 20:31</char></note>Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his place, and strengthened himself against Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he placed troops in all the fortified cities of Judah, and set garrisons in the land of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:5</char></note>Judah and in the cities of Ephraim <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:8</char></note>which Asa his father had taken. <verse number="3" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with Jehoshaphat, because he walked in the former ways of his father David; he did not seek the Baals, <verse number="4" style="v" />but sought the God of his father, and walked in His commandments and not according to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28</char></note>the acts of Israel. <verse number="5" style="v" />Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> established the kingdom in his hand; and all Judah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 10:27; 1 Kin. 10:25</char></note>gave presents to Jehoshaphat, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:1</char></note>and he had riches and honor in abundance. <verse number="6" style="v" />And his heart took delight in the ways of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; moreover <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:43; 2 Chr. 15:17; 19:3; 20:33</char></note>he removed the high places and wooden images from Judah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Also in the third year of his reign he sent his leaders, Ben-Hail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethanel, and Michaiah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:3; 35:3</char></note>to teach in the cities of Judah. <verse number="8" style="v" />And with them <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">sent</char> Levites: Shemaiah, Nethaniah, Zebadiah, Asahel, Shemiramoth, Jehonathan, Adonijah, Tobijah, and Tobadonijah—the Levites; and with them Elishama and Jehoram, the priests. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 6:4–9; 2 Chr. 35:3; Neh. 8:3, 7</char></note>So they taught in Judah, and <char style="it">had</char> the Book of the Law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with them; they went throughout all the cities of Judah and taught the people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:5; 2 Chr. 14:14</char></note>the fear of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> fell on all the kingdoms of the lands that <char style="it">were</char> around Judah, so that they did not make war against Jehoshaphat. <verse number="11" style="v" />Also <char style="it">some</char> of the Philistines <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:2; 2 Chr. 9:14; 26:8</char></note>brought Jehoshaphat presents and silver as tribute; and the Arabians brought him flocks, seven thousand seven hundred rams and seven thousand seven hundred male goats.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So Jehoshaphat became increasingly powerful, and he built fortresses and storage cities in Judah. <verse number="13" style="v" />He had much property in the cities of Judah; and the men of war, mighty men of valor, <char style="it">were</char> in Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />These <char style="it">are</char> their numbers, according to their fathers’ houses. Of Judah, the captains of thousands: Adnah the captain, and with him three hundred thousand mighty men of valor; <verse number="15" style="v" />and next to him <char style="it">was</char> Jehohanan the captain, and with him two hundred and eighty thousand; <verse number="16" style="v" />and next to him <char style="it">was</char> Amasiah the son of Zichri, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:2, 9; 1 Chr. 29:9</char></note>who willingly offered himself to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and with him two hundred thousand mighty men of valor. <verse number="17" style="v" />Of Benjamin: Eliada a mighty man of valor, and with him two hundred thousand men armed with bow and shield; <verse number="18" style="v" />and next to him <char style="it">was</char> Jehozabad, and with him one hundred and eighty thousand prepared for war. <verse number="19" style="v" />These served the king, besides <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:2</char></note>those the king put in the fortified cities throughout all Judah.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Micaiah Warns Ahab</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Jehoshaphat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:5</char></note>had riches and honor in abundance; and by marriage he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:44; 2 Kin. 8:18</char></note>allied himself with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:40</char></note>Ahab. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 23:2); 1 Kin. 22:2</char></note>After some years he went down to <char style="it">visit</char> Ahab in Samaria; and Ahab killed sheep and oxen in abundance for him and the people who were with him, and persuaded him to go up <char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">him</char> to Ramoth Gilead. <verse number="3" style="v" />So Ahab king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat king of Judah, “Will you go with me <char style="it">against</char> Ramoth Gilead?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he answered him, “I <char style="it">am</char> as you <char style="it">are,</char> and my people as your people; <char style="it">we</char> <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> with you in the war.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Also Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 23:2, 4, 9; 2 Sam. 2:1</char></note>“Please inquire for the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> today.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, four hundred men, and said to them, “Shall we go to war against Ramoth Gilead, or shall I refrain?”</para>
	<para style="p">So they said, “Go up, for God will deliver it into the king’s hand.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />But Jehoshaphat said, “<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">there</char> not still a prophet of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> here, that we may inquire of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:11</char></note>Him?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “<char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">is</char> still one man by whom we may inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; but I hate him, because he never prophesies good concerning me, but always evil. He <char style="it">is</char> Micaiah the son of Imla.”</para>
	<para style="p">And Jehoshaphat said, “Let not the king say such things!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then the king of Israel called one <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">his</char> officers and said, “Bring Micaiah the son of Imla quickly!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />The king of Israel and Jehoshaphat king of Judah, clothed in <char style="it">their</char> robes, sat each on his throne; and they sat at a threshing floor at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets prophesied before them. <verse number="10" style="v" />Now Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah had made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Zech. 1:18–21</char></note>horns of iron for himself; and he said, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘With these you shall gore the Syrians until they are destroyed.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And all the prophets prophesied so, saying, “Go up to Ramoth Gilead and prosper, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will deliver <char style="it">it</char> into the king’s hand.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then the messenger who had gone to call Micaiah spoke to him, saying, “Now listen, the words of the prophets with one accord encourage the king. Therefore please let your word be like <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">word</char> <char style="it">of</char> one of them, and speak encouragement.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And Micaiah said, “<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:18–20, 35; 23:12, 26; 1 Kin. 22:14</char></note>whatever my God says, that I will speak.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then he came to the king; and the king said to him, “Micaiah, shall we go to war against Ramoth Gilead, or shall I refrain?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “Go and prosper, and they shall be delivered into your hand!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />So the king said to him, “How many times shall I make you swear that you tell me nothing but the truth in the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Then he said, “I saw all Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 23:1–8; 31:10)</char></note>scattered on the mountains, as sheep that have no <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:17; 1 Kin. 22:17; (Ezek. 34:5–8); Matt. 9:36; Mark 6:34</char></note>shepherd. And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, ‘These have no master. Let each return to his house in peace.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “Did I not tell you he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then <char style="it">Micaiah</char> said, “Therefore hear the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: I saw the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sitting on His <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 6:1–5; Dan. 7:9, 10</char></note>throne, and all the host of heaven standing on His right hand and His left. <verse number="19" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, ‘Who will persuade Ahab king of Israel to go up, that he may fall at Ramoth Gilead?’ So one spoke in this manner, and another spoke in that manner. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 1:6; 2 Thess. 2:9</char></note>spirit came forward and stood before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said, ‘I will persuade him.’ The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, ‘In what way?’ <verse number="21" style="v" />So he said, ‘I will go out and be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’ And <char style="it">the</char> <char style="sc"><char style="it">Lord</char></char> said, ‘You shall persuade <char style="it">him</char> and also prevail; go out and do so.’ <verse number="22" style="v" />Therefore look! <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 12:16, 17; Is. 19:12–14; Ezek. 14:9</char></note>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has put a lying spirit in the mouth of these prophets of yours, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has declared disaster against you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah went near and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 20:2; Mark 14:65; Acts 23:2</char></note>struck Micaiah on the cheek, and said, “Which way did the spirit from the <char style="sc">Lord</char> go from me to speak to you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />And Micaiah said, “Indeed you shall see on that day when you go into an inner chamber to hide!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Then the king of Israel said, “Take Micaiah, and return him to Amon the governor of the city and to Joash the king’s son; <verse number="26" style="v" />and say, ‘Thus says the king: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:10</char></note>“Put this <char style="it">fellow</char> in prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and water of affliction, until I return in peace.” ’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />But Micaiah said, “If you ever return in peace, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has not spoken by <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 18:22</char></note>me.” And he said, “Take heed, all you people!”</para>
	<para style="s">Ahab Dies in Battle</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth Gilead. <verse number="29" style="v" />And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:22</char></note>disguise myself and go into battle; but you put on your robes.” So the king of Israel disguised himself, and they went into battle.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Now the king of Syria had commanded the captains of the chariots who <char style="it">were</char> with him, saying, “Fight with no one small or great, but only with the king of Israel.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />So it was, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, “It <char style="it">is</char> the king of Israel!” Therefore they surrounded him to attack; but Jehoshaphat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:14, 15</char></note>cried out, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> helped him, and God diverted them from him. <verse number="32" style="v" />For so it was, when the captains of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, that they turned back from pursuing him. <verse number="33" style="v" />Now a certain man drew a bow at random, and struck the king of Israel between the joints of his armor. So he said to the driver of his chariot, “Turn around and take me out of the battle, for I am wounded.” <verse number="34" style="v" />The battle increased that day, and the king of Israel propped <char style="it">himself</char> up in <char style="it">his</char> chariot facing the Syrians until evening; and about the time of sunset he died.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Jehoshaphat the king of Judah returned safely to his house in Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v" />And Jehu the son of Hanani <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:9; 1 Kin. 16:1; 2 Chr. 20:34</char></note>the seer went out to meet him, and said to King Jehoshaphat, “Should you help the wicked and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 139:21</char></note>love those who hate the <char style="sc">Lord</char>? Therefore the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:25</char></note>wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> upon you. <verse number="3" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:4, 6</char></note>good things are found in you, in that you have removed the wooden images from the land, and have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:19</char></note>prepared your heart to seek God.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Reforms of Jehoshaphat</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So Jehoshaphat dwelt at Jerusalem; and he went out again among the people from Beersheba to the mountains of Ephraim, and brought them back to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:8–13</char></note>fathers. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then he set <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 16:18–20)</char></note>judges in the land throughout all the fortified cities of Judah, city by city, <verse number="6" style="v" />and said to the judges, “Take heed to what you are doing, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 19:15; Deut. 1:17); Ps. 58:1</char></note>you do not judge for man but for the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 82:1; (Eccl. 5:8)</char></note>who <char style="it">is</char> with you in the judgment. <verse number="7" style="v" />Now therefore, let the fear of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> be upon you; take care and do <char style="it">it,</char> for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Gen. 18:25; Deut. 32:4); Rom. 9:17</char></note><char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no iniquity with the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, no <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 10:17, 18; Job 34:19); Acts 10:34; Rom. 2:11; Gal. 2:6; (Eph. 6:9; Col. 3:25)</char></note>partiality, nor taking of bribes.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Moreover in Jerusalem, for the judgment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and for controversies, Jehoshaphat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 16:18; 2 Chr. 17:8</char></note>appointed some of the Levites and priests, and some of the chief fathers of Israel, when they returned to Jerusalem. <verse number="9" style="v" />And he commanded them, saying, “Thus you shall act <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Sam. 23:3)</char></note>in the fear of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, faithfully and with a loyal heart: <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:8</char></note>Whatever case comes to you from your brethren who dwell in their cities, whether of bloodshed or offenses against law or commandment, against statutes or ordinances, you shall warn them, lest they trespass against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 16:46</char></note>wrath come upon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ezek. 3:18)</char></note>you and your brethren. Do this, and you will not be guilty. <verse number="11" style="v" />And take notice: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 7:3</char></note>Amariah the chief priest <char style="it">is</char> over you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 26:30</char></note>in all matters of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the ruler of the house of Judah, for all the king’s matters; also the Levites <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> officials before you. Behave courageously, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 15:2; 20:17)</char></note>with the good.”</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Ammon, Moab, and Mount Seir Defeated</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />It happened after this <char style="it">that</char> the people of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 18:2</char></note>Moab with the people of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 19:15</char></note>Ammon, and <char style="it">others</char> with them besides the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:7</char></note>Ammonites, came to battle against Jehoshaphat. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then some came and told Jehoshaphat, saying, “A great multitude is coming against you from beyond the sea, from Syria; and they are <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 14:7</char></note>in Hazazon Tamar” (which <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:62</char></note>En Gedi). <verse number="3" style="v" />And Jehoshaphat feared, and set himself to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 19:3</char></note>seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 7:6; Ezra 8:21; Jer. 36:9; Jon. 3:5</char></note>proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah. <verse number="4" style="v" />So Judah gathered together to ask <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:11</char></note><char style="it">help</char> from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and from all the cities of Judah they came to seek the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then Jehoshaphat stood in the assembly of Judah and Jerusalem, in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, before the new court, <verse number="6" style="v" />and said: “O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of our fathers, <char style="it">are</char> You not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:39; Josh. 2:11; (1 Kin. 8:23); Matt. 6:9</char></note>God in heaven, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 22:28; 47:2, 8; Dan. 4:17, 25, 32</char></note>do You <char style="it">not</char> rule over all the kingdoms of the nations, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 29:12; 2 Chr. 25:8; Ps. 62:11; Matt. 6:13</char></note>in Your hand <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">not</char> power and might, so that no one is able to withstand You? <verse number="7" style="v" /><char style="it">Are</char> You not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 13:14–17; 17:7; Ex. 6:7</char></note>our God, <char style="it">who</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 44:2</char></note>drove out the inhabitants of this land before Your people Israel, and gave it to the descendants of Abraham <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 41:8; James 2:23</char></note>Your friend forever? <verse number="8" style="v" />And they dwell in it, and have built You a sanctuary in it for Your name, saying, <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:33, 37; 2 Chr. 6:28–30</char></note>‘If disaster comes upon us—sword, judgment, pestilence, or famine—we will stand before this temple and in Your presence (for Your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:20</char></note>name <char style="it">is</char> in this temple), and cry out to You in our affliction, and You will hear and save.’ <verse number="10" style="v" />And now, here are the people of Ammon, Moab, and Mount Seir—whom You <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:4, 9, 19</char></note>would not let Israel invade when they came out of the land of Egypt, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 20:21</char></note>they turned from them and did not destroy them— <verse number="11" style="v" />here they are, rewarding us <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:1–18</char></note>by coming to throw us out of Your possession which You have given us to inherit. <verse number="12" style="v" />O our God, will You not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:27; (1 Sam. 3:13)</char></note>judge them? For we have no power against this great multitude that is coming against us; nor do we know what to do, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 25:15; 121:1, 2; 123:1, 2; 141:8</char></note>our eyes <char style="it">are</char> upon You.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Now all Judah, with their little ones, their wives, and their children, stood before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 11:25, 26; 24:2; 2 Chr. 15:1; 24:20</char></note>the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon Jahaziel the son of Zechariah, the son of Benaiah, the son of Jeiel, the son of Mattaniah, a Levite of the sons of Asaph, in the midst of the assembly. <verse number="15" style="v" />And he said, “Listen, all you of Judah and you inhabitants of Jerusalem, and you, King Jehoshaphat! Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to you: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:13, 14; (Deut. 1:29, 30; 31:6, 8); 2 Chr. 32:7</char></note>‘Do not be afraid nor dismayed because of this great multitude, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 17:47; Zech. 14:3</char></note>for the battle <char style="it">is</char> not yours, but God’s. <verse number="16" style="v" />Tomorrow go down against them. They will surely come up by the Ascent of Ziz, and you will find them at the end of the brook before the Wilderness of Jeruel. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:13, 14</char></note>You will not <char style="it">need</char> to fight in this <char style="it">battle.</char> Position yourselves, stand still and see the salvation of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, who is with you, O Judah and Jerusalem!’ Do not fear or be dismayed; tomorrow go out against them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:9; (2 Chr. 15:2; 32:8)</char></note>for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> with you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And Jehoshaphat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 4:31; 2 Chr. 7:3; 29:28</char></note>bowed his head with <char style="it">his</char> face to the ground, and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem bowed before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, worshiping the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then the Levites of the children of the Kohathites and of the children of the Korahites stood up to praise the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel with voices loud and high.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So they rose early in the morning and went out into the Wilderness of Tekoa; and as they went out, Jehoshaphat stood and said, “Hear me, O Judah and you inhabitants of Jerusalem: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 7:9</char></note>Believe in the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, and you shall be established; believe His prophets, and you shall prosper.” <verse number="21" style="v" />And when he had consulted with the people, he appointed those who should sing to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 16:29; Ps. 29:2; 90:17; 96:9; 110:3</char></note>and who should praise the beauty of holiness, as they went out before the army and were saying:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 16:34; Ps. 106:1; 136:1</char></note>“Praise the <char style="sc">Lord</char>,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 16:41; 2 Chr. 5:13</char></note>For His mercy <char style="it">endures</char> forever.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Now when they began to sing and to praise, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:22; 1 Sam. 14:20</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> set ambushes against the people of Ammon, Moab, and Mount Seir, who had come against Judah; and they were defeated. <verse number="23" style="v" />For the people of Ammon and Moab stood up against the inhabitants of Mount Seir to utterly kill and destroy <char style="it">them.</char> And when they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:22; 1 Sam. 14:20</char></note>they helped to destroy one another.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So when Judah came to a place overlooking the wilderness, they looked toward the multitude; and there <char style="it">were</char> their dead bodies, fallen on the earth. No one had escaped.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />When Jehoshaphat and his people came to take away their spoil, they found among them an abundance of valuables on the dead bodies, and precious jewelry, which they stripped off for themselves, more than they could carry away; and they were three days gathering the spoil because there was so much. <verse number="26" style="v" />And on the fourth day they assembled in the Valley of Berachah, for there they blessed the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; therefore the name of that place was called The Valley of Berachah until this day. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem, with Jehoshaphat in front of them, to go back to Jerusalem with joy, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 12:43</char></note>made them rejoice over their enemies. <verse number="28" style="v" />So they came to Jerusalem, with stringed instruments and harps and trumpets, to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="29" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:14; 17:10</char></note>the fear of God was on all the kingdoms of <char style="it">those</char> countries when they heard that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had fought against the enemies of Israel. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet, for his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:41–43; 2 Chr. 14:6, 7; 15:15; Job 34:29</char></note>God gave him rest all around.</para>
	<para style="s">The End of Jehoshaphat’s Reign</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Kin. 22:41–43)</char></note>So Jehoshaphat was king over Judah. <char style="it">He</char> <char style="it">was</char> thirty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned twenty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. <verse number="32" style="v" />And he walked in the way of his father <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:2</char></note>Asa, and did not turn aside from it, doing <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="33" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:17; 17:6</char></note>the high places were not taken away, for as yet the people had not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:14; 19:3</char></note>directed their hearts to the God of their fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, first and last, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of Jehu the son of Hanani, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:1, 7</char></note>which <char style="it">is</char> mentioned in the book of the kings of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />After this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:1</char></note>Jehoshaphat king of Judah allied himself with Ahaziah king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:48–53</char></note>who acted very <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 19:2)</char></note>wickedly. <verse number="36" style="v" />And he allied himself with him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:26; 10:22</char></note>to make ships to go to Tarshish, and they made the ships in Ezion Geber. <verse number="37" style="v" />But Eliezer the son of Dodavah of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, saying, “Because you have allied yourself with Ahaziah, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has destroyed your works.” <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:48</char></note>Then the ships were wrecked, so that they were not able to go <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 9:21</char></note>to Tarshish.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jehoram Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:50</char></note>Jehoshaphat rested with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the City of David. Then Jehoram his son reigned in his place. <verse number="2" style="v" />He had brothers, the sons of Jehoshaphat: Azariah, Jehiel, Zechariah, Azaryahu, Michael, and Shephatiah; all these <char style="it">were</char> the sons of Jehoshaphat king of Israel. <verse number="3" style="v" />Their father gave them great gifts of silver and gold and precious things, with fortified cities in Judah; but he gave the kingdom to Jehoram, because he <char style="it">was</char> the firstborn.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Now when Jehoram was established over the kingdom of his father, he strengthened himself and killed all his brothers with the sword, and also <char style="it">others</char> of the princes of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:17–22</char></note>Jehoram <char style="it">was</char> thirty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, just as the house of Ahab had done, for he had the daughter of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:1</char></note>Ahab as a wife; and he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="7" style="v" />Yet the <char style="sc">Lord</char> would not destroy the house of David, because of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:8–17</char></note>covenant that He had made with David, and since He had promised to give a lamp to him and to his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:36; 2 Kin. 8:19; Ps. 132:11</char></note>sons forever.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:20; 14:7, 10; 2 Chr. 25:14, 19</char></note>In his days Edom revolted against Judah’s authority, and made a king over themselves. <verse number="9" style="v" />So Jehoram went out with his officers, and all his chariots with him. And he rose by night and attacked the Edomites who had surrounded him and the captains of the chariots. <verse number="10" style="v" />Thus Edom has been in revolt against Judah’s authority to this day. At that time Libnah revolted against his rule, because he had forsaken the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of his fathers. <verse number="11" style="v" />Moreover he made high places in the mountains of Judah, and caused the inhabitants of Jerusalem to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 20:5)</char></note>commit harlotry, and led Judah astray.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And a letter came to him from Elijah the prophet, saying,</para>
	<para style="q1">Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of your father David:</para>
	<para style="q2">Because you have not walked in the ways of Jehoshaphat your father, or in the ways of Asa king of Judah, <verse number="13" style="v" />but have walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:11</char></note>made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 34:15); Deut. 31:16</char></note>play the harlot like the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:31–33; 2 Kin. 9:22</char></note>harlotry of the house of Ahab, and also have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:32; 2 Chr. 21:4</char></note>killed your brothers, those of your father’s household, <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> better than yourself, <verse number="14" style="v" />behold, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will strike your people with a serious affliction—your children, your wives, and all your possessions; <verse number="15" style="v" />and you <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">become</char> very sick with a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:18, 19</char></note>disease of your intestines, until your intestines come out by reason of the sickness, day by day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Moreover the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:11; (Jer. 51:11)</char></note><char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:14, 23</char></note>stirred up against Jehoram the spirit of the Philistines and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:11</char></note>Arabians who <char style="it">were</char> near the Ethiopians. <verse number="17" style="v" />And they came up into Judah and invaded it, and carried away all the possessions that were found in the king’s house, and also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:7</char></note>his sons and his wives, so that there was not a son left to him except Jehoahaz, the youngest of his sons.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />After all this the <char style="sc">Lord</char> struck him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:20; 21:15; Acts 12:23</char></note>in his intestines with an incurable disease. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then it happened in the course of time, after the end of two years, that his intestines came out because of his sickness; so he died in severe pain. And his people made no burning for him, like <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 16:14</char></note>the burning for his fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />He was thirty-two years old when he became king. He reigned in Jerusalem eight years and, to no one’s sorrow, departed. However they buried him in the City of David, but not in the tombs of the kings.</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Ahaziah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the inhabitants of Jerusalem made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:17; 22:6</char></note>Ahaziah his youngest son king in his place, for the raiders who came with the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:16</char></note>Arabians into the camp had killed all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:17</char></note>older <char style="it">sons.</char> So Ahaziah the son of Jehoram, king of Judah, reigned. <verse number="2" style="v" />Ahaziah <char style="it">was</char> forty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:6</char></note>Athaliah the granddaughter of Omri. <verse number="3" style="v" />He also walked in the ways of the house of Ahab, for his mother advised him to do wickedly. <verse number="4" style="v" />Therefore he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, like the house of Ahab; for they were his counselors after the death of his father, to his destruction. <verse number="5" style="v" />He also followed their advice, and went with Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth Gilead; and the Syrians wounded Joram. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:15</char></note>Then he returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds which he had received at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. And Azariah the son of Jehoram, king of Judah, went down to see Jehoram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was sick.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />His going to Joram <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 14:4; 1 Kin. 12:15; 2 Chr. 10:15</char></note>was God’s occasion for Ahaziah’s downfall; for when he arrived, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:21–24</char></note>he went out with Jehoram against Jehu the son of Nimshi, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:6, 7</char></note>whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had anointed to cut off the house of Ahab. <verse number="8" style="v" />And it happened, when Jehu was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:22–24</char></note>executing judgment on the house of Ahab, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:10–14; Hos. 1:4</char></note>found the princes of Judah and the sons of Ahaziah’s brothers who served Ahaziah, that he killed them. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Kin. 9:27)</char></note>Then he searched for Ahaziah; and they caught him (he was hiding in Samaria), and brought him to Jehu. When they had killed him, they buried him, “because,” they said, “he is the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:24</char></note>Jehoshaphat, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:4; 20:3, 4</char></note>sought the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with all his heart.”</para>
	<para style="p">So the house of Ahaziah had no one to assume power over the kingdom.</para>
	<para style="s">Athaliah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 11:1–3</char></note>Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the royal heirs of the house of Judah. <verse number="11" style="v" />But Jehoshabeath, the daughter of the king, took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:18</char></note>Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him away from among the king’s sons who were being murdered, and put him and his nurse in a bedroom. So Jehoshabeath, the daughter of King Jehoram, the wife of Jehoiada the priest (for she was the sister of Ahaziah), hid him from Athaliah so that she did not kill him. <verse number="12" style="v" />And he was hidden with them in the house of God for six years, while Athaliah reigned over the land.</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Joash Crowned King of Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 11:4</char></note>the seventh year <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:2</char></note>Jehoiada strengthened himself, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">made</char> <char style="it">a</char> covenant with the captains of hundreds: Azariah the son of Jeroham, Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, Azariah the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 2:37, 38</char></note>Obed, Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zichri. <verse number="2" style="v" />And they went throughout Judah and gathered the Levites from all the cities of Judah, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 1:5</char></note>chief fathers of Israel, and they came to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then all the assembly made a covenant with the king in the house of God. And he said to them, “Behold, the king’s son shall reign, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:12; 1 Kin. 2:4; 9:5; 2 Chr. 6:16; 7:18; 21:7</char></note>said of the sons of David. <verse number="4" style="v" />This <char style="it">is</char> what you shall do: One-third of you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 9:25</char></note>entering on the Sabbath, of the priests and the Levites, <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> keeping watch over the doors; <verse number="5" style="v" />one-third <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> at the king’s house; and one-third at the Gate of the Foundation. All the people <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> in the courts of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" />But let no one come into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> except the priests and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:28–32</char></note>those of the Levites who serve. They may go in, for they <char style="it">are</char> holy; but all the people shall keep the watch of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="7" style="v" />And the Levites shall surround the king on all sides, every man with his weapons in his hand; and whoever comes into the house, let him be put to death. You are to be with the king when he comes in and when he goes out.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So the Levites and all Judah did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded. And each man took his men who were to be on duty on the Sabbath, with those who were going <char style="it">off</char> <char style="it">duty</char> on the Sabbath; for Jehoiada the priest had not dismissed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 24:1–31</char></note>the divisions. <verse number="9" style="v" />And Jehoiada the priest gave to the captains of hundreds the spears and the large and small <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:7</char></note>shields which <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">belonged</char> to King David, that <char style="it">were</char> in the temple of God. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then he set all the people, every man with his weapon in his hand, from the right side of the temple to the left side of the temple, along by the altar and by the temple, all around the king. <verse number="11" style="v" />And they brought out the king’s son, put the crown on him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:18</char></note><char style="it">gave</char> <char style="it">him</char> the Testimony, and made him king. Then Jehoiada and his sons anointed him, and said, “<char style="it">Long</char> live the king!”</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Athaliah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Now when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:10</char></note>Athaliah heard the noise of the people running and praising the king, she came to the people <char style="it">in</char> the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" /><char style="it">When</char> she looked, there was the king standing by his pillar at the entrance; and the leaders and the trumpeters <char style="it">were</char> by the king. All the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing trumpets, also the singers with musical instruments, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 25:6–8</char></note>those who led in praise. So Athaliah tore her clothes and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:23</char></note>“Treason! Treason!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And Jehoiada the priest brought out the captains of hundreds who were set over the army, and said to them, “Take her outside under guard, and slay with the sword whoever follows her.” For the priest had said, “Do not kill her in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />So they seized her; and she went by way of the entrance <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 3:28; Jer. 31:40</char></note>of the Horse Gate <char style="it">into</char> the king’s house, and they killed her there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Then Jehoiada made a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:24, 25; 2 Chr. 15:12–15</char></note>covenant between himself, the people, and the king, that they should be the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s people. <verse number="17" style="v" />And all the people went to the temple of Baal, and tore it down. They broke in pieces its altars and images, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:6–9; 1 Kin. 18:40</char></note>killed Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. <verse number="18" style="v" />Also Jehoiada appointed the oversight of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to the hand of the priests, the Levites, whom David had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:6, 30, 31; 24:1</char></note>assigned in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to offer the burnt offerings of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> written in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 28:2</char></note>Law of Moses, with rejoicing and with singing, <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">established</char> by David. <verse number="19" style="v" />And he set the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 26:1–19</char></note>gatekeepers at the gates of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, so that no one <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">was</char> in any way unclean should enter.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:22; 2 Kin. 11:19</char></note>Then he took the captains of hundreds, the nobles, the governors of the people, and all the people of the land, and brought the king down from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and they went through the Upper Gate to the king’s house, and set the king on the throne of the kingdom. <verse number="21" style="v" />So all the people of the land rejoiced; and the city was quiet, for they had slain Athaliah with the sword.</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Joash Repairs the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Joash <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 11:21; 12:1–15</char></note><char style="it">was</char> seven years old when he became king, and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Zibiah of Beersheba. <verse number="2" style="v" />Joash <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:4, 5</char></note>did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all the days of Jehoiada the priest. <verse number="3" style="v" />And Jehoiada took two wives for him, and he had sons and daughters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Now it happened after this <char style="it">that</char> Joash set his heart on repairing the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then he gathered the priests and the Levites, and said to them, “Go out to the cities of Judah, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:4</char></note>gather from all Israel money to repair the house of your God from year to year, and see that you do it quickly.”</para>
	<para style="p">However the Levites did not do it quickly. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:7</char></note>So the king called Jehoiada the chief <char style="it">priest,</char> and said to him, “Why have you not required the Levites to bring in from Judah and from Jerusalem the collection, <char style="it">according</char> <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">commandment</char> of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:12–16</char></note>Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and of the assembly of Israel, for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 1:50; Acts 7:44</char></note>tabernacle of witness?” <verse number="7" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:17</char></note>the sons of Athaliah, that wicked woman, had broken into the house of God, and had also presented all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:4</char></note>dedicated things of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to the Baals.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then at the king’s command <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:9</char></note>they made a chest, and set it outside at the gate of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="9" style="v" />And they made a proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem to bring to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:6</char></note>the collection <char style="it">that</char> Moses the servant of God <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">imposed</char> on Israel in the wilderness. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then all the leaders and all the people rejoiced, brought their contributions, and put <char style="it">them</char> into the chest until all had given. <verse number="11" style="v" />So it was, at that time, when the chest was brought to the king’s official by the hand of the Levites, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:10</char></note>when they saw that <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> much money, that the king’s scribe and the high priest’s officer came and emptied the chest, and took it and returned it to its place. Thus they did day by day, and gathered money in abundance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />The king and Jehoiada gave it to those who did the work of the service of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and they hired masons and carpenters to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:12</char></note>repair the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and also those who worked in iron and bronze to restore the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />So the workmen labored, and the work was completed by them; they restored the house of God to its original condition and reinforced it. <verse number="14" style="v" />When they had finished, they brought the rest of the money before the king and Jehoiada; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:13</char></note>they made from it articles for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, articles for serving and offering, spoons and vessels of gold and silver. And they offered burnt offerings in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> continually all the days of Jehoiada.</para>
	<para style="s">Apostasy of Joash</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />But Jehoiada grew old and was full of days, and he died; <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">was</char> one hundred and thirty years old when he died. <verse number="16" style="v" />And they buried him in the City of David among the kings, because he had done good in Israel, both toward God and His house.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Now after the death of Jehoiada the leaders of Judah came and bowed down to the king. And the king listened to them. <verse number="18" style="v" />Therefore they left the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers, and served <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:23</char></note>wooden images and idols; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 34:12–14); Judg. 5:8; 2 Chr. 19:2; 28:13; 29:8; 32:25</char></note>wrath came upon Judah and Jerusalem because of their trespass. <verse number="19" style="v" />Yet He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:13; 21:10–15; 2 Chr. 36:15, 16; Jer. 7:25, 26; 25:4</char></note>sent prophets to them, to bring them back to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and they testified against them, but they would not listen.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Then the Spirit of God came upon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:34; Matt. 23:35</char></note>Zechariah the son of Jehoiada the priest, who stood above the people, and said to them, “Thus says God: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:41; (Prov. 28:13)</char></note>‘Why do you transgress the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, so that you cannot prosper? <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 15:2)</char></note>Because you have forsaken the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, He also has forsaken you.’ ” <verse number="21" style="v" />So they conspired against him, and at the command of the king they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Neh. 9:26); Matt. 23:35; Acts 7:58, 59</char></note>stoned him with stones in the court of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="22" style="v" />Thus Joash the king did not remember the kindness which Jehoiada his father had done to him, but killed his son; and as he died, he said, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> look on <char style="it">it,</char> and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Gen. 9:5)</char></note>repay!”</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Joash</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />So it happened in the spring of the year <char style="it">that</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:17; Is. 7:2</char></note>the army of Syria came up against him; and they came to Judah and Jerusalem, and destroyed all the leaders of the people from among the people, and sent all their spoil to the king of Damascus. <verse number="24" style="v" />For the army of the Syrians <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:8; (Deut. 32:30); Is. 30:17</char></note>came with a small company of men; but the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:25; (Deut. 28:25)</char></note>delivered a very great army into their hand, because they had forsaken the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers. So they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:8; Is. 10:5</char></note>executed judgment against Joash. <verse number="25" style="v" />And when they had withdrawn from him (for they left him severely wounded), <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:20, 21; 2 Chr. 25:3</char></note>his own servants conspired against him because of the blood of the sons of Jehoiada the priest, and killed him on his bed. So he died. And they buried him in the City of David, but they did not bury him in the tombs of the kings.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />These are the ones who conspired against him: Zabad the son of Shimeath the Ammonitess, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith the Moabitess. <verse number="27" style="v" />Now <char style="it">concerning</char> his sons, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:18</char></note>the many oracles about him, and the repairing of the house of God, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the annals of the book of the kings. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:21</char></note>Then Amaziah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="25" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Amaziah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Amaziah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:1–6</char></note><char style="it">was</char> twenty-five years old <char style="it">when</char> he became king, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Jehoaddan of Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:4; 2 Chr. 25:14</char></note>but not with a loyal heart.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:5; 2 Chr. 24:25</char></note>Now it happened, as soon as the kingdom was established for him, that he executed his servants who had murdered his father the king. <verse number="4" style="v" />However he did not execute their children, but <char style="it">did</char> as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> written in the Law in the Book of Moses, where the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 24:16; 2 Kin. 14:6; Jer. 31:30; (Ezek. 18:20)</char></note>“The fathers shall not be put to death for their children, nor shall the children be put to death for their fathers; but a person shall die for his own sin.”</para>
	<para style="s">The War Against Edom</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Moreover Amaziah gathered Judah together and set over them captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, according to <char style="it">their</char> fathers’ houses, throughout all Judah and Benjamin; and he numbered them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 1:3</char></note>from twenty years old and above, and found them to be three hundred thousand choice <char style="it">men, able</char> to go to war, who could handle spear and shield. <verse number="6" style="v" />He also hired one hundred thousand mighty men of valor from Israel for one hundred talents of silver. <verse number="7" style="v" />But a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:2</char></note>man of God came to him, saying, “O king, do not let the army of Israel go with you, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> not with Israel—<char style="it">not</char> <char style="it">with</char> any of the children of Ephraim. <verse number="8" style="v" />But if you go, be gone! Be strong in battle! <char style="it">Even</char> <char style="it">so,</char> God shall make you fall before the enemy; for God has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 14:11; 20:6</char></note>power to help and to overthrow.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then Amaziah said to the man of God, “But what <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">we</char> do about the hundred talents which I have given to the troops of Israel?”</para>
	<para style="p">And the man of God answered, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 8:18); Prov. 10:22</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> is able to give you much more than this.” <verse number="10" style="v" />So Amaziah discharged the troops that had come to him from Ephraim, to go back home. Therefore their anger was greatly aroused against Judah, and they returned home in great anger.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then Amaziah strengthened himself, and leading his people, he went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:7</char></note>the Valley of Salt and killed ten thousand of the people of Seir. <verse number="12" style="v" />Also the children of Judah took captive ten thousand alive, brought them to the top of the rock, and cast them down from the top of the rock, so that they all were dashed in pieces.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />But as for the soldiers of the army which Amaziah had discharged, so that they would not go with him to battle, they raided the cities of Judah from Samaria to Beth Horon, killed three thousand in them, and took much spoil.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Now it was so, after Amaziah came from the slaughter of the Edomites, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:23</char></note>he brought the gods of the people of Seir, set them up <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">be</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 20:3, 5)</char></note>his gods, and bowed down before them and burned incense to them. <verse number="15" style="v" />Therefore the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was aroused against Amaziah, and He sent him a prophet who said to him, “Why have you sought <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 96:5)</char></note>the gods of the people, which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:11</char></note>could not rescue their own people from your hand?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So it was, as he talked with him, that <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">king</char> said to him, “Have we made you the king’s counselor? Cease! Why should you be killed?”</para>
	<para style="p">Then the prophet ceased, and said, “I know that God has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Sam. 2:25)</char></note>determined to destroy you, because you have done this and have not heeded my advice.”</para>
	<para style="s">Israel Defeats Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:8–14</char></note>Amaziah king of Judah asked advice and sent to Joash the son of Jehoahaz, the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, “Come, let us face one another <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">battle.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And Joash king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, “The thistle that <char style="it">was</char> in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, ‘Give your daughter to my son as wife’; and a wild beast that <char style="it">was</char> in Lebanon passed by and trampled the thistle. <verse number="19" style="v" />Indeed you say that you have defeated the Edomites, and your heart is lifted up to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:16; 32:25; (Prov. 16:18)</char></note>boast. Stay at home now; why should you meddle with trouble, that you should fall—you and Judah with you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />But Amaziah would not heed, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:15; 2 Chr. 22:7</char></note>it <char style="it">came</char> from God, that He might give them into the hand <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">their</char> <char style="it">enemies,</char> because they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:14</char></note>sought the gods of Edom. <verse number="21" style="v" />So Joash king of Israel went out; and he and Amaziah king of Judah faced one another at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:38</char></note>Beth Shemesh, which <char style="it">belongs</char> to Judah. <verse number="22" style="v" />And Judah was defeated by Israel, and every man fled to his tent. <verse number="23" style="v" />Then Joash the king of Israel captured Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash, the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:17; 22:1, 6</char></note>Jehoahaz, at Beth Shemesh; and he brought him to Jerusalem, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from the Gate of Ephraim to the Corner Gate—four hundred cubits. <verse number="24" style="v" />And <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">took</char> all the gold and silver, all the articles that were found in the house of God with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 26:15</char></note>Obed-Edom, the treasures of the king’s house, and hostages, and returned to Samaria.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Amaziah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:17–22</char></note>Amaziah the son of Joash, king of Judah, lived fifteen years after the death of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, king of Israel. <verse number="26" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, from first to last, indeed <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel? <verse number="27" style="v" />After the time that Amaziah turned away from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to Lachish; but they sent after him to Lachish and killed him there. <verse number="28" style="v" />Then they brought him on horses and buried him with his fathers in the City of Judah.</para>
	<chapter number="26" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Uzziah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now all the people of Judah took Uzziah, who <char style="it">was</char> sixteen years old, and made him king instead of his father Amaziah. <verse number="2" style="v" />He built Elath and restored it to Judah, after the king rested with his fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Uzziah <char style="it">was</char> sixteen years old when he became king, and he reigned fifty-two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jecholiah of Jerusalem. <verse number="4" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:2</char></note>right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his father Amaziah had done. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:2</char></note>He sought God in the days of Zechariah, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:15; Dan. 1:17; 10:1</char></note>had understanding in the visions of God; and as long as he sought the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, God made him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 15:2; 20:20; 31:21)</char></note>prosper.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Now he went out and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 14:29</char></note>made war against the Philistines, and broke down the wall of Gath, the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Ashdod; and he built cities <char style="it">around</char> Ashdod and among the Philistines. <verse number="7" style="v" />God helped him against <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:16</char></note>the Philistines, against the Arabians who lived in Gur Baal, and against the Meunites. <verse number="8" style="v" />Also the Ammonites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:2; 2 Chr. 17:11</char></note>brought tribute to Uzziah. His fame spread as far as the entrance of Egypt, for he became exceedingly strong.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem at the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:13; 2 Chr. 25:23; Neh. 3:13, 19, 32; Zech. 14:10</char></note>Corner Gate, at the Valley Gate, and at the corner buttress of the wall; then he fortified them. <verse number="10" style="v" />Also he built towers in the desert. He dug many wells, for he had much livestock, both in the lowlands and in the plains; <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">also</char> <char style="it">had</char> farmers and vinedressers in the mountains and in Carmel, for he loved the soil.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Moreover Uzziah had an army of fighting men who went out to war by companies, according to the number on their roll as prepared by Jeiel the scribe and Maaseiah the officer, under the hand of Hananiah, <char style="it">one</char> of the king’s captains. <verse number="12" style="v" />The total number of chief officers of the mighty men of valor <char style="it">was</char> two thousand six hundred. <verse number="13" style="v" />And under their authority <char style="it">was</char> an army of three hundred and seven thousand five hundred, that made war with mighty power, to help the king against the enemy. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then Uzziah prepared for them, for the entire army, shields, spears, helmets, body armor, bows, and slings <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">cast</char> stones. <verse number="15" style="v" />And he made devices in Jerusalem, invented by <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 39:3, 8</char></note>skillful men, to be on the towers and the corners, to shoot arrows and large stones. So his fame spread far and wide, for he was marvelously helped till he became strong.</para>
	<para style="s">The Penalty for Uzziah’s Pride</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 32:15)</char></note>when he was strong his heart was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 8:14; 2 Chr. 25:19</char></note>lifted up, to <char style="it">his</char> destruction, for he transgressed against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:1–4; 2 Kin. 16:12, 13</char></note>by entering the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to burn incense on the altar of incense. <verse number="17" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:10</char></note>Azariah the priest went in after him, and with him were eighty priests of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>—valiant men. <verse number="18" style="v" />And they withstood King Uzziah, and said to him, “<char style="it">It</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Num. 3:10; 16:39, 40; 18:7)</char></note>is not for you, Uzziah, to burn incense to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:7, 8; Heb. 7:14</char></note>priests, the sons of Aaron, who are consecrated to burn incense. Get out of the sanctuary, for you have trespassed! You <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">have</char> no honor from the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then Uzziah became furious; and he <char style="it">had</char> a censer in his hand to burn incense. And while he was angry with the priests, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 13:42; Num. 12:10; 2 Kin. 5:25–27</char></note>leprosy broke out on his forehead, before the priests in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, beside the incense altar. <verse number="20" style="v" />And Azariah the chief priest and all the priests looked at him, and there, on his forehead, he <char style="it">was</char> leprous; so they thrust him out of that place. Indeed he also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 6:12</char></note>hurried to get out, because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had struck him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:5</char></note>King Uzziah was a leper until the day of his death. He dwelt in an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 13:46; Num. 5:2)</char></note>isolated house, because he was a leper; for he was cut off from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Then Jotham his son <char style="it">was</char> over the king’s house, judging the people of the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Uzziah, from first to last, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:1; 2 Chr. 32:20, 32; Is. 1:1</char></note>the prophet Isaiah the son of Amoz wrote. <verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:7; 2 Chr. 21:20; 28:27; Is. 6:1</char></note>So Uzziah rested with his fathers, and they buried him with his fathers in the field of burial which <char style="it">belonged</char> to the kings, for they said, “He is a leper.” Then Jotham his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="27" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jotham Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Jotham <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:32–35</char></note><char style="it">was</char> twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Jerushah the daughter of Zadok. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his father Uzziah had done (although he did not enter the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>). But still <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:35; Ezek. 20:44; 30:13</char></note>the people acted corruptly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />He built the Upper Gate of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and he built extensively on the wall of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:14; Neh. 3:26</char></note>Ophel. <verse number="4" style="v" />Moreover he built cities in the mountains of Judah, and in the forests he built fortresses and towers. <verse number="5" style="v" />He also fought with the king of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:8</char></note>Ammonites and defeated them. And the people of Ammon gave him in that year one hundred talents of silver, ten thousand kors of wheat, and ten thousand of barley. The people of Ammon paid this to him in the second and third years also. <verse number="6" style="v" />So Jotham became mighty, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:5</char></note>because he prepared his ways before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all his wars and his ways, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. <verse number="8" style="v" />He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:38</char></note>So Jotham rested with his fathers, and they buried him in the City of David. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 1:1; Hos. 1:1; Mic. 1:1</char></note>Ahaz his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="28" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Ahaz Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Ahaz <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:2–4</char></note><char style="it">was</char> twenty years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem; and he did not do <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as his father David <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">done.</char> <verse number="2" style="v" />For he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:17; Lev. 19:4</char></note>molded images for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:11</char></note>the Baals. <verse number="3" style="v" />He burned incense in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:8</char></note>the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, and burned <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:10</char></note>his children in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:21); 2 Kin. 16:3; 2 Chr. 33:6</char></note>fire, according to the abominations of the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:24–30)</char></note>cast out before the children of Israel. <verse number="4" style="v" />And he sacrificed and burned incense on the high places, on the hills, and under every green tree.</para>
	<para style="s">Syria and Israel Defeat Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 10:5)</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God delivered him into the hand of the king of Syria. They <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:5, 6; (2 Chr. 24:24); Is. 7:1, 17</char></note>defeated him, and carried away a great multitude of them as captives, and brought <char style="it">them</char> to Damascus. Then he was also delivered into the hand of the king of Israel, who defeated him with a great slaughter. <verse number="6" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:27</char></note>Pekah the son of Remaliah killed one hundred and twenty thousand in Judah in one day, all valiant men, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 29:8)</char></note>because they had forsaken the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers. <verse number="7" style="v" />Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, killed Maaseiah the king’s son, Azrikam the officer over the house, and Elkanah <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">was</char> second to the king. <verse number="8" style="v" />And the children of Israel carried away captive of their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:25, 41; 2 Chr. 11:4</char></note>brethren two hundred thousand women, sons, and daughters; and they also took away much spoil from them, and brought the spoil to Samaria.</para>
	<para style="s">Israel Returns the Captives</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />But a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:15</char></note>prophet of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was there, whose name <char style="it">was</char> Oded; and he went out before the army that came to Samaria, and said to them: “Look, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 69:26; (Is. 10:5; 47:6); Ezek. 25:12, 15; 26:2; Obad. 10; (Zech. 1:15)</char></note>because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of your fathers was angry with Judah, He has delivered them into your hand; but you have killed them in a rage <char style="it">that</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 9:6; Rev. 18:5</char></note>reaches up to heaven. <verse number="10" style="v" />And now you propose to force the children of Judah and Jerusalem to be your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 25:39, 42, 43, 46)</char></note>male and female slaves; <char style="it">but</char> <char style="it">are</char> you not also guilty before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God? <verse number="11" style="v" />Now hear me, therefore, and return the captives, whom you have taken captive from your brethren, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 78:49; James 2:13</char></note>for the fierce wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> upon you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then some of the heads of the children of Ephraim, Azariah the son of Johanan, Berechiah the son of Meshillemoth, Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai, stood up against those who came from the war, <verse number="13" style="v" />and said to them, “You shall not bring the captives here, for we <char style="it">already</char> have offended the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. You intend to add to our sins and to our guilt; for our guilt is great, and <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> fierce wrath against Israel.” <verse number="14" style="v" />So the armed men left the captives and the spoil before the leaders and all the assembly. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then the men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:12</char></note>who were designated by name rose up and took the captives, and from the spoil they clothed all who were naked among them, dressed them and gave them sandals, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 25:21, 22; Luke 6:27; Rom. 12:20)</char></note>gave them food and drink, and anointed them; and they let all the feeble ones ride on donkeys. So they brought them to their brethren at Jericho, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 34:3; Judg. 1:16</char></note>the city of palm trees. Then they returned to Samaria.</para>
	<para style="s">Assyria Refuses to Help Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:7</char></note>At the same time King Ahaz sent to the kings of Assyria to help him. <verse number="17" style="v" />For again the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:10; Obad. 10–14</char></note>Edomites had come, attacked Judah, and carried away captives. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:16, 17; Ezek. 16:27, 57</char></note>The Philistines also had invaded the cities of the lowland and of the South of Judah, and had taken Beth Shemesh, Aijalon, Gederoth, Sochoh with its villages, Timnah with its villages, and Gimzo with its villages; and they dwelt there. <verse number="19" style="v" />For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> brought Judah low because of Ahaz king of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:2; 2 Chr. 21:2</char></note>Israel, for he had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:25</char></note>encouraged moral decline in Judah and had been continually unfaithful to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="20" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:29; 16:7–9; 1 Chr. 5:26</char></note>Tiglath-Pileser king of Assyria came to him and distressed him, and did not assist him. <verse number="21" style="v" />For Ahaz took part <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">treasures</char> from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, from the house of the king, and from the leaders, and he gave <char style="it">it</char> to the king of Assyria; but he did not help him.</para>
	<para style="s">Apostasy and Death of Ahaz</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Now in the time of his distress King Ahaz became increasingly unfaithful to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. This <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">that</char> King Ahaz. <verse number="23" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:14</char></note>he sacrificed to the gods of Damascus which had defeated him, saying, “Because the gods of the kings of Syria help them, I will sacrifice to them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 44:17, 18</char></note>that they may help me.” But they were the ruin of him and of all Israel. <verse number="24" style="v" />So Ahaz gathered the articles of the house of God, cut in pieces the articles of the house of God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:3, 7</char></note>shut up the doors of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and made for himself altars in every corner of Jerusalem. <verse number="25" style="v" />And in every single city of Judah he made high places to burn incense to other gods, and provoked to anger the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of his fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:19, 20</char></note>Now the rest of his acts and all his ways, from first to last, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse number="27" style="v" />So Ahaz rested with his fathers, and they buried him in the city, in Jerusalem; but they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:20; 24:25</char></note>did not bring him into the tombs of the kings of Israel. Then Hezekiah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="29" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Hezekiah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Hezekiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:1; 2 Chr. 32:22, 33</char></note>became king <char style="it">when</char> <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">was</char> twenty-five years old, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Abijah the daughter of Zechariah. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his father David had done.</para>
	<para style="s">Hezekiah Cleanses the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />In the first year of his reign, in the first month, he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:24; 29:7</char></note>opened the doors of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and repaired them. <verse number="4" style="v" />Then he brought in the priests and the Levites, and gathered them in the East Square, <verse number="5" style="v" />and said to them: “Hear me, Levites! Now sanctify yourselves, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 15:12; 2 Chr. 29:15, 34; 35:6</char></note>sanctify the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of your fathers, and carry out the rubbish from the holy <char style="it">place.</char> <verse number="6" style="v" />For our fathers have trespassed and done evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God; they have forsaken Him, have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 1:4); Jer. 2:27; Ezek. 8:16</char></note>turned their faces away from the dwelling place of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and turned <char style="it">their</char> backs <char style="it">on</char> <char style="it">Him.</char> <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:24</char></note>They have also shut up the doors of the vestibule, put out the lamps, and have not burned incense or offered burnt offerings in the holy <char style="it">place</char> to the God of Israel. <verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:18</char></note>wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> fell upon Judah and Jerusalem, and He has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:5</char></note>given them up to trouble, to desolation, and to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:8; Jer. 18:16; 19:8; 25:9, 18; 29:18</char></note>jeering, as you see with your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:32</char></note>eyes. <verse number="9" style="v" />For indeed, because of this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:25; 2 Chr. 28:5–8, 17</char></note>our fathers have fallen by the sword; and our sons, our daughters, and our wives <char style="it">are</char> in captivity.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />“Now <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> in my heart to make <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:12; 23:16</char></note>a covenant with the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, that His fierce wrath may turn away from us. <verse number="11" style="v" />My sons, do not be negligent now, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 3:6; 8:14; 18:2, 6; 2 Chr. 30:16, 17</char></note>chosen you to stand before Him, to serve Him, and that you should minister to Him and burn incense.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then these Levites arose: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 31:13</char></note>Mahath the son of Amasai and Joel the son of Azariah, of the sons of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 3:19, 20</char></note>Kohathites; of the sons of Merari, Kish the son of Abdi and Azariah the son of Jehallelel; of the Gershonites, Joah the son of Zimmah and Eden the son of Joah; <verse number="13" style="v" />of the sons of Elizaphan, Shimri and Jeiel; of the sons of Asaph, Zechariah and Mattaniah; <verse number="14" style="v" />of the sons of Heman, Jehiel and Shimei; and of the sons of Jeduthun, Shemaiah and Uzziel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And they gathered their brethren, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:5</char></note>sanctified themselves, and went according to the commandment of the king, at the words of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:28</char></note>to cleanse the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then the priests went into the inner part of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to cleanse <char style="it">it,</char> and brought out all the debris that they found in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to the court of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And the Levites took <char style="it">it</char> out and carried <char style="it">it</char> to the Brook <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:16; 30:14</char></note>Kidron.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Now they began to sanctify on the first <char style="it">day</char> of the first month, and on the eighth day of the month they came to the vestibule of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. So they sanctified the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in eight days, and on the sixteenth day of the first month they finished.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then they went in to King Hezekiah and said, “We have cleansed all the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the altar of burnt offerings with all its articles, and the table of the showbread with all its articles. <verse number="19" style="v" />Moreover all the articles which King Ahaz in his reign had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:24</char></note>cast aside in his transgression we have prepared and sanctified; and there they <char style="it">are,</char> before the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="s">Hezekiah Restores Temple Worship</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Then King Hezekiah rose early, gathered the rulers of the city, and went up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="21" style="v" />And they brought seven bulls, seven rams, seven lambs, and seven male goats for a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:3–14</char></note>sin offering for the kingdom, for the sanctuary, and for Judah. Then he commanded the priests, the sons of Aaron, to offer <char style="it">them</char> on the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="22" style="v" />So they killed the bulls, and the priests received the blood and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:14, 15, 19, 24; Heb. 9:21</char></note>sprinkled <char style="it">it</char> on the altar. Likewise they killed the rams and sprinkled the blood on the altar. They also killed the lambs and sprinkled the blood on the altar. <verse number="23" style="v" />Then they brought out the male goats <char style="it">for</char> the sin offering before the king and the assembly, and they laid their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:15, 24; 8:14</char></note>hands on them. <verse number="24" style="v" />And the priests killed them; and they presented their blood on the altar as a sin offering <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:20</char></note>to make an atonement for all Israel, for the king commanded <char style="it">that</char> the burnt offering and the sin offering <char style="it">be</char> <char style="it">made</char> for all Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 16:4; 25:6</char></note>And he stationed the Levites in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with cymbals, with stringed instruments, and with harps, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:5; 25:1; 2 Chr. 8:14</char></note>according to the commandment of David, of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 24:11</char></note>Gad the king’s seer, and of Nathan the prophet; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:12</char></note>for thus <char style="it">was</char> the commandment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by His prophets. <verse number="26" style="v" />The Levites stood with the instruments <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:5; Amos 6:5</char></note>of David, and the priests with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:8, 10; 1 Chr. 15:24; 16:6; 2 Chr. 5:12</char></note>the trumpets. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then Hezekiah commanded <char style="it">them</char> to offer the burnt offering on the altar. And when the burnt offering began, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:18</char></note>the song of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">also</char> began, with the trumpets and with the instruments of David king of Israel. <verse number="28" style="v" />So all the assembly worshiped, the singers sang, and the trumpeters sounded; all <char style="it">this</char> <char style="it">continued</char> until the burnt offering was finished. <verse number="29" style="v" />And when they had finished offering, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:18</char></note>the king and all who were present with him bowed and worshiped. <verse number="30" style="v" />Moreover King Hezekiah and the leaders commanded the Levites to sing praise to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with the words of David and of Asaph the seer. So they sang praises with gladness, and they bowed their heads and worshiped.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Then Hezekiah answered and said, “Now <char style="it">that</char> you have consecrated yourselves to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, come near, and bring sacrifices and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:12</char></note>thank offerings into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” So the assembly brought in sacrifices and thank offerings, and as many as were of a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 35:5, 22</char></note>willing heart <char style="it">brought</char> burnt offerings. <verse number="32" style="v" />And the number of the burnt offerings which the assembly brought was seventy bulls, one hundred rams, <char style="it">and</char> two hundred lambs; all these <char style="it">were</char> for a burnt offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="33" style="v" />The consecrated things <char style="it">were</char> six hundred bulls and three thousand sheep. <verse number="34" style="v" />But the priests were too few, so that they could not skin all the burnt offerings; therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:11</char></note>their brethren the Levites helped them until the work was ended and until the <char style="it">other</char> priests had sanctified themselves, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:3</char></note>for the Levites were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 7:10</char></note>more diligent in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:5</char></note>sanctifying themselves than the priests. <verse number="35" style="v" />Also the burnt offerings <char style="it">were</char> in abundance, with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:15, 16</char></note>the fat of the peace offerings and <char style="it">with</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:5–10</char></note>the drink offerings for <char style="it">every</char> burnt offering.</para>
	<para style="p">So the service of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was set in order. <verse number="36" style="v" />Then Hezekiah and all the people rejoiced that God had prepared the people, since the events took place so suddenly.</para>
	<chapter number="30" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Hezekiah Keeps the Passover</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Hezekiah sent to all Israel and Judah, and also wrote letters to Ephraim and Manasseh, that they should come to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at Jerusalem, to keep the Passover to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />For the king and his leaders and all the assembly in Jerusalem had agreed to keep the Passover in the second <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 9:10, 11; 2 Chr. 30:13, 15</char></note>month. <verse number="3" style="v" />For they could not keep it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:6, 18</char></note>at the regular time, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:17, 34</char></note>because a sufficient number of priests had not consecrated themselves, nor had the people gathered together at Jerusalem. <verse number="4" style="v" />And the matter pleased the king and all the assembly. <verse number="5" style="v" />So they resolved to make a proclamation throughout all Israel, from Beersheba to Dan, that they should come to keep the Passover to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel at Jerusalem, since they had not done <char style="it">it</char> for a long <char style="it">time</char> in the <char style="it">prescribed</char> manner.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 8:14; Job 9:25; Jer. 51:31</char></note>runners went throughout all Israel and Judah with the letters from the king and his leaders, and spoke according to the command of the king: “Children of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 4:1; Joel 2:13)</char></note>return to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel; then He will return to the remnant of you who have escaped from the hand of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:19, 29</char></note>the kings of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:20</char></note>Assyria. <verse number="7" style="v" />And do not be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 20:18</char></note>like your fathers and your brethren, who trespassed against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers, so that He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 1:9</char></note>gave them up to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:8</char></note>desolation, as you see. <verse number="8" style="v" />Now do not be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:9; Deut. 10:16; Acts 7:51</char></note>stiff-necked, as your fathers <char style="it">were, but</char> yield yourselves to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and enter His sanctuary, which He has sanctified forever, and serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:10</char></note>that the fierceness of His wrath may turn away from you. <verse number="9" style="v" />For if you return to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, your brethren and your children <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> <char style="it">treated</char> with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:46</char></note>compassion by those who lead them captive, so that they may come back to this land; for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 34:6; Mic. 7:18)</char></note>gracious and merciful, and will not turn <char style="it">His</char> face from you if you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 55:7)</char></note>return to Him.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So the runners passed from city to city through the country of Ephraim and Manasseh, as far as Zebulun; but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:16</char></note>they laughed at them and mocked them. <verse number="11" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:16; 30:18, 21</char></note>some from Asher, Manasseh, and Zebulun humbled themselves and came to Jerusalem. <verse number="12" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Cor. 3:5; Phil. 2:13; Heb. 13:20, 21)</char></note>the hand of God was on Judah to give them singleness of heart to obey the command of the king and the leaders, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:25</char></note>at the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Now many people, a very great assembly, gathered at Jerusalem to keep the Feast of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:6; Num. 9:11</char></note>Unleavened Bread in the second month. <verse number="14" style="v" />They arose and took away the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:24</char></note>altars that <char style="it">were</char> in Jerusalem, and they took away all the incense altars and cast <char style="it">them</char> into the Brook <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:16</char></note>Kidron. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then they slaughtered the Passover <char style="it">lambs</char> on the fourteenth <char style="it">day</char> of the second month. The priests and the Levites were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:34</char></note>ashamed, and sanctified themselves, and brought the burnt offerings to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="16" style="v" />They stood in their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:10, 15</char></note>place according to their custom, according to the Law of Moses the man of God; the priests sprinkled the blood <char style="it">received</char> from the hand of the Levites. <verse number="17" style="v" />For <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">were</char> many in the assembly who had not sanctified themselves; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:34</char></note>therefore the Levites had charge of the slaughter of the Passover <char style="it">lambs</char> for everyone <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">was</char> not clean, to sanctify <char style="it">them</char> to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="18" style="v" />For a multitude of the people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:1, 11, 25</char></note>many from Ephraim, Manasseh, Issachar, and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselves, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:43–49; (Num. 9:10)</char></note>yet they ate the Passover contrary to what was written. But Hezekiah prayed for them, saying, “May the good <char style="sc">Lord</char> provide atonement for everyone <verse number="19" style="v" /><char style="it">who</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 19:3</char></note>prepares his heart to seek God, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of his fathers, though <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">is</char> not <char style="it">cleansed</char> according to the purification of the sanctuary.” <verse number="20" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> listened to Hezekiah and healed the people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />So the children of Israel who were present at Jerusalem kept <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:15; 13:6; 1 Kin. 8:65</char></note>the Feast of Unleavened Bread seven days with great gladness; and the Levites and the priests praised the <char style="sc">Lord</char> day by day, <char style="it">singing</char> to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, accompanied by loud instruments. <verse number="22" style="v" />And Hezekiah gave encouragement to all the Levites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 33:10); 2 Chr. 17:9; 35:3</char></note>who taught the good knowledge of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and they ate throughout the feast seven days, offering peace offerings and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 10:11</char></note>making confession to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then the whole assembly agreed to keep <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">feast</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:65; 2 Chr. 35:17, 18</char></note>another seven days, and they kept it <char style="it">another</char> seven days with gladness. <verse number="24" style="v" />For Hezekiah king of Judah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:7, 8</char></note>gave to the assembly a thousand bulls and seven thousand sheep, and the leaders gave to the assembly a thousand bulls and ten thousand sheep; and a great number of priests <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:34</char></note>sanctified themselves. <verse number="25" style="v" />The whole assembly of Judah rejoiced, also the priests and Levites, all the assembly that came from Israel, the sojourners <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:11, 18</char></note>who came from the land of Israel, and those who dwelt in Judah. <verse number="26" style="v" />So there was great joy in Jerusalem, for since the time of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:8–10</char></note>Solomon the son of David, king of Israel, <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">had</char> been nothing like this in Jerusalem. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then the priests, the Levites, arose and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:23</char></note>blessed the people, and their voice was heard; and their prayer came <char style="it">up</char> to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 26:15; Ps. 68:5</char></note>His holy dwelling place, to heaven.</para>
	<chapter number="31" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Reforms of Hezekiah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now when all this was finished, all Israel who were present went out to the cities of Judah and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:4</char></note>broke the <char style="it">sacred</char> pillars in pieces, cut down the wooden images, and threw down the high places and the altars—from all Judah, Benjamin, Ephraim, and Manasseh—until they had utterly destroyed them all. Then all the children of Israel returned to their own cities, every man to his possession.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And Hezekiah appointed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:6; 24:1</char></note>the divisions of the priests and the Levites according to their divisions, each man according to his service, the priests and Levites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:30, 31</char></note>for burnt offerings and peace offerings, to serve, to give thanks, and to praise in the gates of the camp of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="3" style="v" />The king also <char style="it">appointed</char> a portion of his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:7</char></note>possessions for the burnt offerings: for the morning and evening burnt offerings, the burnt offerings for the Sabbaths and the New Moons and the set feasts, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> written in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 28:1—29:40</char></note>Law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Moreover he commanded the people who dwelt in Jerusalem to contribute <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:8; 2 Kin. 12:16; Neh. 13:10; Ezek. 44:29</char></note>support for the priests and the Levites, that they might devote themselves to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Mal. 2:7</char></note>the Law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />As soon as the commandment was circulated, the children of Israel brought in abundance <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:29; Neh. 13:12</char></note>the firstfruits of grain and wine, oil and honey, and of all the produce of the field; and they brought in abundantly the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 27:30); Deut. 14:28; 26:12, 13</char></note>tithe of everything. <verse number="6" style="v" />And the children of Israel and Judah, who dwelt in the cities of Judah, brought the tithe of oxen and sheep; also the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 27:30); Deut. 14:28</char></note>tithe of holy things which were consecrated to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God they laid in heaps.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />In the third month they began laying them in heaps, and they finished in the seventh month. <verse number="8" style="v" />And when Hezekiah and the leaders came and saw the heaps, they blessed the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and His people Israel. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then Hezekiah questioned the priests and the Levites concerning the heaps. <verse number="10" style="v" />And Azariah the chief priest, from the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:8, 9</char></note>house of Zadok, answered him and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Mal. 3:10)</char></note>“Since <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">people</char> began to bring the offerings into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, we have had enough to eat and have plenty left, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has blessed His people; and what is left <char style="it">is</char> this great <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 36:5</char></note>abundance.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Now Hezekiah commanded <char style="it">them</char> to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:5–8</char></note>prepare rooms in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and they prepared them. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then they faithfully brought in the offerings, the tithes, and the dedicated things; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:9; Neh. 13:13</char></note>Cononiah the Levite had charge of them, and Shimei his brother <char style="it">was</char> the next. <verse number="13" style="v" />Jehiel, Azaziah, Nahath, Asahel, Jerimoth, Jozabad, Eliel, Ismachiah, Mahath, and Benaiah <char style="it">were</char> overseers under the hand of Cononiah and Shimei his brother, at the commandment of Hezekiah the king and Azariah the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 9:11; Jer. 20:1</char></note>ruler of the house of God. <verse number="14" style="v" />Kore the son of Imnah the Levite, the keeper of the East Gate, <char style="it">was</char> over the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 23:23; 2 Chr. 35:8</char></note>freewill offerings to God, to distribute the offerings of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the most holy things. <verse number="15" style="v" />And under him <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:12</char></note>Eden, Miniamin, Jeshua, Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah, <char style="it">his</char> faithful assistants in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:1–3, 9</char></note>the cities of the priests, to distribute <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 9:26</char></note>allotments to their brethren by divisions, to the great as well as the small.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Besides those males from three years old and up who were written in the genealogy, they distributed to everyone who entered the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his daily portion for the work of his service, by his division, <verse number="17" style="v" />and to the priests who were written in the genealogy according to their father’s house, and to the Levites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:24, 27</char></note>from twenty years old and up according to their work, by their divisions, <verse number="18" style="v" />and to all who were written in the genealogy—their little ones and their wives, their sons and daughters, the whole company of them—for in their faithfulness they sanctified themselves in holiness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Also for the sons of Aaron the priests, <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:34; Num. 35:1–4</char></note>the fields of the common-lands of their cities, in every single city, <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">were</char> men who were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 31:12–15</char></note>designated by name to distribute portions to all the males among the priests and to all who were listed by genealogies among the Levites.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Thus Hezekiah did throughout all Judah, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:3; 22:2</char></note>did what <char style="it">was</char> good and right and true before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God. <verse number="21" style="v" />And in every work that he began in the service of the house of God, in the law and in the commandment, to seek his God, he did <char style="it">it</char> with all his heart. So he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:5; 32:30; Ps. 1:3</char></note>prospered.</para>
	<chapter number="32" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Sennacherib Boasts Against the <char style="sc">Lord</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />After <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:13—19:37; Is. 36:1—37:38</char></note>these deeds of faithfulness, Sennacherib king of Assyria came and entered Judah; he encamped against the fortified cities, thinking to win them over to himself. <verse number="2" style="v" />And when Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib had come, and that his purpose was to make war against Jerusalem, <verse number="3" style="v" />he consulted with his leaders and commanders to stop the water from the springs which <char style="it">were</char> outside the city; and they helped him. <verse number="4" style="v" />Thus many people gathered together who stopped all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:20</char></note>springs and the brook that ran through the land, saying, “Why should the kings of Assyria come and find much water?” <verse number="5" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 22:9, 10</char></note>he strengthened himself, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:4; 2 Chr. 25:23</char></note>built up all the wall that was broken, raised <char style="it">it</char> up to the towers, and <char style="it">built</char> another wall outside; also he repaired the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:9; 1 Kin. 9:15, 24; 11:27; 2 Kin. 12:20; 1 Chr. 11:8</char></note>Millo <char style="it">in</char> the City of David, and made weapons and shields in abundance. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then he set military captains over the people, gathered them together to him in the open square of the city gate, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:22; Is. 40:2</char></note>gave them encouragement, saying, <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 31:6)</char></note>“Be strong and courageous; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:15</char></note>do not be afraid nor dismayed before the king of Assyria, nor before all the multitude that <char style="it">is</char> with him; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:16; (Rom. 8:31)</char></note><char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">are</char> more with us than with him. <verse number="8" style="v" />With him <char style="it">is</char> an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 17:5; 1 John 4:4)</char></note>arm of flesh; but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:13; (1 Sam. 17:45–47); 2 Chr. 13:12; 20:17; (Rom. 8:31)</char></note>with us <char style="it">is</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, to help us and to fight our battles.” And the people were strengthened by the words of Hezekiah king of Judah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:17</char></note>After this Sennacherib king of Assyria sent his servants to Jerusalem (but he and all the forces with him <char style="it">laid</char> <char style="it">siege</char> against Lachish), to Hezekiah king of Judah, and to all Judah who <char style="it">were</char> in Jerusalem, saying, <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:19</char></note>“Thus says Sennacherib king of Assyria: ‘In what do you trust, that you remain under siege in Jerusalem? <verse number="11" style="v" />Does not Hezekiah persuade you to give yourselves over to die by famine and by thirst, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:30</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God will deliver us from the hand of the king of Assyria”? <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:22</char></note>Has not the same Hezekiah taken away His high places and His altars, and commanded Judah and Jerusalem, saying, “You shall worship before one altar and burn incense on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 31:1, 2</char></note>it”? <verse number="13" style="v" />Do you not know what I and my fathers have done to all the peoples of <char style="it">other</char> lands? <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:33–35</char></note>Were the gods of the nations of those lands in any way able to deliver their lands out of my hand? <verse number="14" style="v" />Who <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">there</char> among all the gods of those nations that my fathers utterly destroyed that could deliver his people from my hand, that your God should be able to deliver you from my <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 10:5–12)</char></note>hand? <verse number="15" style="v" />Now therefore, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:29</char></note>do not let Hezekiah deceive you or persuade you like this, and do not believe him; for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to deliver his people from my hand or the hand of my fathers. How much less will your God deliver you from my hand?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Furthermore, his servants spoke against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God and against His servant Hezekiah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />He also wrote letters to revile the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, and to speak against Him, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:9; (1 Cor. 8:5, 6)</char></note>“As the gods of the nations of <char style="it">other</char> lands have not delivered their people from my hand, so the God of Hezekiah will not deliver His people from my <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:12; Dan. 3:15</char></note>hand.” <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:28; Ps. 59:6</char></note>Then they called out with a loud voice in Hebrew to the people of Jerusalem who <char style="it">were</char> on the wall, to frighten them and trouble them, that they might take the city. <verse number="19" style="v" />And they spoke against the God of Jerusalem, as against the gods of the people of the earth—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:18; (Ps. 96:5; 115:4–8)</char></note>the work of men’s hands.</para>
	<para style="s">Sennacherib’s Defeat and Death</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:15</char></note>Now because of this King Hezekiah and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:2</char></note>the prophet Isaiah, the son of Amoz, prayed and cried out to heaven. <verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:35; Is. 10:12–19; Zech. 14:3</char></note>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sent an angel who cut down every mighty man of valor, leader, and captain in the camp of the king of Assyria. So he returned <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 44:7</char></note>shamefaced to his own land. And when he had gone into the temple of his god, some of his own offspring struck him down with the sword there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Thus the <char style="sc">Lord</char> saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib the king of Assyria, and from the hand of all <char style="it">others,</char> and guided them on every side. <verse number="23" style="v" />And many brought gifts to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at Jerusalem, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:10; 2 Chr. 17:5; 26:8; Ps. 45:12</char></note>presents to Hezekiah king of Judah, so that he was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 1:1</char></note>exalted in the sight of all nations thereafter.</para>
	<para style="s">Hezekiah Humbles Himself</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:1–11; Is. 38:1–8</char></note>In those days Hezekiah was sick and near death, and he prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and He spoke to him and gave him a sign. <verse number="25" style="v" />But Hezekiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 116:12</char></note>did not repay according to the favor <char style="it">shown</char> him, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:16; (Hab. 2:4)</char></note>his heart was lifted up; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:18</char></note>therefore wrath was looming over him and over Judah and Jerusalem. <verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 26:18, 19</char></note>Then Hezekiah humbled himself for the pride of his heart, he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> did not come upon them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:19</char></note>in the days of Hezekiah.</para>
	<para style="s">Hezekiah’s Wealth and Honor</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Hezekiah had very great riches and honor. And he made himself treasuries for silver, for gold, for precious stones, for spices, for shields, and for all kinds of desirable items; <verse number="28" style="v" />storehouses for the harvest of grain, wine, and oil; and stalls for all kinds of livestock, and folds for flocks. <verse number="29" style="v" />Moreover he provided cities for himself, and possessions of flocks and herds in abundance; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 29:12</char></note>God had given him very much property. <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 22:9–11</char></note>This same Hezekiah also stopped the water outlet of Upper Gihon, and brought the water by tunnel to the west side of the City of David. Hezekiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 31:21</char></note>prospered in all his works.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />However, <char style="it">regarding</char> the ambassadors of the princes of Babylon, whom they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:12; Is. 39:1</char></note>sent to him to inquire about the wonder that was <char style="it">done</char> in the land, God withdrew from him, in order to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 8:2, 16)</char></note>test him, that He might know all <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">was</char> in his heart.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Hezekiah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and his goodness, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 36—39</char></note>the vision of Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, <char style="it">and</char> in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18—20</char></note>book of the kings of Judah and Israel. <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:21; 2 Kin. 20:21</char></note>So Hezekiah rested with his fathers, and they buried him in the upper tombs of the sons of David; and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 112:6; Prov. 10:7</char></note>honored him at his death. Then Manasseh his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="33" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Manasseh Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Manasseh <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:1–9</char></note><char style="it">was</char> twelve years old when he became king, and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v" />But he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 18:9–12); 2 Chr. 28:3; (Jer. 15:4)</char></note>abominations of the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had cast out before the children of Israel. <verse number="3" style="v" />For he rebuilt the high places which Hezekiah his father had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:4; 2 Chr. 30:14; 31:1</char></note>broken down; he raised up altars for the Baals, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 16:21; 2 Kin. 23:5, 6</char></note>made wooden images; and he worshiped <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:3</char></note>all the host of heaven and served them. <verse number="4" style="v" />He also built altars in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, of which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:11; 1 Kin. 8:29; 9:3; 2 Chr. 6:6; 7:16</char></note>“In Jerusalem shall My name be forever.” <verse number="5" style="v" />And he built altars for all the host of heaven <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 4:9</char></note>in the two courts of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:21); Deut. 18:10; 2 Kin. 23:10; 2 Chr. 28:3; Ezek. 23:37, 39</char></note>Also he caused his sons to pass through the fire in the Valley of the Son of Hinnom; he practiced <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 18:11; 2 Kin. 17:17</char></note>soothsaying, used witchcraft and sorcery, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 19:31; 20:27); 2 Kin. 21:6</char></note>consulted mediums and spiritists. He did much evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to provoke Him to anger. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:7; 2 Chr. 25:14</char></note>He even set a carved image, the idol which he had made, in the house of God, of which God had said to David and to Solomon his son, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 132:14</char></note>“In this house and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I will put My name forever; <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:10</char></note>and I will not again remove the foot of Israel from the land which I have appointed for your fathers—only if they are careful to do all that I have commanded them, according to the whole law and the statutes and the ordinances by the hand of Moses.” <verse number="9" style="v" />So Manasseh seduced Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to do more evil than the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had destroyed before the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="s">Manasseh Restored After Repentance</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Manasseh and his people, but they would not listen. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:36</char></note>Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> brought upon them the captains of the army of the king of Assyria, who took Manasseh with hooks, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:6; Job 36:8; Ps. 107:10, 11</char></note>bound him with bronze <char style="it">fetters,</char> and carried him off to Babylon. <verse number="12" style="v" />Now when he was in affliction, he implored the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:14; 32:26; (1 Pet. 5:6)</char></note>humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers, <verse number="13" style="v" />and prayed to Him; and He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 5:20; Ezra 8:23</char></note>received his entreaty, heard his supplication, and brought him back to Jerusalem into his kingdom. Then Manasseh <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:13; Ps. 9:16; Dan. 4:25</char></note>knew that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">was</char> God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />After this he built a wall outside the City of David on the west side of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:33</char></note>Gihon, in the valley, as far as the entrance of the Fish Gate; and <char style="it">it</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 27:3</char></note>enclosed Ophel, and he raised it to a very great height. Then he put military captains in all the fortified cities of Judah. <verse number="15" style="v" />He took away <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:3, 5, 7</char></note>the foreign gods and the idol from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and all the altars that he had built in the mount of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in Jerusalem; and he cast <char style="it">them</char> out of the city. <verse number="16" style="v" />He also repaired the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, sacrificed peace offerings and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:12</char></note>thank offerings on it, and commanded Judah to serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:12</char></note>Nevertheless the people still sacrificed on the high places, <char style="it">but</char> only to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Manasseh</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, his prayer to his God, and the words of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:9</char></note>the seers who spoke to him in the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> <char style="it">written</char> in the book of the kings of Israel. <verse number="19" style="v" />Also his prayer and <char style="it">how</char> <char style="it">God</char> received his entreaty, and all his sin and trespass, and the sites where he built high places and set up wooden images and carved images, before he was humbled, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written among the sayings of Hozai. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:21; 2 Kin. 21:18</char></note>So Manasseh rested with his fathers, and they buried him in his own house. Then his son Amon reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Amon’s Reign and Death</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:19–24; 1 Chr. 3:14</char></note>Amon <char style="it">was</char> twenty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. <verse number="22" style="v" />But he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as his father Manasseh had done; for Amon sacrificed to all the carved images which his father Manasseh had made, and served them. <verse number="23" style="v" />And he did not humble himself before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:12, 19</char></note>as his father Manasseh had humbled himself; but Amon trespassed more and more.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:23, 24; 2 Chr. 24:25</char></note>Then his servants conspired against him, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:27</char></note>killed him in his own house. <verse number="25" style="v" />But the people of the land executed all those who had conspired against King Amon. Then the people of the land made his son Josiah king in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="34" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Josiah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Josiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:1, 2; Jer. 1:2; 3:6</char></note><char style="it">was</char> eight years old when he became king, and he reigned thirty-one years in Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and walked in the ways of his father David; <char style="it">he</char> did <char style="it">not</char> turn aside to the right hand or to the left.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />For in the eighth year of his reign, while he was still <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Eccl. 12:1</char></note>young, he began to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 15:2; (Prov. 8:17)</char></note>seek the God of his father David; and in the twelfth year he began <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:2</char></note>to purge Judah and Jerusalem <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:17–19, 22</char></note>of the high places, the wooden images, the carved images, and the molded images. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:30; 2 Kin. 23:4</char></note>They broke down the altars of the Baals in his presence, and the incense altars which <char style="it">were</char> above them he cut down; and the wooden images, the carved images, and the molded images he broke in pieces, and made dust of them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:6</char></note>and scattered <char style="it">it</char> on the graves of those who had sacrificed to them. <verse number="5" style="v" />He also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:2</char></note>burned the bones of the priests on their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:20</char></note>altars, and cleansed Judah and Jerusalem. <verse number="6" style="v" />And <char style="it">so</char> <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">did</char> in the cities of Manasseh, Ephraim, and Simeon, as far as Naphtali and all around, with axes. <verse number="7" style="v" />When he had broken down the altars and the wooden images, had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 9:21</char></note>beaten the carved images into powder, and cut down all the incense altars throughout all the land of Israel, he returned to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="s">Hilkiah Finds the Book of the Law</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:3–20</char></note>In the eighteenth year of his reign, when he had purged the land and the temple, he sent <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:22</char></note>Shaphan the son of Azaliah, Maaseiah the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 18:25</char></note>governor of the city, and Joah the son of Joahaz the recorder, to repair the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God. <verse number="9" style="v" />When they came to Hilkiah the high priest, they delivered <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:4</char></note>the money that was brought into the house of God, which the Levites who kept the doors had gathered from the hand of Manasseh and Ephraim, from all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:6</char></note>remnant of Israel, from all Judah and Benjamin, and <char style="it">which</char> they had brought back to Jerusalem. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then they put <char style="it">it</char> in the hand of the foremen who had the oversight of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and they gave it to the workmen who worked in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to repair and restore the house. <verse number="11" style="v" />They gave <char style="it">it</char> to the craftsmen and builders to buy hewn stone and timber for beams, and to floor the houses which the kings of Judah had destroyed. <verse number="12" style="v" />And the men did the work faithfully. Their overseers <char style="it">were</char> Jahath and Obadiah the Levites, of the sons of Merari, and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of the Kohathites, to supervise. <char style="it">Others</char> <char style="it">of</char> the Levites, all of whom were skillful with instruments of music, <verse number="13" style="v" /><char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:10</char></note>over the burden bearers and <char style="it">were</char> overseers of all who did work in any kind of service. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:4, 5</char></note>And <char style="it">some</char> of the Levites <char style="it">were</char> scribes, officers, and gatekeepers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Now when they brought out the money that was brought into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, Hilkiah the priest <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:8</char></note>found the Book of the Law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">given</char> by Moses. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then Hilkiah answered and said to Shaphan the scribe, “I have found the Book of the Law in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” And Hilkiah gave the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:24, 26</char></note>book to Shaphan. <verse number="16" style="v" />So Shaphan carried the book to the king, bringing the king word, saying, “All that was committed to your servants they are doing. <verse number="17" style="v" />And they have gathered the money that was found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers and the workmen.” <verse number="18" style="v" />Then Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, “Hilkiah the priest has given me a book.” And Shaphan read it before the king.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Thus it happened, when the king heard the words of the Law, that he tore his clothes. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then the king commanded Hilkiah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 26:24</char></note>Ahikam the son of Shaphan, Abdon the son of Micah, Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah a servant of the king, saying, <verse number="21" style="v" />“Go, inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for me, and for those who are left in Israel and Judah, concerning the words of the book that is found; for great <char style="it">is</char> the wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that is poured out on us, because our fathers have not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:15–19</char></note>kept the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to do according to all that is written in this book.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />So Hilkiah and those the king <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">appointed</char> went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tokhath, the son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe. (She dwelt in Jerusalem in the Second Quarter.) And they spoke to her to that <char style="it">effect.</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then she answered them, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, ‘Tell the man who sent you to Me, <verse number="24" style="v" />“Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Behold, I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:14–20</char></note>bring calamity on this place and on its inhabitants, all the curses that are written in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:15–68</char></note>book which they have read before the king of Judah, <verse number="25" style="v" />because they have forsaken Me and burned incense to other gods, that they might provoke Me to anger with all the works of their hands. Therefore My wrath will be poured out on this place, and not be quenched.’ ” ’ <verse number="26" style="v" />But as for the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, in this manner you shall speak to him, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: “<char style="it">Concerning</char> the words which you have heard— <verse number="27" style="v" />because your heart was tender, and you humbled yourself before God when you heard His words against this place and against its inhabitants, and you humbled yourself before Me, and you tore your clothes and wept before Me, I also have heard <char style="it">you,</char>” says the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:19; 2 Chr. 12:7; 30:6; 33:12, 13</char></note><char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="28" style="v" />“Surely I will gather you to your fathers, and you shall be gathered to your grave in peace; and your eyes shall not see all the calamity which I will bring on this place and its inhabitants.” ’ ” So they brought back word to the king.</para>
	<para style="s">Josiah Restores True Worship</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:1–3</char></note>Then the king sent and gathered all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. <verse number="30" style="v" />The king went up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, with all the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem—the priests and the Levites, and all the people, great and small. And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 8:1–3</char></note>read in their hearing all the words of the Book of the Covenant which had been found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="31" style="v" />Then the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 6:13</char></note>stood in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 11:14; 23:3; 2 Chr. 30:16</char></note>his place and made a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:16; 29:10</char></note>covenant before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to follow the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and to keep His commandments and His testimonies and His statutes with all his heart and all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant that were written in this book. <verse number="32" style="v" />And he made all who were present in Jerusalem and Benjamin take a stand. So the inhabitants of Jerusalem did according to the covenant of God, the God of their fathers. <verse number="33" style="v" />Thus Josiah removed all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:5; 2 Chr. 33:2</char></note>abominations from all the country that <char style="it">belonged</char> to the children of Israel, and made all who were present in Israel diligently serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 3:10</char></note>All his days they did not depart from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers.</para>
	<chapter number="35" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Josiah Keeps the Passover</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:21, 22</char></note>Josiah kept a Passover to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Jerusalem, and they slaughtered the Passover <char style="it">lambs</char> on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:6; Num. 9:3; Ezra 6:19</char></note>fourteenth <char style="it">day</char> of the first month. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he set the priests in their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:18; Ezra 6:18</char></note>duties and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:5–15</char></note>encouraged them for the service of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then he said to the Levites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 33:10; 2 Chr. 17:8, 9; Neh. 8:7</char></note>who taught all Israel, who were holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:14</char></note>“Put the holy ark <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:21; 2 Chr. 5:7</char></note>in the house which Solomon the son of David, king of Israel, built. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23:26</char></note><char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">shall</char> no longer <char style="it">be</char> a burden on <char style="it">your</char> shoulders. Now serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God and His people Israel. <verse number="4" style="v" />Prepare <char style="it">yourselves</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 9:10–13</char></note>according to your fathers’ houses, according to your divisions, following the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 23—26</char></note>written instruction of David king of Israel and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:14</char></note>written instruction of Solomon his son. <verse number="5" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 134:1</char></note>stand in the holy <char style="it">place</char> according to the divisions of the fathers’ houses of your brethren the <char style="it">lay</char> people, and <char style="it">according</char> <char style="it">to</char> the division of the father’s house of the Levites. <verse number="6" style="v" />So slaughter the Passover <char style="it">offerings,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:5, 15</char></note>consecrate yourselves, and prepare <char style="it">them</char> for your brethren, that <char style="it">they</char> may do according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by the hand of Moses.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then Josiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:24</char></note>gave the <char style="it">lay</char> people lambs and young goats from the flock, all for Passover <char style="it">offerings</char> for all who were present, to the number of thirty thousand, as well as three thousand cattle; these <char style="it">were</char> from the king’s <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 31:3</char></note>possessions. <verse number="8" style="v" />And his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 7:2</char></note>leaders gave willingly to the people, to the priests, and to the Levites. Hilkiah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, rulers of the house of God, gave to the priests for the Passover <char style="it">offerings</char> two thousand six hundred <char style="it">from</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">flock,</char> and three hundred cattle. <verse number="9" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 31:12</char></note>Conaniah, his brothers Shemaiah and Nethanel, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jozabad, chief of the Levites, gave to the Levites for Passover <char style="it">offerings</char> five thousand <char style="it">from</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">flock</char> and five hundred cattle.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So the service was prepared, and the priests <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 6:18; Heb. 9:6</char></note>stood in their places, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 5:12; 7:6; 8:14, 15; 13:10; 29:25–34</char></note>Levites in their divisions, according to the king’s command. <verse number="11" style="v" />And they slaughtered the Passover <char style="it">offerings;</char> and the priests <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:22; 2 Chr. 29:22</char></note>sprinkled <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">blood</char> with their hands, while the Levites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:34</char></note>skinned <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">animals.</char> <verse number="12" style="v" />Then they removed the burnt offerings that <char style="it">they</char> might give them to the divisions of the fathers’ houses of the <char style="it">lay</char> people, to offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> written <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:3; Ezra 6:18</char></note>in the Book of Moses. And so <char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">did</char> with the cattle. <verse number="13" style="v" />Also they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:8, 9; Deut. 16:7</char></note>roasted the Passover <char style="it">offerings</char> with fire according to the ordinance; but the <char style="it">other</char> holy <char style="it">offerings</char> they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:13–15</char></note>boiled in pots, in caldrons, and in pans, and divided <char style="it">them</char> quickly among all the <char style="it">lay</char> people. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then afterward they prepared portions for themselves and for the priests, because the priests, the sons of Aaron, <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">busy</char> in offering burnt offerings and fat until night; therefore the Levites prepared portions for themselves and for the priests, the sons of Aaron. <verse number="15" style="v" />And the singers, the sons of Asaph, <char style="it">were</char> in their places, according to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 25:1–6</char></note>command of David, Asaph, Heman, and Jeduthun the king’s seer. Also the gatekeepers <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 9:17, 18</char></note>were at each gate; they did not have to leave their position, because their brethren the Levites prepared portions for them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So all the service of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was prepared the same day, to keep the Passover and to offer burnt offerings on the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to the command of King Josiah. <verse number="17" style="v" />And the children of Israel who were present kept the Passover at that time, and the Feast of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:15; 13:6; 2 Chr. 30:21</char></note>Unleavened Bread for seven days. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:22, 23</char></note>There had been no Passover kept in Israel like that since the days of Samuel the prophet; and none of the kings of Israel had kept such a Passover as Josiah kept, with the priests and the Levites, all Judah and Israel who were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. <verse number="19" style="v" />In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah this Passover was kept.</para>
	<para style="s">Josiah Dies in Battle</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:29</char></note>After all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple, Necho king of Egypt came up to fight against <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 10:9; Jer. 46:2</char></note>Carchemish by the Euphrates; and Josiah went out against him. <verse number="21" style="v" />But he sent messengers to him, saying, “What have I to do with you, king of Judah? <char style="it">I</char> <char style="it">have</char> not <char style="it">come</char> against you this day, but against the house with which I have war; for God commanded me to make haste. Refrain <char style="it">from</char> <char style="it">meddling</char> <char style="it">with</char> God, who <char style="it">is</char> with me, lest He destroy you.” <verse number="22" style="v" />Nevertheless Josiah would not turn his face from him, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:30; 2 Chr. 18:29</char></note>disguised himself so that he might fight with him, and did not heed the words of Necho from the mouth of God. So he came to fight in the Valley of Megiddo.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And the archers shot King Josiah; and the king said to his servants, “Take me away, for I am severely wounded.” <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:30</char></note>His servants therefore took him out of that chariot and put him in the second chariot that he had, and they brought him to Jerusalem. So he died, and was buried in <char style="it">one</char> <char style="it">of</char> the tombs of his fathers. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:18; Zech. 12:11</char></note>all Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Jeremiah also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lam. 4:20</char></note>lamented for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 22:10, 11</char></note>Josiah. And to this day <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 9:23</char></note>all the singing men and the singing women speak of Josiah in their lamentations. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 22:20</char></note>They made it a custom in Israel; and indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the Laments.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Josiah and his goodness, according to <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> written in the Law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse number="27" style="v" />and his deeds from first to last, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.</para>
	<chapter number="36" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Reign and Captivity of Jehoahaz</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:30–34</char></note>the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and made him king in his father’s place in Jerusalem. <verse number="2" style="v" />Jehoahaz <char style="it">was</char> twenty-three years old when he became king, and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. <verse number="3" style="v" />Now the king of Egypt deposed him at Jerusalem; and he imposed on the land a tribute of one hundred talents of silver and a talent of gold. <verse number="4" style="v" />Then the king of Egypt made <char style="it">Jehoahaz’s</char> brother Eliakim king over Judah and Jerusalem, and changed his name to Jehoiakim. And Necho took Jehoahaz his brother and carried him off to Egypt.</para>
	<para style="s">The Reign and Captivity of Jehoiakim</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:36, 37; 1 Chr. 3:15</char></note>Jehoiakim <char style="it">was</char> twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. And he did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 22:13–19)</char></note>evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:1; Hab. 1:6</char></note>Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up against him, and bound him in bronze <char style="it">fetters</char> to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 29:22–29); 2 Chr. 33:11; Jer. 36:30</char></note>carry him off to Babylon. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:13; Dan. 1:1, 2</char></note>Nebuchadnezzar also carried off <char style="it">some</char> of the articles from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to Babylon, and put them in his temple at Babylon. <verse number="8" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, the abominations which he did, and what was found against him, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. Then Jehoiachin his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">The Reign and Captivity of Jehoiachin</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:8–17</char></note>Jehoiachin <char style="it">was</char> eight years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem three months and ten days. And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="10" style="v" />At the turn of the year <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:10–17</char></note>King Nebuchadnezzar summoned <char style="it">him</char> and took him to Babylon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:1, 2</char></note>with the costly articles from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and made <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 37:1</char></note>Zedekiah, <char style="it">Jehoiakim’s</char> brother, king over Judah and Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="s">Zedekiah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:18–20; Jer. 52:1</char></note>Zedekiah <char style="it">was</char> twenty-one years old when he became king, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. <verse number="12" style="v" />He did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, <char style="it">and</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 21:3–7; 44:10</char></note>did not humble himself before Jeremiah the prophet, <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">spoke</char> from the mouth of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />And he also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 52:3; Ezek. 17:15</char></note>rebelled against King Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear <char style="it">an</char> <char style="it">oath</char> by God; but he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:14; (2 Chr. 30:8)</char></note>stiffened his neck and hardened his heart against turning to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="14" style="v" />Moreover all the leaders of the priests and the people transgressed more and more, <char style="it">according</char> to all the abominations of the nations, and defiled the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He had consecrated in Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="s">The Fall of Jerusalem</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 7:13; 25:3, 4</char></note>And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers sent <char style="it">warnings</char> to them by His messengers, rising up early and sending <char style="it">them,</char> because He had compassion on His people and on His dwelling place. <verse number="16" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 30:10; Jer. 5:12, 13</char></note>they mocked the messengers of God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 1:24–32)</char></note>despised His words, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 38:6; Matt. 23:34</char></note>scoffed at His prophets, until the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:25; Ps. 79:5</char></note>wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> arose against His people, till <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> no remedy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:56; Deut. 4:26; 28:49; 2 Kin. 25:1; Ezra 9:7; Is. 3:8</char></note>Therefore He brought against them the king of the Chaldeans, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 74:20</char></note>killed their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary, and had no compassion on young man or virgin, on the aged or the weak; He gave <char style="it">them</char> all into his hand. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:13–15; 2 Chr. 36:7, 10</char></note>And all the articles from the house of God, great and small, the treasures of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and the treasures of the king and of his leaders, all <char style="it">these</char> he took to Babylon. <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:9; Ps. 79:1, 7; Is. 1:7, 8; Jer. 52:13</char></note>Then they burned the house of God, broke down the wall of Jerusalem, burned all its palaces with fire, and destroyed all its precious possessions. <verse number="20" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:11; Jer. 5:19; Mic. 4:10</char></note>those who escaped from the sword he carried away to Babylon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 17:4; 27:7</char></note>where they became servants to him and his sons until the rule of the kingdom of Persia, <verse number="21" style="v" />to fulfill the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by the mouth of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 25:9–12; 27:6–8; 29:10</char></note>Jeremiah, until the land <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:34–43; Dan. 9:2</char></note>had enjoyed her Sabbaths. As long as she lay desolate <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:4, 5</char></note>she kept Sabbath, to fulfill seventy years.</para>
	<para style="s">The Proclamation of Cyrus</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 1:1–3</char></note>Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by the mouth of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 29:10</char></note>Jeremiah might be fulfilled, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> stirred up the spirit of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 44:28; 45:1</char></note>Cyrus king of Persia, so that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and also <char style="it">put</char> <char style="it">it</char> in writing, saying,</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 1:2, 3</char></note>Thus says Cyrus king of Persia:</para>
	<para style="q2">All the kingdoms of the earth the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of heaven has given me. And He has commanded me to build Him a house at Jerusalem which is in Judah. Who <char style="it">is</char> among you of all His people? May the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God <char style="it">be</char> with him, and let him go up!</para>
	
</usx>
