<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="2KI" style="id">The Second Book of the Kings</book>
    <para style="mt">The Second Book of the Kings</para>
    <chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="s">God Judges Ahaziah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Moab <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:2</char></note>rebelled against Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:5</char></note>after the death of Ahab.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:40</char></note>Ahaziah fell through the lattice of his upper room in Samaria, and was injured; so he sent messengers and said to them, “Go, inquire of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 1:3, 6, 16; Matt. 10:25; Mark 3:22</char></note>Baal-Zebub, the god of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 5:10</char></note>Ekron, whether I shall recover from this injury.” <verse number="3" style="v" />But the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Elijah the Tishbite, “Arise, go up to meet the messengers of the king of Samaria, and say to them, ‘<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> because <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no God in Israel <char style="it">that</char> you are going to inquire of Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron?’ <verse number="4" style="v" />Now therefore, thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘You shall not come down from the bed to which you have gone up, but you shall surely die.’ ” So Elijah departed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />And when the messengers returned to him, he said to them, “Why have you come back?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So they said to him, “A man came up to meet us, and said to us, ‘Go, return to the king who sent you, and say to him, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> because <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no God in Israel <char style="it">that</char> you are sending to inquire of Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron? Therefore you shall not come down from the bed to which you have gone up, but you shall surely die.’ ” ’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then he said to them, “What kind of man <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">it</char> who came up to meet you and told you these words?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So they answered him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Zech. 13:4; Matt. 3:4; Mark 1:6</char></note>“A hairy man wearing a leather belt around his waist.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:7</char></note>“It <char style="it">is</char> Elijah the Tishbite.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then the king sent to him a captain of fifty with his fifty men. So he went up to him; and there he was, sitting on the top of a hill. And he spoke to him: “Man of God, the king has said, ‘Come down!’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So Elijah answered and said to the captain of fifty, “If I <char style="it">am</char> a man of God, then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:36–38; Luke 9:54</char></note>let fire come down from heaven and consume you and your fifty men.” And fire came down from heaven and consumed him and his fifty. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then he sent to him another captain of fifty with his fifty men.</para>
	<para style="p">And he answered and said to him: “Man of God, thus has the king said, ‘Come down quickly!’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So Elijah answered and said to them, “If I <char style="it">am</char> a man of God, let fire come down from heaven and consume you and your fifty men.” And the fire of God came down from heaven and consumed him and his fifty.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Again, he sent a third captain of fifty with his fifty men. And the third captain of fifty went up, and came and fell on his knees before Elijah, and pleaded with him, and said to him: “Man of God, please let my life and the life of these fifty servants of yours <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 26:21; Ps. 72:14</char></note>be precious in your sight. <verse number="14" style="v" />Look, fire has come down from heaven and burned up the first two captains of fifties with their fifties. But let my life now be precious in your sight.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Elijah, “Go down with him; do not be afraid of him.” So he arose and went down with him to the king. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then he said to him, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Because you have sent messengers to inquire of Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron, <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">it</char> because <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no God in Israel to inquire of His word? Therefore you shall not come down from the bed to which you have gone up, but you shall surely die.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />So <char style="it">Ahaziah</char> died according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which Elijah had spoken. Because he had no son, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:50; 2 Kin. 8:16; Matt. 1:8</char></note>Jehoram became king in his place, in the second year of Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat, king of Judah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Ahaziah which he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Elijah Ascends to Heaven</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass, when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was about to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 5:24; (Heb. 11:5)</char></note>take up Elijah into heaven by a whirlwind, that Elijah went with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:16–21</char></note>Elisha from Gilgal. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then Elijah said to Elisha, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ruth 1:15, 16</char></note>“Stay here, please, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has sent me on to Bethel.”</para>
	<para style="p">But Elisha said, “<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 1:26; 2 Kin. 2:4, 6; 4:30</char></note><char style="it">as</char> your soul lives, I will not leave you!” So they went down to Bethel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:35; 2 Kin. 2:5, 7, 15; 4:1, 38; 9:1</char></note>the sons of the prophets who <char style="it">were</char> at Bethel came out to Elisha, and said to him, “Do you know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will take away your master from over you today?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “Yes, I know; keep silent!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Then Elijah said to him, “Elisha, stay here, please, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has sent me on to Jericho.”</para>
	<para style="p">But he said, “<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, and <char style="it">as</char> your soul lives, I will not leave you!” So they came to Jericho.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Now the sons of the prophets who <char style="it">were</char> at Jericho came to Elisha and said to him, “Do you know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will take away your master from over you today?”</para>
	<para style="p">So he answered, “Yes, I know; keep silent!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then Elijah said to him, “Stay here, please, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has sent me on to the Jordan.”</para>
	<para style="p">But he said, “<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, and <char style="it">as</char> your soul lives, I will not leave you!” So the two of them went on. <verse number="7" style="v" />And fifty men of the sons of the prophets went and stood facing <char style="it">them</char> at a distance, while the two of them stood by the Jordan. <verse number="8" style="v" />Now Elijah took his mantle, rolled <char style="it">it</char> up, and struck the water; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:21, 22; Josh. 3:16; 2 Kin. 2:14</char></note>it was divided this way and that, so that the two of them crossed over on dry <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:17</char></note>ground.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And so it was, when they had crossed over, that Elijah said to Elisha, “Ask! What may I do for you, before I am taken away from you?”</para>
	<para style="p">Elisha said, “Please let a double portion of your spirit be upon me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So he said, “You have asked a hard thing. <char style="it">Nevertheless,</char> if you see me <char style="it">when</char> <char style="it">I</char> <char style="it">am</char> taken from you, it shall be so for you; but if not, it shall not be <char style="it">so.</char>” <verse number="11" style="v" />Then it happened, as they continued on and talked, that suddenly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:17; Ps. 104:4</char></note>a chariot of fire <char style="it">appeared</char> with horses of fire, and separated the two of them; and Elijah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 5:24; Heb. 11:5</char></note>went up by a whirlwind into heaven.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And Elisha saw <char style="it">it,</char> and he cried out, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:14</char></note>“My father, my father, the chariot of Israel and its horsemen!” So he saw him no more. And he took hold of his own clothes and tore them into two pieces. <verse number="13" style="v" />He also took up the mantle of Elijah that had fallen from him, and went back and stood by the bank of the Jordan. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then he took the mantle of Elijah that had fallen from him, and struck the water, and said, “Where <char style="it">is</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Elijah?” And when he also had struck the water, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:8</char></note>it was divided this way and that; and Elisha crossed over.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Now when the sons of the prophets who <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:7</char></note>from Jericho saw him, they said, “The spirit of Elijah rests on Elisha.” And they came to meet him, and bowed to the ground before him. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then they said to him, “Look now, there are fifty strong men with your servants. Please let them go and search for your master, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:12; Ezek. 8:3; Acts 8:39</char></note>lest perhaps the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has taken him up and cast him upon some mountain or into some valley.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “You shall not send anyone.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />But when they urged him till he was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:11</char></note>ashamed, he said, “Send <char style="it">them!</char>” Therefore they sent fifty men, and they searched for three days but did not find him. <verse number="18" style="v" />And when they came back to him, for he had stayed in Jericho, he said to them, “Did I not say to you, ‘Do not go’?”</para>
	<para style="s">Elisha Performs Miracles</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then the men of the city said to Elisha, “Please notice, the situation of this city <char style="it">is</char> pleasant, as my lord sees; but the water <char style="it">is</char> bad, and the ground barren.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And he said, “Bring me a new bowl, and put salt in it.” So they brought <char style="it">it</char> to him. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then he went out to the source of the water, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:25, 26; 2 Kin. 4:41; 6:6; John 9:6</char></note>cast in the salt there, and said, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘I have healed this water; from it there shall be no more death or barrenness.’ ” <verse number="22" style="v" />So the water remains <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 47:8, 9</char></note>healed to this day, according to the word of Elisha which he spoke.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then he went up from there to Bethel; and as he was going up the road, some youths came from the city and mocked him, and said to him, “Go up, you baldhead! Go up, you baldhead!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So he turned around and looked at them, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 27:13–26</char></note>pronounced a curse on them in the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And two female bears came out of the woods and mauled forty-two of the youths.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Then he went from there to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:19, 20; 2 Kin. 4:25</char></note>Mount Carmel, and from there he returned to Samaria.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Moab Rebels Against Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 1:17</char></note>Jehoram the son of Ahab became king over Israel at Samaria in the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and reigned twelve years. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but not like his father and mother; for he put away the <char style="it">sacred</char> pillar of Baal <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:31, 32</char></note>that his father had made. <verse number="3" style="v" />Nevertheless he persisted in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28–32</char></note>the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin; he did not depart from them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Now Mesha king of Moab was a sheepbreeder, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:2</char></note>regularly paid the king of Israel one hundred thousand <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 16:1, 2</char></note>lambs and the wool of one hundred thousand rams. <verse number="5" style="v" />But it happened, when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 1:1</char></note>Ahab died, that the king of Moab rebelled against the king of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So King Jehoram went out of Samaria at that time and mustered all Israel. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then he went and sent to Jehoshaphat king of Judah, saying, “The king of Moab has rebelled against me. Will you go with me to fight against Moab?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “I will go up; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:4</char></note>I <char style="it">am</char> as you <char style="it">are,</char> my people as your people, my horses as your horses.” <verse number="8" style="v" />Then he said, “Which way shall we go up?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he answered, “By way of the Wilderness of Edom.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So the king of Israel went with the king of Judah and the king of Edom, and they marched on that roundabout route seven days; and there was no water for the army, nor for the animals that followed them. <verse number="10" style="v" />And the king of Israel said, “Alas! For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has called these three kings together to deliver them into the hand of Moab.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:7</char></note>Jehoshaphat said, “<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">there</char> no prophet of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> here, that we may inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by him?”</para>
	<para style="p">So one of the servants of the king of Israel answered and said, “Elisha the son of Shaphat <char style="it">is</char> here, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:21; (John 13:4, 5, 13, 14)</char></note>poured water on the hands of Elijah.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And Jehoshaphat said, “The word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is with him.” So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:25</char></note>went down to him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then Elisha said to the king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ezek. 14:3)</char></note>“What have I to do with you? <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:14; Ruth 1:15</char></note>Go to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:6–11</char></note>the prophets of your father and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:19</char></note>prophets of your mother.”</para>
	<para style="p">But the king of Israel said to him, “No, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has called these three kings <char style="it">together</char> to deliver them into the hand of Moab.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And Elisha said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 17:1; 2 Kin. 5:16</char></note>“<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> of hosts lives, before whom I stand, surely were it not that I regard the presence of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, I would not look at you, nor see you. <verse number="15" style="v" />But now bring me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 10:5</char></note>a musician.”</para>
	<para style="p">Then it happened, when the musician <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 16:16, 23; 1 Chr. 25:1</char></note>played, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 1:3; 3:14, 22; 8:1</char></note>the hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon him. <verse number="16" style="v" />And he said, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 14:3</char></note>‘Make this valley full of ditches.’ <verse number="17" style="v" />For thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘You shall not see wind, nor shall you see rain; yet that valley shall be filled with water, so that you, your cattle, and your animals may drink.’ <verse number="18" style="v" />And this is a simple matter in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; He will also deliver the Moabites into your hand. <verse number="19" style="v" />Also you shall attack every fortified city and every choice city, and shall cut down every good tree, and stop up every spring of water, and ruin every good piece of land with stones.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Now it happened in the morning, when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:39, 40</char></note>the grain offering was offered, that suddenly water came by way of Edom, and the land was filled with water.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And when all the Moabites heard that the kings had come up to fight against them, all who were able to bear arms and older were gathered; and they stood at the border. <verse number="22" style="v" />Then they rose up early in the morning, and the sun was shining on the water; and the Moabites saw the water on the other side <char style="it">as</char> red as blood. <verse number="23" style="v" />And they said, “This is blood; the kings have surely struck swords and have killed one another; now therefore, Moab, to the spoil!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So when they came to the camp of Israel, Israel rose up and attacked the Moabites, so that they fled before them; and they entered <char style="it">their</char> land, killing the Moabites. <verse number="25" style="v" />Then they destroyed the cities, and each man threw a stone on every good piece of land and filled it; and they stopped up all the springs of water and cut down all the good trees. But they left the stones of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 16:7, 11; Jer. 48:31, 36</char></note>Kir Haraseth <char style="it">intact.</char> However the slingers surrounded and attacked it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />And when the king of Moab saw that the battle was too fierce for him, he took with him seven hundred men who drew swords, to break through to the king of Edom, but they could not. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 18:10; Amos 2:1; Mic. 6:7)</char></note>he took his eldest son who would have reigned in his place, and offered him <char style="it">as</char> a burnt offering upon the wall; and there was great indignation against Israel. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:20</char></note>So they departed from him and returned to <char style="it">their</char> <char style="it">own</char> land.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Elisha and the Widow’s Oil</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />A certain woman of the wives of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:35; 2 Kin. 2:3</char></note>the sons of the prophets cried out to Elisha, saying, “Your servant my husband is dead, and you know that your servant feared the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And the creditor is coming <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 25:39–41, 48); 1 Sam. 22:2; Neh. 5:2–5; Matt. 18:25</char></note>to take my two sons to be his slaves.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />So Elisha said to her, “What shall I do for you? Tell me, what do you have in the house?” And she said, “Your maidservant has nothing in the house but a jar of oil.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then he said, “Go, borrow vessels from everywhere, from all your neighbors—empty vessels; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:16</char></note>do not gather just a few. <verse number="4" style="v" />And when you have come in, you shall shut the door behind you and your sons; then pour it into all those vessels, and set aside the full ones.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So she went from him and shut the door behind her and her sons, who brought <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">vessels</char> to her; and she poured <char style="it">it</char> out. <verse number="6" style="v" />Now it came to pass, when the vessels were full, that she said to her son, “Bring me another vessel.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said to her, “<char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">is</char> not another vessel.” So the oil ceased. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then she came and told the man of God. And he said, “Go, sell the oil and pay your debt; and you <char style="it">and</char> your sons live on the rest.”</para>
	<para style="s">Elisha Raises the Shunammite’s Son</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Now it happened one day that Elisha went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:18</char></note>Shunem, where there <char style="it">was</char> a notable woman, and she persuaded him to eat some food. So it was, as often as he passed by, he would turn in there to eat some food. <verse number="9" style="v" />And she said to her husband, “Look now, I know that this <char style="it">is</char> a holy man of God, who passes by us regularly. <verse number="10" style="v" />Please, let us make a small upper room on the wall; and let us put a bed for him there, and a table and a chair and a lampstand; so it will be, whenever he comes to us, he can turn in there.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And it happened one day that he came there, and he turned in to the upper room and lay down there. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then he said to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:29–31; 5:20–27; 8:4, 5</char></note>Gehazi his servant, “Call this Shunammite woman.” When he had called her, she stood before him. <verse number="13" style="v" />And he said to him, “Say now to her, ‘Look, you have been concerned for us with all this care. What <char style="it">can</char> <char style="it">I</char> do for you? Do you want me to speak on your behalf to the king or to the commander of the army?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">She answered, “I dwell among my own people.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So he said, “What then <char style="it">is</char> to be done for her?”</para>
	<para style="p">And Gehazi answered, “Actually, she has no son, and her husband is old.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />So he said, “Call her.” When he had called her, she stood in the doorway. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then he said, “About this time next year you shall embrace a son.”</para>
	<para style="p">And she said, “No, my lord. Man of God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:28</char></note>do not lie to your maidservant!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />But the woman conceived, and bore a son when the appointed time had come, of which Elisha had told her.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And the child grew. Now it happened one day that he went out to his father, to the reapers. <verse number="19" style="v" />And he said to his father, “My head, my head!”</para>
	<para style="p">So he said to a servant, “Carry him to his mother.” <verse number="20" style="v" />When he had taken him and brought him to his mother, he sat on her knees till noon, and <char style="it">then</char> died. <verse number="21" style="v" />And she went up and laid him on the bed of the man of God, shut <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">door</char> upon him, and went out. <verse number="22" style="v" />Then she called to her husband, and said, “Please send me one of the young men and one of the donkeys, that I may run to the man of God and come back.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />So he said, “Why are you going to him today? <char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> neither the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:10; 28:11; 1 Chr. 23:31</char></note>New Moon nor the Sabbath.”</para>
	<para style="p">And she said, “<char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> well.” <verse number="24" style="v" />Then she saddled a donkey, and said to her servant, “Drive, and go forward; do not slacken the pace for me unless I tell you.” <verse number="25" style="v" />And so she departed, and went to the man of God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:25</char></note>at Mount Carmel.</para>
	<para style="p">So it was, when the man of God saw her afar off, that he said to his servant Gehazi, “Look, the Shunammite woman! <verse number="26" style="v" />Please run now to meet her, and say to her, ‘<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> well with you? <char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> well with your husband? <char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> well with the child?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">And she answered, “<char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> well.” <verse number="27" style="v" />Now when she came to the man of God at the hill, she caught him by the feet, but Gehazi came near to push her away. But the man of God said, “Let her alone; for her soul <char style="it">is</char> in deep distress, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has hidden <char style="it">it</char> from me, and has not told me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />So she said, “Did I ask a son of my lord? <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:16</char></note>Did I not say, ‘Do not deceive me’?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Then he said to Gehazi, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:46; 2 Kin. 9:1</char></note>“Get yourself ready, and take my staff in your hand, and be on your way. If you meet anyone, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 10:4</char></note>do not greet him; and if anyone greets you, do not answer him; but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 7:19; 14:16; 2 Kin. 2:8, 14; Acts 19:12</char></note>lay my staff on the face of the child.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />And the mother of the child said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:2</char></note>“<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, and <char style="it">as</char> your soul lives, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:4</char></note>I will not leave you.” So he arose and followed her. <verse number="31" style="v" />Now Gehazi went on ahead of them, and laid the staff on the face of the child; but <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> neither voice nor hearing. Therefore he went back to meet him, and told him, saying, “The child has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">John 11:11</char></note>not awakened.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />When Elisha came into the house, there was the child, lying dead on his bed. <verse number="33" style="v" />He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:4; (Matt. 6:6); Luke 8:51</char></note>went in therefore, shut the door behind the two of them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 17:20</char></note>and prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="34" style="v" />And he went up and lay on the child, and put his mouth on his mouth, his eyes on his eyes, and his hands on his hands; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 17:21–23; Acts 20:10</char></note>he stretched himself out on the child, and the flesh of the child became warm. <verse number="35" style="v" />He returned and walked back and forth in the house, and again went up <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 17:21</char></note>and stretched himself out on him; then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:1, 5</char></note>the child sneezed seven times, and the child opened his eyes. <verse number="36" style="v" />And he called Gehazi and said, “Call this Shunammite woman.” So he called her. And when she came in to him, he said, “Pick up your son.” <verse number="37" style="v" />So she went in, fell at his feet, and bowed to the ground; then she <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 17:23; (Heb. 11:35)</char></note>picked up her son and went out.</para>
	<para style="s">Elisha Purifies the Pot of Stew</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />And Elisha returned to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:1</char></note>Gilgal, and <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:1</char></note>famine in the land. Now the sons of the prophets <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 10:39; Acts 22:3</char></note>sitting before him; and he said to his servant, “Put on the large pot, and boil stew for the sons of the prophets.” <verse number="39" style="v" />So one went out into the field to gather herbs, and found a wild vine, and gathered from it a lapful of wild gourds, and came and sliced <char style="it">them</char> into the pot of stew, though they did not know <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">were.</char> <verse number="40" style="v" />Then they served it to the men to eat. Now it happened, as they were eating the stew, that they cried out and said, “Man of God, <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 10:17</char></note>death in the pot!” And they could not eat <char style="it">it.</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />So he said, “Then bring some flour.” And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:25; 2 Kin. 2:21</char></note>he put <char style="it">it</char> into the pot, and said, “Serve <char style="it">it</char> to the people, that they may eat.” And there was nothing harmful in the pot.</para>
	<para style="s">Elisha Feeds One Hundred Men</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" />Then a man came from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:4</char></note>Baal Shalisha, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:7; (1 Cor. 9:11; Gal. 6:6)</char></note>and brought the man of God bread of the firstfruits, twenty loaves of barley bread, and newly ripened grain in his knapsack. And he said, “Give <char style="it">it</char> to the people, that they may eat.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" />But his servant said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 9:13; John 6:9</char></note>“What? Shall I set this before one hundred men?”</para>
	<para style="p">He said again, “Give it to the people, that they may eat; for thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 9:17; John 6:11</char></note>‘They shall eat and have <char style="it">some</char> left over.’ ” <verse number="44" style="v" />So he set <char style="it">it</char> before them; and they ate <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 14:20; 15:37; John 6:13</char></note>and had <char style="it">some</char> left over, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Naaman’s Leprosy Healed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 4:27</char></note>Naaman, commander of the army of the king of Syria, was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 11:3</char></note>a great and honorable man in the eyes of his master, because by him the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had given victory to Syria. He was also a mighty man of valor, <char style="it">but</char> a leper. <verse number="2" style="v" />And the Syrians had gone out <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:23; 13:20</char></note>on raids, and had brought back captive a young girl from the land of Israel. She waited on Naaman’s wife. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then she said to her mistress, “If only my master <char style="it">were</char> with the prophet who <char style="it">is</char> in Samaria! For he would heal him of his leprosy.” <verse number="4" style="v" />And <char style="it">Naaman</char> went in and told his master, saying, “Thus and thus said the girl who <char style="it">is</char> from the land of Israel.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then the king of Syria said, “Go now, and I will send a letter to the king of Israel.”</para>
	<para style="p">So he departed and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:8; 2 Kin. 8:8, 9</char></note>took with him ten talents of silver, six thousand <char style="it">shekels</char> of gold, and ten changes of clothing. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then he brought the letter to the king of Israel, which said,</para>
	<para style="q1">Now be advised, when this letter comes to you, that I have sent Naaman my servant to you, that you may heal him of his leprosy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And it happened, when the king of Israel read the letter, that he tore his clothes and said, “<char style="it">Am</char> I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Gen. 30:2; Deut. 32:39; 1 Sam. 2:6)</char></note>God, to kill and make alive, that this man sends a man to me to heal him of his leprosy? Therefore please consider, and see how he seeks a quarrel with me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So it was, when Elisha the man of God heard that the king of Israel had torn his clothes, that he sent to the king, saying, “Why have you torn your clothes? Please let him come to me, and he shall know that there is a prophet in Israel.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then Naaman went with his horses and chariot, and he stood at the door of Elisha’s house. <verse number="10" style="v" />And Elisha sent a messenger to him, saying, “Go and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:41; John 9:7</char></note>wash in the Jordan seven times, and your flesh shall be restored to you, and <char style="it">you</char> <char style="it">shall</char> be clean.” <verse number="11" style="v" />But Naaman became furious, and went away and said, “Indeed, I said to myself, ‘He will surely come out <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">me,</char> and stand and call on the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, and wave his hand over the place, and heal the leprosy.’ <verse number="12" style="v" /><char style="it">Are</char> not the Abanah and the Pharpar, the rivers of Damascus, better than all the waters of Israel? Could I not wash in them and be clean?” So he turned and went away in a rage. <verse number="13" style="v" />And his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 28:23</char></note>servants came near and spoke to him, and said, “My father, <char style="it">if</char> the prophet had told you <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">do</char> something great, would you not have done <char style="it">it?</char> How much more then, when he says to you, ‘Wash, and be clean’?” <verse number="14" style="v" />So he went down and dipped seven times in the Jordan, according to the saying of the man of God; and his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 5:10; Job 33:25</char></note>flesh was restored like the flesh of a little child, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 4:27; 5:13</char></note>he was clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And he returned to the man of God, he and all his aides, and came and stood before him; and he said, “Indeed, now I know that <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:47; 3:29; 6:26, 27</char></note>no God in all the earth, except in Israel; now therefore, please take <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 33:11</char></note>a gift from your servant.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />But he said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:14</char></note>“<char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, before whom I stand, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 14:22, 23; 2 Kin. 5:20, 26; (Matt. 10:8); Acts 8:18, 20</char></note>I will receive nothing.” And he urged him to take <char style="it">it,</char> but he refused.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />So Naaman said, “Then, if not, please let your servant be given two mule-loads of earth; for your servant will no longer offer either burnt offering or sacrifice to other gods, but to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="18" style="v" />Yet in this thing may the <char style="sc">Lord</char> pardon your servant: when my master goes into the temple of Rimmon to worship there, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 7:2, 17</char></note>he leans on my hand, and I bow down in the temple of Rimmon—when I bow down in the temple of Rimmon, may the <char style="sc">Lord</char> please pardon your servant in this thing.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then he said to him, “Go in peace.” So he departed from him a short distance.</para>
	<para style="s">Gehazi’s Greed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:12; 8:4, 5</char></note>Gehazi, the servant of Elisha the man of God, said, “Look, my master has spared Naaman this Syrian, while not receiving from his hands what he brought; but <char style="it">as</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, I will run after him and take something from him.” <verse number="21" style="v" />So Gehazi pursued Naaman. When Naaman saw <char style="it">him</char> running after him, he got down from the chariot to meet him, and said, “<char style="it">Is</char> all well?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And he said, “All <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:26</char></note>well. My master has sent me, saying, ‘Indeed, just now two young men of the sons of the prophets have come to me from the mountains of Ephraim. Please give them a talent of silver and two changes of garments.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />So Naaman said, “Please, take two talents.” And he urged him, and bound two talents of silver in two bags, with two changes of garments, and handed <char style="it">them</char> to two of his servants; and they carried <char style="it">them</char> on ahead of him. <verse number="24" style="v" />When he came to the citadel, he took <char style="it">them</char> from their hand, and stored <char style="it">them</char> away in the house; then he let the men go, and they departed. <verse number="25" style="v" />Now he went in and stood before his master. Elisha said to him, “Where <char style="it">did</char> <char style="it">you</char> <char style="it">go,</char> Gehazi?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “Your servant did not go anywhere.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then he said to him, “Did not my heart go <char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">you</char> when the man turned back from his chariot to meet you? <char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Eccl. 3:1, 6)</char></note>time to receive money and to receive clothing, olive groves and vineyards, sheep and oxen, male and female servants? <verse number="27" style="v" />Therefore the leprosy of Naaman <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Tim. 6:10)</char></note>shall cling to you and your descendants forever.” And he went out from his presence <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 4:6; Num. 12:10; 2 Kin. 15:5</char></note>leprous, <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">white</char> as snow.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Floating Ax Head</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:38</char></note>the sons of the prophets said to Elisha, “See now, the place where we dwell with you is too small for us. <verse number="2" style="v" />Please, let us go to the Jordan, and let every man take a beam from there, and let us make there a place where we may dwell.”</para>
	<para style="p">So he answered, “Go.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then one said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 5:23</char></note>“Please consent to go with your servants.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he answered, “I will go.” <verse number="4" style="v" />So he went with them. And when they came to the Jordan, they cut down trees. <verse number="5" style="v" />But as one was cutting down a tree, the iron <char style="it">ax</char> <char style="it">head</char> fell into the water; and he cried out and said, “Alas, master! For it was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 22:14)</char></note>borrowed.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So the man of God said, “Where did it fall?” And he showed him the place. So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:25; 2 Kin. 2:21; 4:41</char></note>he cut off a stick, and threw <char style="it">it</char> in there; and he made the iron float. <verse number="7" style="v" />Therefore he said, “Pick <char style="it">it</char> up for yourself.” So he reached out his hand and took it.</para>
	<para style="s">The Blinded Syrians Captured</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Now the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:28, 29</char></note>king of Syria was making war against Israel; and he consulted with his servants, saying, “My camp <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> in such and such a place.” <verse number="9" style="v" />And the man of God sent to the king of Israel, saying, “Beware that you do not pass this place, for the Syrians are coming down there.” <verse number="10" style="v" />Then the king of Israel sent <char style="it">someone</char> to the place of which the man of God had told him. Thus he warned him, and he was watchful there, not just once or twice.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Therefore the heart of the king of Syria was greatly troubled by this thing; and he called his servants and said to them, “Will you not show me which of us <char style="it">is</char> for the king of Israel?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And one of his servants said, “None, my lord, O king; but Elisha, the prophet who <char style="it">is</char> in Israel, tells the king of Israel the words that you speak in your bedroom.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So he said, “Go and see where he <char style="it">is,</char> that I may send and get him.”</para>
	<para style="p">And it was told him, saying, “Surely <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">is</char> in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 37:17</char></note>Dothan.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Therefore he sent horses and chariots and a great army there, and they came by night and surrounded the city. <verse number="15" style="v" />And when the servant of the man of God arose early and went out, there was an army, surrounding the city with horses and chariots. And his servant said to him, “Alas, my master! What shall we do?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So he answered, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:13; 1 Kin. 17:13</char></note>“Do not fear, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:7; Ps. 55:18; (Rom. 8:31)</char></note>those who <char style="it">are</char> with us <char style="it">are</char> more than those who <char style="it">are</char> with them.” <verse number="17" style="v" />And Elisha prayed, and said, “<char style="sc">Lord</char>, I pray, open his eyes that he may see.” Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:31; Luke 24:31</char></note>opened the eyes of the young man, and he saw. And behold, the mountain <char style="it">was</char> full of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:11; Ps. 34:7; 68:17; Zech. 1:8; 6:1–7</char></note>horses and chariots of fire all around Elisha. <verse number="18" style="v" />So when <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">Syrians</char> came down to him, Elisha prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said, “Strike this people, I pray, with blindness.” And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:11; Acts 13:11</char></note>He struck them with blindness according to the word of Elisha.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Now Elisha said to them, “This <char style="it">is</char> not the way, nor <char style="it">is</char> this the city. Follow me, and I will bring you to the man whom you seek.” But he led them to Samaria.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So it was, when they had come to Samaria, that Elisha said, “<char style="sc">Lord</char>, open the eyes of these <char style="it">men,</char> that they may see.” And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> opened their eyes, and they saw; and there <char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">were,</char> inside Samaria!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Now when the king of Israel saw them, he said to Elisha, “My <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:12; 5:13; 8:9</char></note>father, shall I kill <char style="it">them?</char> Shall I kill <char style="it">them?</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />But he answered, “You shall not kill <char style="it">them.</char> Would you kill those whom you have taken captive with your sword and your bow? <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rom. 12:20)</char></note>Set food and water before them, that they may eat and drink and go to their master.” <verse number="23" style="v" />Then he prepared a great feast for them; and after they ate and drank, he sent them away and they went to their master. So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 5:2; 6:8, 9</char></note>the bands of Syrian <char style="it">raiders</char> came no more into the land of Israel.</para>
	<para style="s">Syria Besieges Samaria in Famine</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />And it happened after this that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:1</char></note>Ben-Hadad king of Syria gathered all his army, and went up and besieged Samaria. <verse number="25" style="v" />And there was a great <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:38; 8:1</char></note>famine in Samaria; and indeed they besieged it until a donkey’s head was <char style="it">sold</char> for eighty <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver, and one-fourth of a kab of dove droppings for five <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then, as the king of Israel was passing by on the wall, a woman cried out to him, saying, “Help, my lord, O king!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />And he said, “If the <char style="sc">Lord</char> does not help you, where can I find help for you? From the threshing floor or from the winepress?” <verse number="28" style="v" />Then the king said to her, “What is troubling you?”</para>
	<para style="p">And she answered, “This woman said to me, ‘Give your son, that we may eat him today, and we will eat my son tomorrow.’ <verse number="29" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:27–29; Deut. 28:52–57; Lam. 4:10</char></note>we boiled my son, and ate him. And I said to her on the next day, ‘Give your son, that we may eat him’; but she has hidden her son.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Now it happened, when the king heard the words of the woman, that he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:27</char></note>tore his clothes; and as he passed by on the wall, the people looked, and there underneath <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">had</char> sackcloth on his body. <verse number="31" style="v" />Then he said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ruth 1:17; 1 Kin. 19:2</char></note>“God do so to me and more also, if the head of Elisha the son of Shaphat remains on him today!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />But Elisha was sitting in his house, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 8:1; 14:1; 20:1</char></note>the elders were sitting with him. And <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">king</char> sent a man ahead of him, but before the messenger came to him, he said to the elders, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 13:32</char></note>“Do you see how this son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:4, 13, 14; 21:10, 13</char></note>a murderer has sent someone to take away my head? Look, when the messenger comes, shut the door, and hold him fast at the door. <char style="it">Is</char> not the sound of his master’s feet behind him?” <verse number="33" style="v" />And while he was still talking with them, there was the messenger, coming down to him; and then <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">king</char> said, “Surely this calamity <char style="it">is</char> from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 2:9</char></note>why should I wait for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> any longer?”</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Elisha said, “Hear the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 7:18, 19</char></note>‘Tomorrow about this time a seah of fine flour <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> <char style="it">sold</char> for a shekel, and two seahs of barley for a shekel, at the gate of Samaria.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 5:18; 7:17, 19, 20</char></note>So an officer on whose hand the king leaned answered the man of God and said, “Look, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 7:11; Mal. 3:10</char></note><char style="it">if</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> would make windows in heaven, could this thing be?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “In fact, you shall see <char style="it">it</char> with your eyes, but you shall not eat of it.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Syrians Flee</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Now there were four leprous men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 13:45, 46; Num. 5:2–4; 12:10–14)</char></note>at the entrance of the gate; and they said to one another, “Why are we sitting here until we die? <verse number="4" style="v" />If we say, ‘We will enter the city,’ the famine <char style="it">is</char> in the city, and we shall die there. And if we sit here, we die also. Now therefore, come, let us surrender to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:24</char></note>army of the Syrians. If they keep us alive, we shall live; and if they kill us, we shall only die.” <verse number="5" style="v" />And they rose at twilight to go to the camp of the Syrians; and when they had come to the outskirts of the Syrian camp, to their surprise no one <char style="it">was</char> there. <verse number="6" style="v" />For the Lord had caused the army of the Syrians <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:24; 2 Kin. 19:7; Job 15:21</char></note>to hear the noise of chariots and the noise of horses—the noise of a great army; so they said to one another, “Look, the king of Israel has hired against us <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:29</char></note>the kings of the Hittites and the kings of the Egyptians to attack us!” <verse number="7" style="v" />Therefore they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 48:4–6; (Prov. 28:1)</char></note>arose and fled at twilight, and left the camp intact—their tents, their horses, and their donkeys—and they fled for their lives. <verse number="8" style="v" />And when these lepers came to the outskirts of the camp, they went into one tent and ate and drank, and carried from it silver and gold and clothing, and went and hid <char style="it">them;</char> then they came back and entered another tent, and carried <char style="it">some</char> from there <char style="it">also,</char> and went and hid <char style="it">it.</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then they said to one another, “We are not doing right. This day <char style="it">is</char> a day of good news, and we remain silent. If we wait until morning light, some punishment will come upon us. Now therefore, come, let us go and tell the king’s household.” <verse number="10" style="v" />So they went and called to the gatekeepers of the city, and told them, saying, “We went to the Syrian camp, and surprisingly no one <char style="it">was</char> there, not a human sound—only horses and donkeys tied, and the tents intact.” <verse number="11" style="v" />And the gatekeepers called out, and they told <char style="it">it</char> to the king’s household inside.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So the king arose in the night and said to his servants, “Let me now tell you what the Syrians have done to us. They know that we <char style="it">are</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:24–29</char></note>hungry; therefore they have gone out of the camp to hide themselves in the field, saying, ‘When they come out of the city, we shall catch them alive, and get into the city.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And one of his servants answered and said, “Please, let several <char style="it">men</char> take five of the remaining horses which are left in the city. Look, they <char style="it">may</char> <char style="it">either</char> <char style="it">become</char> like all the multitude of Israel that are left in it; or indeed, <char style="it">I</char> <char style="it">say,</char> they <char style="it">may</char> <char style="it">become</char> like all the multitude of Israel left from those who are consumed; so let us send them and see.” <verse number="14" style="v" />Therefore they took two chariots with horses; and the king sent them in the direction of the Syrian army, saying, “Go and see.” <verse number="15" style="v" />And they went after them to the Jordan; and indeed all the road <char style="it">was</char> full of garments and weapons which the Syrians had thrown away in their haste. So the messengers returned and told the king. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then the people went out and plundered the tents of the Syrians. So a seah of fine flour was <char style="it">sold</char> for a shekel, and two seahs of barley for a shekel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 7:1</char></note>according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Now the king had appointed the officer on whose hand he leaned to have charge of the gate. But the people trampled him in the gate, and he died, just <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:32; 7:2</char></note>as the man of God had said, who spoke when the king came down to him. <verse number="18" style="v" />So it happened just as the man of God had spoken to the king, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 7:1</char></note>“Two seahs of barley for a shekel, and a seah of fine flour for a shekel, shall be <char style="it">sold</char> tomorrow about this time in the gate of Samaria.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then that officer had answered the man of God, and said, “Now look, <char style="it">if</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> would make windows in heaven, could such a thing be?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he had said, “In fact, you shall see <char style="it">it</char> with your eyes, but you shall not eat of it.” <verse number="20" style="v" />And so it happened to him, for the people trampled him in the gate, and he died.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The King Restores the Shunammite’s Land</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Elisha spoke to the woman <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:18, 31–35</char></note>whose son he had restored to life, saying, “Arise and go, you and your household, and stay wherever you can; for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 105:16; Hag. 1:11</char></note>has called for a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 21:1; 1 Kin. 18:2; 2 Kin. 4:38; 6:25</char></note>famine, and furthermore, it will come upon the land for seven years.” <verse number="2" style="v" />So the woman arose and did according to the saying of the man of God, and she went with her household and dwelt in the land of the Philistines seven years.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />It came to pass, at the end of seven years, that the woman returned from the land of the Philistines; and she went to make an appeal to the king for her house and for her land. <verse number="4" style="v" />Then the king talked with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:12; 5:20–27</char></note>Gehazi, the servant of the man of God, saying, “Tell me, please, all the great things Elisha has done.” <verse number="5" style="v" />Now it happened, as he was telling the king how he had restored the dead to life, that there was the woman whose son he had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:35</char></note>restored to life, appealing to the king for her house and for her land. And Gehazi said, “My lord, O king, this <char style="it">is</char> the woman, and this <char style="it">is</char> her son whom Elisha restored to life.” <verse number="6" style="v" />And when the king asked the woman, she told him.</para>
	<para style="p">So the king appointed a certain officer for her, saying, “Restore all that <char style="it">was</char> hers, and all the proceeds of the field from the day that she left the land until now.”</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Ben-Hadad</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then Elisha went to Damascus, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:24</char></note>Ben-Hadad king of Syria was sick; and it was told him, saying, “The man of God has come here.” <verse number="8" style="v" />And the king said to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:15</char></note>Hazael, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:7; 1 Kin. 14:3; 2 Kin. 5:5</char></note>“Take a present in your hand, and go to meet the man of God, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 1:2</char></note>inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by him, saying, ‘Shall I recover from this disease?’ ” <verse number="9" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:15</char></note>Hazael went to meet him and took a present with him, of every good thing of Damascus, forty camel-loads; and he came and stood before him, and said, “Your son Ben-Hadad king of Syria has sent me to you, saying, ‘Shall I recover from this disease?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And Elisha said to him, “Go, say to him, ‘You shall certainly recover.’ However the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has shown me that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:15</char></note>he will really die.” <verse number="11" style="v" />Then he set his countenance in a stare until he was ashamed; and the man of God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 19:41</char></note>wept. <verse number="12" style="v" />And Hazael said, “Why is my lord weeping?”</para>
	<para style="p">He answered, “Because I know <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:32; 12:17; 13:3, 7; Amos 1:3, 4</char></note>the evil that you will do to the children of Israel: Their strongholds you will set on fire, and their young men you will kill with the sword; and you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:16; Hos. 13:16; Amos 1:13; Nah. 3:10</char></note>will dash their children, and rip open their women with child.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So Hazael said, “But what <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 17:43; 2 Sam. 9:8</char></note><char style="it">is</char> your servant—a dog, that he should do this gross thing?”</para>
	<para style="p">And Elisha answered, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:15</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has shown me that you <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">become</char> king over Syria.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then he departed from Elisha, and came to his master, who said to him, “What did Elisha say to you?” And he answered, “He told me you would surely recover.” <verse number="15" style="v" />But it happened on the next day that he took a thick cloth and dipped <char style="it">it</char> in water, and spread <char style="it">it</char> over his face so that he died; and Hazael reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Jehoram Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 1:17; 3:1</char></note>in the fifth year of Joram the son of Ahab, king of Israel, Jehoshaphat <char style="it">having</char> <char style="it">been</char> king of Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:3</char></note>Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat began to reign as king of Judah. <verse number="17" style="v" />He was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 21:5–10</char></note>thirty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. <verse number="18" style="v" />And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, just as the house of Ahab had done, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:26, 27</char></note>the daughter of Ahab was his wife; and he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="19" style="v" />Yet the <char style="sc">Lord</char> would not destroy Judah, for the sake of His servant David, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:13; 1 Kin. 11:36; 15:4; 2 Chr. 21:7</char></note>as He promised him to give a lamp to him <char style="it">and</char> his sons forever.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />In his days <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 27:40; 2 Chr. 21:8–10</char></note>Edom revolted against Judah’s authority, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:47</char></note>and made a king over themselves. <verse number="21" style="v" />So Joram went to Zair, and all his chariots with him. Then he rose by night and attacked the Edomites who had surrounded him and the captains of the chariots; and the troops fled to their tents. <verse number="22" style="v" />Thus Edom has been in revolt against Judah’s authority to this day. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:13; 2 Kin. 19:8; 2 Chr. 21:10</char></note>And Libnah revolted at that time.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Joram, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="24" style="v" />So Joram rested with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the City of David. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:1, 7</char></note>Ahaziah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Ahaziah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />In the twelfth year of Joram the son of Ahab, king of Israel, Ahaziah the son of Jehoram, king of Judah, began to reign. <verse number="26" style="v" />Ahaziah <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:2</char></note>twenty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Athaliah the granddaughter of Omri, king of Israel. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:3, 4</char></note>And he walked in the way of the house of Ahab, and did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, like the house of Ahab, for he <char style="it">was</char> the son-in-law of the house of Ahab.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Now he went <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:5</char></note>with Joram the son of Ahab to war against Hazael king of Syria at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:3, 29</char></note>Ramoth Gilead; and the Syrians wounded Joram. <verse number="29" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:15</char></note>King Joram went back to Jezreel to recover from the wounds which the Syrians had inflicted on him at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:16; 2 Chr. 22:6, 7</char></note>And Ahaziah the son of Jehoram, king of Judah, went down to see Joram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was sick.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jehu Anointed King of Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And Elisha the prophet called one of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:35</char></note>the sons of the prophets, and said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:29; Jer. 1:17</char></note>“Get yourself ready, take this flask of oil in your hand, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:28, 29</char></note>and go to Ramoth Gilead. <verse number="2" style="v" />Now when you arrive at that place, look there for Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat, the son of Nimshi, and go in and make him rise up from among <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:5, 11</char></note>his associates, and take him to an inner room. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:16</char></note>take the flask of oil, and pour <char style="it">it</char> on his head, and say, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: “I have anointed you king over Israel.” ’ Then open the door and flee, and do not delay.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So the young man, the servant of the prophet, went to Ramoth Gilead. <verse number="5" style="v" />And when he arrived, there <char style="it">were</char> the captains of the army sitting; and he said, “I have a message for you, Commander.”</para>
	<para style="p">Jehu said, “For which <char style="it">one</char> of us?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “For you, Commander.” <verse number="6" style="v" />Then he arose and went into the house. And he poured the oil on his head, and said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:7, 8; 1 Kin. 19:16; 2 Kin. 9:3; 2 Chr. 22:7</char></note>“Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: ‘I have anointed you king over the people of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, over Israel. <verse number="7" style="v" />You shall strike down the house of Ahab your master, that I may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 32:35, 41)</char></note>avenge the blood of My servants the prophets, and the blood of all the servants of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:4; 21:15</char></note>at the hand of Jezebel. <verse number="8" style="v" />For the whole house of Ahab shall perish; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:10; 21:21; 2 Kin. 10:17</char></note>I will cut off from Ahab all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:22</char></note>the males in Israel, both <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:36; 2 Kin. 14:26</char></note>bond and free. <verse number="9" style="v" />So I will make the house of Ahab like the house of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:10; 15:29; 21:22</char></note>Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:3, 11</char></note>Baasha the son of Ahijah. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:23; 2 Kin. 9:35, 36</char></note>The dogs shall eat Jezebel on the plot <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">ground</char> at Jezreel, and <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> none to bury <char style="it">her.</char>’ ” And he opened the door and fled.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then Jehu came out to the servants of his master, and <char style="it">one</char> said to him, “<char style="it">Is</char> all well? Why did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 29:26; Hos. 9:7; Mark 3:21; John 10:20; Acts 26:24; (1 Cor. 4:10)</char></note>this madman come to you?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said to them, “You know the man and his babble.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And they said, “A lie! Tell us now.”</para>
	<para style="p">So he said, “Thus and thus he spoke to me, saying, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: “I have anointed you king over Israel.” ’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then each man hastened <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 21:7, 8; Mark 11:7, 8</char></note>to take his garment and put <char style="it">it</char> under him on the top of the steps; and they blew trumpets, saying, “Jehu is king!”</para>
	<para style="s">Joram of Israel Killed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat, the son of Nimshi, conspired against <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:28</char></note>Joram. (Now Joram had been defending Ramoth Gilead, he and all Israel, against Hazael king of Syria. <verse number="15" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:29</char></note>King Joram had returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds which the Syrians had inflicted on him when he fought with Hazael king of Syria.) And Jehu said, “If you are so minded, let no one leave <char style="it">or</char> escape from the city to go and tell <char style="it">it</char> in Jezreel.” <verse number="16" style="v" />So Jehu rode in a chariot and went to Jezreel, for Joram was laid up there; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:29</char></note>and Ahaziah king of Judah had come down to see Joram.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Now a watchman stood on the tower in Jezreel, and he saw the company of Jehu as he came, and said, “I see a company of men.”</para>
	<para style="p">And Joram said, “Get a horseman and send him to meet them, and let him say, ‘<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> peace?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />So the horseman went to meet him, and said, “Thus says the king: ‘<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> peace?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">And Jehu said, “What have you to do with peace? Turn around and follow me.”</para>
	<para style="p">So the watchman reported, saying, “The messenger went to them, but is not coming back.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then he sent out a second horseman who came to them, and said, “Thus says the king: ‘<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> peace?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">And Jehu answered, “What have you to do with peace? Turn around and follow me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So the watchman reported, saying, “He went up to them and is not coming back; and the driving <char style="it">is</char> like the driving of Jehu the son of Nimshi, for he drives furiously!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then Joram said, “Make ready.” And his chariot was made ready. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:17; 2 Chr. 22:7</char></note>Joram king of Israel and Ahaziah king of Judah went out, each in his chariot; and they went out to meet Jehu, and met him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:1–14</char></note>on the property of Naboth the Jezreelite.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Now it happened, when Joram saw Jehu, that he said, “<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> peace, Jehu?”</para>
	<para style="p">So he answered, “What peace, as long as the harlotries of your mother Jezebel and her witchcraft <char style="it">are</char> <char style="it">so</char> many?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then Joram turned around and fled, and said to Ahaziah, “Treachery, Ahaziah!” <verse number="24" style="v" />Now Jehu drew his bow with full strength and shot Jehoram between his arms; and the arrow came out at his heart, and he sank down in his chariot. <verse number="25" style="v" />Then <char style="it">Jehu</char> said to Bidkar his captain, “Pick <char style="it">him</char> up, <char style="it">and</char> throw him into the tract of the field of Naboth the Jezreelite; for remember, when you and I were riding together behind Ahab his father, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:19, 24–29</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> laid this <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 13:1</char></note>burden upon him: <verse number="26" style="v" />‘Surely I saw yesterday the blood of Naboth and the blood of his sons,’ says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:13, 19</char></note>‘and I will repay you in this plot,’ says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Now therefore, take <char style="it">and</char> throw him on the plot <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">ground,</char> according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="s">Ahaziah of Judah Killed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />But when Ahaziah king of Judah saw <char style="it">this,</char> he fled by the road to Beth Haggan. So Jehu pursued him, and said, “Shoot him also in the chariot.” <char style="it">And</char> <char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">shot</char> <char style="it">him</char> at the Ascent of Gur, which is by Ibleam. Then he fled to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:7, 9</char></note>Megiddo, and died there. <verse number="28" style="v" />And his servants carried him in the chariot to Jerusalem, and buried him in his tomb with his fathers in the City of David. <verse number="29" style="v" />In the eleventh year of Joram the son of Ahab, Ahaziah had become king over Judah.</para>
	<para style="s">Jezebel’s Violent Death</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Now when Jehu had come to Jezreel, Jezebel heard <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">it;</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 4:30); Ezek. 23:40</char></note>and she put paint on her eyes and adorned her head, and looked through a window. <verse number="31" style="v" />Then, as Jehu entered at the gate, she said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:9–20; 2 Kin. 9:18–22</char></note>“<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> peace, Zimri, murderer of your master?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />And he looked up at the window, and said, “Who <char style="it">is</char> on my side? Who?” So two <char style="it">or</char> three eunuchs looked out at him. <verse number="33" style="v" />Then he said, “Throw her down.” So they threw her down, and <char style="it">some</char> of her blood spattered on the wall and on the horses; and he trampled her underfoot. <verse number="34" style="v" />And when he had gone in, he ate and drank. Then he said, “Go now, see to this accursed <char style="it">woman,</char> and bury her, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 22:28); 1 Kin. 16:31</char></note>she was a king’s daughter.” <verse number="35" style="v" />So they went to bury her, but they found no more of her than the skull and the feet and the palms of <char style="it">her</char> hands. <verse number="36" style="v" />Therefore they came back and told him. And he said, “This <char style="it">is</char> the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which He spoke by His servant Elijah the Tishbite, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:23</char></note>‘On the plot <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">ground</char> at Jezreel dogs shall eat the flesh of Jezebel; <verse number="37" style="v" />and the corpse of Jezebel shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:10</char></note>as refuse on the surface of the field, in the plot at Jezreel, so that they shall not say, “Here <char style="it">lies</char> Jezebel.” ’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Ahab’s Seventy Sons Killed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now Ahab had seventy sons in Samaria. And Jehu wrote and sent letters to Samaria, to the rulers of Jezreel, to the elders, and to those who reared Ahab’s <char style="it">sons,</char> saying:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="2" style="v" />Now as soon as this letter comes to you, since your master’s sons <char style="it">are</char> with you, and you have chariots and horses, a fortified city also, and weapons, <verse number="3" style="v" />choose the best qualified of your master’s sons, set <char style="it">him</char> on his father’s throne, and fight for your master’s house.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />But they were exceedingly afraid, and said, “Look, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:24, 27</char></note>two kings could not stand up to him; how then can we stand?” <verse number="5" style="v" />And he who <char style="it">was</char> in charge of the house, and he who <char style="it">was</char> in charge of the city, the elders also, and those who reared <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">sons,</char> sent to Jehu, saying, “We <char style="it">are</char> your servants, we will do all you tell us; but we will not make anyone king. Do <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">is</char> good in your sight.” <verse number="6" style="v" />Then he wrote a second letter to them, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1">If you <char style="it">are</char> for me and will obey my voice, take the heads of the men, your master’s sons, and come to me at Jezreel by this time tomorrow.</para>
	<para style="p">Now the king’s sons, seventy persons, <char style="it">were</char> with the great men of the city, <char style="it">who</char> were rearing them. <verse number="7" style="v" />So it was, when the letter came to them, that they took the king’s sons and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:5; 1 Kin. 21:21; 2 Kin. 11:1</char></note>slaughtered seventy persons, put their heads in baskets and sent <char style="it">them</char> to him at Jezreel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then a messenger came and told him, saying, “They have brought the heads of the king’s sons.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said, “Lay them in two heaps at the entrance of the gate until morning.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So it was, in the morning, that he went out and stood, and said to all the people, “You <char style="it">are</char> righteous. Indeed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:14–24</char></note>I conspired against my master and killed him; but who killed all these? <verse number="10" style="v" />Know now that nothing shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 3:19; 1 Kin. 8:56; Jer. 44:28</char></note>fall to the earth of the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke concerning the house of Ahab; for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has done what He spoke <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:17–24, 29</char></note>by His servant Elijah.” <verse number="11" style="v" />So Jehu killed all who remained of the house of Ahab in Jezreel, and all his great men and his close acquaintances and his priests, until he left him none remaining.</para>
	<para style="s">Ahaziah’s Forty-two Brothers Killed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And he arose and departed and went to Samaria. On the way, at Beth Eked of the Shepherds, <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:8</char></note>Jehu met with the brothers of Ahaziah king of Judah, and said, “Who <char style="it">are</char> you?”</para>
	<para style="p">So they answered, “We <char style="it">are</char> the brothers of Ahaziah; we have come down to greet the sons of the king and the sons of the queen mother.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And he said, “Take them alive!” So they took them alive, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:8</char></note>killed them at the well of Beth Eked, forty-two men; and he left none of them.</para>
	<para style="s">The Rest of Ahab’s Family Killed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Now when he departed from there, he met <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 35:6</char></note>Jehonadab the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 2:55</char></note>Rechab, <char style="it">coming</char> to meet him; and he greeted him and said to him, “Is your heart right, as my heart <char style="it">is</char> toward your heart?”</para>
	<para style="p">And Jehonadab answered, “It is.”</para>
	<para style="p"><char style="it">Jehu</char> <char style="it">said,</char> “If it is, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 10:19; Ezek. 17:18</char></note>give <char style="it">me</char> your hand.” So he gave <char style="it">him</char> his hand, and he took him up to him into the chariot. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then he said, “Come with me, and see my <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:10</char></note>zeal for the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” So they had him ride in his chariot. <verse number="17" style="v" />And when he came to Samaria, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:8; 2 Chr. 22:8</char></note>he killed all who remained to Ahab in Samaria, till he had destroyed them, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:21, 29</char></note>which He spoke to Elijah.</para>
	<para style="s">Worshipers of Baal Killed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then Jehu gathered all the people together, and said to them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:31, 32</char></note>“Ahab served Baal a little, Jehu will serve him much. <verse number="19" style="v" />Now therefore, call to me all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:19; 22:6</char></note>prophets of Baal, all his servants, and all his priests. Let no one be missing, for I have a great sacrifice for Baal. Whoever is missing shall not live.” But Jehu acted deceptively, with the intent of destroying the worshipers of Baal. <verse number="20" style="v" />And Jehu said, “Proclaim a solemn assembly for Baal.” So they proclaimed <char style="it">it.</char> <verse number="21" style="v" />Then Jehu sent throughout all Israel; and all the worshipers of Baal came, so that there was not a man left who did not come. So they came into the temple of Baal, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:32; 2 Kin. 11:18</char></note>temple of Baal was full from one end to the other. <verse number="22" style="v" />And he said to the one in charge of the wardrobe, “Bring out vestments for all the worshipers of Baal.” So he brought out vestments for them. <verse number="23" style="v" />Then Jehu and Jehonadab the son of Rechab went into the temple of Baal, and said to the worshipers of Baal, “Search and see that no servants of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> are here with you, but only the worshipers of Baal.” <verse number="24" style="v" />So they went in to offer sacrifices and burnt offerings. Now Jehu had appointed for himself eighty men on the outside, and had said, “<char style="it">If</char> any of the men whom I have brought into your hands escapes, <char style="it">whoever</char> <char style="it">lets</char> <char style="it">him</char> <char style="it">escape, it shall be</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:39</char></note>his life for the life of the other.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Now it happened, as soon as he had made an end of offering the burnt offering, that Jehu said to the guard and to the captains, “Go in <char style="it">and</char> kill them; let no one come out!” And they killed them with the edge of the sword; then the guards and the officers threw <char style="it">them</char> out, and went into the inner room of the temple of Baal. <verse number="26" style="v" />And they brought the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 7:5, 25); 1 Kin. 14:23; 2 Kin. 3:2</char></note><char style="it">sacred</char> pillars out of the temple of Baal and burned them. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then they broke down the <char style="it">sacred</char> pillar of Baal, and tore down the temple of Baal and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 6:11; Dan. 2:5; 3:29</char></note>made it a refuse dump to this day. <verse number="28" style="v" />Thus Jehu destroyed Baal from Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />However Jehu did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin, <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">is,</char> from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28–30; 13:33, 34</char></note>the golden calves that <char style="it">were</char> at Bethel and Dan. <verse number="30" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:6, 7</char></note>said to Jehu, “Because you have done well in doing <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">is</char> right in My sight, <char style="it">and</char> have done to the house of Ahab all that <char style="it">was</char> in My heart, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:1, 10; 14:23; 15:8, 12</char></note>your sons shall sit on the throne of Israel to the fourth <char style="it">generation.</char>” <verse number="31" style="v" />But Jehu took no heed to walk in the law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel with all his heart; for he did not depart from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:16</char></note>the sins of Jeroboam, who had made Israel sin.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Jehu</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />In those days the <char style="sc">Lord</char> began to cut off <char style="it">parts</char> of Israel; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 19:17; 2 Kin. 8:12; 13:22</char></note>Hazael conquered them in all the territory of Israel <verse number="33" style="v" />from the Jordan eastward: all the land of Gilead—Gad, Reuben, and Manasseh—from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:36</char></note>Aroer, which <char style="it">is</char> by the River Arnon, including <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Amos 1:3–5</char></note>Gilead and Bashan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehu, all that he did, and all his might, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="35" style="v" />So Jehu rested with his fathers, and they buried him in Samaria. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:1</char></note>Jehoahaz his son reigned in his place. <verse number="36" style="v" />And the period that Jehu reigned over Israel in Samaria <char style="it">was</char> twenty-eight years.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Athaliah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />When <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 22:10</char></note>Athaliah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:26</char></note>the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 9:27</char></note>dead, she arose and destroyed all the royal heirs. <verse number="2" style="v" />But Jehosheba, the daughter of King Joram, sister of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:25</char></note>Ahaziah, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him away from among the king’s sons <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> being murdered; and they hid him and his nurse in the bedroom, from Athaliah, so that he was not killed. <verse number="3" style="v" />So he was hidden with her in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for six years, while Athaliah reigned over the land.</para>
	<para style="s">Joash Crowned King of Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:2; 2 Chr. 23:1</char></note>the seventh year Jehoiada sent and brought the captains of hundreds—of the bodyguards and the escorts—and brought them into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to him. And he made a covenant with them and took an oath from them in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and showed them the king’s son. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then he commanded them, saying, “This <char style="it">is</char> what you shall do: one-third of you who come on duty <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 9:25</char></note>on the Sabbath shall be keeping watch over the king’s house, <verse number="6" style="v" />one-third <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> at the gate of Sur, and one-third at the gate behind the escorts. You shall keep the watch of the house, lest it be broken down. <verse number="7" style="v" />The two contingents of you who go off duty on the Sabbath shall keep the watch of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for the king. <verse number="8" style="v" />But you shall surround the king on all sides, every man with his weapons in his hand; and whoever comes within range, let him be put to death. You are to be with the king as he goes out and as he comes in.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:8</char></note>So the captains of the hundreds did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded. Each of them took his men who were to be on duty on the Sabbath, with those who were going off duty on the Sabbath, and came to Jehoiada the priest. <verse number="10" style="v" />And the priest gave the captains of hundreds the spears and shields which <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">belonged</char> to King David, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:7; 1 Chr. 18:7</char></note>that were in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then the escorts stood, every man with his weapons in his hand, all around the king, from the right side of the temple to the left side of the temple, by the altar and the house. <verse number="12" style="v" />And he brought out the king’s son, put the crown on him, and <char style="it">gave</char> <char style="it">him</char> the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:16; 31:18</char></note>Testimony; they made him king and anointed him, and they clapped their hands and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 10:24</char></note>“Long live the king!”</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Athaliah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:26; 2 Chr. 23:12</char></note>Now when Athaliah heard the noise of the escorts <char style="it">and</char> the people, she came to the people <char style="it">in</char> the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="14" style="v" />When she looked, there was the king standing by <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:3; 2 Chr. 34:31</char></note>a pillar according to custom; and the leaders and the trumpeters were by the king. All the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing trumpets. So Athaliah tore her clothes and cried out, “Treason! Treason!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And Jehoiada the priest commanded the captains of the hundreds, the officers of the army, and said to them, “Take her outside under guard, and slay with the sword whoever follows her.” For the priest had said, “Do not let her be killed in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” <verse number="16" style="v" />So they seized her; and she went by way of the horses’ entrance <char style="it">into</char> the king’s house, and there she was killed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:16</char></note>Then Jehoiada <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:24, 25; 2 Chr. 15:12–15</char></note>made a covenant between the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the king, and the people, that they should be the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s people, and <char style="it">also</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 5:3</char></note>between the king and the people. <verse number="18" style="v" />And all the people of the land went to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:26, 27</char></note>temple of Baal, and tore it down. They thoroughly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 12:3)</char></note>broke in pieces its altars and images, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:40; 2 Kin. 10:11</char></note>killed Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:18</char></note>the priest appointed officers over the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then he took the captains of hundreds, the bodyguards, the escorts, and all the people of the land; and they brought the king down from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and went by way of the gate of the escorts to the king’s house. Then he sat on the throne of the kings. <verse number="20" style="v" />So all the people of the land rejoiced; and the city was quiet, for they had slain Athaliah with the sword <char style="it">in</char> the king’s house. <verse number="21" style="v" />Jehoash <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:1–14</char></note>seven years old when he became king.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jehoash Repairs the Temple</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the seventh year of Jehu, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:1</char></note>Jehoash became king, and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Zibiah of Beersheba. <verse number="2" style="v" />Jehoash did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all the days in which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 11:4</char></note>Jehoiada the priest instructed him. <verse number="3" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:14; 22:43; 2 Kin. 14:4; 15:35</char></note>the high places were not taken away; the people still sacrificed and burned incense on the high places.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And Jehoash said to the priests, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:4</char></note>“All the money of the dedicated gifts that are brought into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>—each man’s <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:13–16</char></note>census money, each man’s <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:2–28</char></note>assessment money—<char style="it">and</char> all the money that a man <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 35:5; 1 Chr. 29:3–9</char></note>purposes in his heart to bring into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse number="5" style="v" />let the priests take <char style="it">it</char> themselves, each from his constituency; and let them repair the damages of the temple, wherever any dilapidation is found.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Now it was so, by the twenty-third year of King Jehoash, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:5</char></note><char style="it">that</char> the priests had not repaired the damages of the temple. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:6</char></note>So King Jehoash called Jehoiada the priest and the <char style="it">other</char> priests, and said to them, “Why have you not repaired the damages of the temple? Now therefore, do not take <char style="it">more</char> money from your constituency, but deliver it for repairing the damages of the temple.” <verse number="8" style="v" />And the priests agreed that they would neither receive <char style="it">more</char> money from the people, nor repair the damages of the temple.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then Jehoiada the priest took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:1; 24:8</char></note>a chest, bored a hole in its lid, and set it beside the altar, on the right side as one comes into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and the priests who kept the door put <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Mark 12:41; Luke 21:1</char></note>there all the money brought into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="10" style="v" />So it was, whenever they saw that <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> much money in the chest, that the king’s <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:17; 2 Kin. 19:2; 22:3, 4, 12</char></note>scribe and the high priest came up and put it in bags, and counted the money that was found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then they gave the money, which had been apportioned, into the hands of those who did the work, who had the oversight of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and they paid it out to the carpenters and builders who worked on the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse number="12" style="v" />and to masons and stonecutters, and for buying timber and hewn stone, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:5, 6</char></note>repair the damage of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and for all that was paid out to repair the temple. <verse number="13" style="v" />However <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:14</char></note>there were not made for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> basins of silver, trimmers, sprinkling-bowls, trumpets, any articles of gold or articles of silver, from the money brought into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="14" style="v" />But they gave that to the workmen, and they repaired the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with it. <verse number="15" style="v" />Moreover <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:7; (1 Cor. 4:2); 2 Cor. 8:20</char></note>they did not require an account from the men into whose hand they delivered the money to be paid to workmen, for they dealt faithfully. <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 5:15, 18)</char></note>The money from the trespass offerings and the money from the sin offerings was not brought into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 7:7; Num. 18:9)</char></note>It belonged to the priests.</para>
	<para style="s">Hazael Threatens Jerusalem</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:12</char></note>Hazael king of Syria went up and fought against Gath, and took it; then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:23</char></note>Hazael set his face to go up to Jerusalem. <verse number="18" style="v" />And Jehoash king of Judah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:18; 2 Kin. 16:8; 18:15, 16</char></note>took all the sacred things that his fathers, Jehoshaphat and Jehoram and Ahaziah, kings of Judah, had dedicated, and his own sacred things, and all the gold found in the treasuries of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in the king’s house, and sent <char style="it">them</char> to Hazael king of Syria. Then he went away from Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Joash</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Joash, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah?</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:5; 2 Chr. 24:25</char></note>his servants arose and formed a conspiracy, and killed Joash in the house of the Millo, which goes down to Silla. <verse number="21" style="v" />For Jozachar the son of Shimeath and Jehozabad the son of Shomer, his servants, struck him. So he died, and they buried him with his fathers in the City of David. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 24:27</char></note>Amaziah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jehoahaz Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the twenty-third year of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:1</char></note>Joash the son of Ahaziah, king of Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:35</char></note>Jehoahaz the son of Jehu became king over Israel in Samaria, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> seventeen years. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and followed the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:26–33</char></note>sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin. He did not depart from them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:14</char></note>the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was aroused against Israel, and He delivered them into the hand of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:12</char></note>Hazael king of Syria, and into the hand of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Amos 1:4</char></note>Ben-Hadad the son of Hazael, all <char style="it">their</char> days. <verse number="4" style="v" />So Jehoahaz <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 78:34)</char></note>pleaded with the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> listened to him; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 3:7, 9; Judg. 2:18); 2 Kin. 14:26</char></note>He saw the oppression of Israel, because the king of Syria oppressed them. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:25; 14:25, 27; Neh. 9:27</char></note>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave Israel a deliverer, so that they escaped from under the hand of the Syrians; and the children of Israel dwelt in their tents as before. <verse number="6" style="v" />Nevertheless they did not depart from the sins of the house of Jeroboam, who had made Israel sin, <char style="it">but</char> walked in them; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:33</char></note>and the wooden image also remained in Samaria. <verse number="7" style="v" />For He left of the army of Jehoahaz only fifty horsemen, ten chariots, and ten thousand foot soldiers; for the king of Syria had destroyed them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:32</char></note>and made them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Amos 1:3)</char></note>like the dust at threshing.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehoahaz, all that he did, and his might, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="9" style="v" />So Jehoahaz rested with his fathers, and they buried him in Samaria. Then Joash his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Jehoash Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />In the thirty-seventh year of Joash king of Judah, Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz became king over Israel in Samaria, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> sixteen years. <verse number="11" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He did not depart from all the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who made Israel sin, <char style="it">but</char> walked in them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:8–15</char></note>Now the rest of the acts of Joash, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:14–19, 25</char></note>all that he did, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:9; 2 Chr. 25:17–25</char></note>his might with which he fought against Amaziah king of Judah, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="13" style="v" />So Joash <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:16</char></note>rested with his fathers. Then Jeroboam sat on his throne. And Joash was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Elisha</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Elisha had become sick with the illness of which he would die. Then Joash the king of Israel came down to him, and wept over his face, and said, “O my father, my father, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:12</char></note>the chariots of Israel and their horsemen!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And Elisha said to him, “Take a bow and some arrows.” So he took himself a bow and some arrows. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then he said to the king of Israel, “Put your hand on the bow.” So he put his hand <char style="it">on</char> <char style="it">it,</char> and Elisha put his hands on the king’s hands. <verse number="17" style="v" />And he said, “Open the east window”; and he opened <char style="it">it.</char> Then Elisha said, “Shoot”; and he shot. And he said, “The arrow of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s deliverance and the arrow of deliverance from Syria; for you must strike the Syrians at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:26</char></note>Aphek till you have destroyed <char style="it">them.</char>” <verse number="18" style="v" />Then he said, “Take the arrows”; so he took <char style="it">them.</char> And he said to the king of Israel, “Strike the ground”; so he struck three times, and stopped. <verse number="19" style="v" />And the man of God was angry with him, and said, “You should have struck five or six times; then you would have struck Syria till you had destroyed <char style="it">it!</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:25</char></note>But now you will strike Syria <char style="it">only</char> three times.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Then Elisha died, and they buried him. And the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 3:5; 24:2</char></note><char style="it">raiding</char> bands from Moab invaded the land in the spring of the year. <verse number="21" style="v" />So it was, as they were burying a man, that suddenly they spied a band <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">raiders;</char> and they put the man in the tomb of Elisha; and when the man was let down and touched the bones of Elisha, he revived and stood on his feet.</para>
	<para style="s">Israel Recaptures Cities from Syria</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:12, 13</char></note>Hazael king of Syria oppressed Israel all the days of Jehoahaz. <verse number="23" style="v" />But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:27</char></note>gracious to them, had compassion on them, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 2:24, 25)</char></note>regarded them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 13:16, 17; 17:2–7; Ex. 32:13</char></note>because of His covenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and would not yet destroy them or cast them from His presence.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Now Hazael king of Syria died. Then Ben-Hadad his son reigned in his place. <verse number="25" style="v" />And Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz recaptured from the hand of Ben-Hadad, the son of Hazael, the cities which he had taken out of the hand of Jehoahaz his father by war. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:18, 19</char></note>Three times Joash defeated him and recaptured the cities of Israel.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Amaziah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:10</char></note>the second year of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:1, 2</char></note>Amaziah the son of Joash, king of Judah, became king. <verse number="2" style="v" />He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jehoaddan of Jerusalem. <verse number="3" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, yet not like his father David; he did everything <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:2</char></note>as his father Joash had done. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:3</char></note>However the high places were not taken away, and the people still sacrificed and burned incense on the high places.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Now it happened, as soon as the kingdom was established in his hand, that he executed his servants <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:20</char></note>who had murdered his father the king. <verse number="6" style="v" />But the children of the murderers he did not execute, according to what is written in the Book of the Law of Moses, in which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 24:16; (Jer. 31:30; Ezek. 18:4, 20)</char></note>“Fathers shall not be put to death for their children, nor shall children be put to death for their fathers; but a person shall be put to death for his own sin.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:5–16</char></note>He killed ten thousand Edomites in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:13; 1 Chr. 18:12; Ps. 60:title</char></note>the Valley of Salt, and took Sela by war, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:38</char></note>and called its name Joktheel to this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:17, 18</char></note>Then Amaziah sent messengers to Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz, the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, “Come, let us face one another <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">battle.</char>” <verse number="9" style="v" />And Jehoash king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:8–15</char></note>“The thistle that <char style="it">was</char> in Lebanon sent to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:33</char></note>cedar that <char style="it">was</char> in Lebanon, saying, ‘Give your daughter to my son as wife’; and a wild beast that <char style="it">was</char> in Lebanon passed by and trampled the thistle. <verse number="10" style="v" />You have indeed defeated Edom, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 8:14; 2 Chr. 32:25; (Ezek. 28:2, 5, 17; Hab. 2:4)</char></note>your heart has lifted you up. Glory <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">that,</char> and stay at home; for why should you meddle with trouble so that you fall—you and Judah with you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />But Amaziah would not heed. Therefore Jehoash king of Israel went out; so he and Amaziah king of Judah faced one another at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:38; 21:16</char></note>Beth Shemesh, which <char style="it">belongs</char> to Judah. <verse number="12" style="v" />And Judah was defeated by Israel, and every man fled to his tent. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then Jehoash king of Israel captured Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Jehoash, the son of Ahaziah, at Beth Shemesh; and he went to Jerusalem, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 8:16; 12:39</char></note>the Gate of Ephraim to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 31:38; Zech. 14:10</char></note>the Corner Gate—four hundred cubits. <verse number="14" style="v" />And he took all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:51; 2 Kin. 12:18; 16:8</char></note>the gold and silver, all the articles that were found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in the treasuries of the king’s house, and hostages, and returned to Samaria.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 13:12, 13</char></note>Now the rest of the acts of Jehoash which he did—his might, and how he fought with Amaziah king of Judah—<char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="16" style="v" />So Jehoash rested with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel. Then Jeroboam his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:25–28</char></note>Amaziah the son of Joash, king of Judah, lived fifteen years after the death of Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz, king of Israel. <verse number="18" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="19" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 25:27</char></note>they formed a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:31</char></note>Lachish; but they sent after him to Lachish and killed him there. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then they brought him on horses, and he was buried at Jerusalem with his fathers in the City of David.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And all the people of Judah took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:13; 2 Chr. 26:1</char></note>Azariah, who <char style="it">was</char> sixteen years old, and made him king instead of his father Amaziah. <verse number="22" style="v" />He built <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:26; 2 Kin. 16:6; 2 Chr. 8:17</char></note>Elath and restored it to Judah, after the king rested with his fathers.</para>
	<para style="s">Jeroboam II Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />In the fifteenth year of Amaziah the son of Joash, king of Judah, Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel, became king in Samaria, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> forty-one years. <verse number="24" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; he did not depart from all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:26–33</char></note>sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin. <verse number="25" style="v" />He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:32; 13:5, 25</char></note>restored the territory of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:21; 34:8; 1 Kin. 8:65</char></note>from the entrance of Hamath to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:17</char></note>the Sea of the Arabah, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, which He had spoken through His servant <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jon. 1:1; Matt. 12:39, 40</char></note>Jonah the son of Amittai, the prophet who <char style="it">was</char> from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:13</char></note>Gath Hepher. <verse number="26" style="v" />For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:7; 2 Kin. 13:4; Ps. 106:44</char></note>saw <char style="it">that</char> the affliction of Israel <char style="it">was</char> very bitter; and whether bond or free, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:36</char></note>there was no helper for Israel. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Kin. 13:5, 23)</char></note>And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> did not say that He would blot out the name of Israel from under heaven; but He saved them by the hand of Jeroboam the son of Joash.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jeroboam, and all that he did—his might, how he made war, and how he recaptured for Israel, from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:24</char></note>Damascus and Hamath, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:6; 1 Kin. 11:24; 2 Chr. 8:3</char></note><char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">belonged</char> to Judah—<char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="29" style="v" />So Jeroboam rested with his fathers, the kings of Israel. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:8</char></note>Zechariah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Azariah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the twenty-seventh year of Jeroboam king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:13, 30</char></note>Azariah the son of Amaziah, king of Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:21; 2 Chr. 26:1, 3, 4</char></note>became king. <verse number="2" style="v" />He was sixteen years old when he became king, and he reigned fifty-two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Jecholiah of Jerusalem. <verse number="3" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his father Amaziah had done, <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:3; 14:4; 15:35</char></note>except that the high places were not removed; the people still sacrificed and burned incense on the high places. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:19–23; Ps. 78:31</char></note>struck the king, so that he was a leper until the day of his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 6:1</char></note>death; so he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 13:46); Num. 12:14</char></note>dwelt in an isolated house. And Jotham the king’s son <char style="it">was</char> over the <char style="it">royal</char> house, judging the people of the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Azariah, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="7" style="v" />So Azariah rested with his fathers, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:23</char></note>they buried him with his fathers in the City of David. Then Jotham his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Zechariah Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />In the thirty-eighth year of Azariah king of Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:29</char></note>Zechariah the son of Jeroboam reigned over Israel in Samaria six months. <verse number="9" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:24</char></note>as his fathers had done; he did not depart from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then Shallum the son of Jabesh conspired against him, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Amos 7:9</char></note>struck and killed him in front of the people; and he reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Zechariah, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />This <char style="it">was</char> the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He spoke to Jehu, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:30</char></note>“Your sons shall sit on the throne of Israel to the fourth <char style="it">generation.</char>” And so it was.</para>
	<para style="s">Shallum Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Shallum the son of Jabesh became king in the thirty-ninth year of Uzziah king of Judah; and he reigned a full month in Samaria. <verse number="14" style="v" />For Menahem the son of Gadi went up from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:17; Song 6:4</char></note>Tirzah, came to Samaria, and struck Shallum the son of Jabesh in Samaria and killed him; and he reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Shallum, and the conspiracy which he led, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then from Tirzah, Menahem attacked <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:24</char></note>Tiphsah, all who <char style="it">were</char> there, and its territory. Because they did not surrender, therefore he attacked <char style="it">it.</char> All <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:12; Hos. 13:16</char></note>the women there who were with child he ripped open.</para>
	<para style="s">Menahem Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />In the thirty-ninth year of Azariah king of Judah, Menahem the son of Gadi became king over Israel, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> ten years in Samaria. <verse number="18" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; he did not depart all his days from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin. <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 5:26; Is. 66:19; Hos. 8:9</char></note>Pul king of Assyria came against the land; and Menahem gave Pul a thousand talents of silver, that his hand might be with him to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:5</char></note>strengthen the kingdom under his control. <verse number="20" style="v" />And Menahem <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:35</char></note>exacted the money from Israel, from all the very wealthy, from each man fifty shekels of silver, to give to the king of Assyria. So the king of Assyria turned back, and did not stay there in the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Menahem, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? <verse number="22" style="v" />So Menahem rested with his fathers. Then Pekahiah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Pekahiah Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />In the fiftieth year of Azariah king of Judah, Pekahiah the son of Menahem became king over Israel in Samaria, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> two years. <verse number="24" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; he did not depart from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin. <verse number="25" style="v" />Then Pekah the son of Remaliah, an officer of his, conspired against him and killed him in Samaria, in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:18</char></note>citadel of the king’s house, along with Argob and Arieh; and with him were fifty men of Gilead. He killed him and reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Pekahiah, and all that he did, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</para>
	<para style="s">Pekah Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />In the fifty-second year of Azariah king of Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:6; Is. 7:1</char></note>Pekah the son of Remaliah became king over Israel in Samaria, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> twenty years. <verse number="28" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; he did not depart from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who had made Israel sin. <verse number="29" style="v" />In the days of Pekah king of Israel, Tiglath-Pileser king of Assyria <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:7, 10; 1 Chr. 5:26</char></note>came and took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:20</char></note>Ijon, Abel Beth Maachah, Janoah, Kedesh, Hazor, Gilead, and Galilee, all the land of Naphtali; and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:6</char></note>carried them captive to Assyria. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then Hoshea the son of Elah led a conspiracy against Pekah the son of Remaliah, and struck and killed him; so he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:1; (Hos. 10:3, 7, 15)</char></note>reigned in his place in the twentieth year of Jotham the son of Uzziah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Pekah, and all that he did, indeed they <char style="it">are</char> written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</para>
	<para style="s">Jotham Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />In the second year of Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 27:1</char></note>Jotham the son of Uzziah, king of Judah, began to reign. <verse number="33" style="v" />He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Jerusha the daughter of Zadok. <verse number="34" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; he did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:3, 4; 2 Chr. 26:4, 5</char></note>according to all that his father Uzziah had done. <verse number="35" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:4</char></note>However the high places were not removed; the people still sacrificed and burned incense on the high places. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 23:20; 27:3</char></note>He built the Upper Gate of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="37" style="v" />In those days the <char style="sc">Lord</char> began to send <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:5–9; Is. 7:1–17</char></note>Rezin king of Syria and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:26, 27</char></note>Pekah the son of Remaliah against Judah. <verse number="38" style="v" />So Jotham rested with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the City of David his father. Then Ahaz his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Ahaz Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the seventeenth year of Pekah the son of Remaliah, Ahaz the son of Jotham, king of Judah, began to reign. <verse number="2" style="v" />Ahaz <char style="it">was</char> twenty years old when he became king, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem; and he did not do <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, as his father David <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">done.</char> <verse number="3" style="v" />But he walked in the way of the kings of Israel; indeed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:21); 2 Kin. 17:17; 2 Chr. 28:3; Ps. 106:37, 38; Is. 1:1</char></note>he made his son pass through the fire, according to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 12:31); 2 Kin. 21:2, 11</char></note>abominations of the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had cast out from before the children of Israel. <verse number="4" style="v" />And he sacrificed and burned incense on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:34, 35</char></note>high places, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 12:2); 1 Kin. 14:23</char></note>on the hills, and under every green tree.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:37; Is. 7:1, 4</char></note>Then Rezin king of Syria and Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, came up to Jerusalem to <char style="it">make</char> war; and they besieged Ahaz but could not overcome <char style="it">him.</char> <verse number="6" style="v" />At that time Rezin king of Syria <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:22; 2 Chr. 26:2</char></note>captured Elath for Syria, and drove the men of Judah from Elath. Then the Edomites went to Elath, and dwell there to this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So Ahaz sent messengers to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:29; 1 Chr. 5:26; 2 Chr. 28:20</char></note>Tiglath-Pileser king of Assyria, saying, “I <char style="it">am</char> your servant and your son. Come up and save me from the hand of the king of Syria and from the hand of the king of Israel, who rise up against me.” <verse number="8" style="v" />And Ahaz <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:17, 18; 2 Chr. 28:21</char></note>took the silver and gold that was found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and in the treasuries of the king’s house, and sent <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">as</char> a present to the king of Assyria. <verse number="9" style="v" />So the king of Assyria heeded him; for the king of Assyria went up against <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:28</char></note>Damascus and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Amos 1:5</char></note>took it, carried <char style="it">its</char> <char style="it">people</char> captive to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 22:6; Amos 9:7</char></note>Kir, and killed Rezin.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Now King Ahaz went to Damascus to meet Tiglath-Pileser king of Assyria, and saw an altar that <char style="it">was</char> at Damascus; and King Ahaz sent to Urijah the priest the design of the altar and its pattern, according to all its workmanship. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 8:2</char></note>Urijah the priest built an altar according to all that King Ahaz had sent from Damascus. So Urijah the priest made <char style="it">it</char> before King Ahaz came back from Damascus. <verse number="12" style="v" />And when the king came back from Damascus, the king saw the altar; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:16, 19</char></note>the king approached the altar and made offerings on it. <verse number="13" style="v" />So he burned his burnt offering and his grain offering; and he poured his drink offering and sprinkled the blood of his peace offerings on the altar. <verse number="14" style="v" />He also brought <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:1, 2; 40:6, 29; 2 Chr. 4:1</char></note>the bronze altar which <char style="it">was</char> before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, from the front of the temple—from between the <char style="it">new</char> altar and the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>—and put it on the north side of the <char style="it">new</char> altar. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then King Ahaz commanded Urijah the priest, saying, “On the great <char style="it">new</char> altar burn <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:39–41</char></note>the morning burnt offering, the evening grain offering, the king’s burnt sacrifice, and his grain offering, with the burnt offering of all the people of the land, their grain offering, and their drink offerings; and sprinkle on it all the blood of the burnt offering and all the blood of the sacrifice. And the bronze altar shall be for me to inquire <char style="it">by.</char>” <verse number="16" style="v" />Thus did Urijah the priest, according to all that King Ahaz commanded.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:24</char></note>And King Ahaz cut off <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:27–29</char></note>the panels of the carts, and removed the lavers from them; and he took down <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:23–25</char></note>the Sea from the bronze oxen that <char style="it">were</char> under it, and put it on a pavement of stones. <verse number="18" style="v" />Also he removed the Sabbath pavilion which they had built in the temple, and he removed the king’s outer entrance from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, on account of the king of Assyria.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Ahaz which he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="20" style="v" />So Ahaz rested with his fathers, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:27</char></note>was buried with his fathers in the City of David. Then Hezekiah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Hoshea Reigns in Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the twelfth year of Ahaz king of Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:30</char></note>Hoshea the son of Elah became king of Israel in Samaria, <char style="it">and</char> <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">reigned</char> nine years. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but not as the kings of Israel who were before him. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:9–12</char></note>Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up against him; and Hoshea <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:1</char></note>became his vassal, and paid him tribute money. <verse number="4" style="v" />And the king of Assyria uncovered a conspiracy by Hoshea; for he had sent messengers to So, king of Egypt, and brought no tribute to the king of Assyria, as <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">done</char> year by year. Therefore the king of Assyria shut him up, and bound him in prison.</para>
	<para style="s">Israel Carried Captive to Assyria</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:9; Hos. 13:16</char></note>the king of Assyria went throughout all the land, and went up to Samaria and besieged it for three years. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:10, 11; Is. 7:7–9; Hos. 1:4; 13:16; Amos 4:2</char></note>In the ninth year of Hoshea, the king of Assyria took Samaria and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:32, 33; (Deut. 28:36, 64; 29:27, 28)</char></note>carried Israel away to Assyria, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 5:26</char></note>and placed them in Halah and by the Habor, the River of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Josh. 23:16)</char></note>so it was that the children of Israel had sinned against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, who had brought them up out of the land of Egypt, from under the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt; and they had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:10</char></note>feared other gods, <verse number="8" style="v" />and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:3; Deut. 18:9); 2 Kin. 16:3</char></note>had walked in the statutes of the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had cast out from before the children of Israel, and of the kings of Israel, which they had made. <verse number="9" style="v" />Also the children of Israel secretly did against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God things that <char style="it">were</char> not right, and they built for themselves high places in all their cities, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:8</char></note>from watchtower to fortified city. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:23; Is. 57:5</char></note>They set up for themselves <char style="it">sacred</char> pillars and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 34:12–14; Deut. 16:21); Mic. 5:14</char></note>wooden images <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 12:2); 2 Kin. 16:4</char></note>on every high hill and under every green tree. <verse number="11" style="v" />There they burned incense on all the high places, like the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had carried away before them; and they did wicked things to provoke the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to anger, <verse number="12" style="v" />for they served idols, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 20:3–5; Lev. 26:1; Deut. 5:7, 8)</char></note>of which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said to them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 4:19)</char></note>“You shall not do this thing.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Yet the <char style="sc">Lord</char> testified against Israel and against Judah, by all of His <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 9:29, 30</char></note>prophets, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:9</char></note>every seer, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Jer. 18:11; 25:5; 35:15; Ezek. 18:31)</char></note>“Turn from your evil ways, and keep My commandments <char style="it">and</char> My statutes, according to all the law which I commanded your fathers, and which I sent to you by My servants the prophets.” <verse number="14" style="v" />Nevertheless they would not hear, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:9; 33:3; Deut. 31:27; (Prov. 29:1; Acts 7:51)</char></note>stiffened their necks, like the necks of their fathers, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 9:23; Ps. 78:22</char></note>did not believe in the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God. <verse number="15" style="v" />And they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 44:3</char></note>rejected His statutes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 24:6–8; Deut. 29:25</char></note>and His covenant that He had made with their fathers, and His testimonies which He had testified against them; they followed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:21; 1 Kin. 16:31; (1 Cor. 8:4)</char></note>idols, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 13:7; Jer. 2:5; (Rom. 1:21–23)</char></note>became idolaters, and <char style="it">went</char> after the nations who <char style="it">were</char> all around them, <char style="it">concerning</char> whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had charged them that they should <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 12:30, 31)</char></note>not do like them. <verse number="16" style="v" />So they left all the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:8; 1 Kin. 12:28</char></note>made for themselves a molded image <char style="it">and</char> two calves, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Kin. 14:15)</char></note>made a wooden image and worshiped all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 4:19)</char></note>host of heaven, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:31; 22:53</char></note>and served Baal. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:21); 2 Kin. 16:3; Ezek. 23:37</char></note>And they caused their sons and daughters to pass through the fire, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 19:26; Deut. 18:10–12)</char></note>practiced witchcraft and soothsaying, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:20</char></note>sold themselves to do evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to provoke Him to anger. <verse number="18" style="v" />Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was very angry with Israel, and removed them from His sight; there was none left <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:13, 32</char></note>but the tribe of Judah alone.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 3:8</char></note>Judah did not keep the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, but walked in the statutes of Israel which they made. <verse number="20" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> rejected all the descendants of Israel, afflicted them, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:14; 2 Kin. 13:3; 15:29</char></note>delivered them into the hand of plunderers, until He had cast them from His <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:20</char></note>sight. <verse number="21" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:11, 31</char></note>He tore Israel from the house of David, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:20, 28</char></note>they made Jeroboam the son of Nebat king. Then Jeroboam drove Israel from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and made them commit a great sin. <verse number="22" style="v" />For the children of Israel walked in all the sins of Jeroboam which he did; they did not depart from them, <verse number="23" style="v" />until the <char style="sc">Lord</char> removed Israel out of His sight, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:16; Is. 8:4</char></note>as He had said by all His servants the prophets. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:6</char></note>So Israel was carried away from their own land to Assyria, <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> to this day.</para>
	<para style="s">Assyria Resettles Samaria</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 4:2, 10</char></note>Then the king of Assyria brought <char style="it">people</char> from Babylon, Cuthah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:34</char></note>Ava, Hamath, and from Sepharvaim, and placed <char style="it">them</char> in the cities of Samaria instead of the children of Israel; and they took possession of Samaria and dwelt in its cities. <verse number="25" style="v" />And it was so, at the beginning of their dwelling there, <char style="it">that</char> they did not fear the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sent lions among them, which killed <char style="it">some</char> of them. <verse number="26" style="v" />So they spoke to the king of Assyria, saying, “The nations whom you have removed and placed in the cities of Samaria do not know the rituals of the God of the land; therefore He has sent lions among them, and indeed, they are killing them because they do not know the rituals of the God of the land.” <verse number="27" style="v" />Then the king of Assyria commanded, saying, “Send there one of the priests whom you brought from there; let him go and dwell there, and let him teach them the rituals of the God of the land.” <verse number="28" style="v" />Then one of the priests whom they had carried away from Samaria came and dwelt in Bethel, and taught them how they should fear the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />However every nation continued to make gods of its own, and put <char style="it">them</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:31; 13:32</char></note>in the shrines on the high places which the Samaritans had made, <char style="it">every</char> nation in the cities where they dwelt. <verse number="30" style="v" />The men of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:24</char></note>Babylon made Succoth Benoth, the men of Cuth made Nergal, the men of Hamath made Ashima, <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 4:9</char></note>and the Avites made Nibhaz and Tartak; and the Sepharvites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:21; Deut. 12:31)</char></note>burned their children in fire to Adrammelech and Anammelech, the gods of Sepharvaim. <verse number="32" style="v" />So they feared the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:31; 13:33</char></note>and from every class they appointed for themselves priests of the high places, who sacrificed for them in the shrines of the high places. <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Zeph. 1:5</char></note>They feared the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, yet served their own gods—according to the rituals of the nations from among whom they were carried away.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />To this day they continue practicing the former rituals; they do not fear the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, nor do they follow their statutes or their ordinances, or the law and commandment which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded the children of Jacob, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:28; 35:10</char></note>whom He named Israel, <verse number="35" style="v" />with whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had made a covenant and charged them, saying: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:10</char></note>“You shall not fear other gods, nor <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 20:5)</char></note>bow down to them nor serve them nor sacrifice to them; <verse number="36" style="v" />but the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:15–30</char></note>brought you up from the land of Egypt with great power and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 6:6; 9:15</char></note>an outstretched arm, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 10:20)</char></note>Him you shall fear, Him you shall worship, and to Him you shall offer sacrifice. <verse number="37" style="v" />And the statutes, the ordinances, the law, and the commandment which He wrote for you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 5:32</char></note>you shall be careful to observe forever; you shall not fear other gods. <verse number="38" style="v" />And the covenant that I have made with you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:23; 6:12</char></note>you shall not forget, nor shall you fear other gods. <verse number="39" style="v" />But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God you shall fear; and He will deliver you from the hand of all your enemies.” <verse number="40" style="v" />However they did not obey, but they followed their former rituals. <verse number="41" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:32, 33</char></note>So these nations feared the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, yet served their carved images; also their children and their children’s children have continued doing as their fathers did, even to this day.</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Hezekiah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now it came to pass in the third year of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:1</char></note>Hoshea the son of Elah, king of Israel, <char style="it">that</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 28:27; 29:1</char></note>Hezekiah the son of Ahaz, king of Judah, began to reign. <verse number="2" style="v" />He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 38:5</char></note>Abi the daughter of Zechariah. <verse number="3" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his father David had done.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 31:1</char></note>He removed the high places and broke the <char style="it">sacred</char> pillars, cut down the wooden image and broke in pieces the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:5–9</char></note>bronze serpent that Moses had made; for until those days the children of Israel burned incense to it, and called it Nehushtan. <verse number="5" style="v" />He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:10; (Job 13:15; Ps. 13:5)</char></note>trusted in the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:25</char></note>so that after him was none like him among all the kings of Judah, nor who were before him. <verse number="6" style="v" />For he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 10:20; Josh. 23:8</char></note>held fast to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; he did not depart from following Him, but kept His commandments, which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses. <verse number="7" style="v" />The <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Chr. 15:2)</char></note>was with him; he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 39:2, 3; 1 Sam. 18:5, 14; Ps. 60:12</char></note>prospered wherever he went. And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:7</char></note>rebelled against the king of Assyria and did not serve him. <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 4:41; 2 Chr. 28:18; Is. 14:29</char></note>He subdued the Philistines, as far as Gaza and its territory, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:9</char></note>from watchtower to fortified city.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:3</char></note>it came to pass in the fourth year of King Hezekiah, which <char style="it">was</char> the seventh year of Hoshea the son of Elah, king of Israel, <char style="it">that</char> Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up against Samaria and besieged it. <verse number="10" style="v" />And at the end of three years they took it. In the sixth year of Hezekiah, that <char style="it">is,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:6</char></note>the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel, Samaria was taken. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:6; Hos. 1:4; Amos 4:2</char></note>Then the king of Assyria carried Israel away captive to Assyria, and put them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 5:26</char></note>in Halah and by the Habor, the River of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes, <verse number="12" style="v" />because they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:7–18</char></note>did not obey the voice of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, but transgressed His covenant <char style="it">and</char> all that Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded; and they would neither hear nor do <char style="it">them.</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:1; Is. 36:1—39:8</char></note>in the fourteenth year of King Hezekiah, Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the fortified cities of Judah and took them. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then Hezekiah king of Judah sent to the king of Assyria at Lachish, saying, “I have done wrong; turn away from me; whatever you impose on me I will pay.” And the king of Assyria assessed Hezekiah king of Judah three hundred talents of silver and thirty talents of gold. <verse number="15" style="v" />So Hezekiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 15:18, 19; 2 Kin. 12:18; 16:8</char></note>gave <char style="it">him</char> all the silver that was found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in the treasuries of the king’s house. <verse number="16" style="v" />At that time Hezekiah stripped <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">gold</char> <char style="it">from</char> the doors of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <char style="it">from</char> the pillars which Hezekiah king of Judah had overlaid, and gave it to the king of Assyria.</para>
	<para style="s">Sennacherib Boasts Against the <char style="sc">Lord</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then the king of Assyria sent <char style="it">the</char> Tartan, <char style="it">the</char> Rabsaris, <char style="it"> and the</char> Rabshakeh from Lachish, with a great army against Jerusalem, to King Hezekiah. And they went up and came to Jerusalem. When they had come up, they went and stood by the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:20</char></note>aqueduct from the upper pool, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 7:3</char></note>which <char style="it">was</char> on the highway to the Fuller’s Field. <verse number="18" style="v" />And when they had called to the king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:2; Is. 22:20</char></note>Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who <char style="it">was</char> over the household, Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph, the recorder, came out to them. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then <char style="it">the</char> Rabshakeh said to them, “Say now to Hezekiah, ‘Thus says the great king, the king of Assyria: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:10; (Ps. 118:8, 9)</char></note>“What confidence <char style="it">is</char> this in which you trust? <verse number="20" style="v" />You speak of <char style="it">having</char> plans and power for war; but <char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">are</char> mere words. And in whom do you trust, that you rebel against me? <verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 30:2–7; Ezek. 29:6, 7</char></note>Now look! You are trusting in the staff of this broken reed, Egypt, on which if a man leans, it will go into his hand and pierce it. So <char style="it">is</char> Pharaoh king of Egypt to all who trust in him. <verse number="22" style="v" />But if you say to me, ‘We trust in the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God,’ <char style="it">is</char> it not He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:4; 2 Chr. 31:1; 32:12</char></note>whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah has taken away, and said to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘You shall worship before this altar in Jerusalem’?” ’ <verse number="23" style="v" />Now therefore, I urge you, give a pledge to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give you two thousand horses—if you are able on your part to put riders on them! <verse number="24" style="v" />How then will you repel one captain of the least of my master’s servants, and put your trust in Egypt for chariots and horsemen? <verse number="25" style="v" />Have I now come up without the <char style="sc">Lord</char> against this place to destroy it? The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to me, ‘Go up against this land, and destroy it.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 36:11—39:8</char></note>Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, Shebna, and Joah said to <char style="it">the</char> Rabshakeh, “Please speak to your servants in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 4:7; Dan. 2:4</char></note>Aramaic, for we understand <char style="it">it;</char> and do not speak to us in Hebrew in the hearing of the people who <char style="it">are</char> on the wall.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />But <char style="it">the</char> Rabshakeh said to them, “Has my master sent me to your master and to you to speak these words, and not to the men who sit on the wall, who will eat and drink their own waste with you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Then <char style="it">the</char> Rabshakeh stood and called out with a loud voice in Hebrew, and spoke, saying, “Hear the word of the great king, the king of Assyria! <verse number="29" style="v" />Thus says the king: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:15</char></note>‘Do not let Hezekiah deceive you, for he shall not be able to deliver you from his hand; <verse number="30" style="v" />nor let Hezekiah make you trust in the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will surely deliver us; this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.” ’ <verse number="31" style="v" />Do not listen to Hezekiah; for thus says the king of Assyria: ‘Make <char style="it">peace</char> with me by a present and come out to me; and every one of you eat from his own <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:20, 25</char></note>vine and every one from his own fig tree, and every one of you drink the waters of his own cistern; <verse number="32" style="v" />until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 8:7–9; 11:12</char></note>a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive groves and honey, that you may live and not die. But do not listen to Hezekiah, lest he persuade you, saying, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will deliver us.” <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:12; Is. 10:10, 11</char></note>Has any of the gods of the nations at all delivered its land from the hand of the king of Assyria? <verse number="34" style="v" />Where <char style="it">are</char> the gods of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:13</char></note>Hamath and Arpad? Where <char style="it">are</char> the gods of Sepharvaim and Hena and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:24</char></note>Ivah? Indeed, have they delivered Samaria from my hand? <verse number="35" style="v" />Who among all the gods of the lands have delivered their countries from my hand, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 3:15</char></note>that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> should deliver Jerusalem from my hand?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />But the people held their peace and answered him not a word; for the king’s commandment was, “Do not answer him.” <verse number="37" style="v" />Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who <char style="it">was</char> over the household, Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph, the recorder, came to Hezekiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 33:7</char></note>with <char style="it">their</char> clothes torn, and told him the words of <char style="it">the</char> Rabshakeh.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Isaiah Assures Deliverance</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:13; 2 Chr. 32:20–22; Is. 37:1</char></note>so it was, when King Hezekiah heard <char style="it">it,</char> that he tore his clothes, covered himself with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 69:11</char></note>sackcloth, and went into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="2" style="v" />Then he sent Eliakim, who <char style="it">was</char> over the household, Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz. <verse number="3" style="v" />And they said to him, “Thus says Hezekiah: ‘This day <char style="it">is</char> a day of trouble, and rebuke, and blasphemy; for the children have come to birth, but <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no strength to bring them forth. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 16:12</char></note>It may be that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will hear all the words of <char style="it">the</char> Rabshakeh, whom his master the king of Assyria has sent to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:35</char></note>reproach the living God, and will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 50:21</char></note>rebuke the words which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has heard. Therefore lift up <char style="it">your</char> prayer for the remnant that is left.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So the servants of King Hezekiah came to Isaiah. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 37:6</char></note>And Isaiah said to them, “Thus you shall say to your master, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: “Do not be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 112:7)</char></note>afraid of the words which you have heard, with which the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:17</char></note>servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed Me. <verse number="7" style="v" />Surely I will send <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:35–37; Jer. 51:1</char></note>a spirit upon him, and he shall hear a rumor and return to his own land; and I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.” ’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Sennacherib’s Threat and Hezekiah’s Prayer</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then <char style="it">the</char> Rabshakeh returned and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah, for he heard that he had departed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:14, 17</char></note>from Lachish. <verse number="9" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 23:27; Is. 37:9</char></note>the king heard concerning Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, “Look, he has come out to make war with you.” So he again sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying, <verse number="10" style="v" />“Thus you shall speak to Hezekiah king of Judah, saying: ‘Do not let your God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:5</char></note>in whom you trust deceive you, saying, “Jerusalem shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.” <verse number="11" style="v" />Look! You have heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands by utterly destroying them; and shall you be delivered? <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:33, 34</char></note>Have the gods of the nations delivered those whom my fathers have destroyed, Gozan and Haran and Rezeph, and the people of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 27:23</char></note>Eden who <char style="it">were</char> in Telassar? <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:34</char></note>Where <char style="it">is</char> the king of Hamath, the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivah?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 37:14</char></note>And Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers, and read it; and Hezekiah went up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and spread it before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then Hezekiah prayed before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said: “O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">One</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:22; Ps. 80:1; Is. 37:16</char></note>who dwells <char style="it">between</char> the cherubim, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 44:6)</char></note>You are God, You alone, of all the kingdoms of the earth. You have made heaven and earth. <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 31:2; Is. 37:17</char></note>Incline Your ear, O <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and hear; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:29; 2 Chr. 6:40</char></note>open Your eyes, O <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and see; and hear the words of Sennacherib, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:4</char></note>which he has sent to reproach the living God. <verse number="17" style="v" />Truly, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the kings of Assyria have laid waste the nations and their lands, <verse number="18" style="v" />and have cast their gods into the fire; for they <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 44:9–20; Jer. 10:3–5)</char></note>not gods, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 115:4; Jer. 10:3; (Acts 17:29)</char></note>the work of men’s hands—wood and stone. Therefore they destroyed them. <verse number="19" style="v" />Now therefore, O <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, I pray, save us from his hand, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:18</char></note>that all the kingdoms of the earth may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:42, 43</char></note>know that You <char style="it">are</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God, You alone.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> Concerning Sennacherib</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 37:21</char></note>‘Because you have prayed to Me against Sennacherib king of Assyria, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:5; Ps. 65:2</char></note>I have heard.’ <verse number="21" style="v" />This <char style="it">is</char> the word which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has spoken concerning him:</para>
	<para style="q1">‘The virgin, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 14:17; Lam. 2:13</char></note>the daughter of Zion,</para>
	<para style="q2">Has despised you, laughed you to scorn;</para>
	<para style="q2">The daughter of Jerusalem</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 22:7, 8</char></note>Has shaken <char style="it">her</char> head behind your back!</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="22" style="v" />‘Whom have you reproached and blasphemed?</para>
	<para style="q2">Against whom have you raised <char style="it">your</char> voice,</para>
	<para style="q2">And lifted up your eyes on high?</para>
	<para style="q2">Against <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 51:5</char></note>the Holy <char style="it">One</char> of Israel.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:17</char></note>By your messengers you have reproached the Lord,</para>
	<para style="q2">And said: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 20:7</char></note>“By the multitude of my chariots</para>
	<para style="q2">I have come up to the height of the mountains,</para>
	<para style="q2">To the limits of Lebanon;</para>
	<para style="q2">I will cut down its tall cedars</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">And</char> its choice cypress trees;</para>
	<para style="q2">I will enter the extremity of its borders,</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">To</char> its fruitful forest.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="24" style="v" />I have dug and drunk strange water,</para>
	<para style="q2">And with the soles of my feet I have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 19:6</char></note>dried up</para>
	<para style="q2">All the brooks of defense.”</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="25" style="v" />‘Did you not hear long ago</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">How</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 45:7)</char></note>I made it,</para>
	<para style="q2">From ancient times that I formed it?</para>
	<para style="q2">Now I have brought it to pass,</para>
	<para style="q2">That <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 10:5, 6</char></note>you should be</para>
	<para style="q2">For crushing fortified cities <char style="it">into</char> heaps of ruins.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="26" style="v" />Therefore their inhabitants had little power;</para>
	<para style="q2">They were dismayed and confounded;</para>
	<para style="q2">They were <char style="it">as</char> the grass of the field</para>
	<para style="q2">And the green herb,</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">As</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 129:6</char></note>the grass on the housetops</para>
	<para style="q2">And <char style="it">grain</char> blighted before it is grown.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="27" style="v" />‘But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 139:1–3; Is. 37:28</char></note>I know your dwelling place,</para>
	<para style="q2">Your going out and your coming in,</para>
	<para style="q2">And your rage against Me.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="28" style="v" />Because your rage against Me and your tumult</para>
	<para style="q2">Have come up to My ears,</para>
	<para style="q2">Therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 41:2; Ezek. 29:4; 38:4; Amos 4:2</char></note>I will put My hook in your nose</para>
	<para style="q2">And My bridle in your lips,</para>
	<para style="q2">And I will turn you back</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:33, 36</char></note>By the way which you came.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="29" style="v" />‘This <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:12; 1 Sam. 2:34; 2 Kin. 20:8, 9; Is. 7:11–14; Luke 2:12</char></note>sign to you:</para>
	<para style="q2">You shall eat this year such as grows of itself,</para>
	<para style="q2">And in the second year what springs from the same;</para>
	<para style="q2">Also in the third year sow and reap,</para>
	<para style="q2">Plant vineyards and eat the fruit of them.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:4; 2 Chr. 32:22, 23</char></note>And the remnant who have escaped of the house of Judah</para>
	<para style="q2">Shall again take root downward,</para>
	<para style="q2">And bear fruit upward.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="31" style="v" />For out of Jerusalem shall go a remnant,</para>
	<para style="q2">And those who escape from Mount Zion.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:26; Is. 9:7</char></note>The zeal of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> of hosts will do this.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />“Therefore thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> concerning the king of Assyria:</para>
	<para style="q1">‘He shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 8:7–10</char></note>not come into this city,</para>
	<para style="q2">Nor shoot an arrow there,</para>
	<para style="q2">Nor come before it with shield,</para>
	<para style="q2">Nor build a siege mound against it.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="33" style="v" />By the way that he came,</para>
	<para style="q2">By the same shall he return;</para>
	<para style="q2">And he shall not come into this city,’</para>
	<para style="q2">Says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="34" style="v" />‘For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:6; 2 Chr. 32:21</char></note>I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 31:5</char></note>defend this city, to save it</para>
	<para style="q2">For My own sake and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:12, 13</char></note>for My servant David’s sake.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Sennacherib’s Defeat and Death</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:29; Is. 10:12–19; 37:36; Hos. 1:7</char></note>it came to pass on a certain night that the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> went out, and killed in the camp of the Assyrians one hundred and eighty-five thousand; and when <char style="it">people</char> arose early in the morning, there were the corpses—all dead. <verse number="36" style="v" />So Sennacherib king of Assyria departed and went away, returned <char style="it">home,</char> and remained at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 10:11</char></note>Nineveh. <verse number="37" style="v" />Now it came to pass, as he was worshiping in the temple of Nisroch his god, that his sons <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:31</char></note>Adrammelech and Sharezer <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:7; 2 Chr. 32:21</char></note>struck him down with the sword; and they escaped into the land of Ararat. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 4:2</char></note>Esarhaddon his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Hezekiah’s Life Extended</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:13; 2 Chr. 32:24; Is. 38:1–22</char></note>those days Hezekiah was sick and near death. And Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, went to him and said to him, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Set your house in order, for you shall die, and not live.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Then he turned his face toward the wall, and prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:3–6; Neh. 13:22</char></note>“Remember now, O <char style="sc">Lord</char>, I pray, how I have walked before You in truth and with a loyal heart, and have done <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> good in Your sight.” And Hezekiah wept bitterly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />And it happened, before Isaiah had gone out into the middle court, that the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to him, saying, <verse number="5" style="v" />“Return and tell Hezekiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:16; 10:1</char></note>the leader of My people, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of David your father: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:20; Ps. 65:2</char></note>“I have heard your prayer, I have seen <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 39:12; 56:8</char></note>your tears; surely I will heal you. On the third day you shall go up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" />And I will add to your days fifteen years. I will deliver you and this city from the hand of the king of Assyria; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:34; 2 Chr. 32:21</char></note>I will defend this city for My own sake, and for the sake of My servant David.” ’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 38:21</char></note>Isaiah said, “Take a lump of figs.” So they took and laid <char style="it">it</char> on the boil, and he recovered.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And Hezekiah said to Isaiah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:17, 37, 39; Is. 7:11, 14; 38:22</char></note>“What <char style="it">is</char> the sign that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will heal me, and that I shall go up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> the third day?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Then Isaiah said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 23:19; Is. 38:7, 8</char></note>“This is the sign to you from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will do the thing which He has spoken: <char style="it">shall</char> the shadow go forward ten degrees or go backward ten degrees?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And Hezekiah answered, “It is an easy thing for the shadow to go down ten degrees; no, but let the shadow go backward ten degrees.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So Isaiah the prophet cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:12–14; Is. 38:8</char></note>He brought the shadow ten degrees backward, by which it had gone down on the sundial of Ahaz.</para>
	<para style="s">The Babylonian Envoys</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 8:8, 9; 2 Chr. 32:31; Is. 39:1–8</char></note>At that time Berodach-Baladan the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present to Hezekiah, for he heard that Hezekiah had been sick. <verse number="13" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:9; 2 Chr. 32:27, 31</char></note>Hezekiah was attentive to them, and showed them all the house of his treasures—the silver and gold, the spices and precious ointment, and all his armory—all that was found among his treasures. There was nothing in his house or in all his dominion that Hezekiah did not show them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then Isaiah the prophet went to King Hezekiah, and said to him, “What did these men say, and from where did they come to you?”</para>
	<para style="p">So Hezekiah said, “They came from a far country, from Babylon.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And he said, “What have they seen in your house?”</para>
	<para style="p">So Hezekiah answered, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:13</char></note>“They have seen all that <char style="it">is</char> in my house; there is nothing among my treasures that I have not shown them.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Then Isaiah said to Hezekiah, “Hear the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <verse number="17" style="v" />‘Behold, the days are coming when all that <char style="it">is</char> in your house, and what your fathers have accumulated until this day, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:13; 25:13–15; 2 Chr. 36:10; Jer. 27:21, 22; 52:17</char></note>shall be carried to Babylon; nothing shall be left,’ says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="18" style="v" />‘And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:12; 2 Chr. 33:11</char></note>they shall take away some of your sons who will descend from you, whom you will beget; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:3–7</char></note>and they shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:11, 18</char></note>eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />So Hezekiah said to Isaiah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 3:18</char></note>“The word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which you have spoken <char style="it">is</char> good!” For he said, “Will there not be peace and truth at least in my days?”</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Hezekiah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:32</char></note>Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah—all his might, and how he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 3:16</char></note>made a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:17; Is. 7:3</char></note>pool and a tunnel and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 32:3, 30</char></note>brought water into the city—<char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="21" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:20; 2 Chr. 32:33</char></note>Hezekiah rested with his fathers. Then Manasseh his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Manasseh Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Manasseh <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:1–9</char></note><char style="it">was</char> twelve years old when he became king, and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Hephzibah. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:3</char></note>according to the abominations of the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had cast out before the children of Israel. <verse number="3" style="v" />For he rebuilt the high places <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:4, 22</char></note>which Hezekiah his father had destroyed; he raised up altars for Baal, and made a wooden image, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:31–33</char></note>as Ahab king of Israel had done; and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 4:19; 17:2–5); 2 Kin. 17:16; 23:5</char></note>worshiped all the host of heaven and served them. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 7:30; 32:34</char></note>He also built altars in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, of which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:13</char></note>“In Jerusalem I will put My name.” <verse number="5" style="v" />And he built altars for all the host of heaven in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 6:36; 7:12; 2 Kin. 23:12</char></note>two courts of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:21; 20:2); 2 Kin. 16:3; 17:17</char></note>Also he made his son pass through the fire, practiced <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:26, 31; (Deut. 18:10–14); 2 Kin. 17:17</char></note>soothsaying, used witchcraft, and consulted spiritists and mediums. He did much evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to provoke <char style="it">Him</char> to anger. <verse number="7" style="v" />He even set a carved image of Asherah that he had made, in the house of which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said to David and to Solomon his son, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:13; 1 Kin. 8:29; 9:3; 2 Kin. 23:27; 2 Chr. 7:12, 16; Jer. 32:34</char></note>“In this house and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I will put My name forever; <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:10; (2 Kin. 18:11, 12)</char></note>and I will not make the feet of Israel wander anymore from the land which I gave their fathers—only if they are careful to do according to all that I have commanded them, and according to all the law that My servant Moses commanded them.” <verse number="9" style="v" />But they paid no attention, and Manasseh <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 29:12)</char></note>seduced them to do more evil than the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had destroyed before the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:13</char></note>by His servants the prophets, saying, <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:26, 27; 24:3, 4</char></note>“Because Manasseh king of Judah has done these abominations (<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:26</char></note>he has acted more wickedly than all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:16</char></note>Amorites who <char style="it">were</char> before him, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:9</char></note>has also made Judah sin with his idols), <verse number="12" style="v" />therefore thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: ‘Behold, <char style="it">I</char> am bringing <char style="it">such</char> calamity upon Jerusalem and Judah, that whoever hears of it, both <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 3:11; Jer. 19:3</char></note>his ears will tingle. <verse number="13" style="v" />And I will stretch over Jerusalem <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lam. 2:8; Amos 7:7, 8</char></note>the measuring line of Samaria and the plummet of the house of Ahab; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:16–19; 25:4–11</char></note>I will wipe Jerusalem as <char style="it">one</char> wipes a dish, wiping <char style="it">it</char> and turning <char style="it">it</char> upside down. <verse number="14" style="v" />So I will forsake the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 6:9</char></note>remnant of My inheritance and deliver them into the hand of their enemies; and they shall become victims of plunder to all their enemies, <verse number="15" style="v" />because they have done evil in My sight, and have provoked Me to anger since the day their fathers came out of Egypt, even to this day.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:4</char></note>Moreover Manasseh shed very much innocent blood, till he had filled Jerusalem from one end to another, besides his sin by which he made Judah sin, in doing evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:11–19</char></note>the rest of the acts of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:21</char></note>Manasseh—all that he did, and the sin that he committed—<char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="18" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:20</char></note>Manasseh rested with his fathers, and was buried in the garden of his own house, in the garden of Uzza. Then his son Amon reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="s">Amon’s Reign and Death</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 33:21–23</char></note>Amon <char style="it">was</char> twenty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Meshullemeth the daughter of Haruz of Jotbah. <verse number="20" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:2–6, 11, 16</char></note>as his father Manasseh had done. <verse number="21" style="v" />So he walked in all the ways that his father had walked; and he served the idols that his father had served, and worshiped them. <verse number="22" style="v" />He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:12, 13; 1 Kin. 11:33; 1 Chr. 28:9</char></note>forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of his fathers, and did not walk in the way of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 3:14; 2 Chr. 33:24, 25; Matt. 1:10</char></note>Then the servants of Amon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:20; 14:19</char></note>conspired against him, and killed the king in his own house. <verse number="24" style="v" />But the people of the land <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:5</char></note>executed all those who had conspired against King Amon. Then the people of the land made his son Josiah king in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Amon which he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="26" style="v" />And he was buried in his tomb in the garden of Uzza. Then Josiah his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Josiah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Josiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:2; 2 Chr. 34:1</char></note><char style="it">was</char> eight years old when he became king, and he reigned thirty-one years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Jedidah the daughter of Adaiah of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:39</char></note>Bozkath. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and walked in all the ways of his father David; he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 5:32; Josh. 1:7</char></note>did not turn aside to the right hand or to the left.</para>
	<para style="s">Hilkiah Finds the Book of the Law</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:8</char></note>Now it came to pass, in the eighteenth year of King Josiah, <char style="it">that</char> the king sent Shaphan the scribe, the son of Azaliah, the son of Meshullam, to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying: <verse number="4" style="v" />“Go up to Hilkiah the high priest, that he may count the money which has been <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:4</char></note>brought into the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:9, 10</char></note>the doorkeepers have gathered from the people. <verse number="5" style="v" />And let them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:11–14</char></note>deliver it into the hand of those doing the work, who are the overseers in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; let them give it to those who <char style="it">are</char> in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> doing the work, to repair the damages of the house— <verse number="6" style="v" />to carpenters and builders and masons—and to buy timber and hewn stone to repair the house. <verse number="7" style="v" />However <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:15; (1 Cor. 4:2)</char></note>there need be no accounting made with them of the money delivered into their hand, because they deal faithfully.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then Hilkiah the high priest said to Shaphan the scribe, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:24–26; 2 Chr. 34:14</char></note>“I have found the Book of the Law in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” And Hilkiah gave the book to Shaphan, and he read it. <verse number="9" style="v" />So Shaphan the scribe went to the king, bringing the king word, saying, “Your servants have gathered the money that was found in the house, and have delivered it into the hand of those who do the work, who oversee the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” <verse number="10" style="v" />Then Shaphan the scribe showed the king, saying, “Hilkiah the priest has given me a book.” And Shaphan read it before the king.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Now it happened, when the king heard the words of the Book of the Law, that he tore his clothes. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then the king commanded Hilkiah the priest, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:22; Jer. 26:24</char></note>Ahikam the son of Shaphan, Achbor the son of Michaiah, Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah a servant of the king, saying, <verse number="13" style="v" />“Go, inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for me, for the people and for all Judah, concerning the words of this book that has been found; for great <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 29:23–28; 31:17, 18)</char></note>the wrath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that is aroused against us, because our fathers have not obeyed the words of this book, to do according to all that is written concerning us.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So Hilkiah the priest, Ahikam, Achbor, Shaphan, and Asaiah went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:22</char></note>Tikvah, the son of Harhas, keeper of the wardrobe. (She dwelt in Jerusalem in the Second Quarter.) And they spoke with her. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then she said to them, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, ‘Tell the man who sent you to Me, <verse number="16" style="v" />“Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 29:27; (Dan. 9:11–14)</char></note>I will bring calamity on this place and on its inhabitants—all the words of the book which the king of Judah has read— <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 29:25–27; 2 Kin. 21:22</char></note>because they have forsaken Me and burned incense to other gods, that they might provoke Me to anger with all the works of their hands. Therefore My wrath shall be aroused against this place and shall not be quenched.’ ” ’ <verse number="18" style="v" />But as for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:26</char></note>the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, in this manner you shall speak to him, ‘Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: “<char style="it">Concerning</char> the words which you have heard— <verse number="19" style="v" />because your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 24:5; (Ps. 51:17; Is. 57:15)</char></note>heart was tender, and you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 10:3; 1 Kin. 21:29; (2 Chr. 7:14)</char></note>humbled yourself before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> when you heard what I spoke against this place and against its inhabitants, that they would become <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:31, 32</char></note>a desolation and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 26:6; 44:22</char></note>a curse, and you tore your clothes and wept before Me, I also have heard <char style="it">you,</char>” says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="20" style="v" />“Surely, therefore, I will gather you to your fathers, and you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:30; (Ps. 37:37; Is. 57:1, 2)</char></note>shall be gathered to your grave in peace; and your eyes shall not see all the calamity which I will bring on this place.” ’ ” So they brought back word to the king.</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Josiah Restores True Worship</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 19:11; 2 Chr. 34:29, 30</char></note>the king sent them to gather all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem to him. <verse number="2" style="v" />The king went up to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with all the men of Judah, and with him all the inhabitants of Jerusalem—the priests and the prophets and all the people, both small and great. And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:10–13</char></note>read in their hearing all the words of the Book of the Covenant <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:8</char></note>which had been found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 11:14</char></note>stood by a pillar and made a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 11:17</char></note>covenant before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to follow the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and to keep His commandments and His testimonies and His statutes, with all <char style="it">his</char> heart and all <char style="it">his</char> soul, to perform the words of this covenant that were written in this book. And all the people took a stand for the covenant. <verse number="4" style="v" />And the king commanded Hilkiah the high priest, the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:18; Jer. 52:24</char></note>priests of the second order, and the doorkeepers, to bring <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:3–7</char></note>out of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all the articles that were made for Baal, for Asherah, and for all the host of heaven; and he burned them outside Jerusalem in the fields of Kidron, and carried their ashes to Bethel. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then he removed the idolatrous priests whom the kings of Judah had ordained to burn incense on the high places in the cities of Judah and in the places all around Jerusalem, and those who burned incense to Baal, to the sun, to the moon, to the constellations, and to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:3</char></note>all the host of heaven. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he brought out the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:7</char></note>wooden image from the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to the Brook Kidron outside Jerusalem, burned it at the Brook Kidron and ground <char style="it">it</char> to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:20</char></note>ashes, and threw its ashes on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:4</char></note>the graves of the common people. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then he tore down the <char style="it">ritual</char> booths <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 14:24; 15:12</char></note>of the perverted persons that <char style="it">were</char> in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 35:25, 26; Ezek. 16:16</char></note>where the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 38:8</char></note>women wove hangings for the wooden image. <verse number="8" style="v" />And he brought all the priests from the cities of Judah, and defiled the high places where the priests had burned incense, from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:17; 1 Kin. 15:22</char></note>Geba to Beersheba; also he broke down the high places at the gates which <char style="it">were</char> at the entrance of the Gate of Joshua the governor of the city, which <char style="it">were</char> to the left of the city gate. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ezek. 44:10–14)</char></note>Nevertheless the priests of the high places did not come up to the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Jerusalem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:36</char></note>but they ate unleavened bread among their brethren.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And he defiled <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 30:33; Jer. 7:31, 32</char></note>Topheth, which <char style="it">is</char> in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:8</char></note>the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 18:21; Deut. 18:10); Ezek. 23:37–39</char></note>that no man might make his son or his daughter <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:6</char></note>pass through the fire to Molech. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then he removed the horses that the kings of Judah had dedicated to the sun, at the entrance to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, by the chamber of Nathan-Melech, the officer who <char style="it">was</char> in the court; and he burned the chariots of the sun with fire. <verse number="12" style="v" />The altars that <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 19:13; Zeph. 1:5</char></note>on the roof, the upper chamber of Ahaz, which the kings of Judah had made, and the altars which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:5; 2 Chr. 33:5</char></note>Manasseh had made in the two courts of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the king broke down and pulverized there, and threw their dust into the Brook Kidron. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then the king defiled the high places that <char style="it">were</char> east of Jerusalem, which <char style="it">were</char> on the south of the Mount of Corruption, which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:5–7</char></note>Solomon king of Israel had built for Ashtoreth the abomination of the Sidonians, for Chemosh the abomination of the Moabites, and for Milcom the abomination of the people of Ammon. <verse number="14" style="v" />And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 23:24; Deut. 7:5–25)</char></note>broke in pieces the <char style="it">sacred</char> pillars and cut down the wooden images, and filled their places with the bones of men.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Moreover the altar that <char style="it">was</char> at Bethel, <char style="it">and</char> the high place <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:28–33</char></note>which Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who made Israel sin, had made, both that altar and the high place he broke down; and he burned the high place <char style="it">and</char> crushed <char style="it">it</char> to powder, and burned the wooden image. <verse number="16" style="v" />As Josiah turned, he saw the tombs that <char style="it">were</char> there on the mountain. And he sent and took the bones out of the tombs and burned <char style="it">them</char> on the altar, and defiled it according to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:2</char></note>word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which the man of God proclaimed, who proclaimed these words. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then he said, “What gravestone <char style="it">is</char> this that I see?”</para>
	<para style="p">So the men of the city told him, “<char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:1, 30, 31</char></note>the tomb of the man of God who came from Judah and proclaimed these things which you have done against the altar of Bethel.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And he said, “Let him alone; let no one move his bones.” So they let his bones alone, with the bones of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:11, 31</char></note>the prophet who came from Samaria.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Now Josiah also took away all the shrines of the high places that <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:6, 7</char></note>in the cities of Samaria, which the kings of Israel had made to provoke the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to anger; and he did to them according to all the deeds he had done in Bethel. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:2</char></note>He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 22:20); 1 Kin. 18:40; 2 Kin. 10:25; 11:18</char></note>executed all the priests of the high places who <char style="it">were</char> there, on the altars, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 34:5</char></note>burned men’s bones on them; and he returned to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then the king commanded all the people, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 9:5; Josh. 5:10; 2 Chr. 35:1</char></note>“Keep the Passover to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:3; Lev. 23:5; Num. 9:2; Deut. 16:2–8</char></note>as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> written in this Book of the Covenant.” <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:18, 19</char></note>Such a Passover surely had never been held since the days of the judges who judged Israel, nor in all the days of the kings of Israel and the kings of Judah. <verse number="23" style="v" />But in the eighteenth year of King Josiah this Passover was held before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Jerusalem. <verse number="24" style="v" />Moreover Josiah put away those who consulted mediums and spiritists, the household gods and idols, all the abominations that were seen in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem, that he might perform the words of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 19:31; 20:27); Deut. 18:11</char></note>the law which were written in the book <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:8</char></note>that Hilkiah the priest found in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 18:5</char></note>Now before him there was no king like him, who turned to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with all his heart, with all his soul, and with all his might, according to all the Law of Moses; nor after him did <char style="it">any</char> arise like him.</para>
	<para style="s">Impending Judgment on Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Nevertheless the <char style="sc">Lord</char> did not turn from the fierceness of His great wrath, with which His anger was aroused against Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:11, 12; 24:3, 4; Jer. 15:4</char></note>because of all the provocations with which Manasseh had provoked Him. <verse number="27" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, “I will also remove Judah from My sight, as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:18, 20; 18:11; 21:13</char></note>I have removed Israel, and will cast off this city Jerusalem which I have chosen, and the house of which I said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:29; 9:3; 2 Kin. 21:4, 7</char></note>‘My name shall be there.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Josiah Dies in Battle</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:20; Jer. 2:16; 46:2</char></note>In his days Pharaoh Necho king of Egypt went to the aid of the king of Assyria, to the River Euphrates; and King Josiah went against him. And <char style="it">Pharaoh</char> <char style="it">Necho</char> killed him at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:19; Zech. 12:11</char></note>Megiddo when he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:8</char></note>confronted him. <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:24; 2 Kin. 22:20</char></note>Then his servants moved his body in a chariot from Megiddo, brought him to Jerusalem, and buried him in his own tomb. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:1–4</char></note>the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, anointed him, and made him king in his father’s place.</para>
	<para style="s">The Reign and Captivity of Jehoahaz</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 3:15; Jer. 22:11</char></note>Jehoahaz <char style="it">was</char> twenty-three years old when he became king, and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:18</char></note>Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. <verse number="32" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his fathers had done. <verse number="33" style="v" />Now Pharaoh Necho put him in prison <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:6; Jer. 52:27</char></note>at Riblah in the land of Hamath, that he might not reign in Jerusalem; and he imposed on the land a tribute of one hundred talents of silver and a talent of gold. <verse number="34" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:4</char></note>Pharaoh Necho made Eliakim the son of Josiah king in place of his father Josiah, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:17; Dan. 1:7</char></note>changed his name to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 1:11</char></note>Jehoiakim. And <char style="it">Pharaoh</char> took Jehoahaz <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 22:11, 12; Ezek. 19:3, 4</char></note>and went to Egypt, and he died there.</para>
	<para style="s">Jehoiakim Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />So Jehoiakim gave <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:33</char></note>the silver and gold to Pharaoh; but he taxed the land to give money according to the command of Pharaoh; he exacted the silver and gold from the people of the land, from every one according to his assessment, to give <char style="it">it</char> to Pharaoh Necho. <verse number="36" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:5; Jer. 22:18, 19; 26:1</char></note>Jehoiakim <char style="it">was</char> twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Zebudah the daughter of Pedaiah of Rumah. <verse number="37" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his fathers had done.</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Judah Overrun by Enemies</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:6; Jer. 25:1, 9; Dan. 1:1</char></note>his days Nebuchadnezzar king of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:14</char></note>Babylon came up, and Jehoiakim became his vassal <char style="it">for</char> three years. Then he turned and rebelled against him. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 25:9; 32:28; 35:11; Ezek. 19:8</char></note>And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sent against him <char style="it">raiding</char> bands of Chaldeans, bands of Syrians, bands of Moabites, and bands of the people of Ammon; He sent them against Judah to destroy it, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:17; 21:12–14; 23:27</char></note>according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He had spoken by His servants the prophets. <verse number="3" style="v" />Surely at the commandment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">this</char> came upon Judah, to remove <char style="it">them</char> from His sight <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:2, 11; 23:26</char></note>because of the sins of Manasseh, according to all that he had done, <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 21:16</char></note>and also because of the innocent blood that he had shed; for he had filled Jerusalem with innocent blood, which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> would not pardon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and all that he did, <char style="it">are</char> they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:6, 8; Jer. 22:18, 19</char></note>So Jehoiakim rested with his fathers. Then Jehoiachin his son reigned in his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 37:5–7</char></note>the king of Egypt did not come out of his land anymore, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 46:2</char></note>the king of Babylon had taken all that belonged to the king of Egypt from the Brook of Egypt to the River Euphrates.</para>
	<para style="s">The Reign and Captivity of Jehoiachin</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 3:16; 2 Chr. 36:9</char></note>Jehoiachin <char style="it">was</char> eighteen years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem three months. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> Nehushta the daughter of Elnathan of Jerusalem. <verse number="9" style="v" />And he did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that his father had done.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:1</char></note>At that time the servants of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up against Jerusalem, and the city was besieged. <verse number="11" style="v" />And Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came against the city, as his servants were besieging it. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 22:24–30; 24:1; 29:1, 2; Ezek. 17:12</char></note>Then Jehoiachin king of Judah, his mother, his servants, his princes, and his officers went out to the king of Babylon; and the king of Babylon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:10</char></note>in the eighth year of his reign, took him prisoner.</para>
	<para style="s">The Captivity of Jerusalem</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:17; Is. 39:6</char></note>And he carried out from there all the treasures of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the treasures of the king’s house, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:2, 3</char></note>cut in pieces all the articles of gold which Solomon king of Israel had made in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 20:5</char></note>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said. <verse number="14" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 3:2, 3; Jer. 24:1</char></note>he carried into captivity all Jerusalem: all the captains and all the mighty men of valor, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:16; Jer. 52:28</char></note>ten thousand captives, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 13:19</char></note>all the craftsmen and smiths. None remained except <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:12</char></note>the poorest people of the land. <verse number="15" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:10;  Esth. 2:6; Jer. 22:24–28; Ezek. 17:12</char></note>he carried Jehoiachin captive to Babylon. The king’s mother, the king’s wives, his officers, and the mighty of the land he carried into captivity from Jerusalem to Babylon. <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 52:28</char></note>All the valiant men, seven thousand, and craftsmen and smiths, one thousand, all <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> strong <char style="it">and</char> fit for war, these the king of Babylon brought captive to Babylon.</para>
	<para style="s">Zedekiah Reigns in Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 37:1</char></note>the king of Babylon made Mattaniah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 3:15; 2 Chr. 36:10</char></note>Jehoiachin’s uncle, king in his place, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:4</char></note>changed his name to Zedekiah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:11; Jer. 52:1</char></note>Zedekiah <char style="it">was</char> twenty-one years old when he became king, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:31</char></note>Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:12</char></note>He also did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to all that Jehoiakim had done. <verse number="20" style="v" />For because of the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">this</char> happened in Jerusalem and Judah, that He finally cast them out from His presence. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:13; Ezek. 17:15</char></note>Then Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon.</para>
	<chapter number="25" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Fall and Captivity of Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now it came to pass <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:17; Jer. 6:6; 34:2; Ezek. 4:2; 24:1, 2; Hab. 1:6</char></note>in the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth <char style="it">day</char> of the month, <char style="it">that</char> Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon and all his army came against Jerusalem and encamped against it; and they built a siege wall against it all around. <verse number="2" style="v" />So the city was besieged until the eleventh year of King Zedekiah. <verse number="3" style="v" />By the ninth <char style="it">day</char> of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:24, 25; Is. 3:1; Jer. 39:2; Lam. 4:9, 10</char></note><char style="it">fourth</char> month the famine had become so severe in the city that there was no food for the people of the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 39:2</char></note>the city wall was broken through, and all the men of war <char style="it">fled</char> at night by way of the gate between two walls, which was by the king’s garden, even though the Chaldeans <char style="it">were</char> still encamped all around against the city. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 39:4–7; Ezek. 12:12</char></note><char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">king</char> went by way of the plain. <verse number="5" style="v" />But the army of the Chaldeans pursued the king, and they overtook him in the plains of Jericho. All his army was scattered from him. <verse number="6" style="v" />So they took the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 23:33; Jer. 52:9</char></note>at Riblah, and they pronounced judgment on him. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then they killed the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 39:7; Ezek. 17:16</char></note>put out the eyes of Zedekiah, bound him with bronze fetters, and took him to Babylon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And in the fifth month, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 52:12</char></note>on the seventh <char style="it">day</char> of the month (which <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:12</char></note>the nineteenth year of King Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon), <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 39:9</char></note>Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard, a servant of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:13; 2 Chr. 36:19; Ps. 79:1; Jer. 7:14</char></note>He burned the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 39:8</char></note>and the king’s house; all the houses of Jerusalem, that is, all the houses of the great, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 17:27</char></note>he burned with fire. <verse number="10" style="v" />And all the army of the Chaldeans who <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">with</char> the captain of the guard <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:13; Neh. 1:3</char></note>broke down the walls of Jerusalem all around.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carried away captive <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 1:9; Jer. 5:19; 39:9</char></note>the rest of the people <char style="it">who</char> remained in the city and the defectors who had deserted to the king of Babylon, with the rest of the multitude. <verse number="12" style="v" />But the captain of the guard <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:14; Jer. 39:10; 40:7; 52:16</char></note>left <char style="it">some</char> of the poor of the land as vinedressers and farmers. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 52:17</char></note>The bronze <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:15</char></note>pillars that <char style="it">were</char> in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:27</char></note>the carts and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:23</char></note>the bronze Sea that <char style="it">were</char> in the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the Chaldeans broke in pieces, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:17; Jer. 27:19–22</char></note>carried their bronze to Babylon. <verse number="14" style="v" />They also took away <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:3; 1 Kin. 7:45</char></note>the pots, the shovels, the trimmers, the spoons, and all the bronze utensils with which the priests ministered. <verse number="15" style="v" />The firepans and the basins, the things of solid gold and solid silver, the captain of the guard took away. <verse number="16" style="v" />The two pillars, one Sea, and the carts, which Solomon had made for the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:47</char></note>the bronze of all these articles was beyond measure. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 7:15–22; Jer. 52:21</char></note>The height of one pillar <char style="it">was</char> eighteen cubits, and the capital on it <char style="it">was</char> of bronze. The height of the capital was three cubits, and the network and pomegranates all around the capital were all of bronze. The second pillar was the same, with a network.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 39:9–13; 52:12–16, 24</char></note>And the captain of the guard took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:14; Ezra 7:1</char></note>Seraiah the chief priest, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 21:1; 29:25, 29</char></note>Zephaniah the second priest, and the three doorkeepers. <verse number="19" style="v" />He also took out of the city an officer who had charge of the men of war, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 1:14; Jer. 52:25</char></note>five men of the king’s close associates who were found in the city, the chief recruiting officer of the army, who mustered the people of the land, and sixty men of the people of the land <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> found in the city. <verse number="20" style="v" />So Nebuzaradan, captain of the guard, took these and brought them to the king of Babylon at Riblah. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then the king of Babylon struck them and put them to death at Riblah in the land of Hamath. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:33; Deut. 28:36, 64; 2 Kin. 23:27</char></note>Thus Judah was carried away captive from its own land.</para>
	<para style="s">Gedaliah Made Governor of Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then he made Gedaliah the son of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 22:12</char></note>Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, governor over <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 1:9; Jer. 40:5</char></note>the people who remained in the land of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had left. <verse number="23" style="v" />Now when all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 40:7–9</char></note>captains of the armies, they and <char style="it">their</char> men, heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah governor, they came to Gedaliah at Mizpah—Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, Johanan the son of Careah, Seraiah the son of Tanhumeth the Netophathite, and Jaazaniah the son of a Maachathite, they and their men. <verse number="24" style="v" />And Gedaliah took an oath before them and their men, and said to them, “Do not be afraid of the servants of the Chaldeans. Dwell in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it shall be well with you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 41:1–3</char></note>it happened in the seventh month that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama, of the royal family, came with ten men and struck and killed Gedaliah, the Jews, as well as the Chaldeans who were with him at Mizpah. <verse number="26" style="v" />And all the people, small and great, and the captains of the armies, arose <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:31; Jer. 43:4–7</char></note>and went to Egypt; for they were afraid of the Chaldeans.</para>
	<para style="s">Jehoiachin Released from Prison</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:12, 15; Jer. 52:31–34</char></note>Now it came to pass in the thirty-seventh year of the captivity of Jehoiachin king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-seventh <char style="it">day</char> of the month, <char style="it">that</char> Evil-Merodach king of Babylon, in the year that he began to reign, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 40:13, 20</char></note>released Jehoiachin king of Judah from prison. <verse number="28" style="v" />He spoke kindly to him, and gave him a more prominent seat than those of the kings who <char style="it">were</char> with him in Babylon. <verse number="29" style="v" />So Jehoiachin changed from his prison garments, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 9:7</char></note>ate bread regularly before the king all the days of his life. <verse number="30" style="v" />And as for his provisions, <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> a regular ration given him by the king, a portion for each day, all the days of his life.</para>
	
</usx>