<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="DAN" style="id">The Book of Daniel</book>
    <para style="mt">The Book of Daniel</para>
    <chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Daniel and His Friends Obey God</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the third year of the reign of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:1, 2; 2 Chr. 36:5–7; Jer. 25:1; 52:12–30</char></note>Jehoiakim king of Judah, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and besieged it. <verse number="2" style="v" />And the Lord gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:7; Jer. 27:19, 20; Dan. 5:2</char></note>some of the articles of the house of God, which he carried <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 10:10; 11:2; Is. 11:11; Zech. 5:11</char></note>into the land of Shinar to the house of his god; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:7</char></note>and he brought the articles into the treasure house of his god.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then the king instructed Ashpenaz, the master of his eunuchs, to bring <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 20:17, 18; Is. 39:7</char></note>some of the children of Israel and some of the king’s descendants and some of the nobles, <verse number="4" style="v" />young men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 24:19, 20</char></note>in whom <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> no blemish, but good-looking, gifted in all wisdom, possessing knowledge and quick to understand, who <char style="it">had</char> ability to serve in the king’s palace, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 7:22</char></note>whom they might teach the language and literature of the Chaldeans. <verse number="5" style="v" />And the king appointed for them a daily provision of the king’s delicacies and of the wine which he drank, and three years of training for them, so that at the end of <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">time</char> they might <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:46; 1 Sam. 16:22; 1 Kin. 10:8; Dan. 1:19</char></note>serve before the king. <verse number="6" style="v" />Now from among those of the sons of Judah were Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:45; 2 Kin. 24:17</char></note>To them the chief of the eunuchs gave names: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:26; 4:8; 5:12</char></note>he gave Daniel <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">name</char> Belteshazzar; to Hananiah, Shadrach; to Mishael, Meshach; and to Azariah, Abed-Nego.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />But Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not defile himself <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:47; Deut. 32:38; Ezek. 4:13; Hos. 9:3</char></note>with the portion of the king’s delicacies, nor with the wine which he drank; therefore he requested of the chief of the eunuchs that he might not defile himself. <verse number="9" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 39:21; 1 Kin. 8:50; (Job 5:15, 16); Ps. 106:46; (Prov. 16:7); Acts 7:10; 27:3</char></note>God had brought Daniel into the favor and goodwill of the chief of the eunuchs. <verse number="10" style="v" />And the chief of the eunuchs said to Daniel, “I fear my lord the king, who has appointed your food and drink. For why should he see your faces looking worse than the young men who <char style="it">are</char> your age? Then you would endanger my head before the king.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So Daniel said to the steward whom the chief of the eunuchs had set over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, <verse number="12" style="v" />“Please test your servants for ten days, and let them give us vegetables to eat and water to drink. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then let our appearance be examined before you, and the appearance of the young men who eat the portion of the king’s delicacies; and as you see fit, <char style="it">so</char> deal with your servants.” <verse number="14" style="v" />So he consented with them in this matter, and tested them ten days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And at the end of ten days their features appeared better and fatter in flesh than all the young men who ate the portion of the king’s delicacies. <verse number="16" style="v" />Thus the steward took away their portion of delicacies and the wine that they were to drink, and gave them vegetables.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />As for these four young men, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:12, 28; 2 Chr. 1:10–12; (Luke 21:15; James 1:5–7)</char></note>God gave them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 7:22</char></note>knowledge and skill in all literature and wisdom; and Daniel had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 12:6; 2 Chr. 26:5; Dan. 5:11, 12, 14; 10:1</char></note>understanding in all visions and dreams.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Now at the end of the days, when the king had said that they should be brought in, the chief of the eunuchs brought them in before Nebuchadnezzar. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then the king interviewed them, and among them all none was found like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah; therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:46; (Prov. 22:29); Dan. 1:5</char></note>they served before the king. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:1</char></note>And in all matters of wisdom <char style="it">and</char> understanding about which the king examined them, he found them ten times better than all the magicians <char style="it">and</char> astrologers who <char style="it">were</char> in all his realm. <verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:28; 10:1</char></note>Thus Daniel continued until the first year of King Cyrus.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Nebuchadnezzar’s Dream</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now in the second year of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign, Nebuchadnezzar had dreams; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 40:5–8; 41:1, 8; Job33:15–17; Dan. 2:3; 4:5</char></note>and his spirit was <char style="it">so</char> troubled that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 6:1; Dan. 6:18</char></note>his sleep left him. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:8; Ex. 7:11; Is. 47:12, 13; Dan. 1:20; 2:10, 27; 4:6; 5:7</char></note>Then the king gave the command to call the magicians, the astrologers, the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans to tell the king his dreams. So they came and stood before the king. <verse number="3" style="v" />And the king said to them, “I have had a dream, and my spirit is anxious to know the dream.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Then the Chaldeans spoke to the king in Aramaic, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 1:31; Dan. 3:9; 5:10; 6:6, 21</char></note>“O king, live forever! Tell your servants the dream, and we will give the interpretation.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, “My decision is firm: if you do not make known the dream to me, and its interpretation, you shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 10:27; Ezra 6:11; Dan. 3:29</char></note>cut in pieces, and your houses shall be made an ash heap. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:16</char></note>However, if you tell the dream and its interpretation, you shall receive from me gifts, rewards, and great honor. Therefore tell me the dream and its interpretation.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />They answered again and said, “Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will give its interpretation.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />The king answered and said, “I know for certain that you would gain time, because you see that my decision is firm: <verse number="9" style="v" />if you do not make known the dream to me, <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">only</char> one decree for you! For you have agreed to speak lying and corrupt words before me till the time has changed. Therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that you can give me its interpretation.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />The Chaldeans answered the king, and said, “There is not a man on earth who can tell the king’s matter; therefore no king, lord, or ruler has <char style="it">ever</char> asked such things of any magician, astrologer, or Chaldean. <verse number="11" style="v" /><char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> a difficult thing that the king requests, and there is no other who can tell it to the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:39; Dan. 5:11</char></note>except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />For this reason the king was angry and very furious, and gave the command to destroy all the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon. <verse number="13" style="v" />So the decree went out, and they began killing the wise <char style="it">men;</char> and they sought <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:19, 20</char></note>Daniel and his companions, to kill <char style="it">them.</char></para>
	<para style="s">God Reveals Nebuchadnezzar’s Dream</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then with counsel and wisdom Daniel answered Arioch, the captain of the king’s guard, who had gone out to kill the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon; <verse number="15" style="v" />he answered and said to Arioch the king’s captain, “Why is the decree from the king so urgent?” Then Arioch made the decision known to Daniel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So Daniel went in and asked the king to give him time, that he might tell the king the interpretation. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then Daniel went to his house, and made the decision known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions, <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 9:9; Matt. 18:19)</char></note>that they might seek mercies from the God of heaven concerning this secret, so that Daniel and his companions might not perish with the rest of the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then the secret was revealed to Daniel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 12:6; Job 33:15; (Prov. 3:32); Amos 3:7</char></note>in a night vision. So Daniel blessed the God of heaven.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Daniel answered and said:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 113:2</char></note>“Blessed be the name of God forever and ever,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Chr. 29:11, 12; Job 12:13; Ps. 147:5; Jer. 32:19; Matt. 6:13; Rom. 11:33)</char></note>For wisdom and might are His.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="21" style="v" />And He changes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 31:15;  Esth. 1:13; Dan. 2:9; 7:25</char></note>the times and the seasons;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 12:18; (Ps. 75:6, 7; Jer. 27:5; Dan. 4:35)</char></note>He removes kings and raises up kings;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 3:9, 10; 4:29; (James 1:5)</char></note>He gives wisdom to the wise</para>
	<para style="q2">And knowledge to those who have understanding.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 12:22; Ps. 25:14; (Prov. 3:22)</char></note>He reveals deep and secret things;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 26:6; Ps. 139:12; (Is. 45:7; Jer. 23:24; Heb. 4:13)</char></note>He knows what <char style="it">is</char> in the darkness,</para>
	<para style="q2">And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 36:9); Dan. 5:11, 14; (1 Tim. 6:16; James 1:17; 1 John 1:5)</char></note>light dwells with Him.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="23" style="v" />“I thank You and praise You,</para>
	<para style="q2">O God of my fathers;</para>
	<para style="q2">You have given me wisdom and might,</para>
	<para style="q2">And have now made known to me what we <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 21:2, 4; Dan. 2:18, 29, 30</char></note>asked of You,</para>
	<para style="q2">For You have made known to us the king’s demand.”</para>
	<para style="s">Daniel Explains the Dream</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Therefore Daniel went to Arioch, whom the king had appointed to destroy the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon. He went and said thus to him: “Do not destroy the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon; take me before the king, and I will tell the king the interpretation.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Then Arioch quickly brought Daniel before the king, and said thus to him, “I have found a man of the captives of Judah, who will make known to the king the interpretation.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name <char style="it">was</char> Belteshazzar, “Are you able to make known to me the dream which I have seen, and its interpretation?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />Daniel answered in the presence of the king, and said, “The secret which the king has demanded, the wise <char style="it">men,</char> the astrologers, the magicians, and the soothsayers cannot declare to the king. <verse number="28" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 40:8; Amos 4:13</char></note>But there is a God in heaven who reveals secrets, and He has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 49:1; Is. 2:2; Dan. 10:14; Mic. 4:1</char></note>what will be in the latter days. Your dream, and the visions of your head upon your bed, were these: <verse number="29" style="v" />As for you, O king, thoughts came <char style="it">to</char> your <char style="it">mind</char> <char style="it">while</char> on your bed, <char style="it">about</char> what would come to pass after this; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 2:22, 28)</char></note>and He who reveals secrets has made known to you what will be. <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 3:12</char></note>But as for me, this secret has not been revealed to me because I have more wisdom than anyone living, but for <char style="it">our</char> sakes who make known the interpretation to the king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:47</char></note>and that you may know the thoughts of your heart.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />“You, O king, were watching; and behold, a great image! This great image, whose splendor <char style="it">was</char> excellent, stood before you; and its form <char style="it">was</char> awesome. <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:38, 45</char></note>This image’s head <char style="it">was</char> of fine gold, its chest and arms of silver, its belly and thighs of bronze, <verse number="33" style="v" />its legs of iron, its feet partly of iron and partly of clay. <verse number="34" style="v" />You watched while a stone was cut out <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:25; (Zech. 4:6); 2 Cor. 5:1; Heb. 9:24</char></note>without hands, which struck the image on its feet of iron and clay, and broke them in pieces. <verse number="35" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:23–27; (Rev. 16:14)</char></note>Then the iron, the clay, the bronze, the silver, and the gold were crushed together, and became <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 1:4; Is. 17:13; 41:15, 16; Hos. 13:3</char></note>like chaff from the summer threshing floors; the wind carried them away so that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 37:10, 36</char></note>no trace of them was found. And the stone that struck the image <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 2:2, 3); Mic. 4:1</char></note>became a great mountain <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 80:9</char></note>and filled the whole earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />“This <char style="it">is</char> the dream. Now we will tell the interpretation of it before the king. <verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 7:12; Is. 47:5; Jer. 27:6, 7; Ezek. 26:7; Hos. 8:10</char></note>You, O king, <char style="it">are</char> a king of kings. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 1:2</char></note>For the God of heaven has given you a kingdom, power, strength, and glory; <verse number="38" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 50:10, 11; Jer. 27:6; Dan. 4:21, 22</char></note>and wherever the children of men dwell, or the beasts of the field and the birds of the heaven, He has given <char style="it">them</char> into your hand, and has made you ruler over them all—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:32</char></note>you <char style="it">are</char> this head of gold. <verse number="39" style="v" />But after you shall arise <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:28, 31</char></note>another kingdom <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:32</char></note>inferior to yours; then another, a third kingdom of bronze, which shall rule over all the earth. <verse number="40" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:7, 23</char></note>the fourth kingdom shall be as strong as iron, inasmuch as iron breaks in pieces and shatters everything; and like iron that crushes, <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">kingdom</char> will break in pieces and crush all the others. <verse number="41" style="v" />Whereas you saw the feet and toes, partly of potter’s clay and partly of iron, the kingdom shall be divided; yet the strength of the iron shall be in it, just as you saw the iron mixed with ceramic clay. <verse number="42" style="v" />And <char style="it">as</char> the toes of the feet <char style="it">were</char> partly of iron and partly of clay, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:24</char></note><char style="it">so</char> the kingdom shall be partly strong and partly fragile. <verse number="43" style="v" />As you saw iron mixed with ceramic clay, they will mingle with the seed of men; but they will not adhere to one another, just as iron does not mix with clay. <verse number="44" style="v" />And in the days of these kings <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:28, 37</char></note>the God of heaven will set up a kingdom <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 9:6, 7; Ezek. 37:25; Dan. 4:3, 34; 6:26; 7:14, 27; Mic. 4:7; (Luke 1:32, 33)</char></note>which shall never be destroyed; and the kingdom shall not be left to other people; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 2:9; Is. 60:12; Dan. 2:34, 35; (1 Cor. 15:24)</char></note>it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, and it shall stand forever. <verse number="45" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:35; Is. 28:16</char></note>Inasmuch as you saw that the stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, and that it broke in pieces the iron, the bronze, the clay, the silver, and the gold—the great God has made known to the king what will come to pass after this. The dream is certain, and its interpretation is sure.”</para>
	<para style="s">Daniel and His Friends Promoted</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 3:5, 7; Acts 10:25; 14:13; Rev. 19:10; 22:8</char></note>Then King Nebuchadnezzar fell on his face, prostrate before Daniel, and commanded that they should present an offering <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:31; Ezra 6:10</char></note>and incense to him. <verse number="47" style="v" />The king answered Daniel, and said, “Truly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 3:28, 29; 4:34–37</char></note>your God <char style="it">is</char> the God of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 10:17)</char></note>gods, the Lord of kings, and a revealer of secrets, since you could reveal this secret.” <verse number="48" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 14:35; 21:1)</char></note>Then the king promoted Daniel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:6</char></note>and gave him many great gifts; and he made him ruler over the whole province of Babylon, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:9; 5:11</char></note>chief administrator over all the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon. <verse number="49" style="v" />Also Daniel petitioned the king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:7; 3:12</char></note>and he set Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego over the affairs of the province of Babylon; but Daniel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 2:19, 21, 3:2; Amos 5:15</char></note><char style="it">sat</char> in the gate of the king.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Image of Gold</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height <char style="it">was</char> sixty cubits <char style="it">and</char> its width six cubits. He set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon. <verse number="2" style="v" />And King Nebuchadnezzar sent <char style="it">word</char> to gather together the satraps, the administrators, the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the magistrates, and all the officials of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image which King Nebuchadnezzar had set up. <verse number="3" style="v" />So the satraps, the administrators, the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the magistrates, and all the officials of the provinces gathered together for the dedication of the image that King Nebuchadnezzar had set up; and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up. <verse number="4" style="v" />Then a herald cried aloud: “To you it is commanded, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:1; 6:25</char></note>O peoples, nations, and languages, <verse number="5" style="v" /><char style="it">that</char> at the time you hear the sound of the horn, flute, harp, lyre, <char style="it">and</char> psaltery, in symphony with all kinds of music, you shall fall down and worship the gold image that King Nebuchadnezzar has set up; <verse number="6" style="v" />and whoever does not fall down and worship shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 29:22; Ezek. 22:18–22; Matt. 13:42, 50; Rev. 9:2; 13:15; 14:11</char></note>be cast immediately into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So at that time, when all the people heard the sound of the horn, flute, harp, <char style="it">and</char> lyre, in symphony with all kinds of music, all the people, nations, and languages fell down <char style="it">and</char> worshiped the gold image which King Nebuchadnezzar had set up.</para>
	<para style="s">Daniel’s Friends Disobey the King</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore at that time certain Chaldeans <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 4:12–16;  Esth. 3:8, 9; Dan. 6:12, 13</char></note>came forward and accused the Jews. <verse number="9" style="v" />They spoke and said to King Nebuchadnezzar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:4; 5:10; 6:6, 21</char></note>“O king, live forever! <verse number="10" style="v" />You, O king, have made a decree that everyone who hears the sound of the horn, flute, harp, lyre, <char style="it">and</char> psaltery, in symphony with all kinds of music, shall fall down and worship the gold image; <verse number="11" style="v" />and whoever does not fall down and worship shall be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:49</char></note>There are certain Jews whom you have set over the affairs of the province of Babylon: Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego; these men, O king, have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:8; 6:12, 13</char></note>not paid due regard to you. They do not serve your gods or worship the gold image which you have set up.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then Nebuchadnezzar, in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:12; 3:19</char></note>rage and fury, gave the command to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego. So they brought these men before the king. <verse number="14" style="v" />Nebuchadnezzar spoke, saying to them, “<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> true, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, <char style="it">that</char> you do not serve my gods or worship the gold image which I have set up? <verse number="15" style="v" />Now if you are ready at the time you hear the sound of the horn, flute, harp, lyre, <char style="it">and</char> psaltery, in symphony with all kinds of music, and you fall down and worship the image which I have made, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:32; Luke 13:9</char></note><char style="it">good!</char> But if you do not worship, you shall be cast immediately into the midst of a burning fiery furnace. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 5:2; 2 Kin. 18:35; Is. 36:18–20; Dan. 2:47</char></note>And who <char style="it">is</char> the god who will deliver you from my hands?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego answered and said to the king, “O Nebuchadnezzar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 10:19)</char></note>we have no need to answer you in this matter. <verse number="17" style="v" />If that <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">case,</char> our <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 5:19; (Ps. 27:1, 2; Is. 26:3, 4); Jer. 1:8; 15:20, 21; Dan. 6:19–22</char></note>God whom we serve is able to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 17:37; Jer. 1:8; 15:20, 21; 42:11; Dan. 6:16, 19–22; Mic. 7:7; 2 Cor. 1:10</char></note>deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and He will deliver <char style="it">us</char> from your hand, O king. <verse number="18" style="v" />But if not, let it be known to you, O king, that we do not serve your gods, nor will we <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 13:15</char></note>worship the gold image which you have set up.”</para>
	<para style="s">Saved in Fiery Trial</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then Nebuchadnezzar was full of fury, and the expression on his face changed toward Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego. He spoke and commanded that they heat the furnace seven times more than it was usually heated. <verse number="20" style="v" />And he commanded certain mighty men of valor who <char style="it">were</char> in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, <char style="it">and</char> cast <char style="it">them</char> into the burning fiery furnace. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then these men were bound in their coats, their trousers, their turbans, and their <char style="it">other</char> garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace. <verse number="22" style="v" />Therefore, because the king’s command was urgent, and the furnace exceedingly hot, the flame of the fire killed those men who took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego. <verse number="23" style="v" />And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Then King Nebuchadnezzar was astonished; and he rose in haste <char style="it">and</char> spoke, saying to his counselors, “Did we not cast three men bound into the midst of the fire?”</para>
	<para style="p">They answered and said to the king, “True, O king.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />“Look!” he answered, “I see four men loose, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 91:3–9); Is. 43:2</char></note>walking in the midst of the fire; and they are not hurt, and the form of the fourth is like <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 1:6; 38:7; (Ps. 34:7); Dan. 3:28</char></note>the Son of God.”</para>
	<para style="s">Nebuchadnezzar Praises God</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then Nebuchadnezzar went near the mouth of the burning fiery furnace <char style="it">and</char> spoke, saying, “Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, servants of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 4:2, 3, 17, 34, 35)</char></note>Most High God, come out, and come <char style="it">here.</char>” Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego came from the midst of the fire. <verse number="27" style="v" />And the satraps, administrators, governors, and the king’s counselors gathered together, and they saw these men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 43:2); Heb. 11:34</char></note>on whose bodies the fire had no power; the hair of their head was not singed nor were their garments affected, and the smell of fire was not on them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Nebuchadnezzar spoke, saying, “Blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, who sent His <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 34:7, 8); Is. 37:36; (Jer. 17:7); Dan. 6:22, 23; Acts 5:19; 12:7</char></note>Angel and delivered His servants who trusted in Him, and they have frustrated the king’s word, and yielded their bodies, that they should not serve nor worship any god except their own God! <verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:26</char></note>Therefore I make a decree that any people, nation, or language which speaks anything amiss against the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:46, 47; 4:34–37</char></note>God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 6:11; Dan. 2:5</char></note>cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made an ash heap; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:27</char></note>because there is no other God who can deliver like this.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego in the province of Babylon.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Nebuchadnezzar’s Second Dream</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Nebuchadnezzar the king,</para>
	<para style="p"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 4:17; Dan. 3:4; 6:25</char></note>To all peoples, nations, and languages that dwell in all the earth:</para>
	<para style="p">Peace be multiplied to you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />I thought it good to declare the signs and wonders <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 3:26</char></note>that the Most High God has worked for me.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:16; Ps. 89:35–37; Dan. 6:27; 7:13, 14; (Luke 1:31–33)</char></note>How great <char style="it">are</char> His signs,</para>
	<para style="q2">And how mighty His wonders!</para>
	<para style="q2">His kingdom <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 2:44; 4:34; 6:26)</char></note>an everlasting kingdom,</para>
	<para style="q2">And His dominion <char style="it">is</char> from generation to generation.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />I, Nebuchadnezzar, was at rest in my house, and flourishing in my palace. <verse number="5" style="v" />I saw a dream which made me afraid, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:28, 29</char></note>and the thoughts on my bed and the visions of my head <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:1</char></note>troubled me. <verse number="6" style="v" />Therefore I issued a decree to bring in all the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon before me, that they might make known to me the interpretation of the dream. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:2</char></note>Then the magicians, the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers came in, and I told them the dream; but they did not make known to me its interpretation. <verse number="8" style="v" />But at last Daniel came before me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:7</char></note>(his name <char style="it">is</char> Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 63:11; Dan. 2:11; 4:18; 5:11, 14</char></note>in him <char style="it">is</char> the Spirit of the Holy God), and I told the dream before him, <char style="it">saying:</char> <verse number="9" style="v" />“Belteshazzar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:48; 5:11</char></note>chief of the magicians, because I know that the Spirit of the Holy God <char style="it">is</char> in you, and no secret troubles you, explain to me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and its interpretation.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />“These <char style="it">were</char> the visions of my head <char style="it">while</char> on my bed:</para>
	<para style="q1">I was looking, and behold,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 31:3; Dan. 4:20</char></note>A tree in the midst of the earth,</para>
	<para style="q2">And its height was great.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="11" style="v" />The tree grew and became strong;</para>
	<para style="q2">Its height reached to the heavens,</para>
	<para style="q2">And it could be seen to the ends of all the earth.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="12" style="v" />Its leaves <char style="it">were</char> lovely,</para>
	<para style="q2">Its fruit abundant,</para>
	<para style="q2">And in it <char style="it">was</char> food for all.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 27:6; Ezek. 17:23; 31:6; Lam. 4:20</char></note>The beasts of the field found shade under it,</para>
	<para style="q2">The birds of the heavens dwelt in its branches,</para>
	<para style="q2">And all flesh was fed from it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />“I saw in the visions of my head <char style="it">while</char> on my bed, and there was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 4:17, 23)</char></note>a watcher, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 33:2; Ps. 89:7; Dan. 8:13; Zech. 14:5; Jude 14</char></note>a holy one, coming down from heaven. <verse number="14" style="v" />He cried aloud and said thus:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 31:10–14; Dan. 4:23; (Matt. 3:10; 7:19; Luke 13:7–9)</char></note>‘Chop down the tree and cut off its branches,</para>
	<para style="q2">Strip off its leaves and scatter its fruit.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 31:12, 13; Dan. 4:12</char></note>Let the beasts get out from under it,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the birds from its branches.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="15" style="v" />Nevertheless leave the stump and roots in the earth,</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">Bound</char> with a band of iron and bronze,</para>
	<para style="q2">In the tender grass of the field.</para>
	<para style="q2">Let it be wet with the dew of heaven,</para>
	<para style="q2">And <char style="it">let</char> him graze with the beasts</para>
	<para style="q2">On the grass of the earth.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="16" style="v" />Let his heart be changed from <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">of</char> a man,</para>
	<para style="q2">Let him be given the heart of a beast,</para>
	<para style="q2">And let seven <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:13; 12:7</char></note>times pass over him.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="17" style="v" />‘This decision <char style="it">is</char> by the decree of the watchers,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the sentence by the word of the holy ones,</para>
	<para style="q2">In order <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 9:16; 83:18</char></note>that the living may know</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:21; 4:25, 32; 5:21</char></note>That the Most High rules in the kingdom of men,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 27:5–7; Ezek. 29:18–20; Dan. 2:37; 5:18</char></note>Gives it to whomever He will,</para>
	<para style="q2">And sets over it the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:8; Dan. 11:21</char></note>lowest of men.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />“This dream I, King Nebuchadnezzar, have seen. Now you, Belteshazzar, declare its interpretation, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:8, 15; Dan. 5:8, 15</char></note>since all the wise <char style="it">men</char> of my kingdom are not able to make known to me the interpretation; but you <char style="it">are</char> able, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:8, 9; 5:11, 14</char></note>for the Spirit of the Holy God <char style="it">is</char> in you.”</para>
	<para style="s">Daniel Explains the Second Dream</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then Daniel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:8</char></note>whose name <char style="it">was</char> Belteshazzar, was astonished for a time, and his thoughts <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 4:19; Dan. 7:15, 28; 8:27</char></note>troubled him. <char style="it">So</char> the king spoke, and said, “Belteshazzar, do not let the dream or its interpretation trouble you.” Belteshazzar answered and said, “My lord, <char style="it">may</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 18:32; Jer. 29:7; Dan. 4:24; 10:16</char></note>the dream concern those who hate you, and its interpretation concern your enemies!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:10–12</char></note>“The tree that you saw, which grew and became strong, whose height reached to the heavens and which <char style="it">could</char> <char style="it">be</char> seen by all the earth, <verse number="21" style="v" />whose leaves <char style="it">were</char> lovely and its fruit abundant, in which <char style="it">was</char> food for all, under which the beasts of the field dwelt, and in whose branches the birds of the heaven had their home— <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:37, 38</char></note>it <char style="it">is</char> you, O king, who have grown and become strong; for your greatness has grown and reaches to the heavens, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 27:6–8</char></note>and your dominion to the end of the earth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:13–15</char></note>“And inasmuch as the king saw a watcher, a holy one, coming down from heaven and saying, ‘Chop down the tree and destroy it, but leave its stump and roots in the earth, <char style="it">bound</char> with a band of iron and bronze in the tender grass of the field; let it be wet with the dew of heaven, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:21</char></note>and let him graze with the beasts of the field, till seven times pass over him’; <verse number="24" style="v" />this is the interpretation, O king, and this is the decree of the Most High, which has come upon my lord the king: <verse number="25" style="v" />They shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:32; 5:21</char></note>drive you from men, your dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field, and they shall make you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:20</char></note>eat grass like oxen. They shall wet you with the dew of heaven, and seven times shall pass over you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:18; Dan. 4:2, 17, 32</char></note>till you know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 27:5</char></note>gives it to whomever He chooses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />“And inasmuch as they gave the command to leave the stump <char style="it">and</char> roots of the tree, your kingdom shall be assured to you, after you come to know that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 21:25; Luke 15:18</char></note>Heaven rules. <verse number="27" style="v" />Therefore, O king, let my advice be acceptable to you; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 28:13); Is. 55:7; Ezek. 18:21, 22; (Rom. 2:9–11; 1 Pet. 4:8)</char></note>break off your sins by <char style="it">being</char> righteous, and your iniquities by showing mercy to <char style="it">the</char> poor. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 41:1–3); Is. 58:6, 7, 10</char></note>Perhaps there may be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 21:29</char></note>a lengthening of your prosperity.”</para>
	<para style="s">Nebuchadnezzar’s Humiliation</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />All <char style="it">this</char> came upon King Nebuchadnezzar. <verse number="29" style="v" />At the end of the twelve months he was walking about the royal palace of Babylon. <verse number="30" style="v" />The king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 16:18; Is. 13:19; Dan. 5:20</char></note>spoke, saying, “Is not this great Babylon, that I have built for a royal dwelling by my mighty power and for the honor of my majesty?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:5; Luke 12:20</char></note>While the word <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">still</char> in the king’s mouth, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:24</char></note>a voice fell from heaven: “King Nebuchadnezzar, to you it is spoken: the kingdom has departed from you! <verse number="32" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 4:25)</char></note>they shall drive you from men, and your dwelling <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> with the beasts of the field. They shall make you eat grass like oxen; and seven times shall pass over you, until you know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever He chooses.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />That very hour the word was fulfilled concerning Nebuchadnezzar; he was driven from men and ate grass like oxen; his body was wet with the dew of heaven till his hair had grown like eagles’ <char style="it">feathers</char> and his nails like birds’ <char style="it">claws.</char></para>
	<para style="s">Nebuchadnezzar Praises God</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:26</char></note>at the end of the time I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted my eyes to heaven, and my understanding returned to me; and I blessed the Most High and praised and honored Him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 102:24–27; Dan. 6:26; 12:7; (Rev. 4:10)</char></note>who lives forever:</para>
	<para style="q1">For His dominion <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 10:16); Dan. 2:44; 7:14; Mic. 4:7; (Luke 1:33)</char></note>an everlasting dominion,</para>
	<para style="q2">And His kingdom <char style="it">is</char> from generation to generation.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="35" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 39:5; Is. 40:15, 17</char></note>All the inhabitants of the earth <char style="it">are</char> reputed as nothing;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 115:3; 135:6; Dan. 6:27</char></note>He does according to His will in the army of heaven</para>
	<para style="q2">And <char style="it">among</char> the inhabitants of the earth.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 34:29; Is. 43:13</char></note>No one can restrain His hand</para>
	<para style="q2">Or say to Him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 9:12; Is. 45:9; Jer. 18:6; Rom. 9:20; (1 Cor. 2:16)</char></note>“What have You done?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />At the same time my reason returned to me, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:26</char></note>and for the glory of my kingdom, my honor and splendor returned to me. My counselors and nobles resorted to me, I was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 20:20</char></note>restored to my kingdom, and excellent majesty was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 42:12; (Prov. 22:4; Matt. 6:33)</char></note>added to me. <verse number="37" style="v" />Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:46, 47; 3:28, 29</char></note>praise and extol and honor the King of heaven, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:4; (Ps. 33:4); Is. 5:16; (Rev. 15:3)</char></note>all of whose works <char style="it">are</char> truth, and His ways justice. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 18:11; Job 40:11, 12; Dan. 5:20</char></note>And those who walk in pride He is able to put down.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Belshazzar’s Feast</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Belshazzar the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 1:3; Is. 22:12–14</char></note>made a great feast for a thousand of his lords, and drank wine in the presence of the thousand. <verse number="2" style="v" />While he tasted the wine, Belshazzar gave the command to bring the gold and silver vessels <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 24:13; 25:15; Ezra 1:7–11; Jer. 52:19; Dan. 1:2</char></note>which his father Nebuchadnezzar had taken from the temple which <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">been</char> in Jerusalem, that the king and his lords, his wives, and his concubines might drink from them. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then they brought the gold <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:10</char></note>vessels that had been taken from the temple of the house of God which <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">been</char> in Jerusalem; and the king and his lords, his wives, and his concubines drank from them. <verse number="4" style="v" />They drank wine, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 42:8; Dan. 5:23; Rev. 9:20</char></note>and praised the gods of gold and silver, bronze and iron, wood and stone.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:31</char></note>In the same hour the fingers of a man’s hand appeared and wrote opposite the lampstand on the plaster of the wall of the king’s palace; and the king saw the part of the hand that wrote. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then the king’s countenance changed, and his thoughts troubled him, so that the joints of his hips were loosened and his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 7:17; 21:7</char></note>knees knocked against each other. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:6, 7; 5:11, 15</char></note>The king cried aloud to bring in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 47:13</char></note>the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers. The king spoke, saying to the wise <char style="it">men</char> of Babylon, “Whoever reads this writing, and tells me its interpretation, shall be clothed with purple and <char style="it">have</char> a chain of gold around his neck; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:2, 3</char></note>and he shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.” <verse number="8" style="v" />Now all the king’s wise <char style="it">men</char> came, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:8; Dan. 2:27; 4:7; 5:15</char></note>but they could not read the writing, or make known to the king its interpretation. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then King Belshazzar was greatly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 18:11; Is. 21:2–4; Jer. 6:24; Dan. 2:1; 5:6</char></note>troubled, his countenance was changed, and his lords were astonished.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />The queen, because of the words of the king and his lords, came to the banquet hall. The queen spoke, saying, “O king, live forever! Do not let your thoughts trouble you, nor let your countenance change. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:48; 4:8, 9, 18</char></note>There is a man in your kingdom in whom <char style="it">is</char> the Spirit of the Holy God. And in the days of your father, light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods, were found in him; and King Nebuchadnezzar your father—your father the king—made him chief of the magicians, astrologers, Chaldeans, <char style="it">and</char> soothsayers. <verse number="12" style="v" />Inasmuch as an excellent spirit, knowledge, understanding, interpreting dreams, solving riddles, and explaining enigmas were found in this Daniel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:7; 4:8</char></note>whom the king named Belteshazzar, now let Daniel be called, and he will give the interpretation.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Writing on the Wall Explained</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then Daniel was brought in before the king. The king spoke, and said to Daniel, “<char style="it">Are</char> you that Daniel who is one of the captives from Judah, whom my father the king brought from Judah? <verse number="14" style="v" />I have heard of you, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:8, 9, 18; 5:11, 12</char></note>the Spirit of God <char style="it">is</char> in you, and <char style="it">that</char> light and understanding and excellent wisdom are found in you. <verse number="15" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:7, 8</char></note>the wise <char style="it">men,</char> the astrologers, have been brought in before me, that they should read this writing and make known to me its interpretation, but they could not give the interpretation of the thing. <verse number="16" style="v" />And I have heard of you, that you can give interpretations and explain enigmas. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:7, 29</char></note>Now if you can read the writing and make known to me its interpretation, you shall be clothed with purple and <char style="it">have</char> a chain of gold around your neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then Daniel answered, and said before the king, “Let your gifts be for yourself, and give your rewards to another; yet I will read the writing to the king, and make known to him the interpretation. <verse number="18" style="v" />O king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 27:5–7; Dan. 2:37, 38; 4:17, 22, 25</char></note>the Most High God gave Nebuchadnezzar your father a kingdom and majesty, glory and honor. <verse number="19" style="v" />And because of the majesty that He gave him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 27:7</char></note>all peoples, nations, and languages trembled and feared before him. Whomever he wished, he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:12, 13; 3:6</char></note>executed; whomever he wished, he kept alive; whomever he wished, he set up; and whomever he wished, he put down. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 9:17; Job 15:25; Is. 14:13–15; Dan. 4:30, 37</char></note>But when his heart was lifted up, and his spirit was hardened in pride, he was deposed from his kingly throne, and they took his glory from him. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then he was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 30:3–7; Dan. 4:32, 33</char></note>driven from the sons of men, his heart was made like the beasts, and his dwelling <char style="it">was</char> with the wild donkeys. They fed him with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 9:14–16; Ps. 83:17, 18; Ezek. 17:24; (Dan. 4:17, 34, 35)</char></note>till he knew that the Most High God rules in the kingdom of men, and appoints over it whomever He chooses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />“But you his son, Belshazzar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 10:3; 2 Chr. 33:23; 36:12</char></note>have not humbled your heart, although you knew all this. <verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:3, 4</char></note>And you have lifted yourself up against the Lord of heaven. They have brought the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:9; Num. 18:3; Is. 52:11; Heb. 9:21</char></note>vessels of His house before you, and you and your lords, your wives and your concubines, have drunk wine from them. And you have praised the gods of silver and gold, bronze and iron, wood and stone, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 115:5, 6; Is. 37:19; Hab. 2:18, 19; Acts 17:24–26; Rom. 1:21</char></note>which do not see or hear or know; and the God who <char style="it">holds</char> your breath in His hand <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 139:3; Prov. 20:24; (Jer. 10:23)</char></note>and owns all your ways, you have not glorified. <verse number="24" style="v" />Then the fingers of the hand were sent from Him, and this writing was written.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />“And this is the inscription that was written:</para>
	<para style="pc">MENE, MENE, TEKEL, UPHARSIN.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />This <char style="it">is</char> the interpretation of <char style="it">each</char> word. <char style="sls">MENE</char>: God has numbered your kingdom, and finished it; <verse number="27" style="v" /><char style="sls">TEKEL</char>: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 31:6; Ps. 62:9; Jer. 6:30</char></note>You have been weighed in the balances, and found wanting; <verse number="28" style="v" /><char style="sls">PERES</char>: Your kingdom has been divided, and given to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 21:2; Dan. 5:31; 9:1</char></note>Medes and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 6:28; Acts 2:9</char></note>Persians.” <verse number="29" style="v" />Then Belshazzar gave the command, and they clothed Daniel with purple and <char style="it">put</char> a chain of gold around his neck, and made a proclamation concerning him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:7, 16</char></note>that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom.</para>
	<para style="s">Belshazzar’s Fall</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 51:31, 39, 57</char></note>That very night Belshazzar, king of the Chaldeans, was slain. <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:39; 9:1</char></note>And Darius the Mede received the kingdom, <char style="it">being</char> about sixty-two years old.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Plot Against Daniel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom one hundred and twenty satraps, to be over the whole kingdom; <verse number="2" style="v" />and over these, three governors, of whom Daniel <char style="it">was</char> one, that the satraps might give account to them, so that the king would suffer no loss. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then this Daniel distinguished himself above the governors and satraps, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:12</char></note>because an excellent spirit <char style="it">was</char> in him; and the king gave thought to setting him over the whole realm. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Eccl. 4:4</char></note>So the governors and satraps sought to find <char style="it">some</char> charge against Daniel concerning the kingdom; but they could find no charge or fault, because he <char style="it">was</char> faithful; nor was there any error or fault found in him. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then these men said, “We shall not find any charge against this Daniel unless we find <char style="it">it</char> against him concerning the law of his God.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So these governors and satraps thronged before the king, and said thus to him: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 2:3; Dan. 2:4; 6:21</char></note>“King Darius, live forever! <verse number="7" style="v" />All the governors of the kingdom, the administrators and satraps, the counselors and advisors, have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 59:3; 62:4; 64:2–6</char></note>consulted together to establish a royal statute and to make a firm decree, that whoever petitions any god or man for thirty days, except you, O king, shall be cast into the den of lions. <verse number="8" style="v" />Now, O king, establish the decree and sign the writing, so that it cannot be changed, according to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 1:19; 8:8; Dan. 6:12, 15</char></note>law of the Medes and Persians, which does not alter.” <verse number="9" style="v" />Therefore King Darius signed the written decree.</para>
	<para style="s">Daniel in the Lions’ Den</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Now when Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went home. And in his upper room, with his windows open <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:29, 30, 46–48; Ps. 5:7; Jon. 2:4</char></note>toward Jerusalem, he knelt down on his knees <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 55:17; Acts 2:1, 2, 15; (Phil. 4:6); 1 Thess. 5:17, 18</char></note>three times that day, and prayed and gave thanks before his God, as was his custom since early days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then these men assembled and found Daniel praying and making supplication before his God. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 3:8–12; Acts 16:19–21</char></note>And they went before the king, and spoke concerning the king’s decree: “Have you not signed a decree that every man who petitions any god or man within thirty days, except you, O king, shall be cast into the den of lions?”</para>
	<para style="p">The king answered and said, “The thing <char style="it">is</char> true, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 1:19; Dan. 6:8, 15</char></note>according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which does not alter.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So they answered and said before the king, “That Daniel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:6; 5:13</char></note>who is one of the captives from Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 3:8; Dan. 3:12; Acts 5:29</char></note>does not show due regard for you, O king, or for the decree that you have signed, but makes his petition three times a day.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And the king, when he heard <char style="it">these</char> words, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Mark 6:26</char></note>was greatly displeased with himself, and set <char style="it">his</char> heart on Daniel to deliver him; and he labored till the going down of the sun to deliver him. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then these men approached the king, and said to the king, “Know, O king, that <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 8:8; Ps. 94:20, 21; Dan. 6:8, 12</char></note>the law of the Medes and Persians that no decree or statute which the king establishes may be changed.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So the king gave the command, and they brought Daniel and cast <char style="it">him</char> into the den of lions. <char style="it">But</char> the king spoke, saying to Daniel, “Your God, whom you serve continually, He will deliver you.” <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lam. 3:53</char></note>Then a stone was brought and laid on the mouth of the den, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 27:66</char></note>and the king sealed it with his own signet ring and with the signets of his lords, that the purpose concerning Daniel might not be changed.</para>
	<para style="s">Daniel Saved from the Lions</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Now the king went to his palace and spent the night fasting; and no musicians were brought before him. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Esth. 6:1; Ps. 77:4; Dan. 2:1</char></note>Also his sleep went from him. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 3:24</char></note>king arose very early in the morning and went in haste to the den of lions. <verse number="20" style="v" />And when he came to the den, he cried out with a lamenting voice to Daniel. The king spoke, saying to Daniel, “Daniel, servant of the living God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:14; Num. 11:23; Jer. 32:17; Dan. 3:17; (Luke 1:37)</char></note>has your God, whom you serve continually, been able to deliver you from the lions?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then Daniel said to the king, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:4; 6:6</char></note>“O king, live forever! <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 20:16; Is. 63:9; Dan. 3:28; Acts 12:11; (Heb. 1:14)</char></note>My God sent His angel and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 91:11–13; 2 Tim. 4:17; Heb. 11:33</char></note>shut the lions’ mouths, so that they have not hurt me, because I was found innocent before Him; and also, O king, I have done no wrong before you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Now the king was exceedingly glad for him, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no injury whatever was found on him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Heb. 11:33</char></note>because he believed in his God.</para>
	<para style="s">Darius Honors God</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />And the king gave the command, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 19:18, 19;  Esth. 7:10</char></note>and they brought those men who had accused Daniel, and they cast <char style="it">them</char> into the den of lions—them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 24:16; 2 Kin. 14:6;  Esth. 9:10</char></note>their children, and their wives; and the lions overpowered them, and broke all their bones in pieces before they ever came to the bottom of the den.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 1:1, 2;  Esth. 3:12; 8:9; Dan. 4:1</char></note>Then King Darius wrote:</para>
	<para style="p">To all peoples, nations, and languages that dwell in all the earth:</para>
	<para style="p">Peace be multiplied to you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 6:8–12; 7:13; Dan. 3:29</char></note>I make a decree that in every dominion of my kingdom <char style="it">men</char> <char style="it">must</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 99:1</char></note>tremble and fear before the God of Daniel.</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:34; 6:20; Hos. 1:10; Rom. 9:26</char></note>For He <char style="it">is</char> the living God,</para>
	<para style="q2">And steadfast forever;</para>
	<para style="q2">His kingdom <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">one</char> which shall not be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:44; 4:3; 7:14, 27; (Luke 1:33)</char></note>destroyed,</para>
	<para style="q2">And His dominion <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">endure</char> to the end.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="27" style="v" />He delivers and rescues,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:2, 3</char></note>And He works signs and wonders</para>
	<para style="q2">In heaven and on earth,</para>
	<para style="q2">Who has delivered Daniel from the power of the lions.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />So this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:21</char></note>and in the reign of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 1:1, 2</char></note>Cyrus the Persian.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Vision of the Four Beasts</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 12:6; (Amos 3:7)</char></note>Daniel had a dream and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 2:28)</char></note>visions of his head <char style="it">while</char> on his bed. Then he wrote down the dream, telling the main facts.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Daniel spoke, saying, “I saw in my vision by night, and behold, the four winds of heaven were stirring up the Great Sea. <verse number="3" style="v" />And four great beasts <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:17; Rev. 13:1; 17:8</char></note>came up from the sea, each different from the other. <verse number="4" style="v" />The first <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:49; 2 Sam. 1:23; Jer. 48:40; Ezek. 17:3; Hab. 1:8</char></note>like a lion, and had eagle’s wings. I watched till its wings were plucked off; and it was lifted up from the earth and made to stand on two feet like a man, and a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:16, 34</char></note>man’s heart was given to it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:39</char></note>“And suddenly another beast, a second, like a bear. It was raised up on one side, and <char style="it">had</char> three ribs in its mouth between its teeth. And they said thus to it: ‘Arise, devour much flesh!’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />“After this I looked, and there was another, like a leopard, which had on its back four wings of a bird. The beast also had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:8, 22</char></note>four heads, and dominion was given to it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />“After this I saw in the night visions, and behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:40</char></note>a fourth beast, dreadful and terrible, exceedingly strong. It had huge iron teeth; it was devouring, breaking in pieces, and trampling the residue with its feet. It <char style="it">was</char> different from all the beasts that <char style="it">were</char> before it, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:41; Rev. 12:3; 13:1</char></note>and it had ten horns. <verse number="8" style="v" />I was considering the horns, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:9</char></note>there was another horn, a little one, coming up among them, before whom three of the first horns were plucked out by the roots. And there, in this horn, <char style="it">were</char> eyes like the eyes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 9:7</char></note>of a man, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 12:3; Rev. 13:5, 6</char></note>and a mouth speaking pompous words.</para>
	<para style="s">Vision of the Ancient of Days</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="9" style="v" />“I<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rev. 20:4)</char></note> watched till thrones were put in place,</para>
	<para style="q2">And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 90:2</char></note>the Ancient of Days was seated;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 104:2; Rev. 1:14</char></note>His garment <char style="it">was</char> white as snow,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the hair of His head <char style="it">was</char> like pure wool.</para>
	<para style="q2">His throne <char style="it">was</char> a fiery flame,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 1:15</char></note>Its wheels a burning fire;</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 50:3; Is. 30:33; 66:15</char></note>A fiery stream issued</para>
	<para style="q2">And came forth from before Him.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 33:2; 1 Kin. 22:19; Ps. 68:17; Rev. 5:11</char></note>A thousand thousands ministered to Him;</para>
	<para style="q2">Ten thousand times ten thousand stood before Him.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 12:1; (Rev. 20:11–15)</char></note>The court was seated,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the books were opened.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />“I watched then because of the sound of the pompous words which the horn was speaking; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rev. 19:20; 20:10)</char></note>I watched till the beast was slain, and its body destroyed and given to the burning flame. <verse number="12" style="v" />As for the rest of the beasts, they had their dominion taken away, yet their lives were prolonged for a season and a time.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="13" style="v" />“I was watching in the night visions,</para>
	<para style="q2">And behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 1:26; (Matt. 24:30; 26:64; Mark 13:26; 14:62; Luke 21:27; Rev. 1:7, 13; 14:14)</char></note><char style="it">One</char> like the Son of Man,</para>
	<para style="q2">Coming with the clouds of heaven!</para>
	<para style="q2">He came to the Ancient of Days,</para>
	<para style="q2">And they brought Him near before Him.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 2:6–8; Dan. 7:27; (Matt. 28:18; John 3:35, 36; 1 Cor. 15:27; Eph. 1:22; Phil. 2:9–11; Rev. 1:6; 11:15)</char></note>Then to Him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom,</para>
	<para style="q2">That all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 3:4</char></note>peoples, nations, and languages should serve Him.</para>
	<para style="q2">His dominion <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 145:13; Mic. 4:7; (Luke 1:33); John 12:34; Heb. 12:28</char></note>an everlasting dominion,</para>
	<para style="q2">Which shall not pass away,</para>
	<para style="q2">And His kingdom <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">one</char></para>
	<para style="q2">Which shall not be destroyed.</para>
	<para style="s">Daniel’s Visions Interpreted</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />“I, Daniel, was grieved in my spirit within <char style="it">my</char> body, and the visions of my head troubled me. <verse number="16" style="v" />I came near to one of those who stood by, and asked him the truth of all this. So he told me and made known to me the interpretation of these things: <verse number="17" style="v" />‘Those great beasts, which are four, <char style="it">are</char> four kings <char style="it">which</char> arise out of the earth. <verse number="18" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 149:5–9; Is. 60:12–14; Dan. 7:14; (2 Tim. 2:11; Rev. 2:26, 27; 20:4; 22:5)</char></note>the saints of the Most High shall receive the kingdom, and possess the kingdom forever, even forever and ever.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />“Then I wished to know the truth about the fourth beast, which was different from all the others, exceedingly dreadful, <char style="it">with</char> its teeth of iron and its nails of bronze, <char style="it">which</char> devoured, broke in pieces, and trampled the residue with its feet; <verse number="20" style="v" />and the ten horns that <char style="it">were</char> on its head, and the other <char style="it">horn</char> which came up, before which three fell, namely, that horn which had eyes and a mouth which spoke pompous words, whose appearance <char style="it">was</char> greater than his fellows.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />“I was watching; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 11:7; 13:7; 17:14</char></note>and the same horn was making war against the saints, and prevailing against them, <verse number="22" style="v" />until the Ancient of Days came, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rev. 1:6)</char></note>and a judgment was made <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">favor</char> of the saints of the Most High, and the time came for the saints to possess the kingdom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />“Thus he said:</para>
	<para style="q1">‘The fourth beast shall be</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:40</char></note>A fourth kingdom on earth,</para>
	<para style="q2">Which shall be different from all <char style="it">other</char> kingdoms,</para>
	<para style="q2">And shall devour the whole earth,</para>
	<para style="q2">Trample it and break it in pieces.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:7; Rev. 13:1; 17:12</char></note>The ten horns <char style="it">are</char> ten kings</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">Who</char> shall arise from this kingdom.</para>
	<para style="q2">And another shall rise after them;</para>
	<para style="q2">He shall be different from the first <char style="it">ones,</char></para>
	<para style="q2">And shall subdue three kings.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 37:23; Dan. 11:36; Rev. 13:1–6</char></note>He shall speak <char style="it">pompous</char> words against the Most High,</para>
	<para style="q2">Shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 17:6</char></note>persecute the saints of the Most High,</para>
	<para style="q2">And shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 2:21</char></note>intend to change times and law.</para>
	<para style="q2">Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 13:7; 18:24</char></note><char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">saints</char> shall be given into his hand</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 12:7; Rev. 12:14</char></note>For a time and times and half a time.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v" />‘But<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Dan. 2:35; 7:10, 22)</char></note> the court shall be seated,</para>
	<para style="q2">And they shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 19:20</char></note>take away his dominion,</para>
	<para style="q2">To consume and destroy <char style="it">it</char> forever.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="27" style="v" />Then the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 54:3; Dan. 7:14, 18, 22; Rev. 20:4</char></note>kingdom and dominion,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven,</para>
	<para style="q2">Shall be given to the people, the saints of the Most High.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 7:16; Ps. 89:35–37; Is. 9:7; Dan. 2:44; 4:34; 7:14; (Luke 1:33, 34); John 12:34; (Rev. 11:15; 22:5)</char></note>His kingdom <char style="it">is</char> an everlasting kingdom,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 2:6–12; 22:27; 72:11; 86:9; Is. 60:12; Rev. 11:1</char></note>And all dominions shall serve and obey Him.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />“This <char style="it">is</char> the end of the account. As for me, Daniel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:27</char></note>my thoughts greatly troubled me, and my countenance changed; but I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 2:19, 51</char></note>kept the matter in my heart.”</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Vision of a Ram and a Goat</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the third year of the reign of King Belshazzar a vision appeared <char style="it">to</char> me—to me, Daniel—after the one that appeared to me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:1</char></note>the first time. <verse number="2" style="v" />I saw in the vision, and it so happened while I was looking, that I <char style="it">was</char> in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 1:1; Esth. 1:2, 2:8</char></note>Shushan, the citadel, which <char style="it">is</char> in the province of Elam; and I saw in the vision that I was by the River Ulai. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then I lifted my eyes and saw, and there, standing beside the river, was a ram which had two horns, and the two horns <char style="it">were</char> high; but one <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:5</char></note>higher than the other, and the higher <char style="it">one</char> came up last. <verse number="4" style="v" />I saw the ram pushing westward, northward, and southward, so that no animal could withstand him; nor <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">any</char> that could deliver from his hand, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:19</char></note>but he did according to his will and became great.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />And as I was considering, suddenly a male goat came from the west, across the surface of the whole earth, without touching the ground; and the goat <char style="it">had</char> a notable <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:8, 21; 11:3</char></note>horn between his eyes. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then he came to the ram that had two horns, which I had seen standing beside the river, and ran at him with furious power. <verse number="7" style="v" />And I saw him confronting the ram; he was moved with rage against him, attacked the ram, and broke his two horns. There was no power in the ram to withstand him, but he cast him down to the ground and trampled him; and there was no one that could deliver the ram from his hand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore the male goat grew very great; but when he became strong, the large horn was broken, and in place of it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:6; 8:22; 11:4</char></note>four notable ones came up toward the four winds of heaven. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:21</char></note>And out of one of them came a little horn which grew exceedingly great toward the south, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:25</char></note>toward the east, and toward the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 48:2</char></note>Glorious <char style="it">Land.</char> <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:28</char></note>And it grew up to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 14:13; Jer. 48:26</char></note>the host of heaven; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 12:4</char></note>it cast down <char style="it">some</char> of the host and <char style="it">some</char> of the stars to the ground, and trampled them. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:22, 23; 2 Chr. 32:15–17; Is. 37:23; Dan. 8:25; 11:36, 37</char></note>He even exalted <char style="it">himself</char> as high as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:14</char></note>the Prince of the host; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 46:14; Dan. 11:31; 12:11</char></note>and by him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:38</char></note>the daily <char style="it">sacrifices</char> were taken away, and the place of His sanctuary was cast down. <verse number="12" style="v" />Because of transgression, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:31</char></note>an army was given over <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">horn</char> to oppose the daily <char style="it">sacrifices;</char> and he cast <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 119:43; Is. 59:14</char></note>truth down to the ground. He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:4; 11:36</char></note>did <char style="it">all</char> <char style="it">this</char> and prospered.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then I heard <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:13, 23; 1 Pet. 1:12</char></note>a holy one speaking; and <char style="it">another</char> holy one said to that certain <char style="it">one</char> who was speaking, “How long <char style="it">will</char> the vision <char style="it">be, concerning</char> the daily <char style="it">sacrifices</char> and the transgression of desolation, the giving of both the sanctuary and the host to be trampled underfoot?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />And he said to me, “For two thousand three hundred days; then the sanctuary shall be cleansed.”</para>
	<para style="s">Gabriel Interprets the Vision</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then it happened, when I, Daniel, had seen the vision and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Pet. 1:10</char></note>was seeking the meaning, that suddenly there stood before me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 1:26</char></note>one having the appearance of a man. <verse number="16" style="v" />And I heard a man’s voice <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 12:6, 7</char></note>between <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">banks</char> <char style="it">of</char> the Ulai, who called, and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 9:21; Luke 1:19, 26</char></note>“Gabriel, make this <char style="it">man</char> understand the vision.” <verse number="17" style="v" />So he came near where I stood, and when he came I was afraid and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 1:28; 44:4; Dan. 2:46; Rev. 1:17</char></note>fell on my face; but he said to me, “Understand, son of man, that the vision <char style="it">refers</char> to the time of the end.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:9; Luke 9:32</char></note>Now, as he was speaking with me, I was in a deep sleep with my face to the ground; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 2:2; Dan. 10:10, 16, 18</char></note>but he touched me, and stood me upright. <verse number="19" style="v" />And he said, “Look, I am making known to you what shall happen in the latter time of the indignation; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Hab. 2:3</char></note>for at the appointed time the end <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be.</char> <verse number="20" style="v" />The ram which you saw, having the two horns—<char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">are</char> the kings of Media and Persia. <verse number="21" style="v" />And the male goat <char style="it">is</char> the kingdom of Greece. The large horn that <char style="it">is</char> between its eyes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:3</char></note><char style="it">is</char> the first king. <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:4</char></note>As for the broken <char style="it">horn</char> and the four that stood up in its place, four kingdoms shall arise out of that nation, but not with its power.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="23" style="v" />“And in the latter time of their kingdom,</para>
	<para style="q2">When the transgressors have reached their fullness,</para>
	<para style="q2">A king shall arise,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:50</char></note>Having fierce features,</para>
	<para style="q2">Who understands sinister schemes.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="24" style="v" />His power shall be mighty, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 17:13</char></note>but not by his own power;</para>
	<para style="q2">He shall destroy fearfully,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:36</char></note>And shall prosper and thrive;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:25</char></note>He shall destroy the mighty, and <char style="it">also</char> the holy people.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="25" style="v" />“Through<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:21</char></note> his cunning</para>
	<para style="q2">He shall cause deceit to prosper under his rule;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:11–13; 11:36; 12:7</char></note>And he shall exalt <char style="it">himself</char> in his heart.</para>
	<para style="q2">He shall destroy many in <char style="it">their</char> prosperity.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:36; Rev. 19:19, 20</char></note>He shall even rise against the Prince of princes;</para>
	<para style="q2">But he shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 34:20; Lam. 4:6</char></note>broken without <char style="it">human</char> means.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v" />“And the vision of the evenings and mornings</para>
	<para style="q2">Which was told is true;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 12:27; Dan. 12:4, 9; Rev. 22:10</char></note>Therefore seal up the vision,</para>
	<para style="q2">For <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">refers</char> to many days <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">future.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:28; 8:17; Hab. 3:16</char></note>And I, Daniel, fainted and was sick for days; afterward I arose and went about the king’s business. I was astonished by the vision, but no one understood it.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Daniel’s Prayer for the People</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the first year <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:21</char></note>of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the lineage of the Medes, who was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans— <verse number="2" style="v" />in the first year of his reign I, Daniel, understood by the books the number of the years <char style="it">specified</char> by the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> through <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:21; Ezra 1:1; Jer. 25:11, 12; 29:10; Zech. 7:5</char></note>Jeremiah the prophet, that He would accomplish seventy years in the desolations of Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 1:4; Dan. 6:10; 10:15</char></note>Then I set my face toward the Lord God to make request by prayer and supplications, with fasting, sackcloth, and ashes. <verse number="4" style="v" />And I prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God, and made confession, and said, “O <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:6</char></note>Lord, great and awesome God, who keeps His covenant and mercy with those who love Him, and with those who keep His commandments, <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:47, 48; Neh. 9:33; Ps. 106:6; Is. 64:5–7; Jer. 14:7</char></note>we have sinned and committed iniquity, we have done wickedly and rebelled, even by departing from Your precepts and Your judgments. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:15; Jer. 44:4, 5</char></note>Neither have we heeded Your servants the prophets, who spoke in Your name to our kings and our princes, to our fathers and all the people of the land. <verse number="7" style="v" />O Lord, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 9:33</char></note>righteousness <char style="it">belongs</char> to You, but to us shame of face, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> this day—to the men of Judah, to the inhabitants of Jerusalem and all Israel, those near and those far off in all the countries to which You have driven them, because of the unfaithfulness which they have committed against You.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />“O Lord, to us <char style="it">belongs</char> shame of face, to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, because we have sinned against You. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Neh. 9:17; Ps. 130:4, 7)</char></note>To the Lord our God <char style="it">belong</char> mercy and forgiveness, though we have rebelled against Him. <verse number="10" style="v" />We have not obeyed the voice of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, to walk in His laws, which He set before us by His servants the prophets. <verse number="11" style="v" />Yes, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 1:3–6; Jer. 8:5–10</char></note>all Israel has transgressed Your law, and has departed so as not to obey Your voice; therefore the curse and the oath written in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:14; Neh. 1:6; Ps. 106:6</char></note>Law of Moses the servant of God have been poured out on us, because we have sinned against Him. <verse number="12" style="v" />And He has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 44:26; Jer. 44:2–6; Lam. 2:17; Zech. 1:6</char></note>confirmed His words, which He spoke against us and against our judges who judged us, by bringing upon us a great disaster; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lam. 1:12; 2:13; Ezek. 5:9; (Amos 3:2)</char></note>for under the whole heaven such has never been done as what has been done to Jerusalem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:14–45; Deut.rl 263208 28:15–68; Lam. 2:17</char></note>“As <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> written in the Law of Moses, all this disaster has come upon us; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 36:13; Is. 9:13; Jer. 2:30; Hos. 7:7</char></note>yet we have not made our prayer before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, that we might turn from our iniquities and understand Your truth. <verse number="14" style="v" />Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 31:28; 44:27</char></note>kept the disaster in mind, and brought it upon us; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 9:33</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God <char style="it">is</char> righteous in all the works which He does, though we have not obeyed His voice. <verse number="15" style="v" />And now, O Lord our God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:11; 1 Kin. 8:51; Neh. 1:10</char></note>who brought Your people out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and made Yourself <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:18; Neh. 9:10; Jer. 32:20</char></note>a name, as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> this day—we have sinned, we have done wickedly!</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />“O Lord, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 12:7; Ps. 31:1; Mic. 6:4, 5</char></note>according to all Your righteousness, I pray, let Your anger and Your fury be turned away from Your city Jerusalem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 87:1–3; Dan. 9:20; Joel 3:17; Zech. 8:3</char></note>Your holy mountain; because for our sins, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:5</char></note>and for the iniquities of our fathers, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 122:6; Jer. 29:7; Lam. 2:16</char></note>Jerusalem and Your people <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 79:4</char></note><char style="it">are</char> a reproach to all <char style="it">those</char> around us. <verse number="17" style="v" />Now therefore, our God, hear the prayer of Your servant, and his supplications, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:24–26; Ps. 80:3, 7, 19</char></note>and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lam. 5:18</char></note>for the Lord’s sake cause Your face to shine on Your sanctuary, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(John 16:24)</char></note>which is desolate. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 37:17</char></note>O my God, incline Your ear and hear; open Your eyes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:7</char></note>and see our desolations, and the city <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 25:29</char></note>which is called by Your name; for we do not present our supplications before You because of our righteous deeds, but because of Your great mercies. <verse number="19" style="v" />O Lord, hear! O Lord, forgive! O Lord, listen and act! Do not delay for Your own sake, my God, for Your city and Your people are called by Your name.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Seventy-Weeks Prophecy</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Now while I <char style="it">was</char> speaking, praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God for the holy mountain of my God, <verse number="21" style="v" />yes, while I <char style="it">was</char> speaking in prayer, the man <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:16; Luke 1:19, 26</char></note>Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, being caused to fly swiftly, reached me about the time of the evening offering. <verse number="22" style="v" />And he informed <char style="it">me,</char> and talked with me, and said, “O Daniel, I have now come forth to give you skill to understand. <verse number="23" style="v" />At the beginning of your supplications the command went out, and I have come to tell <char style="it">you,</char> for you <char style="it">are</char> greatly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:11, 19</char></note>beloved; therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 24:15</char></note>consider the matter, and understand the vision:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="24" style="v" />“Seventy weeks are determined</para>
	<para style="q2">For your people and for your holy city,</para>
	<para style="q2">To finish the transgression,</para>
	<para style="q2">To make an end of sins,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 29:24; (Is. 53:10); Acts 10:43; (Rom. 5:10); Heb. 9:12, 14</char></note>To make reconciliation for iniquity,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 14:6</char></note>To bring in everlasting righteousness,</para>
	<para style="q2">To seal up vision and prophecy,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 45:7</char></note>And to anoint the Most Holy.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="25" style="v" />“Know therefore and understand,</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">That</char> from the going forth of the command</para>
	<para style="q2">To restore and build Jerusalem</para>
	<para style="q2">Until <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 2:1, 2; John 1:41; 4:25</char></note>Messiah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 55:4</char></note>the Prince,</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> seven weeks and sixty-two weeks;</para>
	<para style="q2">The street shall be built again, and the wall,</para>
	<para style="q2">Even in troublesome times.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="26" style="v" />“And after the sixty-two weeks</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 53:8); Matt. 27:50; Mark 9:12; 15:37; (Luke 23:46; 24:26); John 19:30; Acts 8:32</char></note>Messiah shall be cut off, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 Pet. 2:21)</char></note>but not for Himself;</para>
	<para style="q2">And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 22:7</char></note>the people of the prince who is to come</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 24:2; Mark 13:2; Luke 19:43, 44</char></note>Shall destroy the city and the sanctuary.</para>
	<para style="q2">The end of it <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> with a flood,</para>
	<para style="q2">And till the end of the war desolations are determined.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="27" style="v" />Then he shall confirm <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 42:6</char></note>a covenant with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 26:28)</char></note>many for one week;</para>
	<para style="q2">But in the middle of the week</para>
	<para style="q2">He shall bring an end to sacrifice and offering.</para>
	<para style="q2">And on the wing of abominations shall be one who makes desolate,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:36</char></note>Even until the consummation, which is determined,</para>
	<para style="q2">Is poured out on the desolate.”</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Vision of the Glorious Man</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a message was revealed to Daniel, whose <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 1:7</char></note>name was called Belteshazzar. The message <char style="it">was</char> true, but the appointed time <char style="it">was</char> long; and he understood the message, and had understanding of the vision. <verse number="2" style="v" />In those days I, Daniel, was mourning three full weeks. <verse number="3" style="v" />I ate no pleasant food, no meat or wine came into my mouth, nor did I anoint myself at all, till three whole weeks were fulfilled.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Now on the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, that <char style="it">is,</char> the Tigris, <verse number="5" style="v" />I lifted my eyes and looked, and behold, a certain man clothed in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 9:2; 10:2</char></note>linen, whose waist <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 1:13; 15:6</char></note>girded with gold of Uphaz! <verse number="6" style="v" />His body <char style="it">was</char> like beryl, his face like the appearance of lightning, his eyes like torches of fire, his arms and feet like burnished bronze in color, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rev. 1:15)</char></note>and the sound of his words like the voice of a multitude.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And I, Daniel, alone saw the vision, for the men who were with me did not see the vision; but a great terror fell upon them, so that they fled to hide themselves. <verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore I was left alone when I saw this great vision, and no strength remained in me; for my vigor was turned to frailty in me, and I retained no strength. <verse number="9" style="v" />Yet I heard the sound of his words; and while I heard the sound of his words I was in a deep sleep on my face, with my face to the ground.</para>
	<para style="s">Prophecies Concerning Persia and Greece</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 9:21</char></note>Suddenly, a hand touched me, which made me tremble on my knees and <char style="it">on</char> the palms of my hands. <verse number="11" style="v" />And he said to me, “O Daniel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 9:23</char></note>man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak to you, and stand upright, for I have now been sent to you.” While he was speaking this word to me, I stood trembling.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then he said to me, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 1:17</char></note>“Do not fear, Daniel, for from the first day that you set your heart to understand, and to humble yourself before your God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 9:3, 4, 22, 23; Acts 10:4</char></note>your words were heard; and I have come because of your words. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:20</char></note>But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me twenty-one days; and behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:21; 12:1; Jude 9; (Rev. 12:7)</char></note>Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me, for I had been left alone there with the kings of Persia. <verse number="14" style="v" />Now I have come to make you understand what will happen to your people <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 49:1; Deut. 31:29; Dan. 2:28</char></note>in the latter days, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:26; 10:1</char></note>for the vision <char style="it">refers</char> to <char style="it">many</char> days yet <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">come.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />When he had spoken such words to me, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:18; 10:9</char></note>I turned my face toward the ground and became speechless. <verse number="16" style="v" />And suddenly, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:15</char></note><char style="it">one</char> having the likeness of the sons of men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 1:9; Dan. 10:10</char></note>touched my lips; then I opened my mouth and spoke, saying to him who stood before me, “My lord, because of the vision <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:8, 9</char></note>my sorrows have overwhelmed me, and I have retained no strength. <verse number="17" style="v" />For how can this servant of my lord talk with you, my lord? As for me, no strength remains in me now, nor is any breath left in me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then again, <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">one</char> having the likeness of a man touched me and strengthened me. <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:11</char></note>And he said, “O man greatly beloved, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:23; Is. 43:1; Dan. 10:12</char></note>fear not! Peace <char style="it">be</char> to you; be strong, yes, be strong!”</para>
	<para style="p">So when he spoke to me I was strengthened, and said, “Let my lord speak, for you have strengthened me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Then he said, “Do you know why I have come to you? And now I must return to fight <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:13</char></note>with the prince of Persia; and when I have gone forth, indeed the prince of Greece will come. <verse number="21" style="v" />But I will tell you what is noted in the Scripture of Truth. (No one upholds me against these, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:13; Jude 9; (Rev. 12:7)</char></note>except Michael your prince.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />“Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 9:1</char></note>in the first year of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:31</char></note>Darius the Mede, I, <char style="it">even</char> I, stood up to confirm and strengthen him.) <verse number="2" style="v" />And now I will tell you the truth: Behold, three more kings will arise in Persia, and the fourth shall be far richer than <char style="it">them</char> all; by his strength, through his riches, he shall stir up all against the realm of Greece. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:6; 8:5</char></note>a mighty king shall arise, who shall rule with great dominion, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:4; 11:16, 36</char></note>do according to his will. <verse number="4" style="v" />And when he has arisen, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 49:36; Ezek. 37:9; Dan. 7:2; 8:8; Zech. 2:6; Rev. 7:1</char></note>his kingdom shall be broken up and divided toward the four winds of heaven, but not among his posterity <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:22</char></note>nor according to his dominion with which he ruled; for his kingdom shall be uprooted, even for others besides these.</para>
	<para style="s">Warring Kings of North and South</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />“Also the king of the South shall become strong, as well as <char style="it">one</char> of his princes; and he shall gain power over him and have dominion. His dominion <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> a great dominion. <verse number="6" style="v" />And at the end of <char style="it">some</char> years they shall join forces, for the daughter of the king of the South shall go to the king of the North to make an agreement; but she shall not retain the power of her authority, and neither he nor his authority shall stand; but she shall be given up, with those who brought her, and with him who begot her, and with him who strengthened her in <char style="it">those</char> times. <verse number="7" style="v" />But from a branch of her roots <char style="it">one</char> shall arise in his place, who shall come with an army, enter the fortress of the king of the North, and deal with them and prevail. <verse number="8" style="v" />And he shall also carry their gods captive to Egypt, with their princes <char style="it">and</char> their precious articles of silver and gold; and he shall continue <char style="it">more</char> years than the king of the North.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />“Also <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">king</char> <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">North</char> shall come to the kingdom of the king of the South, but shall return to his own land. <verse number="10" style="v" />However his sons shall stir up strife, and assemble a multitude of great forces; and <char style="it">one</char> shall certainly come <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 8:8; Jer. 46:7, 8; 51:42; Dan. 9:26; 11:26, 40</char></note>and overwhelm and pass through; then he shall return <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:7</char></note>to his fortress and stir up strife.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />“And the king of the South shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 16:14</char></note>moved with rage, and go out and fight with him, with the king of the North, who shall muster a great multitude; but the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 33:10, 16)</char></note>multitude shall be given into the hand of his <char style="it">enemy.</char> <verse number="12" style="v" />When he has taken away the multitude, his heart will be lifted up; and he will cast down tens of thousands, but he will not prevail. <verse number="13" style="v" />For the king of the North will return and muster a multitude greater than the former, and shall certainly come at the end of some years with a great army and much equipment.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />“Now in those times many shall rise up against the king of the South. Also, violent men of your people shall exalt themselves in fulfillment of the vision, but they shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 9:13</char></note>fall. <verse number="15" style="v" />So the king of the North shall come and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 6:6; Ezek. 4:2; 17:17</char></note>build a siege mound, and take a fortified city; and the forces of the South shall not withstand <char style="it">him.</char> Even his choice troops <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">have</char> no strength to resist. <verse number="16" style="v" />But he who comes against him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:4, 7</char></note>shall do according to his own will, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:5</char></note>no one shall stand against him. He shall stand in the Glorious Land with destruction in his power.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />“He shall also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 12:17; 2 Chr. 20:3; Ezek. 4:3, 7</char></note>set his face to enter with the strength of his whole kingdom, and upright ones with him; thus shall he do. And he shall give him the daughter of women to destroy it; but she shall not stand <char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">him,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 9:26</char></note>or be for him. <verse number="18" style="v" />After this he shall turn his face to the coastlands, and shall take many. But a ruler shall bring the reproach against them to an end; and with the reproach removed, he shall turn back on him. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then he shall turn his face toward the fortress of his own land; but he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 27:2; Jer. 46:6</char></note>stumble and fall, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 20:8; Ps. 37:36; Ezek. 26:21</char></note>and not be found.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />“There shall arise in his place one who imposes taxes <char style="it">on</char> the glorious kingdom; but within a few days he shall be destroyed, but not in anger or in battle. <verse number="21" style="v" />And in his place <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:8</char></note>shall arise a vile person, to whom they will not give the honor of royalty; but he shall come in peaceably, and seize the kingdom by intrigue. <verse number="22" style="v" />With the force of a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 9:26</char></note>flood they shall be swept away from before him and be broken, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:10, 11</char></note>and also the prince of the covenant. <verse number="23" style="v" />And after the league <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">made</char> with him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:25</char></note>he shall act deceitfully, for he shall come up and become strong with a small <char style="it">number</char> <char style="it">of</char> people. <verse number="24" style="v" />He shall enter peaceably, even into the richest places of the province; and he shall do <char style="it">what</char> his fathers have not done, nor his forefathers: he shall disperse among them the plunder, spoil, and riches; and he shall devise his plans against the strongholds, but <char style="it">only</char> for a time.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />“He shall stir up his power and his courage against the king of the South with a great army. And the king of the South shall be stirred up to battle with a very great and mighty army; but he shall not stand, for they shall devise plans against him. <verse number="26" style="v" />Yes, those who eat of the portion of his delicacies shall destroy him; his army shall be swept away, and many shall fall down slain. <verse number="27" style="v" />Both these kings’ hearts <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> bent on evil, and they shall speak lies at the same table; but it shall not prosper, for the end <char style="it">will</char> still <char style="it">be</char> at the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:19; Hab. 2:3</char></note>appointed time. <verse number="28" style="v" />While returning to his land with great riches, his heart shall be <char style="it">moved</char> against the holy covenant; so he shall do <char style="it">damage</char> and return to his own land.</para>
	<para style="s">The Northern King’s Blasphemies</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />“At the appointed time he shall return and go toward the south; but it shall not be like the former or the latter. <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 10:4; Num. 24:24; Is. 23:1, 12; Jer. 2:10</char></note>For ships from Cyprus shall come against him; therefore he shall be grieved, and return in rage against the holy covenant, and do <char style="it">damage.</char></para>
	<para style="p">“So he shall return and show regard for those who forsake the holy covenant. <verse number="31" style="v" />And forces shall be mustered by him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:11–13; 12:11</char></note>and they shall defile the sanctuary fortress; then they shall take away the daily <char style="it">sacrifices,</char> and place <char style="it">there</char> the abomination of desolation. <verse number="32" style="v" />Those who do wickedly against the covenant he shall corrupt with flattery; but the people who know their God shall be strong, and carry out <char style="it">great</char> <char style="it">exploits.</char> <verse number="33" style="v" />And those of the people who understand shall instruct many; yet <char style="it">for</char> <char style="it">many</char> days they shall fall by sword and flame, by captivity and plundering. <verse number="34" style="v" />Now when they fall, they shall be aided with a little help; but many shall join with them by intrigue. <verse number="35" style="v" />And <char style="it">some</char> of those of understanding shall fall, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 8:16; Prov. 17:3); Dan. 12:10; Zech. 13:9; Mal. 3:2, 3</char></note>to refine them, purify <char style="it">them,</char> and make <char style="it">them</char> white, <char style="it">until</char> the time of the end; because <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> still for the appointed time.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />“Then the king shall do according to his own will: he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:8, 25</char></note>exalt and magnify himself above every god, shall speak blasphemies against the God of gods, and shall prosper till the wrath has been accomplished; for what has been determined shall be done. <verse number="37" style="v" />He shall regard neither the God of his fathers nor the desire of women, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 14:13; 2 Thess. 2:4</char></note>nor regard any god; for he shall exalt himself above <char style="it">them</char> all. <verse number="38" style="v" />But in their place he shall honor a god of fortresses; and a god which his fathers did not know he shall honor with gold and silver, with precious stones and pleasant things. <verse number="39" style="v" />Thus he shall act against the strongest fortresses with a foreign god, which he shall acknowledge, <char style="it">and</char> advance <char style="it">its</char> glory; and he shall cause them to rule over many, and divide the land for gain.</para>
	<para style="s">The Northern King’s Conquests</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" />“At the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 11:27, 35; 12:4, 9</char></note>time of the end the king of the South shall attack him; and the king of the North shall come against him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 21:1</char></note>like a whirlwind, with chariots, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 38:4; Rev. 9:16</char></note>horsemen, and with many ships; and he shall enter the countries, overwhelm <char style="it">them,</char> and pass through. <verse number="41" style="v" />He shall also enter the Glorious Land, and many <char style="it">countries</char> shall be overthrown; but these shall escape from his hand: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 11:14</char></note>Edom, Moab, and the prominent people of Ammon. <verse number="42" style="v" />He shall stretch out his hand against the countries, and the land of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Joel 3:19</char></note>Egypt shall not escape. <verse number="43" style="v" />He shall have power over the treasures of gold and silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt; also the Libyans and Ethiopians <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">follow</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 11:8</char></note>at his heels. <verse number="44" style="v" />But news from the east and the north shall trouble him; therefore he shall go out with great fury to destroy and annihilate many. <verse number="45" style="v" />And he shall plant the tents of his palace between the seas and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 48:2</char></note>the glorious holy mountain; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rev. 19:20</char></note>yet he shall come to his end, and no one will help him.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Prophecy of the End Time</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="1" style="v" />“At that time Michael shall stand up,</para>
	<para style="q2">The great prince who stands <char style="it">watch</char> over the sons of your people;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 26:20; Jer. 30:7; Ezek. 5:9; Dan. 9:12; Matt. 24:21; Mark 13:19</char></note>And there shall be a time of trouble,</para>
	<para style="q2">Such as never was since there was a nation,</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">Even</char> to that time.</para>
	<para style="q2">And at that time your people <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rom. 11:26</char></note>shall be delivered,</para>
	<para style="q2">Every one who is found <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:32; Ps. 56:8</char></note>written in the book.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="2" style="v" />And many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 25:46; John 5:28, 29; Acts 24:15)</char></note>Some to everlasting life,</para>
	<para style="q2">Some to shame <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 66:24; Rom. 9:21)</char></note><char style="it">and</char> everlasting contempt.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="3" style="v" />Those who are wise shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 3:35; Dan. 11:33, 35; Matt. 13:43</char></note>shine</para>
	<para style="q2">Like the brightness of the firmament,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 11:30; (James 5:19, 20)</char></note>And those who turn many to righteousness</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Cor. 15:41</char></note>Like the stars forever and ever.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />“But you, Daniel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 8:16; Dan. 12:9; Rev. 22:10</char></note>shut up the words, and seal the book until the time of the end; many shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Amos 8:12</char></note>run to and fro, and knowledge shall increase.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then I, Daniel, looked; and there stood two others, one on this riverbank and the other on that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:4</char></note>riverbank. <verse number="6" style="v" />And <char style="it">one</char> said to the man clothed in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 9:2; Dan. 10:5</char></note>linen, who <char style="it">was</char> above the waters of the river, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:13; 12:8; Matt. 24:3; Mark 13:4</char></note>“How long shall the fulfillment of these wonders <char style="it">be?</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then I heard the man clothed in linen, who <char style="it">was</char> above the waters of the river, when he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:40</char></note>held up his right hand and his left hand to heaven, and swore by Him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 4:34</char></note>who lives forever, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 7:25; Rev. 12:14</char></note>that <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> for a time, times, and half <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">time;</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 21:24</char></note>and when the power of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 8:24</char></note>the holy people has been completely shattered, all these <char style="it">things</char> shall be finished.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Although I heard, I did not understand. Then I said, “My lord, what <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> the end of these <char style="it">things?</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And he said, “Go <char style="it">your</char> <char style="it">way,</char> Daniel, for the words <char style="it">are</char> closed up and sealed till the time of the end. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Zech. 13:9</char></note>Many shall be purified, made white, and refined, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 32:6, 7; Rev. 22:11</char></note>but the wicked shall do wickedly; and none of the wicked shall understand, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 12:3; Hos. 14:9; John 7:17; 8:47</char></note>the wise shall understand.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />“And from the time <char style="it">that</char> the daily <char style="it">sacrifice</char> is taken away, and the abomination of desolation is set up, <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> one thousand two hundred and ninety days. <verse number="12" style="v" />Blessed <char style="it">is</char> he who waits, and comes to the one thousand three hundred and thirty-five days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />“But you, go <char style="it">your</char> <char style="it">way</char> till the end; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 57:2; Rev. 14:13</char></note>for you shall rest, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 1:5</char></note>and will arise to your inheritance at the end of the days.”</para>
	
</usx>