<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="JDG" style="id">The Book of Judges</book>
    <para style="mt">The Book of Judges</para>
    <chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Continuing Conquest of Canaan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now after the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:29</char></note>death of Joshua it came to pass that the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:21; Judg. 20:18</char></note>asked the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, “Who shall be first to go up for us against the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:12, 13</char></note>Canaanites to fight against them?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 49:8, 9; Rev. 5:5</char></note>“Judah shall go up. Indeed I have delivered the land into his hand.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />So Judah said to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:1</char></note>Simeon his brother, “Come up with me to my allotted territory, that we may fight against the Canaanites; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:17</char></note>I will likewise go with you to your allotted territory.” And Simeon went with him. <verse number="4" style="v" />Then Judah went up, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered the Canaanites and the Perizzites into their hand; and they killed ten thousand men at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 11:8</char></note>Bezek. <verse number="5" style="v" />And they found Adoni-Bezek in Bezek, and fought against him; and they defeated the Canaanites and the Perizzites. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then Adoni-Bezek fled, and they pursued him and caught him and cut off his thumbs and big toes. <verse number="7" style="v" />And Adoni-Bezek said, “Seventy kings with their thumbs and big toes cut off used to gather <char style="it">scraps</char> under my table; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 24:19; 1 Sam. 15:33; (James 2:13)</char></note>as I have done, so God has repaid me.” Then they brought him to Jerusalem, and there he died.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:63; Judg. 1:21</char></note>the children of Judah fought against Jerusalem and took it; they struck it with the edge of the sword and set the city on fire. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:36; 11:21; 15:13</char></note>And afterward the children of Judah went down to fight against the Canaanites who dwelt in the mountains, in the South, and in the lowland. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then Judah went against the Canaanites who dwelt in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:13–19</char></note>Hebron. (Now the name of Hebron <char style="it">was</char> formerly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:15</char></note>Kirjath Arba.) And they killed Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:15</char></note>From there they went against the inhabitants of Debir. (The name of Debir <char style="it">was</char> formerly Kirjath Sepher.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:16, 17</char></note>Then Caleb said, “Whoever attacks Kirjath Sepher and takes it, to him I will give my daughter Achsah as wife.” <verse number="13" style="v" />And Othniel the son of Kenaz, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:9</char></note>Caleb’s younger brother, took it; so he gave him his daughter Achsah as wife. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:18, 19</char></note>Now it happened, when she came <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">him,</char> that she urged him to ask her father for a field. And she dismounted from <char style="it">her</char> donkey, and Caleb said to her, “What do you wish?” <verse number="15" style="v" />So she said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 33:11</char></note>“Give me a blessing; since you have given me land in the South, give me also springs of water.”</para>
	<para style="p">And Caleb gave her the upper springs and the lower springs.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:29–32; Judg. 4:11, 17; 1 Sam. 15:6; 1 Chr. 2:55</char></note>Now the children of the Kenite, Moses’ father-in-law, went up <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 34:3; Judg. 3:13</char></note>from the City of Palms with the children of Judah into the Wilderness of Judah, which <char style="it">lies</char> in the South <char style="it">near</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:14</char></note>Arad; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 15:6</char></note>and they went and dwelt among the people. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:3</char></note>And Judah went with his brother Simeon, and they attacked the Canaanites who inhabited Zephath, and utterly destroyed it. So the name of the city was called <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:3; Josh. 19:4</char></note>Hormah. <verse number="18" style="v" />Also Judah took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:22</char></note>Gaza with its territory, Ashkelon with its territory, and Ekron with its territory. <verse number="19" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with Judah. And they drove out the mountaineers, but they could not drive out the inhabitants of the lowland, because they had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:16, 18; Judg. 4:3, 13</char></note>chariots of iron. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:24; Josh. 14:9, 14</char></note>And they gave Hebron to Caleb, as Moses had said. Then he expelled from there the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:14; Judg. 1:10</char></note>three sons of Anak. <verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:63; Judg. 1:8</char></note>But the children of Benjamin did not drive out the Jebusites who inhabited Jerusalem; so the Jebusites dwell with the children of Benjamin in Jerusalem to this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And the house of Joseph also went up against Bethel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:19</char></note>and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">was</char> with them. <verse number="23" style="v" />So the house of Joseph <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:1; 7:2</char></note>sent men to spy out Bethel. (The name of the city <char style="it">was</char> formerly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 28:19</char></note>Luz.) <verse number="24" style="v" />And when the spies saw a man coming out of the city, they said to him, “Please show us the entrance to the city, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:12, 14</char></note>we will show you mercy.” <verse number="25" style="v" />So he showed them the entrance to the city, and they struck the city with the edge of the sword; but they let the man and all his family go. <verse number="26" style="v" />And the man went to the land of the Hittites, built a city, and called its name Luz, which <char style="it">is</char> its name to this day.</para>
	<para style="s">Incomplete Conquest of the Land</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:11–13</char></note>However, Manasseh did not drive out <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">inhabitants</char> <char style="it">of</char> Beth Shean and its villages, or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:25</char></note>Taanach and its villages, or the inhabitants of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:11</char></note>Dor and its villages, or the inhabitants of Ibleam and its villages, or the inhabitants of Megiddo and its villages; for the Canaanites were determined to dwell in that land. <verse number="28" style="v" />And it came to pass, when Israel was strong, that they put the Canaanites under tribute, but did not completely drive them out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:10; 1 Kin. 9:16</char></note>Nor did Ephraim drive out the Canaanites who dwelt in Gezer; so the Canaanites dwelt in Gezer among them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Nor did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:10–16</char></note>Zebulun drive out the inhabitants of Kitron or the inhabitants of Nahalol; so the Canaanites dwelt among them, and were put under tribute.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:24–31</char></note>Nor did Asher drive out the inhabitants of Acco or the inhabitants of Sidon, or of Ahlab, Achzib, Helbah, Aphik, or Rehob. <verse number="32" style="v" />So the Asherites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:34, 35</char></note>dwelt among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land; for they did not drive them out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:32–39</char></note>Nor did Naphtali drive out the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh or the inhabitants of Beth Anath; but they dwelt among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land. Nevertheless the inhabitants of Beth Shemesh and Beth Anath were put under tribute to them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />And the Amorites forced the children of Dan into the mountains, for they would not allow them to come down to the valley; <verse number="35" style="v" />and the Amorites were determined to dwell in Mount Heres, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:42</char></note>in Aijalon, and in Shaalbim; yet when the strength of the house of Joseph became greater, they were put under tribute.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />Now the boundary of the Amorites <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:4; Josh. 15:3</char></note>from the Ascent of Akrabbim, from Sela, and upward.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Israel’s Disobedience</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came up from Gilgal to Bochim, and said: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:2; Judg. 6:8, 9</char></note>“I led you up from Egypt and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 1:8</char></note>brought you to the land of which I swore to your fathers; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:7, 8; Lev. 26:42, 44; Deut. 7:9; Ps. 89:34</char></note>I said, ‘I will never break My covenant with you. <verse number="2" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:32; Deut. 7:2</char></note>you shall make no covenant with the inhabitants of this land; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:12, 13; Deut. 12:3</char></note>you shall tear down their altars.’ <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:34</char></note>But you have not obeyed My voice. Why have you done this? <verse number="3" style="v" />Therefore I also said, ‘I will not drive them out before you; but they shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:55; Josh. 23:13</char></note><char style="it">thorns</char> in your side, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:6</char></note>their gods shall be a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:33; Deut. 7:16; Ps. 106:36</char></note>snare to you.’ ” <verse number="4" style="v" />So it was, when the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke these words to all the children of Israel, that the people lifted up their voices and wept.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then they called the name of that place Bochim; and they sacrificed there to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" />And when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:6; 24:28–31</char></note>Joshua had dismissed the people, the children of Israel went each to his own inheritance to possess the land.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Joshua</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:31</char></note>So the people served the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua, who had seen all the great works of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He had done for Israel. <verse number="8" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:29</char></note>Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, died <char style="it">when</char> <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">was</char> one hundred and ten years old. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:30</char></note>And they buried him within the border of his inheritance at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:49, 50</char></note>Timnath Heres, in the mountains of Ephraim, on the north side of Mount Gaash. <verse number="10" style="v" />When all that generation had been gathered to their fathers, another generation arose after them who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 5:2; 1 Sam. 2:12; Gal. 4:8; (Titus 1:16)</char></note>did not know the <char style="sc">Lord</char> nor the work which He had done for Israel.</para>
	<para style="s">Israel’s Unfaithfulness</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then the children of Israel did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:7, 12; 4:1; 6:1</char></note>evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and served the Baals; <verse number="12" style="v" />and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:16; Judg. 8:33; 10:6</char></note>forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of their fathers, who had brought them out of the land of Egypt; and they followed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 6:14</char></note>other gods from <char style="it">among</char> the gods of the people who <char style="it">were</char> all around them, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:5</char></note>bowed down to them; and they provoked the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to anger. <verse number="13" style="v" />They forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:6; Ps. 106:36</char></note>and served Baal and the Ashtoreths. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:17; Judg. 3:8; Ps. 106:40–42</char></note>And the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was hot against Israel. So He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:20</char></note>delivered them into the hands of plunderers who despoiled them; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 50:1</char></note>He sold them into the hands of their enemies all around, so that they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:37; Josh. 7:12, 13</char></note>could no longer stand before their enemies. <verse number="15" style="v" />Wherever they went out, the hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was against them for calamity, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said, and as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:14–26; Deut. 28:15–68</char></note>sworn to them. And they were greatly distressed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Nevertheless, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:9, 10, 15; Ps. 106:43–45</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> raised up judges who delivered them out of the hand of those who plundered them. <verse number="17" style="v" />Yet they would not listen to their judges, but they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:15</char></note>played the harlot with other gods, and bowed down to them. They turned quickly from the way in which their fathers walked, in obeying the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; they did not do so. <verse number="18" style="v" />And when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> raised up judges for them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:5</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with the judge and delivered them out of the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 6:6</char></note>for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was moved to pity by their groaning because of those who oppressed them and harassed them. <verse number="19" style="v" />And it came to pass, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:12</char></note>when the judge was dead, that they reverted and behaved more corruptly than their fathers, by following other gods, to serve them and bow down to them. They did not cease from their own doings nor from their stubborn way.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Then the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was hot against Israel; and He said, “Because this nation has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Josh. 23:16)</char></note>transgressed My covenant which I commanded their fathers, and has not heeded My voice, <verse number="21" style="v" />I also will no longer drive out before them any of the nations which Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 23:4, 5, 13</char></note>left when he died, <verse number="22" style="v" />so <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:1, 4</char></note>that through them I may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 8:2, 16; 13:3</char></note>test Israel, whether they will keep the ways of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to walk in them as their fathers kept <char style="it">them,</char> or not.” <verse number="23" style="v" />Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> left those nations, without driving them out immediately; nor did He deliver them into the hand of Joshua.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Nations Remaining in the Land</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now these <char style="it">are</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:1; 2:21, 22</char></note>the nations which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> left, that He might test Israel by them, <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">is,</char> all who had not known any of the wars in Canaan <verse number="2" style="v" />(<char style="it">this</char> <char style="it">was</char> only so that the generations of the children of Israel might be taught to know war, at least those who had not formerly known it), <verse number="3" style="v" /><char style="it">namely,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:3</char></note>five lords of the Philistines, all the Canaanites, the Sidonians, and the Hivites who dwelt in Mount Lebanon, from Mount Baal Hermon to the entrance of Hamath. <verse number="4" style="v" />And they were <char style="it">left, that He might</char> test Israel by them, to know whether they would obey the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which He had commanded their fathers by the hand of Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:35</char></note>Thus the children of Israel dwelt among the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites. <verse number="6" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:15, 16; Deut. 7:3, 4; Josh. 23:12</char></note>they took their daughters to be their wives, and gave their daughters to their sons; and they served their gods.</para>
	<para style="s">Othniel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So the children of Israel did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:11</char></note>evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. They <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:18</char></note>forgot the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, and served the Baals and Asherahs. <verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was hot against Israel, and He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:30; Judg. 2:14</char></note>sold them into the hand of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Hab. 3:7</char></note>Cushan-Rishathaim king of Mesopotamia; and the children of Israel served Cushan-Rishathaim eight years. <verse number="9" style="v" />When the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:15</char></note>cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:16</char></note>raised up a deliverer for the children of Israel, who delivered them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:13</char></note>Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb’s younger brother. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:18; 1 Sam. 11:6; 2 Chr. 15:1</char></note>The Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon him, and he judged Israel. He went out to war, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered Cushan-Rishathaim king of Mesopotamia into his hand; and his hand prevailed over Cushan-Rishathaim. <verse number="11" style="v" />So the land had rest for forty years. Then Othniel the son of Kenaz died.</para>
	<para style="s">Ehud</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:19</char></note>And the children of Israel again did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> strengthened <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 12:9</char></note>Eglon king of Moab against Israel, because they had done evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then he gathered to himself the people of Ammon and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:14</char></note>Amalek, went and defeated Israel, and took possession of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 34:3; Judg. 1:16; 2 Chr. 28:15</char></note>the City of Palms. <verse number="14" style="v" />So the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:48</char></note>served Eglon king of Moab eighteen years.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />But when the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 78:34</char></note>cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> raised up a deliverer for them: Ehud the son of Gera, the Benjamite, a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:16</char></note>left-handed man. By him the children of Israel sent tribute to Eglon king of Moab. <verse number="16" style="v" />Now Ehud made himself a dagger (it was double-edged and a cubit in length) and fastened it under his clothes on his right thigh. <verse number="17" style="v" />So he brought the tribute to Eglon king of Moab. (Now Eglon <char style="it">was</char> a very fat man.) <verse number="18" style="v" />And when he had finished presenting the tribute, he sent away the people who had carried the tribute. <verse number="19" style="v" />But he himself turned back <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:20</char></note>from the stone images that <char style="it">were</char> at Gilgal, and said, “I have a secret message for you, O king.”</para>
	<para style="p">He said, “Keep silence!” And all who attended him went out from him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So Ehud came to him (now he was sitting upstairs in his cool private chamber). Then Ehud said, “I have a message from God for you.” So he arose from <char style="it">his</char> seat. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then Ehud reached with his left hand, took the dagger from his right thigh, and thrust it into his belly. <verse number="22" style="v" />Even the hilt went in after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade, for he did not draw the dagger out of his belly; and his entrails came out. <verse number="23" style="v" />Then Ehud went out through the porch and shut the doors of the upper room behind him and locked them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />When he had gone out, <char style="it">Eglon’s</char> servants came to look, and <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">their</char> surprise, the doors of the upper room were locked. So they said, “He is probably <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 24:3</char></note>attending to his needs in the cool chamber.” <verse number="25" style="v" />So they waited till they were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 2:17; 8:11</char></note>embarrassed, and still he had not opened the doors of the upper room. Therefore they took the key and opened <char style="it">them.</char> And there was their master, fallen dead on the floor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />But Ehud had escaped while they delayed, and passed beyond the stone images and escaped to Seirah. <verse number="27" style="v" />And it happened, when he arrived, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:34; 1 Sam. 13:3</char></note>he blew the trumpet in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:15</char></note>mountains of Ephraim, and the children of Israel went down with him from the mountains; and he led them. <verse number="28" style="v" />Then he said to them, “Follow <char style="it">me,</char> for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:9, 15; 1 Sam. 17:47</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has delivered your enemies the Moabites into your hand.” So they went down after him, seized the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:7; Judg. 12:5</char></note>fords of the Jordan leading to Moab, and did not allow anyone to cross over. <verse number="29" style="v" />And at that time they killed about ten thousand men of Moab, all stout men of valor; not a man escaped. <verse number="30" style="v" />So Moab was subdued that day under the hand of Israel. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:11</char></note>the land had rest for eighty years.</para>
	<para style="s">Shamgar</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />After him was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:6</char></note>Shamgar the son of Anath, who killed six hundred men of the Philistines <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 17:47</char></note>with an ox goad; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:16</char></note>and he also delivered <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 4:1</char></note>Israel.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Deborah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />When Ehud was dead, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:19</char></note>the children of Israel again did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:11</char></note>evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="2" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:14</char></note>sold them into the hand of Jabin king of Canaan, who reigned in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:1, 10</char></note>Hazor. The commander of his army <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 12:9; Ps. 83:9</char></note>Sisera, who dwelt in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:13, 16</char></note>Harosheth Hagoyim. <verse number="3" style="v" />And the children of Israel cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; for Jabin had nine hundred <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:1; Judg. 1:19</char></note>chariots of iron, and for twenty years <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:42</char></note>he had harshly oppressed the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Now Deborah, a prophetess, the wife of Lapidoth, was judging Israel at that time. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:8</char></note>And she would sit under the palm tree of Deborah between Ramah and Bethel in the mountains of Ephraim. And the children of Israel came up to her for judgment. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then she sent and called for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Heb. 11:32</char></note>Barak the son of Abinoam from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:37; 21:32</char></note>Kedesh in Naphtali, and said to him, “Has not the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel commanded, ‘Go and deploy <char style="it">troops</char> at Mount <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:18</char></note>Tabor; take with you ten thousand men of the sons of Naphtali and of the sons of Zebulun; <verse number="7" style="v" />and against you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:4</char></note>I will deploy Sisera, the commander of Jabin’s army, with his chariots and his multitude at the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:21; 1 Kin. 18:40; Ps. 83:9, 10</char></note>River Kishon; and I will deliver him into your hand’?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And Barak said to her, “If you will go with me, then I will go; but if you will not go with me, I will not go!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So she said, “I will surely go with you; nevertheless there will be no glory for you in the journey you are taking, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:14</char></note>sell Sisera into the hand of a woman.” Then Deborah arose and went with Barak to Kedesh. <verse number="10" style="v" />And Barak called <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:18</char></note>Zebulun and Naphtali to Kedesh; he went up with ten thousand men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 11:8; 1 Kin. 20:10</char></note>under his command, and Deborah went up with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Now Heber <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:16</char></note>the Kenite, of the children of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:29</char></note>Hobab the father-in-law of Moses, had separated himself from the Kenites and pitched his tent near the terebinth tree at Zaanaim, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:6</char></note>which <char style="it">is</char> beside Kedesh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And they reported to Sisera that Barak the son of Abinoam had gone up to Mount Tabor. <verse number="13" style="v" />So Sisera gathered together all his chariots, nine hundred chariots of iron, and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> with him, from Harosheth Hagoyim to the River Kishon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then Deborah said to Barak, “Up! For this <char style="it">is</char> the day in which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has delivered Sisera into your hand. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 9:3; 31:3; 2 Sam. 5:24; Ps. 68:7; Is. 52:12</char></note>Has not the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gone out before you?” So Barak went down from Mount Tabor with ten thousand men following him. <verse number="15" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> routed Sisera and all <char style="it">his</char> chariots and all <char style="it">his</char> army with the edge of the sword before Barak; and Sisera alighted from <char style="it">his</char> chariot and fled away on foot. <verse number="16" style="v" />But Barak pursued the chariots and the army as far as Harosheth Hagoyim, and all the army of Sisera fell by the edge of the sword; not a man was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:28; Ps. 83:9</char></note>left.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />However, Sisera had fled away on foot to the tent of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:6</char></note>Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite; for <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> peace between Jabin king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite. <verse number="18" style="v" />And Jael went out to meet Sisera, and said to him, “Turn aside, my lord, turn aside to me; do not fear.” And when he had turned aside with her into the tent, she covered him with a blanket.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then he said to her, “Please give me a little water to drink, for I am thirsty.” So she opened <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:24–27</char></note>a jug of milk, gave him a drink, and covered him. <verse number="20" style="v" />And he said to her, “Stand at the door of the tent, and if any man comes and inquires of you, and says, ‘Is there any man here?’ you shall say, ‘No.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then Jael, Heber’s wife, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:24–27</char></note>took a tent peg and took a hammer in her hand, and went softly to him and drove the peg into his temple, and it went down into the ground; for he was fast asleep and weary. So he died. <verse number="22" style="v" />And then, as Barak pursued Sisera, Jael came out to meet him, and said to him, “Come, I will show you the man whom you seek.” And when he went into her <char style="it">tent,</char> there lay Sisera, dead with the peg in his temple.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />So on that day God subdued Jabin king of Canaan in the presence of the children of Israel. <verse number="24" style="v" />And the hand of the children of Israel grew stronger and stronger against Jabin king of Canaan, until they had destroyed Jabin king of Canaan.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Song of Deborah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Deborah and Barak the son of Abinoam <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:1; Judg. 4:4</char></note>sang on that day, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="2" style="v" />“When leaders <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 18:47</char></note>lead in Israel,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 17:16</char></note>When the people willingly offer themselves,</para>
	<para style="q2">Bless the <char style="sc">Lord</char>!</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="3" style="v" />“Hear,<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:1, 3</char></note> O kings! Give ear, O princes!</para>
	<para style="q2">I, <char style="it">even</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 27:6</char></note>I, will sing to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>;</para>
	<para style="q2">I will sing praise to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="4" style="v" />“<char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 33:2; Ps. 68:7</char></note>when You went out from Seir,</para>
	<para style="q2">When You marched from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 68:8</char></note>the field of Edom,</para>
	<para style="q2">The earth trembled and the heavens poured,</para>
	<para style="q2">The clouds also poured water;</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 97:5</char></note>The mountains gushed before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:18</char></note>This Sinai, before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="6" style="v" />“In the days of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:31</char></note>Shamgar, son of Anath,</para>
	<para style="q2">In the days of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:17</char></note>Jael,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 33:8</char></note>The highways were deserted,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the travelers walked along the byways.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="7" style="v" />Village life ceased, it ceased in Israel,</para>
	<para style="q2">Until I, Deborah, arose,</para>
	<para style="q2">Arose a mother in Israel.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="8" style="v" />They chose <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:17</char></note>new gods;</para>
	<para style="q2">Then <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> war in the gates;</para>
	<para style="q2">Not a shield or spear was seen among forty thousand in Israel.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="9" style="v" />My heart <char style="it">is</char> with the rulers of Israel</para>
	<para style="q2">Who offered themselves willingly with the people.</para>
	<para style="q2">Bless the <char style="sc">Lord</char>!</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="10" style="v" />“Speak, you who ride on white <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:4; 12:14</char></note>donkeys,</para>
	<para style="q2">Who sit in judges’ attire,</para>
	<para style="q2">And who walk along the road.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="11" style="v" />Far from the noise of the archers, among the watering places,</para>
	<para style="q2">There they shall recount the righteous acts of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>,</para>
	<para style="q2">The righteous acts <char style="it">for</char> His villagers in Israel;</para>
	<para style="q2">Then the people of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> shall go down to the gates.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="12" style="v" />“Awake,<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 57:8</char></note> awake, Deborah!</para>
	<para style="q2">Awake, awake, sing a song!</para>
	<para style="q2">Arise, Barak, and lead your captives away,</para>
	<para style="q2">O son of Abinoam!</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="13" style="v" />“Then the survivors came down, the people against the nobles;</para>
	<para style="q2">The <char style="sc">Lord</char> came down for me against the mighty.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="14" style="v" />From Ephraim <char style="it">were</char> those whose roots were in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:13</char></note>Amalek.</para>
	<para style="q2">After you, Benjamin, with your peoples,</para>
	<para style="q2">From Machir rulers came down,</para>
	<para style="q2">And from Zebulun those who bear the recruiter’s staff.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="15" style="v" />And the princes of Issachar <char style="it">were</char> with Deborah;</para>
	<para style="q2">As Issachar, so <char style="it">was</char> Barak</para>
	<para style="q2">Sent into the valley under his command;</para>
	<para style="q2">Among the divisions of Reuben</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">were</char> great resolves of heart.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="16" style="v" />Why did you sit among the sheepfolds,</para>
	<para style="q2">To hear the pipings for the flocks?</para>
	<para style="q2">The divisions of Reuben have great searchings of heart.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:9</char></note>Gilead stayed beyond the Jordan,</para>
	<para style="q2">And why did Dan remain on ships?</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:29, 31</char></note>Asher continued at the seashore,</para>
	<para style="q2">And stayed by his inlets.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:6, 10</char></note>Zebulun <char style="it">is</char> a people <char style="it">who</char> jeopardized their lives to the point of death,</para>
	<para style="q2">Naphtali also, on the heights of the battlefield.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="19" style="v" />“The kings came <char style="it">and</char> fought,</para>
	<para style="q2">Then the kings of Canaan fought</para>
	<para style="q2">In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:27</char></note>Taanach, by the waters of Megiddo;</para>
	<para style="q2">They took no spoils of silver.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="20" style="v" />They fought from the heavens;</para>
	<para style="q2">The stars from their courses fought against Sisera.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:7</char></note>The torrent of Kishon swept them away,</para>
	<para style="q2">That ancient torrent, the torrent of Kishon.</para>
	<para style="q2">O my soul, march on in strength!</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then the horses’ hooves pounded,</para>
	<para style="q2">The galloping, galloping of his steeds.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="23" style="v" />‘Curse Meroz,’ said the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘Curse its inhabitants bitterly,</para>
	<para style="q2">Because they did not come to the help of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>,</para>
	<para style="q2">To the help of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> against the mighty.’</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="24" style="v" />“Most blessed among women is Jael,</para>
	<para style="q2">The wife of Heber the Kenite;</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Luke 1:28)</char></note>Blessed is she among women in tents.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="25" style="v" />He asked for water, she gave milk;</para>
	<para style="q2">She brought out cream in a lordly bowl.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="26" style="v" />She stretched her hand to the tent peg,</para>
	<para style="q2">Her right hand to the workmen’s hammer;</para>
	<para style="q2">She pounded Sisera, she pierced his head,</para>
	<para style="q2">She split and struck through his temple.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="27" style="v" />At her feet he sank, he fell, he lay still;</para>
	<para style="q2">At her feet he sank, he fell;</para>
	<para style="q2">Where he sank, there he fell <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:18–21</char></note>dead.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="28" style="v" />“The mother of Sisera looked through the window,</para>
	<para style="q2">And cried out through the lattice,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘Why is his chariot <char style="it">so</char> long in coming?</para>
	<para style="q2">Why tarries the clatter of his chariots?’</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="29" style="v" />Her wisest ladies answered her,</para>
	<para style="q2">Yes, she answered herself,</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="30" style="v" />‘Are they not finding and dividing the spoil:</para>
	<para style="q2">To every man a girl <char style="it">or</char> two;</para>
	<para style="q2">For Sisera, plunder of dyed garments,</para>
	<para style="q2">Plunder of garments embroidered and dyed,</para>
	<para style="q2">Two pieces of dyed embroidery for the neck of the looter?’</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="31" style="v" />“Thus let all Your enemies <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 92:9</char></note>perish, O <char style="sc">Lord</char>!</para>
	<para style="q2">But <char style="it">let</char> those who love Him <char style="it">be</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 23:4</char></note>like the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 37:6; 89:36, 37</char></note>sun</para>
	<para style="q2">When it comes out in full <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 19:5</char></note>strength.”</para>
	<para style="p">So the land had rest for forty years.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Midianites Oppress Israel</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the children of Israel did <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:11</char></note>evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered them into the hand of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:4; 31:1–3</char></note>Midian for seven years, <verse number="2" style="v" />and the hand of Midian prevailed against Israel. Because of the Midianites, the children of Israel made for themselves the dens, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 13:6; Heb. 11:38</char></note>the caves, and the strongholds which <char style="it">are</char> in the mountains. <verse number="3" style="v" />So it was, whenever Israel had sown, Midianites would come up; also Amalekites and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:12</char></note>people of the East would come up against them. <verse number="4" style="v" />Then they would encamp against them and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:16</char></note>destroy the produce of the earth as far as Gaza, and leave no sustenance for Israel, neither sheep nor ox nor <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:31</char></note>donkey. <verse number="5" style="v" />For they would come up with their livestock and their tents, coming in as numerous as locusts; both they and their camels were without number; and they would enter the land to destroy it. <verse number="6" style="v" />So Israel was greatly impoverished because of the Midianites, and the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 50:15; Hos. 5:15</char></note>cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And it came to pass, when the children of Israel cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> because of the Midianites, <verse number="8" style="v" />that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sent a prophet to the children of Israel, who said to them, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: ‘I brought you up from Egypt and brought you out of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:17</char></note>house of bondage; <verse number="9" style="v" />and I delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians and out of the hand of all who oppressed you, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 44:2, 3</char></note>drove them out before you and gave you their land. <verse number="10" style="v" />Also I said to you, “I <char style="it">am</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:35, 37, 38; Jer. 10:2</char></note>do not fear the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you dwell.” But you have not obeyed My <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:1, 2</char></note>voice.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Gideon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Now the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came and sat under the terebinth tree which <char style="it">was</char> in Ophrah, which <char style="it">belonged</char> to Joash <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:2; Judg. 6:15</char></note>the Abiezrite, while his son <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:1; Heb. 11:32</char></note>Gideon threshed wheat in the winepress, in order to hide <char style="it">it</char> from the Midianites. <verse number="12" style="v" />And the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:3; Luke 1:11, 28</char></note>Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared to him, and said to him, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:5</char></note>with you, you mighty man of valor!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Gideon said to Him, “O my lord, if the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is with us, why then has all this happened to us? And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 59:1)</char></note>where <char style="it">are</char> all His miracles <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:6, 21; Ps. 44:1</char></note>which our fathers told us about, saying, ‘Did not the <char style="sc">Lord</char> bring us up from Egypt?’ But now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:17; 2 Chr. 15:2; Ps. 44:9–16</char></note>forsaken us and delivered us into the hands of the Midianites.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> turned to him and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 12:11</char></note>“Go in this might of yours, and you shall save Israel from the hand of the Midianites. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:9</char></note>Have I not sent you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />So he said to Him, “O my Lord, how can I save Israel? Indeed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 9:21</char></note>my clan <char style="it">is</char> the weakest in Manasseh, and I <char style="it">am</char> the least in my father’s house.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:12; Josh. 1:5</char></note>“Surely I will be with you, and you shall defeat the Midianites as one man.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then he said to Him, “If now I have found favor in Your sight, then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:36, 37; 2 Kin. 20:8; Ps. 86:17; Is. 7:11; 38:7, 8</char></note>show me a sign that it is You who talk with me. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:3, 5</char></note>Do not depart from here, I pray, until I come to You and bring out my offering and set <char style="it">it</char> before You.”</para>
	<para style="p">And He said, “I will wait until you come back.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:6–8</char></note>So Gideon went in and prepared a young goat, and unleavened bread from an ephah of flour. The meat he put in a basket, and he put the broth in a pot; and he brought <char style="it">them</char> out to Him under the terebinth tree and presented <char style="it">them.</char> <verse number="20" style="v" />The Angel of God said to him, “Take the meat and the unleavened bread and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:19</char></note>lay <char style="it">them</char> on this rock, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:33, 34</char></note>pour out the broth.” And he did so.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> put out the end of the staff that <char style="it">was</char> in His hand, and touched the meat and the unleavened bread; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 9:24</char></note>fire rose out of the rock and consumed the meat and the unleavened bread. And the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> departed out of his sight.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Now Gideon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:30; Ex. 33:20; Judg. 13:21, 22</char></note>perceived that He <char style="it">was</char> the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. So Gideon said, “Alas, O Lord <char style="sc">God</char>! <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 16:13</char></note>For I have seen the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> face to face.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 10:19</char></note>“Peace <char style="it">be</char> with you; do not fear, you shall not die.” <verse number="24" style="v" />So Gideon built an altar there to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and called it The-<char style="sc">Lord</char>-<char style="it">Is</char>-Peace. To this day it <char style="it">is</char> still <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:32</char></note>in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />Now it came to pass the same night that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, “Take your father’s young bull, the second bull of seven years old, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:2</char></note>tear down the altar of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:7</char></note>Baal that your father has, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:13; Deut. 7:5</char></note>cut down the wooden image that <char style="it">is</char> beside it; <verse number="26" style="v" />and build an altar to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God on top of this rock in the proper arrangement, and take the second bull and offer a burnt sacrifice with the wood of the image which you shall cut down.” <verse number="27" style="v" />So Gideon took ten men from among his servants and did as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said to him. But because he feared his father’s household and the men of the city too much to do <char style="it">it</char> by day, he did <char style="it">it</char> by night.</para>
	<para style="s">Gideon Destroys the Altar of Baal</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />And when the men of the city arose early in the morning, there was the altar of Baal, torn down; and the wooden image that <char style="it">was</char> beside it was cut down, and the second bull was being offered on the altar <char style="it">which</char> <char style="it">had</char> <char style="it">been</char> built. <verse number="29" style="v" />So they said to one another, “Who has done this thing?” And when they had inquired and asked, they said, “Gideon the son of Joash has done this thing.” <verse number="30" style="v" />Then the men of the city said to Joash, “Bring out your son, that he may die, because he has torn down the altar of Baal, and because he has cut down the wooden image that <char style="it">was</char> beside it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />But Joash said to all who stood against him, “Would you plead for Baal? Would you save him? Let the one who would plead for him be put to death by morning! If he <char style="it">is</char> a god, let him plead for himself, because his altar has been torn down!” <verse number="32" style="v" />Therefore on that day he called him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:1; 1 Sam. 12:11; 2 Sam. 11:21</char></note>Jerubbaal, saying, “Let Baal plead against him, because he has torn down his altar.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />Then all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:3</char></note>the Midianites and Amalekites, the people of the East, gathered together; and they crossed over and encamped in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:16; Hos. 1:5</char></note>the Valley of Jezreel. <verse number="34" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:10; 1 Chr. 12:18; 2 Chr. 24:20</char></note>the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon Gideon; then he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:3; Judg. 3:27</char></note>blew the trumpet, and the Abiezrites gathered behind him. <verse number="35" style="v" />And he sent messengers throughout all Manasseh, who also gathered behind him. He also sent messengers to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:17; 7:23</char></note>Asher, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:6, 10; 5:18</char></note>Zebulun, and Naphtali; and they came up to meet them.</para>
	<para style="s">The Sign of the Fleece</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />So Gideon said to God, “If You will save Israel by my hand as You have said— <verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 4:3–7)</char></note>look, I shall put a fleece of wool on the threshing floor; if there is dew on the fleece only, and <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> dry on all the ground, then I shall know that You will save Israel by my hand, as You have said.” <verse number="38" style="v" />And it was so. When he rose early the next morning and squeezed the fleece together, he wrung the dew out of the fleece, a bowlful of water. <verse number="39" style="v" />Then Gideon said to God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:32</char></note>“Do not be angry with me, but let me speak just once more: Let me test, I pray, just once more with the fleece; let it now be dry only on the fleece, but on all the ground let there be dew.” <verse number="40" style="v" />And God did so that night. It was dry on the fleece only, but there was dew on all the ground.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Gideon’s Valiant Three Hundred</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:32</char></note>Jerubbaal (that <char style="it">is,</char> Gideon) and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> with him rose early and encamped beside the well of Harod, so that the camp of the Midianites was on the north side of them by the hill of Moreh in the valley.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, “The people who <char style="it">are</char> with you <char style="it">are</char> too many for Me to give the Midianites into their hands, lest Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 8:17; Is. 10:13</char></note>claim glory for itself against Me, saying, ‘My own hand has saved me.’ <verse number="3" style="v" />Now therefore, proclaim in the hearing of the people, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:8</char></note>‘Whoever <char style="it">is</char> fearful and afraid, let him turn and depart at once from Mount Gilead.’ ” And twenty-two thousand of the people returned, and ten thousand remained.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, “The people <char style="it">are</char> still <char style="it">too</char> many; bring them down to the water, and I will test them for you there. Then it will be, <char style="it">that</char> of whom I say to you, ‘This one shall go with you,’ the same shall go with you; and of whomever I say to you, ‘This one shall not go with you,’ the same shall not go.” <verse number="5" style="v" />So he brought the people down to the water. And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, “Everyone who laps from the water with his tongue, as a dog laps, you shall set apart by himself; likewise everyone who gets down on his knees to drink.” <verse number="6" style="v" />And the number of those who lapped, <char style="it">putting</char> their hand to their mouth, was three hundred men; but all the rest of the people got down on their knees to drink water. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 14:6</char></note>“By the three hundred men who lapped I will save you, and deliver the Midianites into your hand. Let all the <char style="it">other</char> people go, every man to his place.” <verse number="8" style="v" />So the people took provisions and their trumpets in their hands. And he sent away all <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">rest</char> <char style="it">of</char> Israel, every man to his tent, and retained those three hundred men. Now the camp of Midian was below him in the valley.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />It happened on the same <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 46:2, 3; Judg. 6:25</char></note>night that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, “Arise, go down against the camp, for I have delivered it into your hand. <verse number="10" style="v" />But if you are afraid to go down, go down to the camp with Purah your servant, <verse number="11" style="v" />and you shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 24:14; 1 Sam. 14:9, 10</char></note>hear what they say; and afterward your hands shall be strengthened to go down against the camp.” Then he went down with Purah his servant to the outpost of the armed men who <char style="it">were</char> in the camp. <verse number="12" style="v" />Now the Midianites and Amalekites, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:3, 33; 8:10</char></note>all the people of the East, were lying in the valley <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:5</char></note>as numerous as locusts; and their camels <char style="it">were</char> without number, as the sand by the seashore in multitude.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And when Gideon had come, there was a man telling a dream to his companion. He said, “I have had a dream: <char style="it">To</char> <char style="it">my</char> surprise, a loaf of barley bread tumbled into the camp of Midian; it came to a tent and struck it so that it fell and overturned, and the tent collapsed.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then his companion answered and said, “This <char style="it">is</char> nothing else but the sword of Gideon the son of Joash, a man of Israel! Into his hand <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:14, 16</char></note>God has delivered Midian and the whole camp.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And so it was, when Gideon heard the telling of the dream and its interpretation, that he worshiped. He returned to the camp of Israel, and said, “Arise, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has delivered the camp of Midian into your hand.” <verse number="16" style="v" />Then he divided the three hundred men <char style="it">into</char> three companies, and he put a trumpet into every man’s hand, with empty pitchers, and torches inside the pitchers. <verse number="17" style="v" />And he said to them, “Look at me and do likewise; watch, and when I come to the edge of the camp you shall do as I do: <verse number="18" style="v" />When I blow the trumpet, I and all who <char style="it">are</char> with me, then you also blow the trumpets on every side of the whole camp, and say, ‘<char style="it">The</char> <char style="it">sword</char> <char style="it">of</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and of Gideon!’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />So Gideon and the hundred men who <char style="it">were</char> with him came to the outpost of the camp at the beginning of the middle watch, just as they had posted the watch; and they blew the trumpets and broke the pitchers that <char style="it">were</char> in their hands. <verse number="20" style="v" />Then the three companies blew the trumpets and broke the pitchers—they held the torches in their left hands and the trumpets in their right hands for blowing—and they cried, “The sword of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and of Gideon!” <verse number="21" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:13, 14; 2 Chr. 20:17</char></note>every man stood in his place all around the camp; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 7:7</char></note>and the whole army ran and cried out and fled. <verse number="22" style="v" />When the three hundred <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:4, 16, 20</char></note>blew the trumpets, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:9; Is. 9:4</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> set <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 14:20; 2 Chr. 20:23</char></note>every man’s sword against his companion throughout the whole camp; and the army fled to Beth Acacia, toward Zererah, as far as the border of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:12</char></note>Abel Meholah, by Tabbath.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And the men of Israel gathered together from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:35</char></note>Naphtali, Asher, and all Manasseh, and pursued the Midianites.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Then Gideon sent messengers throughout all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:27</char></note>mountains of Ephraim, saying, “Come down against the Midianites, and seize from them the watering places as far as Beth Barah and the Jordan.” Then all the men of Ephraim gathered together and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:28</char></note>seized the watering places as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">John 1:28</char></note>Beth Barah and the Jordan. <verse number="25" style="v" />And they captured <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:3</char></note>two princes of the Midianites, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:11; Is. 10:26</char></note>Oreb and Zeeb. They killed Oreb at the rock of Oreb, and Zeeb they killed at the winepress of Zeeb. They pursued Midian and brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:4</char></note>other side of the Jordan.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Gideon Subdues the Midianites</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 12:1; 2 Sam. 19:41</char></note>the men of Ephraim said to him, “Why have you done this to us by not calling us when you went to fight with the Midianites?” And they reprimanded him sharply.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />So he said to them, “What have I done now in comparison with you? <char style="it">Is</char> not the gleaning <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">grapes</char> of Ephraim better than the vintage of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:11</char></note>Abiezer? <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:24, 25</char></note>God has delivered into your hands the princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb. And what was I able to do in comparison with you?” Then their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 15:1</char></note>anger toward him subsided when he said that.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />When Gideon came <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:25</char></note>to the Jordan, he and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:6</char></note>the three hundred men who <char style="it">were</char> with him crossed over, exhausted but still in pursuit. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then he said to the men of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 33:17; Ps. 60:6</char></note>Succoth, “Please give loaves of bread to the people who follow me, for they are exhausted, and I am pursuing Zebah and Zalmunna, kings of Midian.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And the leaders of Succoth said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 20:11; Judg. 8:15</char></note>“<char style="it">Are</char> the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in your hand, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:11</char></note>we should give bread to your army?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So Gideon said, “For this cause, when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has delivered Zebah and Zalmunna into my hand, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:16</char></note>then I will tear your flesh with the thorns of the wilderness and with briers!” <verse number="8" style="v" />Then he went up from there <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:30, 31; 1 Kin. 12:25</char></note>to Penuel and spoke to them in the same way. And the men of Penuel answered him as the men of Succoth had answered. <verse number="9" style="v" />So he also spoke to the men of Penuel, saying, “When I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:27</char></note>come back in peace, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:17</char></note>I will tear down this tower!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Now Zebah and Zalmunna <char style="it">were</char> at Karkor, and their armies with them, about fifteen thousand, all who were left of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:12</char></note>all the army of the people of the East; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:5</char></note>one hundred and twenty thousand men who drew the sword had fallen. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then Gideon went up by the road of those who dwell in tents on the east of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:35, 42</char></note>Nobah and Jogbehah; and he attacked the army while the camp felt <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:27; (1 Thess. 5:3)</char></note>secure. <verse number="12" style="v" />When Zebah and Zalmunna fled, he pursued them; and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:11</char></note>took the two kings of Midian, Zebah and Zalmunna, and routed the whole army.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then Gideon the son of Joash returned from battle, from the Ascent of Heres. <verse number="14" style="v" />And he caught a young man of the men of Succoth and interrogated him; and he wrote down for him the leaders of Succoth and its elders, seventy-seven men. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then he came to the men of Succoth and said, “Here are Zebah and Zalmunna, about whom you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:6</char></note>ridiculed me, saying, ‘<char style="it">Are</char> the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna now in your hand, that we should give bread to your weary men?’ ” <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:7</char></note>And he took the elders of the city, and thorns of the wilderness and briers, and with them he taught the men of Succoth. <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:9</char></note>Then he tore down the tower of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:25</char></note>Penuel and killed the men of the city.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And he said to Zebah and Zalmunna, “What kind of men <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">they</char> whom you killed at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:6; Ps. 89:12</char></note>Tabor?”</para>
	<para style="p">So they answered, “As you <char style="it">are,</char> so <char style="it">were</char> they; each one resembled the son of a king.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then he said, “They <char style="it">were</char> my brothers, the sons of my mother. <char style="it">As</char> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, if you had let them live, I would not kill you.” <verse number="20" style="v" />And he said to Jether his firstborn, “Rise, kill them!” But the youth would not draw his sword; for he was afraid, because he <char style="it">was</char> still a youth.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />So Zebah and Zalmunna said, “Rise yourself, and kill us; for as a man <char style="it">is, so is</char> his strength.” So Gideon arose and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 83:11</char></note>killed Zebah and Zalmunna, and took the crescent ornaments that <char style="it">were</char> on their camels’ necks.</para>
	<para style="s">Gideon’s Ephod</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then the men of Israel said to Gideon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Judg. 9:8)</char></note>“Rule over us, both you and your son, and your grandson also; for you have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:9; 9:17</char></note>delivered us from the hand of Midian.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />But Gideon said to them, “I will not rule over you, nor shall my son rule over you; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 8:7; 10:19; 12:12; Ps. 10:16</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> shall rule over you.” <verse number="24" style="v" />Then Gideon said to them, “I would like to make a request of you, that each of you would give me the earrings from his plunder.” For they had golden earrings, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 37:25, 28</char></note>because they <char style="it">were</char> Ishmaelites.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />So they answered, “We will gladly give <char style="it">them.</char>” And they spread out a garment, and each man threw into it the earrings from his plunder. <verse number="26" style="v" />Now the weight of the gold earrings that he requested was one thousand seven hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of gold, besides the crescent ornaments, pendants, and purple robes which <char style="it">were</char> on the kings of Midian, and besides the chains that <char style="it">were</char> around their camels’ necks. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then Gideon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:5</char></note>made it into an ephod and set it up in his city, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:11, 24</char></note>Ophrah. And all Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 106:39)</char></note>played the harlot with it there. It became <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:16</char></note>a snare to Gideon and to his house.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Thus Midian was subdued before the children of Israel, so that they lifted their heads no more. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:31</char></note>And the country was quiet for forty years in the days of Gideon.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Gideon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:32; 7:1</char></note>Jerubbaal the son of Joash went and dwelt in his own house. <verse number="30" style="v" />Gideon had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:2, 5</char></note>seventy sons who were his own offspring, for he had many wives. <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:1</char></note>And his concubine who <char style="it">was</char> in Shechem also bore him a son, whose name he called Abimelech. <verse number="32" style="v" />Now Gideon the son of Joash died <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 25:8; Job 5:26</char></note>at a good old age, and was buried in the tomb of Joash his father, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:24; 8:27</char></note>in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />So it was, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:19</char></note>as soon as Gideon was dead, that the children of Israel again <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:17</char></note>played the harlot with the Baals, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:4, 46</char></note>and made Baal-Berith their god. <verse number="34" style="v" />Thus the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:9; Judg. 3:7; Ps. 78:11, 42; 106:13, 21</char></note>did not remember the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, who had delivered them from the hands of all their enemies on every side; <verse number="35" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:16–18</char></note>nor did they show kindness to the house of Jerubbaal (Gideon) in accordance with the good he had done for Israel.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Abimelech’s Conspiracy</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Abimelech the son of Jerubbaal went to Shechem, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:31, 35</char></note>his mother’s brothers, and spoke with them and with all the family of the house of his mother’s father, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Please speak in the hearing of all the men of Shechem: ‘Which is better for you, that all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:30; 9:5, 18</char></note>seventy of the sons of Jerubbaal reign over you, or that one reign over you?’ Remember that I <char style="it">am</char> your own flesh and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 29:14</char></note>bone.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />And his mother’s brothers spoke all these words concerning him in the hearing of all the men of Shechem; and their heart was inclined to follow Abimelech, for they said, “He is our <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 29:15</char></note>brother.” <verse number="4" style="v" />So they gave him seventy <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver from the temple of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:33</char></note>Baal-Berith, with which Abimelech hired <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:3; 2 Chr. 13:7; Acts 17:5</char></note>worthless and reckless men; and they followed him. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then he went to his father’s house <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:24</char></note>at Ophrah and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:30; 9:2, 18; 2 Kin. 11:1, 2</char></note>killed his brothers, the seventy sons of Jerubbaal, on one stone. But Jotham the youngest son of Jerubbaal was left, because he hid himself. <verse number="6" style="v" />And all the men of Shechem gathered together, all of Beth Millo, and they went and made Abimelech king beside the terebinth tree at the pillar that <char style="it">was</char> in Shechem.</para>
	<para style="s">The Parable of the Trees</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Now when they told Jotham, he went and stood on top of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 11:29; 27:12; Josh. 8:33; John 4:20</char></note>Mount Gerizim, and lifted his voice and cried out. And he said to them:</para>
	<para style="q1">“Listen to me, you men of Shechem,</para>
	<para style="q2">That God may listen to you!</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="8" style="v" />“The<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:9</char></note> trees once went forth to anoint a king over them.</para>
	<para style="q2">And they said to the olive tree,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:22, 23</char></note>‘Reign over us!’</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="9" style="v" />But the olive tree said to them,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘Should I cease giving my oil,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(John 5:23)</char></note>With which they honor God and men,</para>
	<para style="q2">And go to sway over trees?’</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="10" style="v" />“Then the trees said to the fig tree,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘You come <char style="it">and</char> reign over us!’</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="11" style="v" />But the fig tree said to them,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘Should I cease my sweetness and my good fruit,</para>
	<para style="q2">And go to sway over trees?’</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="12" style="v" />“Then the trees said to the vine,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘You come <char style="it">and</char> reign over us!’</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="13" style="v" />But the vine said to them,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘Should I cease my new wine,</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 104:15</char></note>Which cheers <char style="it">both</char> God and men,</para>
	<para style="q2">And go to sway over trees?’</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="14" style="v" />“Then all the trees said to the bramble,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘You come <char style="it">and</char> reign over us!’</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="15" style="v" />And the bramble said to the trees,</para>
	<para style="q2">‘If in truth you anoint me as king over you,</para>
	<para style="q2"><char style="it">Then</char> come <char style="it">and</char> take shelter in my <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 30:2; Dan. 4:12; Hos. 14:7</char></note>shade;</para>
	<para style="q2">But if not, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:28; Judg. 9:20; Ezek. 19:14</char></note>let fire come out of the bramble</para>
	<para style="q2">And devour the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:9; Is. 2:13; Ezek. 31:3</char></note>cedars of Lebanon!’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />“Now therefore, if you have acted in truth and sincerity in making Abimelech king, and if you have dealt well with Jerubbaal and his house, and have done to him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:35</char></note>as he deserves— <verse number="17" style="v" />for my <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7</char></note>father fought for you, risked his life, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:22</char></note>delivered you out of the hand of Midian; <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:30, 35; 9:2, 5, 6</char></note>but you have risen up against my father’s house this day, and killed his seventy sons on one stone, and made Abimelech, the son of his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:31</char></note>female servant, king over the men of Shechem, because he is your brother— <verse number="19" style="v" />if then you have acted in truth and sincerity with Jerubbaal and with his house this day, <char style="it">then</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 8:6; (Phil. 3:3)</char></note>rejoice in Abimelech, and let him also rejoice in you. <verse number="20" style="v" />“But if not, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:15, 45, 56, 57</char></note>let fire come from Abimelech and devour the men of Shechem and Beth Millo; and let fire come from the men of Shechem and from Beth Millo and devour Abimelech!” <verse number="21" style="v" />And Jotham ran away and fled; and he went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:16</char></note>Beer and dwelt there, for fear of Abimelech his brother.</para>
	<para style="s">Downfall of Abimelech</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />After Abimelech had reigned over Israel three years, <verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 12:15; Is. 19:14</char></note>God sent a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 16:14; 18:9, 10; 1 Kin. 22:22; 2 Chr. 18:22</char></note>spirit of ill will between Abimelech and the men of Shechem; and the men of Shechem <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 33:1</char></note>dealt treacherously with Abimelech, <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:32;  Esth. 9:25; Matt. 23:35, 36</char></note>that the crime <char style="it">done</char> to the seventy sons of Jerubbaal might be settled and their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:33</char></note>blood be laid on Abimelech their brother, who killed them, and on the men of Shechem, who aided him in the killing of his brothers. <verse number="25" style="v" />And the men of Shechem set men in ambush against him on the tops of the mountains, and they robbed all who passed by them along that way; and it was told Abimelech.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Now Gaal the son of Ebed came with his brothers and went over to Shechem; and the men of Shechem put their confidence in him. <verse number="27" style="v" />So they went out into the fields, and gathered <char style="it">grapes</char> from their vineyards and trod <char style="it">them,</char> and made merry. And they went into <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:4</char></note>the house of their god, and ate and drank, and cursed Abimelech. <verse number="28" style="v" />Then Gaal the son of Ebed said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:10; 1 Kin. 12:16</char></note>“Who <char style="it">is</char> Abimelech, and who <char style="it">is</char> Shechem, that we should serve him? <char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">he</char> not the son of Jerubbaal, and <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">not</char> Zebul his officer? Serve the men of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:2, 6; Josh. 24:32</char></note>Hamor the father of Shechem; but why should we serve him? <verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 15:4</char></note>If only this people were under my authority! Then I would remove Abimelech.” So he said to Abimelech, “Increase your army and come out!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />When Zebul, the ruler of the city, heard the words of Gaal the son of Ebed, his anger was aroused. <verse number="31" style="v" />And he sent messengers to Abimelech secretly, saying, “Take note! Gaal the son of Ebed and his brothers have come to Shechem; and here they are, fortifying the city against you. <verse number="32" style="v" />Now therefore, get up by night, you and the people who <char style="it">are</char> with you, and lie in wait in the field. <verse number="33" style="v" />And it shall be, as soon as the sun is up in the morning, <char style="it">that</char> you shall rise early and rush upon the city; and <char style="it">when</char> he and the people who are with him come out against you, you may then do to them as you find opportunity.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />So Abimelech and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> with him rose by night, and lay in wait against Shechem in four companies. <verse number="35" style="v" />When Gaal the son of Ebed went out and stood in the entrance to the city gate, Abimelech and the people who <char style="it">were</char> with him rose from lying in wait. <verse number="36" style="v" />And when Gaal saw the people, he said to Zebul, “Look, people are coming down from the tops of the mountains!”</para>
	<para style="p">But Zebul said to him, “You see the shadows of the mountains as <char style="it">if</char> <char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">were</char> men.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" />So Gaal spoke again and said, “See, people are coming down from the center of the land, and another company is coming from the Diviners’ Terebinth Tree.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />Then Zebul said to him, “Where indeed <char style="it">is</char> your mouth now, with which you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:28, 29</char></note>said, ‘Who is Abimelech, that we should serve him?’ <char style="it">Are</char> not these the people whom you despised? Go out, if you will, and fight with them now.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />So Gaal went out, leading the men of Shechem, and fought with Abimelech. <verse number="40" style="v" />And Abimelech chased him, and he fled from him; and many fell wounded, to the <char style="it">very</char> entrance of the gate. <verse number="41" style="v" />Then Abimelech dwelt at Arumah, and Zebul drove out Gaal and his brothers, so that they would not dwell in Shechem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" />And it came about on the next day that the people went out into the field, and they told Abimelech. <verse number="43" style="v" />So he took his people, divided them into three companies, and lay in wait in the field. And he looked, and there were the people, coming out of the city; and he rose against them and attacked them. <verse number="44" style="v" />Then Abimelech and the company that <char style="it">was</char> with him rushed forward and stood at the entrance of the gate of the city; and the <char style="it">other</char> two companies rushed upon all who <char style="it">were</char> in the fields and killed them. <verse number="45" style="v" />So Abimelech fought against the city all that day; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:20</char></note>he took the city and killed the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it; and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 29:23; 2 Kin. 3:25</char></note>demolished the city and sowed it with salt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" />Now when all the men of the tower of Shechem had heard <char style="it">that,</char> they entered the stronghold of the temple <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:33</char></note>of the god Berith. <verse number="47" style="v" />And it was told Abimelech that all the men of the tower of Shechem were gathered together. <verse number="48" style="v" />Then Abimelech went up to Mount <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 68:14</char></note>Zalmon, he and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> with him. And Abimelech took an ax in his hand and cut down a bough from the trees, and took it and laid <char style="it">it</char> on his shoulder; then he said to the people who were with him, “What you have seen me do, make haste <char style="it">and</char> do as I <char style="it">have</char> <char style="it">done.</char>” <verse number="49" style="v" />So each of the people likewise cut down his own bough and followed Abimelech, put <char style="it">them</char> against the stronghold, and set the stronghold on fire above them, so that all the people of the tower of Shechem died, about a thousand men and women.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" />Then Abimelech went to Thebez, and he encamped against Thebez and took it. <verse number="51" style="v" />But there was a strong tower in the city, and all the men and women—all the people of the city—fled there and shut themselves in; then they went up to the top of the tower. <verse number="52" style="v" />So Abimelech came as far as the tower and fought against it; and he drew near the door of the tower to burn it with fire. <verse number="53" style="v" />But a certain woman <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 11:21</char></note>dropped an upper millstone on Abimelech’s head and crushed his skull. <verse number="54" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 31:4</char></note>he called quickly to the young man, his armorbearer, and said to him, “Draw your sword and kill me, lest men say of me, ‘A woman killed him.’ ” So his young man thrust him through, and he died. <verse number="55" style="v" />And when the men of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, they departed, every man to his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="56" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:24; Job 31:3; Prov. 5:22</char></note>Thus God repaid the wickedness of Abimelech, which he had done to his father by killing his seventy brothers. <verse number="57" style="v" />And all the evil of the men of Shechem God returned on their own heads, and on them came <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:20</char></note>the curse of Jotham the son of Jerubbaal.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Tola</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />After Abimelech there <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:16</char></note>arose to save Israel Tola the son of Puah, the son of Dodo, a man of Issachar; and he dwelt in Shamir in the mountains of Ephraim. <verse number="2" style="v" />He judged Israel twenty-three years; and he died and was buried in Shamir.</para>
	<para style="s">Jair</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />After him arose Jair, a Gileadite; and he judged Israel twenty-two years. <verse number="4" style="v" />Now he had thirty sons who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:10; 12:14</char></note>rode on thirty donkeys; they also had thirty towns, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:14</char></note>which are called “Havoth Jair” to this day, which <char style="it">are</char> in the land of Gilead. <verse number="5" style="v" />And Jair died and was buried in Camon.</para>
	<para style="s">Israel Oppressed Again</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:11; 3:7; 6:1; 13:1</char></note>the children of Israel again did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:13</char></note>served the Baals and the Ashtoreths, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:12</char></note>the gods of Syria, the gods of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:33; Ps. 106:36</char></note>Sidon, the gods of Moab, the gods of the people of Ammon, and the gods of the Philistines; and they forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and did not serve Him. <verse number="7" style="v" />So the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was hot against Israel; and He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:14; 4:2; 1 Sam. 12:9</char></note>sold them into the hands of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:1</char></note>Philistines and into the hands of the people of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:13</char></note>Ammon. <verse number="8" style="v" />From that year they harassed and oppressed the children of Israel for eighteen years—all the children of Israel who <char style="it">were</char> on the other side of the Jordan in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:33</char></note>land of the Amorites, in Gilead. <verse number="9" style="v" />Moreover the people of Ammon crossed over the Jordan to fight against Judah also, against Benjamin, and against the house of Ephraim, so that Israel was severely distressed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:6; 1 Sam. 12:10</char></note>And the children of Israel cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, “We have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 1:41</char></note>sinned against You, because we have both forsaken our God and served the Baals!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to the children of Israel, “<char style="it">Did</char> <char style="it">I</char> not <char style="it">deliver</char> <char style="it">you</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:30</char></note>from the Egyptians and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:21, 24, 25</char></note>from the Amorites and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:12, 13</char></note>from the people of Ammon and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:31</char></note>from the Philistines? <verse number="12" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:31; 5:19</char></note>the Sidonians <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:3; 7:12</char></note>and Amalekites and Maonites  <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:42, 43</char></note>oppressed you; and you cried out to Me, and I delivered you from their hand. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 32:15; Judg. 2:12; Jer. 2:13)</char></note>Yet you have forsaken Me and served other gods. Therefore I will deliver you no more. <verse number="14" style="v" />“Go and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:37, 38</char></note>cry out to the gods which you have chosen; let them deliver you in your time of distress.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And the children of Israel said to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, “We have sinned! <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 3:18; 2 Sam. 15:26</char></note>Do to us whatever seems best to You; only deliver us this day, we pray.” <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 7:14; Jer. 18:7, 8</char></note>So they put away the foreign gods from among them and served the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:44, 45; Is. 63:9</char></note>His soul could no longer endure the misery of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then the people of Ammon gathered together and encamped in Gilead. And the children of Israel assembled together and encamped in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 31:49; Judg. 11:11, 29</char></note>Mizpah. <verse number="18" style="v" />And the people, the leaders of Gilead, said to one another, “Who <char style="it">is</char> the man who will begin the fight against the people of Ammon? He shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:8, 11</char></note>be head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.”</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jephthah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Heb. 11:32</char></note>Jephthah the Gileadite was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:12; 2 Kin. 5:1</char></note>a mighty man of valor, but he <char style="it">was</char> the son of a harlot; and Gilead begot Jephthah. <verse number="2" style="v" />Gilead’s wife bore sons; and when his wife’s sons grew up, they drove Jephthah out, and said to him, “You shall have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 21:10; Deut. 23:2</char></note>no inheritance in our father’s house, for you <char style="it">are</char> the son of another woman.” <verse number="3" style="v" />Then Jephthah fled from his brothers and dwelt in the land of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 10:6, 8</char></note>Tob; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 22:2</char></note>worthless men banded together with Jephthah and went out <char style="it">raiding</char> with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />It came to pass after a time that the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:9, 17</char></note>people of Ammon made war against Israel. <verse number="5" style="v" />And so it was, when the people of Ammon made war against Israel, that the elders of Gilead went to get Jephthah from the land of Tob. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then they said to Jephthah, “Come and be our commander, that we may fight against the people of Ammon.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 26:27</char></note>“Did you not hate me, and expel me from my father’s house? Why have you come to me now when you are in distress?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:18</char></note>And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, “That is why we have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Luke 17:4)</char></note>turned again to you now, that you may go with us and fight against the people of Ammon, and be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:18</char></note>our head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead, “If you take me back home to fight against the people of Ammon, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivers them to me, shall I be your head?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 31:49, 50; Jer. 29:23; 42:5</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will be a witness between us, if we do not do according to your words.” <verse number="11" style="v" />Then Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people made him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:8</char></note>head and commander over them; and Jephthah spoke all his words <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:17; 20:1; 1 Sam. 10:17</char></note>before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Mizpah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Now Jephthah sent messengers to the king of the people of Ammon, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 16:10</char></note>“What do you have against me, that you have come to fight against me in my land?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And the king of the people of Ammon answered the messengers of Jephthah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24–26</char></note>“Because Israel took away my land when they came up out of Egypt, from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:9</char></note>the Arnon as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:22</char></note>the Jabbok, and to the Jordan. Now therefore, restore those <char style="it">lands</char> peaceably.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So Jephthah again sent messengers to the king of the people of Ammon, <verse number="15" style="v" />and said to him, “Thus says Jephthah: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:9, 19</char></note>‘Israel did not take away the land of Moab, nor the land of the people of Ammon; <verse number="16" style="v" />for when Israel came up from Egypt, they walked through the wilderness as far as the Red Sea and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:26; 20:1</char></note>came to Kadesh. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 20:14</char></note>Israel sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, “Please let me pass through your land.” <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 20:14–21</char></note>But the king of Edom would not heed. And in like manner they sent to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:9</char></note>king of Moab, but he would not <char style="it">consent.</char> So Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 20:1</char></note>remained in Kadesh. <verse number="18" style="v" />And they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:9, 18, 19</char></note>went along through the wilderness and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:4</char></note>bypassed the land of Edom and the land of Moab, came to the east side of the land of Moab, and encamped on the other side of the Arnon. But they did not enter the border of Moab, for the Arnon <char style="it">was</char> the border of Moab. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:21; Deut. 2:26–36</char></note>Israel sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites, king of Heshbon; and Israel said to him, “Please <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:22; Deut. 2:27</char></note>let us pass through your land into our place.” <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:23; Deut. 2:27</char></note>But Sihon did not trust Israel to pass through his territory. So Sihon gathered all his people together, encamped in Jahaz, and fought against Israel. <verse number="21" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:8</char></note>delivered Sihon and all his people into the hand of Israel, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24, 25</char></note>defeated them. Thus Israel gained possession of all the land of the Amorites, who inhabited that country. <verse number="22" style="v" />They took possession of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:36, 37</char></note>all the territory of the Amorites, from the Arnon to the Jabbok and from the wilderness to the Jordan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />‘And now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel has dispossessed the Amorites from before His people Israel; should you then possess it? <verse number="24" style="v" />Will you not possess whatever <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:29; 1 Kin. 11:7; Jer. 48:7</char></note>Chemosh your god gives you to possess? So whatever <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 9:4, 5; Josh. 3:10)</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God takes possession of before us, we will possess. <verse number="25" style="v" />And now, <char style="it">are</char> you any better than <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:2; Josh. 24:9; Mic. 6:5</char></note>Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab? Did he ever strive against Israel? Did he ever fight against them? <verse number="26" style="v" />While Israel dwelt in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:25, 26</char></note>Heshbon and its villages, in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:36</char></note>Aroer and its villages, and in all the cities along the banks of the Arnon, for three hundred years, why did you not recover <char style="it">them</char> within that time? <verse number="27" style="v" />Therefore I have not sinned against you, but you wronged me by fighting against me. May the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:25</char></note>the Judge, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 16:5; 31:53; (1 Sam. 24:12, 15)</char></note>render judgment this day between the children of Israel and the people of Ammon.’ ” <verse number="28" style="v" />However, the king of the people of Ammon did not heed the words which Jephthah sent him.</para>
	<para style="s">Jephthah’s Vow and Victory</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:10</char></note>the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon Jephthah, and he passed through Gilead and Manasseh, and passed through Mizpah of Gilead; and from Mizpah of Gilead he advanced <char style="it">toward</char> the people of Ammon. <verse number="30" style="v" />And Jephthah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 28:20; Num. 30:2; 1 Sam. 1:11</char></note>made a vow to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said, “If You will indeed deliver the people of Ammon into my hands, <verse number="31" style="v" />then it will be that whatever comes out of the doors of my house to meet me, when I return in peace from the people of Ammon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:2, 3, 28; 1 Sam. 1:11</char></note>shall surely be the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 66:13</char></note>and I will offer it up as a burnt offering.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />So Jephthah advanced toward the people of Ammon to fight against them, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered them into his hands. <verse number="33" style="v" />And he defeated them from Aroer as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 27:17</char></note>Minnith—twenty cities—and to Abel Keramim, with a very great slaughter. Thus the people of Ammon were subdued before the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="s">Jephthah’s Daughter</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />When Jephthah came to his house at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:17; 11:11</char></note>Mizpah, there was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:20; 1 Sam. 18:6; Ps. 68:25; Jer. 31:4</char></note>his daughter, coming out to meet him with timbrels and dancing; and she <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">his</char> only child. Besides her he had neither son nor daughter. <verse number="35" style="v" />And it came to pass, when he saw her, that he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 37:29, 34</char></note>tore his clothes, and said, “Alas, my daughter! You have brought me very low! You are among those who trouble me! For I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Eccl. 5:2, 4, 5</char></note>have given my word to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 30:2</char></note>I cannot go back on it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />So she said to him, “My father, <char style="it">if</char> you have given your word to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 30:2</char></note>do to me according to what has gone out of your mouth, because <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 18:19, 31</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has avenged you of your enemies, the people of Ammon.” <verse number="37" style="v" />Then she said to her father, “Let this thing be done for me: let me alone for two months, that I may go and wander on the mountains and bewail my virginity, my friends and I.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />So he said, “Go.” And he sent her away <char style="it">for</char> two months; and she went with her friends, and bewailed her virginity on the mountains. <verse number="39" style="v" />And it was so at the end of two months that she returned to her father, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:31</char></note>carried out his vow with her which he had vowed. She knew no man.</para>
	<para style="p">And it became a custom in Israel <verse number="40" style="v" /><char style="it">that</char> the daughters of Israel went four days each year to lament the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Jephthah’s Conflict with Ephraim</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:1</char></note>the men of Ephraim gathered together, crossed over toward Zaphon, and said to Jephthah, “Why did you cross over to fight against the people of Ammon, and did not call us to go with you? We will burn your house down on you with fire!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />And Jephthah said to them, “My people and I were in a great struggle with the people of Ammon; and when I called you, you did not deliver me out of their hands. <verse number="3" style="v" />So when I saw that you would not deliver <char style="it">me,</char> I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 19:5; 28:21; Job 13:14</char></note>took my life in my hands and crossed over against the people of Ammon; and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered them into my hand. Why then have you come up to me this day to fight against me?” <verse number="4" style="v" />Now Jephthah gathered together all the men of Gilead and fought against Ephraim. And the men of Gilead defeated Ephraim, because they said, “You Gileadites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:10</char></note><char style="it">are</char> fugitives of Ephraim among the Ephraimites <char style="it">and</char> among the Manassites.” <verse number="5" style="v" />The Gileadites seized the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:11</char></note>fords of the Jordan before the Ephraimites <char style="it">arrived.</char> And when <char style="it">any</char> Ephraimite who escaped said, “Let me cross over,” the men of Gilead would say to him, “<char style="it">Are</char> you an Ephraimite?” If he said, “No,” <verse number="6" style="v" />then they would say to him, “Then say, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 69:2, 15</char></note>‘Shibboleth’!” And he would say, “Sibboleth,” for he could not pronounce <char style="it">it</char> right. Then they would take him and kill him at the fords of the Jordan. There fell at that time forty-two thousand Ephraimites.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And Jephthah judged Israel six years. Then Jephthah the Gileadite died and was buried in among the cities of Gilead.</para>
	<para style="s">Ibzan, Elon, and Abdon</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />After him, Ibzan of Bethlehem judged Israel. <verse number="9" style="v" />He had thirty sons. And he gave away thirty daughters in marriage, and brought in thirty daughters from elsewhere for his sons. He judged Israel seven years. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then Ibzan died and was buried at Bethlehem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />After him, Elon the Zebulunite judged Israel. He judged Israel ten years. <verse number="12" style="v" />And Elon the Zebulunite died and was buried at Aijalon in the country of Zebulun.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />After him, Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite judged Israel. <verse number="14" style="v" />He had forty sons and thirty grandsons, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:10; 10:4</char></note>rode on seventy young donkeys. He judged Israel eight years. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite died and was buried in Pirathon in the land of Ephraim, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:13, 27; 5:14</char></note>in the mountains of the Amalekites.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Birth of Samson</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Again the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:11</char></note>did evil in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:7; 1 Sam. 12:9</char></note>into the hand of the Philistines for forty years.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Now there was a certain man from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:41; Judg. 16:31</char></note>Zorah, of the family of the Danites, whose name <char style="it">was</char> Manoah; and his wife <char style="it">was</char> barren and had no children. <verse number="3" style="v" />And the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:12</char></note>Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared to the woman and said to her, “Indeed now, you are barren and have borne no children, but you shall conceive and bear a son. <verse number="4" style="v" />Now therefore, please be careful <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:2, 3, 20; Judg. 13:4; Luke 1:15</char></note>not to drink wine or <char style="it">similar</char> drink, and not to eat anything unclean. <verse number="5" style="v" />For behold, you shall conceive and bear a son. And no <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:5; 1 Sam. 1:11</char></note>razor shall come upon his head, for the child shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:2</char></note>a Nazirite to God from the womb; and he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 7:13; 2 Sam. 8:1; 1 Chr. 18:1</char></note>begin to deliver Israel out of the hand of the Philistines.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So the woman came and told her husband, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:24–30</char></note>“A Man of God came to me, and His <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 28:3; Luke 9:29; Acts 6:15</char></note>countenance <char style="it">was</char> like the countenance of the Angel of God, very awesome; but I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:17, 18</char></note>did not ask Him where He <char style="it">was</char> from, and He did not tell me His name. <verse number="7" style="v" />And He said to me, ‘Behold, you shall conceive and bear a son. Now drink no wine or <char style="it">similar</char> drink, nor eat anything unclean, for the child shall be a Nazirite to God from the womb to the day of his death.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then Manoah prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and said, “O my Lord, please let the Man of God whom You sent come to us again and teach us what we shall do for the child who will be born.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And God listened to the voice of Manoah, and the Angel of God came to the woman again as she was sitting in the field; but Manoah her husband <char style="it">was</char> not with her. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then the woman ran in haste and told her husband, and said to him, “Look, the Man who came to me the <char style="it">other</char> day has just now appeared to me!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So Manoah arose and followed his wife. When he came to the Man, he said to Him, “Are You the Man who spoke to this woman?”</para>
	<para style="p">And He said, “I <char style="it">am.</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Manoah said, “Now let Your words come <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">pass!</char> What will be the boy’s rule of life, and his work?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Manoah, “Of all that I said to the woman let her be careful. <verse number="14" style="v" />She may not eat anything that comes from the vine, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:3, 4; Judg. 13:4</char></note>nor may she drink wine or <char style="it">similar</char> drink, nor eat anything unclean. All that I commanded her let her observe.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then Manoah said to the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, “Please <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:5; Judg. 6:18</char></note>let us detain You, and we will prepare a young goat for You.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Manoah, “Though you detain Me, I will not eat your food. But if you offer a burnt offering, you must offer it to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” (For Manoah did not know He <char style="it">was</char> the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />Then Manoah said to the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, “What <char style="it">is</char> Your name, that when Your words come <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">pass</char> we may honor You?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />And the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:29</char></note>“Why do you ask My name, seeing it <char style="it">is</char> wonderful?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />So Manoah took the young goat with the grain offering, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:19–21</char></note>and offered it upon the rock to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And He did a wondrous thing while Manoah and his wife looked on— <verse number="20" style="v" />it happened as the flame went up toward heaven from the altar—the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> ascended in the flame of the altar! When Manoah and his wife saw <char style="it">this,</char> they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 9:24; 1 Chr. 21:16; Ezek. 1:28; Matt. 17:6</char></note>fell on their faces to the ground. <verse number="21" style="v" />When the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared no more to Manoah and his wife, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:22</char></note>then Manoah knew that He <char style="it">was</char> the Angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And Manoah said to his wife, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 32:30; Ex. 33:20; Deut. 5:26; Judg. 6:22, 23</char></note>“We shall surely die, because we have seen God!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />But his wife said to him, “If the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had desired to kill us, He would not have accepted a burnt offering and a grain offering from our hands, nor would He have shown us all these <char style="it">things,</char> nor would He have told us <char style="it">such</char> <char style="it">things</char> as these at this time.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So the woman bore a son and called his name <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Heb. 11:32</char></note>Samson; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 3:19; Luke 1:80</char></note>the child grew, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> blessed him. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:10; 1 Sam. 11:6; Matt. 4:1</char></note>And the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> began to move upon him at Mahaneh Dan <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:33; Judg. 18:11</char></note>between Zorah and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 16:31</char></note>Eshtaol.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Samson’s Philistine Wife</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now Samson went down <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 38:13; Josh. 15:10, 57</char></note>to Timnah, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:2</char></note>saw a woman in Timnah of the daughters of the Philistines. <verse number="2" style="v" />So he went up and told his father and mother, saying, “I have seen a woman in Timnah of the daughters of the Philistines; now therefore, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 21:21</char></note>get her for me as a wife.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then his father and mother said to him, “<char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">there</char> no woman among the daughters of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 24:3, 4</char></note>your brethren, or among all my people, that you must go and get a wife from the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:14; Ex. 34:16; Deut. 7:3</char></note>uncircumcised Philistines?”</para>
	<para style="p">And Samson said to his father, “Get her for me, for she pleases me well.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />But his father and mother did not know that it was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:20; 1 Kin. 12:15; 2 Kin. 6:33; 2 Chr. 10:15</char></note>of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>—that He was seeking an occasion to move against the Philistines. For at that time <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:48; Judg. 13:1</char></note>the Philistines had dominion over Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So Samson went down to Timnah with his father and mother, and came to the vineyards of Timnah.</para>
	<para style="p">Now <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">his</char> surprise, a young lion <char style="it">came</char> roaring against him. <verse number="6" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:10</char></note>the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came mightily upon him, and he tore the lion apart as one would have torn apart a young goat, though <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">had</char> nothing in his hand. But he did not tell his father or his mother what he had done.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then he went down and talked with the woman; and she pleased Samson well. <verse number="8" style="v" />After some time, when he returned to get her, he turned aside to see the carcass of the lion. And behold, a swarm of bees and honey <char style="it">were</char> in the carcass of the lion. <verse number="9" style="v" />He took some of it in his hands and went along, eating. When he came to his father and mother, he gave <char style="it">some</char> to them, and they also ate. But he did not tell them that he had taken the honey out of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:27</char></note>carcass of the lion.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So his father went down to the woman. And Samson gave a feast there, for young men used to do so. <verse number="11" style="v" />And it happened, when they saw him, that they brought thirty companions to be with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then Samson said to them, “Let me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 10:1; Ezek. 17:2</char></note>pose a riddle to you. If you can correctly solve and explain it to me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 29:27</char></note>within the seven days of the feast, then I will give you thirty linen garments and thirty <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 45:22; 2 Kin. 5:22</char></note>changes of clothing. <verse number="13" style="v" />But if you cannot explain <char style="it">it</char> to me, then you shall give me thirty linen garments and thirty changes of clothing.”</para>
	<para style="p">And they said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 17:2</char></note>“Pose your riddle, that we may hear it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So he said to them:</para>
	<para style="q1">“Out of the eater came something to eat,</para>
	<para style="q2">And out of the strong came something sweet.”</para>
	<para style="p">Now for three days they could not explain the riddle.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />But it came to pass on the seventh day that they said to Samson’s wife, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 16:5</char></note>“Entice your husband, that he may explain the riddle to us, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 15:6</char></note>or else we will burn you and your father’s house with fire. Have you invited us in order to take what is ours? <char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">that</char> not <char style="it">so?</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Then Samson’s wife wept on him, and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 16:15</char></note>“You only hate me! You do not love me! You have posed a riddle to the sons of my people, but you have not explained <char style="it">it</char> to me.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said to her, “Look, I have not explained <char style="it">it</char> to my father or my mother; so should I explain <char style="it">it</char> to you?” <verse number="17" style="v" />Now she had wept on him the seven days while their feast lasted. And it happened on the seventh day that he told her, because she pressed him so much. Then she explained the riddle to the sons of her people. <verse number="18" style="v" />So the men of the city said to him on the seventh day before the sun went down:</para>
	<para style="q1">“What <char style="it">is</char> sweeter than honey?</para>
	<para style="q2">And what <char style="it">is</char> stronger than a lion?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said to them:</para>
	<para style="q1">“If you had not plowed with my heifer,</para>
	<para style="q2">You would not have solved my riddle!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:10; 13:25</char></note>the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came upon him mightily, and he went down to Ashkelon and killed thirty of their men, took their apparel, and gave the changes <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">clothing</char> to those who had explained the riddle. So his anger was aroused, and he went back up to his father’s house. <verse number="20" style="v" />And Samson’s wife <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 15:2</char></note>was <char style="it">given</char> to his companion, who had been <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">John 3:29</char></note>his best man.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Samson Defeats the Philistines</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />After a while, in the time of wheat harvest, it happened that Samson visited his wife with a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 38:17</char></note>young goat. And he said, “Let me go in to my wife, into <char style="it">her</char> room.” But her father would not permit him to go in.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Her father said, “I really thought that you thoroughly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 14:20</char></note>hated her; therefore I gave her to your companion. <char style="it">Is</char> not her younger sister better than she? Please, take her instead.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />And Samson said to them, “This time I shall be blameless regarding the Philistines if I harm them!” <verse number="4" style="v" />Then Samson went and caught three hundred foxes; and he took torches, turned <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">foxes</char> tail to tail, and put a torch between each pair of tails. <verse number="5" style="v" />When he had set the torches on fire, he let <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">foxes</char> go into the standing grain of the Philistines, and burned up both the shocks and the standing grain, as well as the vineyards <char style="it">and</char> olive groves.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then the Philistines said, “Who has done this?”</para>
	<para style="p">And they answered, “Samson, the son-in-law of the Timnite, because he has taken his wife and given her to his companion.” <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 14:15</char></note>So the Philistines came up and burned her and her father with fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Samson said to them, “Since you would do a thing like this, I will surely take revenge on you, and after that I will cease.” <verse number="8" style="v" />So he attacked them hip and thigh with a great slaughter; then he went down and dwelt in the cleft of the rock of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 11:6</char></note>Etam.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Now the Philistines went up, encamped in Judah, and deployed themselves <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 15:19</char></note>against Lehi. <verse number="10" style="v" />And the men of Judah said, “Why have you come up against us?”</para>
	<para style="p">So they answered, “We have come up to arrest Samson, to do to him as he has done to us.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />Then three thousand men of Judah went down to the cleft of the rock of Etam, and said to Samson, “Do you not know that the Philistines <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:25; Deut. 28:43; Judg. 13:1; 14:4; Ps. 106:40–42</char></note>rule over us? What <char style="it">is</char> this you have done to us?”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said to them, “As they did to me, so I have done to them.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />But they said to him, “We have come down to arrest you, that we may deliver you into the hand of the Philistines.”</para>
	<para style="p">Then Samson said to them, “Swear to me that you will not kill me yourselves.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />So they spoke to him, saying, “No, but we will tie you securely and deliver you into their hand; but we will surely not kill you.” And they bound him with two <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 16:11, 12</char></note>new ropes and brought him up from the rock.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />When he came to Lehi, the Philistines came shouting against him. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:10; 14:6</char></note>the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came mightily upon him; and the ropes that <char style="it">were</char> on his arms became like flax that is burned with fire, and his bonds broke loose from his hands. <verse number="15" style="v" />He found a fresh jawbone of a donkey, reached out his hand and took it, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:8; Josh. 23:10; Judg. 3:31</char></note>killed a thousand men with it. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then Samson said:</para>
	<para style="q1">“With the jawbone of a donkey,</para>
	<para style="q2">Heaps upon heaps,</para>
	<para style="q2">With the jawbone of a donkey</para>
	<para style="q2">I have slain a thousand men!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And so it was, when he had finished speaking, that he threw the jawbone from his hand, and called that place Ramath Lehi.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then he became very thirsty; so he cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 3:7</char></note>“You have given this great deliverance by the hand of Your servant; and now shall I die of thirst and fall into the hand of the uncircumcised?” <verse number="19" style="v" />So God split the hollow place that <char style="it">is</char> in Lehi, and water came out, and he drank; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 45:27; Is. 40:29</char></note>his spirit returned, and he revived. Therefore he called its name En Hakkore, which is in Lehi to this day. <verse number="20" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:2; 12:7–14</char></note>he judged Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 16:31</char></note>twenty years <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:1</char></note>in the days of the Philistines.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Samson and Delilah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now Samson went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:47</char></note>Gaza and saw a harlot there, and went in to her. <verse number="2" style="v" /><char style="it">When</char> the Gazites <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">told,</char> “Samson has come here!” they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 23:26; Ps. 118:10–12</char></note>surrounded <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">place</char> and lay in wait for him all night at the gate of the city. They were quiet all night, saying, “In the morning, when it is daylight, we will kill him.” <verse number="3" style="v" />And Samson lay <char style="it">low</char> till midnight; then he arose at midnight, took hold of the doors of the gate of the city and the two gateposts, pulled them up, bar and all, put <char style="it">them</char> on his shoulders, and carried them to the top of the hill that faces Hebron.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Afterward it happened that he loved a woman in the Valley of Sorek, whose name <char style="it">was</char> Delilah. <verse number="5" style="v" />And the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:3</char></note>lords of the Philistines came up to her and said to her, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 14:15</char></note>“Entice him, and find out where his great strength <char style="it">lies,</char> and by what <char style="it">means</char> we may overpower him, that we may bind him to afflict him; and every one of us will give you eleven hundred <char style="it">pieces</char> of silver.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So Delilah said to Samson, “Please tell me where your great strength <char style="it">lies,</char> and with what you may be bound to afflict you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And Samson said to her, “If they bind me with seven fresh bowstrings, not yet dried, then I shall become weak, and be like any <char style="it">other</char> man.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So the lords of the Philistines brought up to her seven fresh bowstrings, not yet dried, and she bound him with them. <verse number="9" style="v" />Now <char style="it">men</char> <char style="it">were</char> lying in wait, staying with her in the room. And she said to him, “The Philistines <char style="it">are</char> upon you, Samson!” But he broke the bowstrings as a strand of yarn breaks when it touches fire. So the secret of his strength was not known.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Then Delilah said to Samson, “Look, you have mocked me and told me lies. Now, please tell me what you may be bound with.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />So he said to her, “If they bind me securely with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 15:13</char></note>new ropes that have never been used, then I shall become weak, and be like any <char style="it">other</char> man.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Therefore Delilah took new ropes and bound him with them, and said to him, “The Philistines <char style="it">are</char> upon you, Samson!” And <char style="it">men</char> <char style="it">were</char> lying in wait, staying in the room. But he broke them off his arms like a thread.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Delilah said to Samson, “Until now you have mocked me and told me lies. Tell me what you may be bound with.”</para>
	<para style="p">And he said to her, “If you weave the seven locks of my head into the web of the loom”—</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So she wove <char style="it">it</char> tightly with the batten of the loom, and said to him, “The Philistines <char style="it">are</char> upon you, Samson!” But he awoke from his sleep, and pulled out the batten and the web from the loom.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then she said to him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 14:16</char></note>“How can you say, ‘I love you,’ when your heart <char style="it">is</char> not with me? You have mocked me these three times, and have not told me where your great strength <char style="it">lies.</char>” <verse number="16" style="v" />And it came to pass, when she pestered him daily with her words and pressed him, <char style="it">so</char> that his soul was vexed to death, <verse number="17" style="v" />that he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Mic. 7:5)</char></note>told her all his heart, and said to her, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:5; Judg. 13:5</char></note>“No razor has ever come upon my head, for I <char style="it">have</char> <char style="it">been</char> a Nazirite to God from my mother’s womb. If I am shaven, then my strength will leave me, and I shall become weak, and be like any <char style="it">other</char> man.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />When Delilah saw that he had told her all his heart, she sent and called for the lords of the Philistines, saying, “Come up once more, for he has told me all his heart.” So the lords of the Philistines came up to her and brought the money in their hand. <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 7:26, 27</char></note>Then she lulled him to sleep on her knees, and called for a man and had him shave off the seven locks of his head. Then she began to torment him, and his strength left him. <verse number="20" style="v" />And she said, “The Philistines <char style="it">are</char> upon you, Samson!” So he awoke from his sleep, and said, “I will go out as before, at other times, and shake myself free!” But he did not know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:9, 42, 43; (Josh. 7:12); 1 Sam. 16:14; 18:12; 28:15, 16; 2 Chr. 15:2</char></note>had departed from him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then the Philistines took him and put out his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:7</char></note>eyes, and brought him down to Gaza. They bound him with bronze fetters, and he became a grinder in the prison. <verse number="22" style="v" />However, the hair of his head began to grow again after it had been shaven.</para>
	<para style="s">Samson Dies with the Philistines</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Now the lords of the Philistines gathered together to offer a great sacrifice to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 5:2</char></note>Dagon their god, and to rejoice. And they said:</para>
	<para style="q1">“Our god has delivered into our hands</para>
	<para style="q2">Samson our enemy!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />When the people saw him, they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Dan. 5:4</char></note>praised their god; for they said:</para>
	<para style="q1">“Our god has delivered into our hands our enemy,</para>
	<para style="q2">The destroyer of our land,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the one who multiplied our dead.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />So it happened, when their hearts were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:27</char></note>merry, that they said, “Call for Samson, that he may perform for us.” So they called for Samson from the prison, and he performed for them. And they stationed him between the pillars. <verse number="26" style="v" />Then Samson said to the lad who held him by the hand, “Let me feel the pillars which support the temple, so that I can lean on them.” <verse number="27" style="v" />Now the temple was full of men and women. All the lords of the Philistines <char style="it">were</char> there—about three thousand men and women on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 22:8</char></note>roof watching while Samson performed.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Then Samson called to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, “O Lord <char style="sc">God</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 15:15</char></note>remember me, I pray! Strengthen me, I pray, just this once, O God, that I may with one <char style="it">blow</char> take vengeance on the Philistines for my two eyes!” <verse number="29" style="v" />And Samson took hold of the two middle pillars which supported the temple, and he braced himself against them, one on his right and the other on his left. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then Samson said, “Let me die with the Philistines!” And he pushed with <char style="it">all</char> <char style="it">his</char> might, and the temple fell on the lords and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it. So the dead that he killed at his death were more than he had killed in his life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />And his brothers and all his father’s household came down and took him, and brought <char style="it">him</char> up and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:25</char></note>buried him between Zorah and Eshtaol in the tomb of his father Manoah. He had judged Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 15:20</char></note>twenty years.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Micah’s Idolatry</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now there was a man from the mountains of Ephraim, whose name <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:2</char></note>Micah. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he said to his mother, “The eleven hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver that were taken from you, and on which you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:1</char></note>put a curse, even saying it in my ears—here <char style="it">is</char> the silver with me; I took it.”</para>
	<para style="p">And his mother said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 14:19</char></note>“<char style="it">May</char> <char style="it">you</char> <char style="it">be</char> blessed by the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, my son!” <verse number="3" style="v" />So when he had returned the eleven hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver to his mother, his mother said, “I had wholly dedicated the silver from my hand to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for my son, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:4, 23; 34:17; Lev. 19:4</char></note>make a carved image and a molded image; now therefore, I will return it to you.” <verse number="4" style="v" />Thus he returned the silver to his mother. Then his mother <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 46:6</char></note>took two hundred <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver and gave them to the silversmith, and he made it into a carved image and a molded image; and they were in the house of Micah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />The man Micah had a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:24</char></note>shrine, and made an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:27; 18:14</char></note>ephod and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 31:19, 30; Hos. 3:4</char></note>household idols; and he consecrated one of his sons, who became his priest. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:1; 19:1</char></note>In those days <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> no king in Israel; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:8; Judg. 21:25</char></note>everyone did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in his own eyes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Now there was a young man from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:15; Judg. 19:1; Ruth 1:1, 2; Mic. 5:2; Matt. 2:1, 5, 6</char></note>Bethlehem in Judah, of the family of Judah; he <char style="it">was</char> a Levite, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 18:6</char></note>was staying there. <verse number="8" style="v" />The man departed from the city of Bethlehem in Judah to stay wherever he could find <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">place.</char> Then he came to the mountains of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, as he journeyed. <verse number="9" style="v" />And Micah said to him, “Where do you come from?”</para>
	<para style="p">So he said to him, “I <char style="it">am</char> a Levite from Bethlehem in Judah, and I am on my way to find <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">place</char> to stay.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Micah said to him, “Dwell with me, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:19</char></note>and be a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 45:8; Job 29:16</char></note>father and a priest to me, and I will give you ten <char style="it">shekels</char> of silver per year, a suit of clothes, and your sustenance.” So the Levite went in. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then the Levite was content to dwell with the man; and the young man became like one of his sons to him. <verse number="12" style="v" />So Micah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:5</char></note>consecrated the Levite, and the young man <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:30</char></note>became his priest, and lived in the house of Micah. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then Micah said, “Now I know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will be good to me, since I have a Levite as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:4</char></note>priest!”</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Danites Adopt Micah’s Idolatry</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />In <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:6; 19:1; 21:25</char></note>those days <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> no king in Israel. And in those days <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:40–48</char></note>the tribe of the Danites was seeking an inheritance for itself to dwell in; for until that day <char style="it">their</char> inheritance among the tribes of Israel had not fallen to them. <verse number="2" style="v" />So the children of Dan sent five men of their family from their territory, men of valor from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:25</char></note>Zorah and Eshtaol, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:17; Josh. 2:1</char></note>to spy out the land and search it. They said to them, “Go, search the land.” So they went to the mountains of Ephraim, to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:1</char></note>house of Micah, and lodged there. <verse number="3" style="v" />While they <char style="it">were</char> at the house of Micah, they recognized the voice of the young Levite. They turned aside and said to him, “Who brought you here? What are you doing in this <char style="it">place?</char> What do you have here?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />He said to them, “Thus and so Micah did for me. He has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:10, 12</char></note>hired me, and I have become his priest.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So they said to him, “Please <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:5; (Is. 30:1); Hos. 4:12</char></note>inquire of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:1; 17:5; 18:14</char></note>God, that we may know whether the journey on which we go will be prosperous.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And the priest said to them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:6</char></note>“Go in peace. The presence of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">be</char> with you on your way.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So the five men departed and went to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:47</char></note>Laish. They saw the people who <char style="it">were</char> there, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:27–29</char></note>how they dwelt safely, in the manner of the Sidonians, quiet and secure. <char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">were</char> no rulers in the land who might put <char style="it">them</char> to shame for anything. They <char style="it">were</char> far from the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:12</char></note>Sidonians, and they had no ties with anyone.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">spies</char> came back to their brethren at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:2</char></note>Zorah and Eshtaol, and their brethren said to them, “What <char style="it">is</char> your <char style="it">report?</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So they said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:30; Josh. 2:23, 24</char></note>“Arise, let us go up against them. For we have seen the land, and indeed it <char style="it">is</char> very good. <char style="it">Would</char> you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 22:3</char></note><char style="it">do</char> nothing? Do not hesitate to go, <char style="it">and</char> enter to possess the land. <verse number="10" style="v" />When you go, you will come to a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:7, 27</char></note>secure people and a large land. For God has given it into your hands, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 8:9</char></note>a place where <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no lack of anything that <char style="it">is</char> on the earth.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />And six hundred men of the family of the Danites went from there, from Zorah and Eshtaol, armed with weapons of war. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then they went up and encamped in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:60</char></note>Kirjath Jearim in Judah. (Therefore they call that place <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:25</char></note>Mahaneh Dan to this day. There <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is,</char> west of Kirjath Jearim.) <verse number="13" style="v" />And they passed from there to the mountains of Ephraim, and came to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:2</char></note>the house of Micah.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 14:28</char></note>Then the five men who had gone to spy out the country of Laish answered and said to their brethren, “Do you know that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:5</char></note>there are in these houses an ephod, household idols, a carved image, and a molded image? Now therefore, consider what you should do.” <verse number="15" style="v" />So they turned aside there, and came to the house of the young Levite man—to the house of Micah—and greeted him. <verse number="16" style="v" />The <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:11</char></note>six hundred men armed with their weapons of war, who <char style="it">were</char> of the children of Dan, stood by the entrance of the gate. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:2, 14</char></note>the five men who had gone to spy out the land went up. Entering there, they took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:4, 5</char></note>the carved image, the ephod, the household idols, and the molded image. The priest stood at the entrance of the gate with the six hundred men <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> armed with weapons of war.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />When these went into Micah’s house and took the carved image, the ephod, the household idols, and the molded image, the priest said to them, “What are you doing?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And they said to him, “Be quiet, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 21:5; 29:9; 40:4; Mic. 7:16</char></note>put your hand over your mouth, and come with us; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:10</char></note>be a father and a priest to us. <char style="it">Is</char> <char style="it">it</char> better for you to be a priest to the household of one man, or that you be a priest to a tribe and a family in Israel?” <verse number="20" style="v" />So the priest’s heart was glad; and he took the ephod, the household idols, and the carved image, and took his place among the people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then they turned and departed, and put the little ones, the livestock, and the goods in front of them. <verse number="22" style="v" />When they were a good way from the house of Micah, the men who <char style="it">were</char> in the houses near Micah’s house gathered together and overtook the children of Dan. <verse number="23" style="v" />And they called out to the children of Dan. So they turned around and said to Micah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 6:28</char></note>“What ails you, that you have gathered such a company?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So he said, “You have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 31:30; Judg. 17:5</char></note>taken away my gods which I made, and the priest, and you have gone away. Now what more do I have? How can you say to me, ‘What ails you?’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />And the children of Dan said to him, “Do not let your voice be heard among us, lest angry men fall upon you, and you lose your life, with the lives of your household!” <verse number="26" style="v" />Then the children of Dan went their way. And when Micah saw that they <char style="it">were</char> too strong for him, he turned and went back to his house.</para>
	<para style="s">Danites Settle in Laish</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />So they took <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">things</char> Micah had made, and the priest who had belonged to him, and went to Laish, to a people quiet and secure; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:47</char></note>and they struck them with the edge of the sword and burned the city with fire. <verse number="28" style="v" /><char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">was</char> no deliverer, because it <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:7</char></note>far from Sidon, and they had no ties with anyone. It was in the valley that belongs <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:21; 2 Sam. 10:6</char></note>to Beth Rehob. So they rebuilt the city and dwelt there. <verse number="29" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:47</char></note>they called the name of the city <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:1; 1 Kin. 12:29, 30; 15:20</char></note>Dan, after the name of Dan their father, who was born to Israel. However, the name of the city formerly <char style="it">was</char> Laish.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Then the children of Dan set up for themselves the carved image; and Jonathan the son of Gershom, the son of Manasseh, and his sons were priests to the tribe of Dan <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 15:29</char></note>until the day of the captivity of the land. <verse number="31" style="v" />So they set up for themselves Micah’s carved image which he made, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:1–32; Josh. 18:1, 8; Judg. 19:18; 21:12</char></note>all the time that the house of God was in Shiloh.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Levite’s Concubine</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass in those days, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:6; 18:1; 21:25</char></note>when <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> no king in Israel, that there was a certain Levite staying in the remote mountains of Ephraim. He took for himself a concubine from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:7; Ruth 1:1</char></note>Bethlehem in Judah. <verse number="2" style="v" />But his concubine played the harlot against him, and went away from him to her father’s house at Bethlehem in Judah, and was there four whole months. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then her husband arose and went after her, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:3; 50:21</char></note>speak kindly to her <char style="it">and</char> bring her back, having his servant and a couple of donkeys with him. So she brought him into her father’s house; and when the father of the young woman saw him, he was glad to meet him. <verse number="4" style="v" />Now his father-in-law, the young woman’s father, detained him; and he stayed with him three days. So they ate and drank and lodged there.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />Then it came to pass on the fourth day that they arose early in the morning, and he stood to depart; but the young woman’s father said to his son-in-law, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:5; Judg. 19:8; Ps. 104:15</char></note>“Refresh your heart with a morsel of bread, and afterward go your way.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />So they sat down, and the two of them ate and drank together. Then the young woman’s father said to the man, “Please be content to stay all night, and let your heart be merry.” <verse number="7" style="v" />And when the man stood to depart, his father-in-law urged him; so he lodged there again. <verse number="8" style="v" />Then he arose early in the morning on the fifth day to depart, but the young woman’s father said, “Please refresh your heart.” So they delayed until afternoon; and both of them ate.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And when the man stood to depart—he and his concubine and his servant—his father-in-law, the young woman’s father, said to him, “Look, the day is now drawing toward evening; please spend the night. See, the day is coming to an end; lodge here, that your heart may be merry. Tomorrow go your way early, so that you may get home.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />However, the man was not willing to spend that night; so he rose and departed, and came opposite <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:28; 1 Chr. 11:4, 5</char></note>Jebus (that <char style="it">is,</char> Jerusalem). With him were the two saddled donkeys; his concubine <char style="it">was</char> also with him. <verse number="11" style="v" />They <char style="it">were</char> near Jebus, and the day was far spent; and the servant said to his master, “Come, please, and let us turn aside into this city <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:8, 63; Judg. 1:21; 2 Sam. 5:6</char></note>of the Jebusites and lodge in it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />But his master said to him, “We will not turn aside here into a city of foreigners, who <char style="it">are</char> not of the children of Israel; we will go on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:28</char></note>to Gibeah.” <verse number="13" style="v" />So he said to his servant, “Come, let us draw near to one of these places, and spend the night in Gibeah or in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:25</char></note>Ramah.” <verse number="14" style="v" />And they passed by and went their way; and the sun went down on them near Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin. <verse number="15" style="v" />They turned aside there to go in to lodge in Gibeah. And when he went in, he sat down in the open square of the city, for no one would <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 25:43</char></note>take them into <char style="it">his</char> house to spend the night.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Just then an old man came in from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 104:23</char></note>his work in the field at evening, who also <char style="it">was</char> from the mountains of Ephraim; he was staying in Gibeah, whereas the men of the place <char style="it">were</char> Benjamites. <verse number="17" style="v" />And when he raised his eyes, he saw the traveler in the open square of the city; and the old man said, “Where are you going, and where do you come from?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />So he said to him, “We <char style="it">are</char> passing from Bethlehem in Judah toward the remote mountains of Ephraim; I <char style="it">am</char> from there. I went to Bethlehem in Judah; <char style="it">now</char> I am going to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:1; Judg. 18:31; 20:18; 1 Sam. 1:3, 7</char></note>the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. But there <char style="it">is</char> no one who will take me into his house, <verse number="19" style="v" />although we have both straw and fodder for our donkeys, and bread and wine for myself, for your female servant, and for the young man <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">is</char> with your servant; <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> no lack of anything.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And the old man said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 43:23; Judg. 6:23; 1 Sam. 25:6</char></note>“Peace <char style="it">be</char> with you! However, <char style="it">let</char> all your needs <char style="it">be</char> my responsibility; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:2</char></note>only do not spend the night in the open square.” <verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 24:32; 43:24</char></note>So he brought him into his house, and gave fodder to the donkeys. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:4; John 13:5</char></note>And they washed their feet, and ate and drank.</para>
	<para style="s">Gibeah’s Crime</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />As they were <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 16:25; 19:6, 9</char></note>enjoying themselves, suddenly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:4, 5; Judg. 20:5; Hos. 9:9; 10:9</char></note>certain men of the city, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:13; 1 Sam. 2:12; 1 Kin. 21:10; (2 Cor. 6:15)</char></note>perverted men, surrounded the house <char style="it">and</char> beat on the door. They spoke to the master of the house, the old man, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:5; (Rom. 1:26, 27)</char></note>“Bring out the man who came to your house, that we may know him <char style="it">carnally!</char>”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:6, 7</char></note>the man, the master of the house, went out to them and said to them, “No, my brethren! I beg you, do not act <char style="it">so</char> wickedly! Seeing this man has come into my house, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:7; Deut. 22:21; Judg. 20:6, 10; 2 Sam. 13:12</char></note>do not commit this outrage. <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:8</char></note>Look, <char style="it">here</char> <char style="it">is</char> my virgin daughter and <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">man’s</char> concubine; let me bring them out now. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:2; Deut. 21:14</char></note>Humble them, and do with them as you please; but to this man do not do such a vile thing!” <verse number="25" style="v" />But the men would not heed him. So the man took his concubine and brought <char style="it">her</char> out to them. And they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 4:1</char></note>knew her and abused her all night until morning; and when the day began to break, they let her go.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then the woman came as the day was dawning, and fell down at the door of the man’s house where her master <char style="it">was,</char> till it was light.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />When her master arose in the morning, and opened the doors of the house and went out to go his way, there was his concubine, fallen <char style="it">at</char> the door of the house with her hands on the threshold. <verse number="28" style="v" />And he said to her, “Get up and let us be going.” But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:5</char></note>there was no answer. So the man lifted her onto the donkey; and the man got up and went to his place.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />When he entered his house he took a knife, laid hold of his concubine, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:6; 1 Sam. 11:7</char></note>divided her into twelve pieces, limb by limb, and sent her throughout all the territory of Israel. <verse number="30" style="v" />And so it was that all who saw it said, “No such deed has been done or seen from the day that the children of Israel came up from the land of Egypt until this day. Consider it, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:7; Prov. 13:10</char></note>confer, and speak up!”</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Israel’s War with the Benjamites</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:12; Judg. 20:11; 21:5</char></note>all the children of Israel came out, from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:29; 1 Sam. 3:20; 2 Sam. 3:10; 24:2</char></note>Dan to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:2</char></note>Beersheba, as well as from the land of Gilead, and the congregation gathered together as one man before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 10:17; 1 Sam. 7:5</char></note>at Mizpah. <verse number="2" style="v" />And the leaders of all the people, all the tribes of Israel, presented themselves in the assembly of the people of God, four hundred thousand foot soldiers <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 8:10</char></note>who drew the sword. <verse number="3" style="v" />(Now the children of Benjamin heard that the children of Israel had gone up to Mizpah.)</para>
	<para style="p">Then the children of Israel said, “Tell <char style="it">us,</char> how did this wicked deed happen?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So the Levite, the husband of the woman who was murdered, answered and said, “My concubine and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 19:15</char></note>I went into Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin, to spend the night. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 19:22</char></note>And the men of Gibeah rose against me, and surrounded the house at night because of me. They intended to kill me, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 19:25, 26</char></note>but instead they ravished my concubine so that she died. <verse number="6" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 19:29</char></note>I took hold of my concubine, cut her in pieces, and sent her throughout all the territory of the inheritance of Israel, because they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:15</char></note>committed lewdness and outrage in Israel. <verse number="7" style="v" />Look! All of you <char style="it">are</char> children of Israel; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 19:30</char></note>give your advice and counsel here and now!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So all the people arose as one man, saying, “None <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">us</char> will go to his tent, nor will any turn back to his house; <verse number="9" style="v" />but now this <char style="it">is</char> the thing which we will do to Gibeah: <char style="it">We</char> <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">go</char> <char style="it">up</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:3</char></note>against it by lot. <verse number="10" style="v" />We will take ten men out of <char style="it">every</char> hundred throughout all the tribes of Israel, a hundred out of <char style="it">every</char> thousand, and a thousand out of <char style="it">every</char> ten thousand, to make provisions for the people, that when they come to Gibeah in Benjamin, they may repay all the vileness that they have done in Israel.” <verse number="11" style="v" />So all the men of Israel were gathered against the city, united together as one man.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:14; Josh. 22:13, 16</char></note>Then the tribes of Israel sent men through all the tribe of Benjamin, saying, “What <char style="it">is</char> this wickedness that has occurred among you? <verse number="13" style="v" />Now therefore, deliver up the men, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:13; Judg. 19:22</char></note>the perverted men  who <char style="it">are</char> in Gibeah, that we may put them to death and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:12; 1 Cor. 5:13</char></note>remove the evil from Israel!” But the children of Benjamin would not listen to the voice of their brethren, the children of Israel. <verse number="14" style="v" />Instead, the children of Benjamin gathered together from their cities to Gibeah, to go to battle against the children of Israel. <verse number="15" style="v" />And from their cities at that time <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 1:36, 37; 2:23; 26:41</char></note>the children of Benjamin numbered twenty-six thousand men who drew the sword, besides the inhabitants of Gibeah, who numbered seven hundred select men. <verse number="16" style="v" />Among all this people <char style="it">were</char> seven hundred select men <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:15; 1 Chr. 12:2</char></note>left-handed; every one could sling a stone at a hair’s <char style="it">breadth</char> and not miss. <verse number="17" style="v" />Now besides Benjamin, the men of Israel numbered four hundred thousand men who drew the sword; all of these <char style="it">were</char> men of war.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then the children of Israel arose and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:23, 26</char></note>went up to the house of God to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:21</char></note>inquire of God. They said, “Which of us shall go up first to battle against the children of Benjamin?”</para>
	<para style="p">The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:1, 2</char></note>“Judah first!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />So the children of Israel rose in the morning and encamped against Gibeah. <verse number="20" style="v" />And the men of Israel went out to battle against Benjamin, and the men of Israel put themselves in battle array to fight against them at Gibeah. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Gen. 49:27)</char></note>the children of Benjamin came out of Gibeah, and on that day cut down to the ground twenty-two thousand men of the Israelites. <verse number="22" style="v" />And the people, that is, the men of Israel, encouraged themselves and again formed the battle line at the place where they had put themselves in array on the first day. <verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:26, 27</char></note>Then the children of Israel went up and wept before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> until evening, and asked counsel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, saying, “Shall I again draw near for battle against the children of my brother Benjamin?”</para>
	<para style="p">And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, “Go up against him.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So the children of Israel approached the children of Benjamin on the second day. <verse number="25" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:21</char></note>Benjamin went out against them from Gibeah on the second day, and cut down to the ground eighteen thousand more of the children of Israel; all these drew the sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then all the children of Israel, that is, all the people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:18, 23; 21:2</char></note>went up and came to the house of God and wept. They sat there before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and fasted that day until evening; and they offered burnt offerings and peace offerings before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="27" style="v" />So the children of Israel inquired of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> (<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:1; 1 Sam. 1:3; 3:3; 4:3, 4</char></note>the ark of the covenant of God <char style="it">was</char> there in those days, <verse number="28" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 25:7, 13; Josh. 24:33</char></note>and Phinehas the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 10:8; 18:5</char></note>stood before it in those days), saying, “Shall I yet again go out to battle against the children of my brother Benjamin, or shall I cease?”</para>
	<para style="p">And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, “Go up, for tomorrow I will deliver them into your hand.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Then Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:4</char></note>set men in ambush all around Gibeah. <verse number="30" style="v" />And the children of Israel went up against the children of Benjamin on the third day, and put themselves in battle array against Gibeah as at the other times. <verse number="31" style="v" />So the children of Benjamin went out against the people, <char style="it">and</char> were drawn away from the city. They began to strike down <char style="it">and</char> kill some of the people, as at the other times, in the highways <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 21:19</char></note>(one of which goes up to Bethel and the other to Gibeah) and in the field, about thirty men of Israel. <verse number="32" style="v" />And the children of Benjamin said, “They <char style="it">are</char> defeated before us, as at first.”</para>
	<para style="p">But the children of Israel said, “Let us flee and draw them away from the city to the highways.” <verse number="33" style="v" />So all the men of Israel rose from their place and put themselves in battle array at Baal Tamar. Then Israel’s men in ambush burst forth from their position in the plain of Geba. <verse number="34" style="v" />And ten thousand select men from all Israel came against Gibeah, and the battle was fierce. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:14; Job 21:13; Is. 47:11</char></note>But <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">Benjamites</char> did not know that disaster <char style="it">was</char> upon them. <verse number="35" style="v" />The <char style="sc">Lord</char> defeated Benjamin before Israel. And the children of Israel destroyed that day twenty-five thousand one hundred Benjamites; all these drew the sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />So the children of Benjamin saw that they were defeated. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:15</char></note>The men of Israel had given ground to the Benjamites, because they relied on the men in ambush whom they had set against Gibeah. <verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:19</char></note>And the men in ambush quickly rushed upon Gibeah; the men in ambush spread out and struck the whole city with the edge of the sword. <verse number="38" style="v" />Now the appointed signal between the men of Israel and the men in ambush was that they would make a great cloud of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:20</char></note>smoke rise up from the city, <verse number="39" style="v" />whereupon the men of Israel would turn in battle. Now Benjamin had begun to strike <char style="it">and</char> kill about thirty of the men of Israel. For they said, “Surely they are defeated before us, as <char style="it">in</char> the first battle.” <verse number="40" style="v" />But when the cloud began to rise from the city in a column of smoke, the Benjamites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:20</char></note>looked behind them, and there was the whole city going up <char style="it">in</char> <char style="it">smoke</char> to heaven. <verse number="41" style="v" />And when the men of Israel turned back, the men of Benjamin panicked, for they saw that disaster had come upon them. <verse number="42" style="v" />Therefore they turned <char style="it">their</char> <char style="it">backs</char> before the men of Israel in the direction of the wilderness; but the battle overtook them, and whoever <char style="it">came</char> out of the cities they destroyed in their midst. <verse number="43" style="v" />They surrounded the Benjamites, chased them, <char style="it">and</char> easily trampled them down as far as the front of Gibeah toward the east. <verse number="44" style="v" />And eighteen thousand men of Benjamin fell; all these <char style="it">were</char> men of valor. <verse number="45" style="v" />Then they turned and fled toward the wilderness to the rock of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:32; 1 Chr. 6:77; Zech. 14:10</char></note>Rimmon; and they cut down five thousand of them on the highways. Then they pursued them relentlessly up to Gidom, and killed two thousand of them. <verse number="46" style="v" />So all who fell of Benjamin that day were twenty-five thousand men who drew the sword; all these <char style="it">were</char> men of valor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 21:13</char></note>But six hundred men turned and fled toward the wilderness to the rock of Rimmon, and they stayed at the rock of Rimmon for four months. <verse number="48" style="v" />And the men of Israel turned back against the children of Benjamin, and struck them down with the edge of the sword—from <char style="it">every</char> city, men and beasts, all who were found. They also set fire to all the cities they came to.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Wives Provided for the Benjamites</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:1</char></note>the men of Israel had sworn an oath at Mizpah, saying, “None of us shall give his daughter to Benjamin as a wife.” <verse number="2" style="v" />Then the people came <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:18, 26</char></note>to the house of God, and remained there before God till evening. They lifted up their voices and wept bitterly, <verse number="3" style="v" />and said, “O <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, why has this come to pass in Israel, that today there should be one tribe <char style="it">missing</char> in Israel?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So it was, on the next morning, that the people rose early and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5; 2 Sam. 24:25</char></note>built an altar there, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings. <verse number="5" style="v" />The children of Israel said, “Who <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">there</char> among all the tribes of Israel who did not come up with the assembly to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?” <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:1–3</char></note>For they had made a great oath concerning anyone who had not come up to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at Mizpah, saying, “He shall surely be put to death.” <verse number="6" style="v" />And the children of Israel grieved for Benjamin their brother, and said, “One tribe is cut off from Israel today. <verse number="7" style="v" />What shall we do for wives for those who remain, seeing we have sworn by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that we will not give them our daughters as wives?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And they said, “What one <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">there</char> from the tribes of Israel who did not come up to Mizpah to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?” And, in fact, no one had come to the camp from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 11:1; 31:11</char></note>Jabesh Gilead to the assembly. <verse number="9" style="v" />For when the people were counted, indeed, not one of the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead <char style="it">was</char> there. <verse number="10" style="v" />So the congregation sent out there twelve thousand of their most valiant men, and commanded them, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 31:17; Judg. 5:23; 1 Sam. 11:7</char></note>“Go and strike the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead with the edge of the sword, including the women and children. <verse number="11" style="v" />And this <char style="it">is</char> the thing that you shall do: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 31:17; Deut. 20:13, 14</char></note>You shall utterly destroy every male, and every woman who has known a man intimately.” <verse number="12" style="v" />So they found among the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead four hundred young virgins who had not known a man intimately; and they brought them to the camp at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:1; Judg. 18:31</char></note>Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then the whole congregation sent <char style="it">word</char> to the children of Benjamin <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:47</char></note>who <char style="it">were</char> at the rock of Rimmon, and announced peace to them. <verse number="14" style="v" />So Benjamin came back at that time, and they gave them the women whom they had saved alive of the women of Jabesh Gilead; and yet they had not found enough for them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />And the people <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 21:6</char></note>grieved for Benjamin, because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had made a void in the tribes of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Then the elders of the congregation said, “What shall we do for wives for those who remain, since the women of Benjamin have been destroyed?” <verse number="17" style="v" />And they said, “<char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">must</char> <char style="it">be</char> an inheritance for the survivors of Benjamin, that a tribe may not be destroyed from Israel. <verse number="18" style="v" />However, we cannot give them wives from our daughters, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:35; 21:1</char></note>for the children of Israel have sworn an oath, saying, ‘Cursed <char style="it">be</char> the one who gives a wife to Benjamin.’ ” <verse number="19" style="v" />Then they said, “In fact, <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">is</char> a yearly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:2</char></note>feast of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5; Josh. 18:1; Judg. 18:31; 1 Sam. 1:3</char></note>Shiloh, which <char style="it">is</char> north of Bethel, on the east side of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:31</char></note>highway that goes up from Bethel to Shechem, and south of Lebonah.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />Therefore they instructed the children of Benjamin, saying, “Go, lie in wait in the vineyards, <verse number="21" style="v" />and watch; and just when the daughters of Shiloh come out <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:20; Judg. 11:34; 1 Sam. 18:6</char></note>to perform their dances, then come out from the vineyards, and every man catch a wife for himself from the daughters of Shiloh; then go to the land of Benjamin. <verse number="22" style="v" />Then it shall be, when their fathers or their brothers come to us to complain, that we will say to them, ‘Be kind to them for our sakes, because we did not take a wife for any of them in the war; for <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> not <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">though</char> you have given the <char style="it">women</char> to them at this time, making yourselves guilty of your oath.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />And the children of Benjamin did so; they took enough wives for their number from those who danced, whom they caught. Then they went and returned to their inheritance, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:48</char></note>rebuilt the cities and dwelt in them. <verse number="24" style="v" />So the children of Israel departed from there at that time, every man to his tribe and family; they went out from there, every man to his inheritance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 17:6; 18:1; 19:1</char></note>In those days <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> no king in Israel; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:8; Judg. 17:6</char></note>everyone did <char style="it">what</char> <char style="it">was</char> right in his own eyes.</para>
	
</usx>