<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="JOS" style="id">The Book of Joshua</book>
    <para style="mt">The Book of Joshua</para>
    <chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="s">God’s Commission to Joshua</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />After the death of Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, it came to pass that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua the son of Nun, Moses’ <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 24:13; Num. 13:16; 14:6, 29, 30, 37, 38; Deut. 1:38; Acts 7:45</char></note>assistant, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 12:7; Deut. 34:5</char></note>“Moses My servant is dead. Now therefore, arise, go over this Jordan, you and all this people, to the land which I am giving to them—the children of Israel. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 11:24; Josh. 11:23</char></note>Every place that the sole of your foot will tread upon I have given you, as I said to Moses. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:18; Ex. 23:31; Num. 34:3–12</char></note>From the wilderness and this Lebanon as far as the great river, the River Euphrates, all the land of the Hittites, and to the Great Sea toward the going down of the sun, shall be your territory. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:24</char></note>No man shall <char style="it">be</char> <char style="it">able</char> <char style="it">to</char> stand before you all the days of your life; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:12</char></note>as I was with Moses, <char style="it">so</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:8, 23</char></note>I will be with you. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:6, 7; Heb. 13:5</char></note>I will not leave you nor forsake you. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:7, 23</char></note>Be strong and of good courage, for to this people you shall divide as an inheritance the land which I swore to their fathers to give them. <verse number="7" style="v" />Only be strong and very courageous, that you may observe to do according to all the law <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:23; Deut. 31:7; Josh. 11:15</char></note>which Moses My servant commanded you; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 5:32</char></note>do not turn from it to the right hand or to the left, that you may prosper wherever you go. <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:18, 19; 31:24, 26; Josh. 8:34</char></note>This Book of the Law shall not depart from your mouth, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 29:9; Ps. 1:1–3</char></note>you shall meditate in it day and night, that you may observe to do according to all that is written in it. For then you will make your way prosperous, and then you will have good success. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:7</char></note>Have I not commanded you? Be strong and of good courage; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 27:1</char></note>do not be afraid, nor be dismayed, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God <char style="it">is</char> with you wherever you go.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Order to Cross the Jordan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Then Joshua commanded the officers of the people, saying, <verse number="11" style="v" />“Pass through the camp and command the people, saying, ‘Prepare provisions for yourselves, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 9:1; Josh. 3:17</char></note>within three days you will cross over this Jordan, to go in to possess the land which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God is giving you to possess.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And to the Reubenites, the Gadites, and half the tribe of Manasseh Joshua spoke, saying, <verse number="13" style="v" />“Remember <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:20–28</char></note>the word which Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded you, saying, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God is giving you rest and is giving you this land.’ <verse number="14" style="v" />Your wives, your little ones, and your livestock shall remain in the land which Moses gave you on this side of the Jordan. But you shall pass before your brethren armed, all your mighty men of valor, and help them, <verse number="15" style="v" />until the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given your brethren rest, as He <char style="it">gave</char> you, and they also have taken possession of the land which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God is giving them. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:1–4</char></note>Then you shall return to the land of your possession and enjoy it, which Moses the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s servant gave you on this side of the Jordan toward the sunrise.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So they answered Joshua, saying, “All that you command us we will do, and wherever you send us we will go. <verse number="17" style="v" />Just as we heeded Moses in all things, so we will heed you. Only the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 20:13; 1 Kin. 1:37</char></note>be with you, as He was with Moses. <verse number="18" style="v" />Whoever rebels against your command and does not heed your words, in all that you command him, shall be put to death. Only be strong and of good courage.”</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Rahab Hides the Spies</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now Joshua the son of Nun sent out two men <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 25:1; Josh. 3:1</char></note>from Acacia Grove to spy secretly, saying, “Go, view the land, especially Jericho.” So they went, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Heb. 11:31; James 2:25</char></note>came to the house of a harlot named <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 1:5</char></note>Rahab, and lodged there. <verse number="2" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:22</char></note>it was told the king of Jericho, saying, “Behold, men have come here tonight from the children of Israel to search out the country.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />So the king of Jericho sent to Rahab, saying, “Bring out the men who have come to you, who have entered your house, for they have come to search out all the country.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 17:19, 20</char></note>Then the woman took the two men and hid them. So she said, “Yes, the men came to me, but I did not know where they <char style="it">were</char> from. <verse number="5" style="v" />And it happened as the gate was being shut, when it was dark, that the men went out. Where the men went I do not know; pursue them quickly, for you may overtake them.” <verse number="6" style="v" />(But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 1:17; 2 Sam. 17:19</char></note>she had brought them up to the roof and hidden them with the stalks of flax, which she had laid in order on the roof.) <verse number="7" style="v" />Then the men pursued them by the road to the Jordan, to the fords. And as soon as those who pursued them had gone out, they shut the gate.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Now before they lay down, she came up to them on the roof, <verse number="9" style="v" />and said to the men: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 1:8</char></note>“I know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given you the land, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:5; Ex. 23:27; Deut. 2:25; 11:25; Josh. 9:9, 10</char></note>the terror of you has fallen on us, and that all the inhabitants of the land <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:15; Josh. 5:1</char></note>are fainthearted because of you. <verse number="10" style="v" />For we have heard how the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:21; Josh. 4:23</char></note>dried up the water of the Red Sea for you when you came out of Egypt, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:21–35</char></note>what you did to the two kings of the Amorites who <char style="it">were</char> on the other side of the Jordan, Sihon and Og, whom you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:17; Josh. 6:21</char></note>utterly destroyed. <verse number="11" style="v" />And as soon as we <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:14, 15</char></note>heard <char style="it">these</char> <char style="it">things,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:1; 7:5; Ps. 22:14; Is. 13:7</char></note>our hearts melted; neither did there remain any more courage in anyone because of you, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:39</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, He <char style="it">is</char> God in heaven above and on earth beneath. <verse number="12" style="v" />Now therefore, I beg you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 20:14, 15, 17</char></note>swear to me by the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, since I have shown you kindness, that you also will show kindness to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Tim. 5:8</char></note>my father’s house, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:13; Josh. 2:18</char></note>give me a true token, <verse number="13" style="v" />and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:23–25</char></note>spare my father, my mother, my brothers, my sisters, and all that they have, and deliver our lives from death.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So the men answered her, “Our lives for yours, if none of you tell this business of ours. And it shall be, when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given us the land, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 47:29; Judg. 1:24; (Matt. 5:7)</char></note>we will deal kindly and truly with you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then she <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 9:25</char></note>let them down by a rope through the window, for her house <char style="it">was</char> on the city wall; she dwelt on the wall. <verse number="16" style="v" />And she said to them, “Get to the mountain, lest the pursuers meet you. Hide there three days, until the pursuers have returned. Afterward you may go your way.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />So the men said to her: “We <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:7</char></note>blameless of this oath of yours which you have made us swear, <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:12</char></note>unless, <char style="it">when</char> we come into the land, you bind this line of scarlet cord in the window through which you let us down, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:23</char></note>and unless you bring your father, your mother, your brothers, and all your father’s household to your own home. <verse number="19" style="v" />So it shall be <char style="it">that</char> whoever goes outside the doors of your house into the street, his blood <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> on his own head, and we <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> guiltless. And whoever is with you in the house, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:32; Matt. 27:25</char></note>his blood <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> on our head if a hand is laid on him. <verse number="20" style="v" />And if you tell this business of ours, then we will be free from your oath which you made us swear.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then she said, “According to your words, so <char style="it">be</char> it.” And she sent them away, and they departed. And she bound the scarlet cord in the window.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />They departed and went to the mountain, and stayed there three days until the pursuers returned. The pursuers sought <char style="it">them</char> all along the way, but did not find <char style="it">them.</char> <verse number="23" style="v" />So the two men returned, descended from the mountain, and crossed over; and they came to Joshua the son of Nun, and told him all that had befallen them. <verse number="24" style="v" />And they said to Joshua, “Truly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:31; Josh. 6:2; 21:44</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has delivered all the land into our hands, for indeed all the inhabitants of the country are fainthearted because of us.”</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Israel Crosses the Jordan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Joshua rose early in the morning; and they set out <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:1</char></note>from Acacia Grove and came to the Jordan, he and all the children of Israel, and lodged there before they crossed over. <verse number="2" style="v" />So it was, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:10, 11</char></note>after three days, that the officers went through the camp; <verse number="3" style="v" />and they commanded the people, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:33</char></note>“When you see the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:9, 25</char></note>and the priests, the Levites, bearing it, then you shall set out from your place and go after it. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:12</char></note>Yet there shall be a space between you and it, about two thousand cubits by measure. Do not come near it, that you may know the way by which you must go, for you have not passed <char style="it">this</char> way before.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />And Joshua said to the people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:10, 14, 15; Lev. 20:7; Num. 11:18; Josh. 7:13; 1 Sam. 16:5; Job 1:5; Joel 2:16</char></note>“Sanctify yourselves, for tomorrow the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will do wonders among you.” <verse number="6" style="v" />Then Joshua spoke to the priests, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 4:15</char></note>“Take up the ark of the covenant and cross over before the people.”</para>
	<para style="p">So they took up the ark of the covenant and went before the people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “This day I will begin to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:14; 1 Chr. 29:25; 2 Chr. 1:1</char></note>exalt you in the sight of all Israel, that they may know that, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:5, 9</char></note>as I was with Moses, <char style="it">so</char> I will be with you. <verse number="8" style="v" />You shall command <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:3</char></note>the priests who bear the ark of the covenant, saying, ‘When you have come to the edge of the water of the Jordan, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:17</char></note>you shall stand in the Jordan.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So Joshua said to the children of Israel, “Come here, and hear the words of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.” <verse number="10" style="v" />And Joshua said, “By this you shall know that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 5:26; Josh. 11:23; 1 Sam. 17:26; 2 Kin. 19:4; Hos. 1:10; Matt. 16:16; 1 Thess. 1:9</char></note>the living God <char style="it">is</char> among you, and <char style="it">that</char> He will without fail <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 33:2; Deut. 7:1; 18:12; Ps. 44:2</char></note>drive out from before you the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 13:19</char></note>Canaanites and the Hittites and the Hivites and the Perizzites and the Girgashites and the Amorites and the Jebusites: <verse number="11" style="v" />Behold, the ark of the covenant of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:13; Job 41:11; Ps. 24:1; Mic. 4:13; Zech. 4:14; 6:5</char></note>the Lord of all the earth is crossing over before you into the Jordan. <verse number="12" style="v" />Now therefore, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:2, 4</char></note>take for yourselves twelve men from the tribes of Israel, one man from every tribe. <verse number="13" style="v" />And it shall come to pass, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:15, 16</char></note>as soon as the soles of the feet of the priests who bear the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:11</char></note>the Lord of all the earth, shall rest in the waters of the Jordan, <char style="it">that</char> the waters of the Jordan shall be cut off, the waters that come down from upstream, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 78:13; 114:3</char></note>shall stand as a heap.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So it was, when the people set out from their camp to cross over the Jordan, with the priests bearing the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 132:8; Acts 7:44, 45</char></note>ark of the covenant before the people, <verse number="15" style="v" />and as those who bore the ark came to the Jordan, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:13</char></note>the feet of the priests who bore the ark dipped in the edge of the water (for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 12:15; Jer. 12:5; 49:19</char></note>Jordan overflows all its banks <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:18; 5:10, 12</char></note>during the whole time of harvest), <verse number="16" style="v" />that the waters which came down from upstream stood <char style="it">still, and</char> rose in a heap very far away at Adam, the city that <char style="it">is</char> beside <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:12; 7:46</char></note>Zaretan. So the waters that went down <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:17</char></note>into the Sea of the Arabah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 14:3; Num. 34:3</char></note>the Salt Sea, failed, <char style="it">and</char> were cut off; and the people crossed over opposite Jericho. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then the priests who bore the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> stood firm on dry ground in the midst of the Jordan; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 50:24; Ex. 3:8; 6:1–8; 14:21, 22, 29; 33:1; Deut. 6:10; Heb. 11:29</char></note>and all Israel crossed over on dry ground, until all the people had crossed completely over the Jordan.</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Memorial Stones</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass, when all the people had completely crossed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 27:2; Josh. 3:17</char></note>over the Jordan, that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:12</char></note>“Take for yourselves twelve men from the people, one man from every tribe, <verse number="3" style="v" />and command them, saying, ‘Take for yourselves twelve stones from here, out of the midst of the Jordan, from the place where <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:13</char></note>the priests’ feet stood firm. You shall carry them over with you and leave them in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:19, 20</char></note>the lodging place where you lodge tonight.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Then Joshua called the twelve men whom he had appointed from the children of Israel, one man from every tribe; <verse number="5" style="v" />and Joshua said to them: “Cross over before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God into the midst of the Jordan, and each one of you take up a stone on his shoulder, according to the number of the tribes of the children of Israel, <verse number="6" style="v" />that this may be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 27:2; Ps. 103:2</char></note>a sign among you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:26; 13:14; Deut. 6:20</char></note>when your children ask in time to come, saying, ‘What do these stones <char style="it">mean</char> to you?’ <verse number="7" style="v" />Then you shall answer them that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:13, 16</char></note>the waters of the Jordan were cut off before the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; when it crossed over the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan were cut off. And these stones shall be for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:14; Num. 16:40</char></note>a memorial to the children of Israel forever.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />And the children of Israel did so, just as Joshua commanded, and took up twelve stones from the midst of the Jordan, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had spoken to Joshua, according to the number of the tribes of the children of Israel, and carried them over with them to the place where they lodged, and laid them down there. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then Joshua set up twelve stones in the midst of the Jordan, in the place where the feet of the priests who bore the ark of the covenant stood; and they are there to this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So the priests who bore the ark stood in the midst of the Jordan until everything was finished that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Joshua to speak to the people, according to all that Moses had commanded Joshua; and the people hurried and crossed over. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then it came to pass, when all the people had completely crossed over, that the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:11; 6:11</char></note>ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the priests crossed over in the presence of the people. <verse number="12" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:17, 20, 27, 28; Josh. 1:14</char></note>the men of Reuben, the men of Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh crossed over armed before the children of Israel, as Moses had spoken to them. <verse number="13" style="v" />About forty thousand prepared for war crossed over before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for battle, to the plains of Jericho. <verse number="14" style="v" />On that day the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:7; 1 Chr. 29:25</char></note>exalted Joshua in the sight of all Israel; and they feared him, as they had feared Moses, all the days of his life.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Joshua, saying, <verse number="16" style="v" />“Command the priests who bear <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:16, 22</char></note>the ark of the Testimony to come up from the Jordan.” <verse number="17" style="v" />Joshua therefore commanded the priests, saying, “Come up from the Jordan.” <verse number="18" style="v" />And it came to pass, when the priests who bore the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had come from the midst of the Jordan, <char style="it">and</char> the soles of the priests’ feet touched the dry land, that the waters of the Jordan returned to their place <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:15; 1 Chr. 12:15</char></note>and overflowed all its banks as before.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Now the people came up from the Jordan on the tenth <char style="it">day</char> of the first month, and they camped <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:9</char></note>in Gilgal on the east border of Jericho. <verse number="20" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 11:30; Josh. 4:3; 5:9, 10</char></note>those twelve stones which they took out of the Jordan, Joshua set up in Gilgal. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then he spoke to the children of Israel, saying: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:6</char></note>“When your children ask their fathers in time to come, saying, ‘What <char style="it">are</char> these stones?’ <verse number="22" style="v" />then you shall let your children know, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:26, 27; 13:8–14; Deut. 26:5–9</char></note>‘Israel crossed over this Jordan on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:17</char></note>dry land’; <verse number="23" style="v" />for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God dried up the waters of the Jordan before you until you had crossed over, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God did to the Red Sea, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:21</char></note>which He dried up before us until we had crossed over, <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:42; 2 Kin. 19:19; Ps. 106:8</char></note>that all the peoples of the earth may know the hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that it <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:16; 1 Chr. 29:12; Ps. 89:13</char></note>mighty, that you may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:31; Deut. 6:2; Ps. 76:7; Jer. 10:7</char></note>fear the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God forever.”</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Second Generation Circumcised</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />So it was, when all the kings of the Amorites who <char style="it">were</char> on the west side of the Jordan, and all the kings of the Canaanites <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:29</char></note>who <char style="it">were</char> by the sea, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:14, 15</char></note>heard that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had dried up the waters of the Jordan from before the children of Israel until we had crossed over, that their heart melted; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:10, 11; 9:9; 1 Kin. 10:5</char></note>and there was no spirit in them any longer because of the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />At that time the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Make <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 4:25</char></note>flint knives for yourself, and circumcise the sons of Israel again the second time.” <verse number="3" style="v" />So Joshua made flint knives for himself, and circumcised the sons of Israel at the hill of the foreskins. <verse number="4" style="v" />And this <char style="it">is</char> the reason why Joshua circumcised them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:29; 26:64, 65; Deut. 2:14–16</char></note>All the people who came out of Egypt <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> males, all the men of war, had died in the wilderness on the way, after they had come out of Egypt. <verse number="5" style="v" />For all the people who came out had been circumcised, but all the people born in the wilderness, on the way as they came out of Egypt, had not been circumcised. <verse number="6" style="v" />For the children of Israel walked <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:33; Deut. 1:3; 29:5</char></note>forty years in the wilderness, till all the people <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> men of war, who came out of Egypt, were consumed, because they did not obey the voice of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>—to whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> swore that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:23, 29–35; 26:23–65; Heb. 3:11</char></note>He would not show them the land which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had sworn to their fathers that He would give us, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:8</char></note>“a land flowing with milk and honey.” <verse number="7" style="v" />Then Joshua circumcised <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:31; Deut. 1:39</char></note>their sons <char style="it">whom</char> He raised up in their place; for they were uncircumcised, because they had not been circumcised on the way.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So it was, when they had finished circumcising all the people, that they stayed in their places in the camp <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:25</char></note>till they were healed. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “This day I have rolled away <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:14</char></note>the reproach of Egypt from you.” Therefore the name of the place is called <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:19</char></note>Gilgal to this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Now the children of Israel camped in Gilgal, and kept the Passover <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:6; Num. 9:5</char></note>on the fourteenth day of the month at twilight on the plains of Jericho. <verse number="11" style="v" />And they ate of the produce of the land on the day after the Passover, unleavened bread and parched grain, on the very same day. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 16:35</char></note>the manna ceased on the day after they had eaten the produce of the land; and the children of Israel no longer had manna, but they ate the food of the land of Canaan that year.</para>
	<para style="s">The Commander of the Army of the <char style="sc">Lord</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And it came to pass, when Joshua was by Jericho, that he lifted his eyes and looked, and behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:1, 2; 32:24, 30; Ex. 23:23; Num. 22:31; Zech. 1:8; Acts 1:10</char></note>a Man stood opposite him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:23; 1 Chr. 21:16</char></note>with His sword drawn in His hand. And Joshua went to Him and said to Him, “<char style="it">Are</char> You for us or for our adversaries?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />So He said, “No, but <char style="it">as</char> Commander of the army of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> I have now come.”</para>
	<para style="p">And Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:3; Num. 20:6</char></note>fell on his face to the earth and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:8</char></note>worshiped, and said to Him, “What does my Lord say to His servant?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />Then the Commander of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s army said to Joshua, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:5; Acts 7:33</char></note>“Take your sandal off your foot, for the place where you stand <char style="it">is</char> holy.” And Joshua did so.</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Destruction of Jericho</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:1</char></note>Jericho was securely shut up because of the children of Israel; none went out, and none came in. <verse number="2" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua: “See! <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:9, 24; 8:1</char></note>I have given Jericho into your hand, its <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:24</char></note>king, <char style="it">and</char> the mighty men of valor. <verse number="3" style="v" />You shall march around the city, all <char style="it">you</char> men of war; you shall go all around the city once. This you shall do six days. <verse number="4" style="v" />And seven priests shall bear seven <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:9; Judg. 7:16, 22</char></note>trumpets of rams’ horns before the ark. But the seventh day you shall march around the city <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:43; 2 Kin. 4:35; 5:10</char></note>seven times, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:8</char></note>the priests shall blow the trumpets. <verse number="5" style="v" />It shall come to pass, when they make a long <char style="it">blast</char> with the ram’s horn, <char style="it">and</char> when you hear the sound of the trumpet, that all the people shall shout with a great shout; then the wall of the city will fall down flat. And the people shall go up every man straight before him.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then Joshua the son of Nun called the priests and said to them, “Take up the ark of the covenant, and let seven priests bear seven trumpets of rams’ horns before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” <verse number="7" style="v" />And he said to the people, “Proceed, and march around the city, and let him who is armed advance before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />So it was, when Joshua had spoken to the people, that the seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams’ horns before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> advanced and blew the trumpets, and the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> followed them. <verse number="9" style="v" />The armed men went before the priests who blew the trumpets, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 10:25</char></note>and the rear guard came after the ark, while <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">priests</char> continued blowing the trumpets. <verse number="10" style="v" />Now Joshua had commanded the people, saying, “You shall not shout or make any noise with your voice, nor shall a word proceed out of your mouth, until the day I say to you, ‘Shout!’ Then you shall shout.” <verse number="11" style="v" />So he had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 4:11</char></note>the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> circle the city, going around <char style="it">it</char> once. Then they came into the camp and lodged in the camp.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And Joshua rose early in the morning, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:25</char></note>and the priests took up the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then seven priests bearing seven trumpets of rams’ horns before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> went on continually and blew with the trumpets. And the armed men went before them. But the rear guard came after the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, while <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">priests</char> continued blowing the trumpets. <verse number="14" style="v" />And the second day they marched around the city once and returned to the camp. So they did six days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />But it came to pass on the seventh day that they rose early, about the dawning of the day, and marched around the city seven times in the same manner. On that day only they marched around the city seven times. <verse number="16" style="v" />And the seventh time it happened, when the priests blew the trumpets, that Joshua said to the people: “Shout, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given you the city! <verse number="17" style="v" />Now the city shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:17; Josh. 7:1</char></note>doomed by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to destruction, it and all who <char style="it">are</char> in it. Only <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:1; Matt. 1:5</char></note>Rahab the harlot shall live, she and all who <char style="it">are</char> with her in the house, because <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:4, 6</char></note>she hid the messengers that we sent. <verse number="18" style="v" />And you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:26</char></note>by all means abstain from the accursed things, lest you become accursed when you take of the accursed things, and make the camp of Israel a curse, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:1, 12, 25; 1 Kin. 18:17, 18; (Jon. 1:12)</char></note>and trouble it. <verse number="19" style="v" />But all the silver and gold, and vessels of bronze and iron, <char style="it">are</char> consecrated to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; they shall come into the treasury of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />So the people shouted when <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">priests</char> blew the trumpets. And it happened when the people heard the sound of the trumpet, and the people shouted with a great shout, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Heb. 11:30</char></note>the wall fell down flat. Then the people went up into the city, every man straight before him, and they took the city. <verse number="21" style="v" />And they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:2; 20:16, 17</char></note>utterly destroyed all that <char style="it">was</char> in the city, both man and woman, young and old, ox and sheep and donkey, with the edge of the sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />But Joshua had said to the two men who had spied out the country, “Go into the harlot’s house, and from there bring out the woman and all that she has, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:12–19; Heb. 11:31</char></note>as you swore to her.” <verse number="23" style="v" />And the young men who had been spies went in and brought out Rahab, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 2:13</char></note>her father, her mother, her brothers, and all that she had. So they brought out all her relatives and left them outside the camp of Israel. <verse number="24" style="v" />But they burned the city and all that <char style="it">was</char> in it with fire. Only the silver and gold, and the vessels of bronze and iron, they put into the treasury of the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="25" style="v" />And Joshua spared Rahab the harlot, her father’s household, and all that she had. So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 1:5)</char></note>she dwells in Israel to this day, because she hid the messengers whom Joshua sent to spy out Jericho.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then Joshua charged <char style="it">them</char> at that time, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 16:34</char></note>“Cursed <char style="it">be</char> the man before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> who rises up and builds this city Jericho; he shall lay its foundation with his firstborn, and with his youngest he shall set up its gates.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with Joshua, and his fame spread throughout all the country.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Defeat at Ai</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />But the children of Israel committed a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:20, 21</char></note>trespass regarding the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:17–19</char></note>accursed things, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:20</char></note>Achan the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, took of the accursed things; so the anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> burned against the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />Now Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai, which <char style="it">is</char> beside Beth Aven, on the east side of Bethel, and spoke to them, saying, “Go up and spy out the country.” So the men went up and spied out Ai. <verse number="3" style="v" />And they returned to Joshua and said to him, “Do not let all the people go up, but let about two or three thousand men go up and attack Ai. Do not weary all the people there, for <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">people</char> <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">Ai</char> <char style="it">are</char> few.” <verse number="4" style="v" />So about three thousand men went up there from the people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:17; Deut. 28:25</char></note>but they fled before the men of Ai. <verse number="5" style="v" />And the men of Ai struck down about thirty-six men, for they chased them <char style="it">from</char> before the gate as far as Shebarim, and struck them down on the descent; therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:36; Josh. 2:9, 11</char></note>the hearts of the people melted and became like water.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 37:29, 34</char></note>tore his clothes, and fell to the earth on his face before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> until evening, he and the elders of Israel; and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 4:12</char></note>put dust on their heads. <verse number="7" style="v" />And Joshua said, “Alas, Lord <char style="sc">God</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 17:3; Num. 21:5</char></note>why have You brought this people over the Jordan at all—to deliver us into the hand of the Amorites, to destroy us? Oh, that we had been content, and dwelt on the other side of the Jordan! <verse number="8" style="v" />O Lord, what shall I say when Israel turns its back before its enemies? <verse number="9" style="v" />For the Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the land will hear <char style="it">it,</char> and surround us, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:26</char></note>cut off our name from the earth. Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 32:12; Num. 14:13</char></note>what will You do for Your great name?”</para>
	<para style="s">The Sin of Achan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua: “Get up! Why do you lie thus on your face? <verse number="11" style="v" />Israel has sinned, and they have also transgressed My covenant which I commanded them. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:17–19</char></note>For they have even taken some of the accursed things, and have both stolen and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 5:1, 2</char></note>deceived; and they have also put <char style="it">it</char> among their own stuff. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:14</char></note>Therefore the children of Israel could not stand before their enemies, <char style="it">but</char> turned <char style="it">their</char> backs before their enemies, because <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:26; (Hag. 2:13, 14)</char></note>they have become doomed to destruction. Neither will I be with you anymore, unless you destroy the accursed from among you. <verse number="13" style="v" />Get up, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:10</char></note>sanctify the people, and say, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:5</char></note>‘Sanctify yourselves for tomorrow, because thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: “<char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">is</char> an accursed thing in your midst, O Israel; you cannot stand before your enemies until you take away the accursed thing from among you.” <verse number="14" style="v" />In the morning therefore you shall be brought according to your tribes. And it shall be <char style="it">that</char> the tribe which <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 16:33)</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> takes shall come according to families; and the family which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> takes shall come by households; and the household which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> takes shall come man by man. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 14:38, 39</char></note>Then it shall be <char style="it">that</char> he who is taken with the accursed thing shall be burned with fire, he and all that he has, because he has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:11</char></note>transgressed the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and because he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 34:7; Judg. 20:6</char></note>has done a disgraceful thing in Israel.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So Joshua rose early in the morning and brought Israel by their tribes, and the tribe of Judah was taken. <verse number="17" style="v" />He brought the clan of Judah, and he took the family of the Zarhites; and he brought the family of the Zarhites man by man, and Zabdi was taken. <verse number="18" style="v" />Then he brought his household man by man, and Achan the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 14:42</char></note>was taken.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Now Joshua said to Achan, “My son, I beg you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 6:5; Jer. 13:16; John 9:24</char></note>give glory to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 5:6, 7; 2 Chr. 30:22; Ezra 10:10, 11; Ps. 32:5; Prov. 28:13; Jer. 3:12, 13; Dan. 9:4</char></note>and make confession to Him, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 14:43</char></note>tell me now what you have done; do not hide <char style="it">it</char> from me.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />And Achan answered Joshua and said, “Indeed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:34; 1 Sam. 15:24</char></note>I have sinned against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel, and this is what I have done: <verse number="21" style="v" />When I saw among the spoils a beautiful Babylonian garment, two hundred shekels of silver, and a wedge of gold weighing fifty shekels, I coveted them and took them. And there they are, hidden in the earth in the midst of my tent, with the silver under it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />So Joshua sent messengers, and they ran to the tent; and there it was, hidden in his tent, with the silver under it. <verse number="23" style="v" />And they took them from the midst of the tent, brought them to Joshua and to all the children of Israel, and laid them out before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="24" style="v" />Then Joshua, and all Israel with him, took Achan the son of Zerah, the silver, the garment, the wedge of gold, his sons, his daughters, his oxen, his donkeys, his sheep, his tent, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 16:32, 33; Dan. 6:24</char></note>all that he had, and they brought them to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:26; 15:7</char></note>the Valley of Achor. <verse number="25" style="v" />And Joshua said, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:18; 1 Chr. 2:7; (Gal. 5:12)</char></note>“Why have you troubled us? The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will trouble you this day.” <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:5</char></note>So all Israel stoned him with stones; and they burned them with fire after they had stoned them with stones.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:29; 2 Sam. 18:17; Lam. 3:53</char></note>raised over him a great heap of stones, still there to this day. So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:17</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> turned from the fierceness of His anger. Therefore the name of that place has been called <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:24; Is. 65:10; Hos. 2:15</char></note>the Valley of Achor to this day.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Fall of Ai</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 1:21; 7:18; 31:8; Josh. 1:9; 10:8</char></note>“Do not be afraid, nor be dismayed; take all the people of war with you, and arise, go up to Ai. See, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:2</char></note>I have given into your hand the king of Ai, his people, his city, and his land. <verse number="2" style="v" />And you shall do to Ai and its king as you did to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:21</char></note>Jericho and its king. Only <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:14; Josh. 8:27</char></note>its spoil and its cattle you shall take as booty for yourselves. Lay an ambush for the city behind it.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />So Joshua arose, and all the people of war, to go up against Ai; and Joshua chose thirty thousand mighty men of valor and sent them away by night. <verse number="4" style="v" />And he commanded them, saying: “Behold, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:29</char></note>you shall lie in ambush against the city, behind the city. Do not go very far from the city, but all of you be ready. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then I and all the people who <char style="it">are</char> with me will approach the city; and it will come about, when they come out against us as at the first, that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:5; Judg. 20:32</char></note>we shall flee before them. <verse number="6" style="v" />For they will come out after us till we have drawn them from the city, for they will say, ‘<char style="it">They</char> <char style="it">are</char> fleeing before us as at the first.’ Therefore we will flee before them. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then you shall rise from the ambush and seize the city, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will deliver it into your hand. <verse number="8" style="v" />And it will be, when you have taken the city, <char style="it">that</char> you shall set the city on fire. According to the commandment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> you shall do. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 13:28</char></note>See, I have commanded you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />Joshua therefore sent them out; and they went to lie in ambush, and stayed between Bethel and Ai, on the west side of Ai; but Joshua lodged that night among the people. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then Joshua rose up early in the morning and mustered the people, and went up, he and the elders of Israel, before the people to Ai. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:5</char></note>And all the people of war who <char style="it">were</char> with him went up and drew near; and they came before the city and camped on the north side of Ai. Now a valley <char style="it">lay</char> between them and Ai. <verse number="12" style="v" />So he took about five thousand men and set them in ambush between Bethel and Ai, on the west side of the city. <verse number="13" style="v" />And when they had set the people, all the army that <char style="it">was</char> on the north of the city, and its rear guard on the west of the city, Joshua went that night into the midst of the valley.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Now it happened, when the king of Ai saw <char style="it">it,</char> that the men of the city hurried and rose early and went out against Israel to battle, he and all his people, at an appointed place before the plain. But he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:34; Eccl. 9:12</char></note>did not know that <char style="it">there</char> <char style="it">was</char> an ambush against him behind the city. <verse number="15" style="v" />And Joshua and all Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:36</char></note>made as if they were beaten before them, and fled by the way of the wilderness. <verse number="16" style="v" />So all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in Ai were called together to pursue them. And they pursued Joshua and were drawn away from the city. <verse number="17" style="v" />There was not a man left in Ai or Bethel who did not go out after Israel. So they left the city open and pursued Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, “Stretch out the spear that <char style="it">is</char> in your hand toward Ai, for I will give it into your hand.” And Joshua stretched out the spear that <char style="it">was</char> in his hand toward the city. <verse number="19" style="v" />So <char style="it">those</char> <char style="it">in</char> ambush arose quickly out of their place; they ran as soon as he had stretched out his hand, and they entered the city and took it, and hurried to set the city on fire. <verse number="20" style="v" />And when the men of Ai looked behind them, they saw, and behold, the smoke of the city ascended to heaven. So they had no power to flee this way or that way, and the people who had fled to the wilderness turned back on the pursuers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Now when Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had taken the city and that the smoke of the city ascended, they turned back and struck down the men of Ai. <verse number="22" style="v" />Then the others came out of the city against them; so they were <char style="it">caught</char> in the midst of Israel, some on this side and some on that side. And they struck them down, so that they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:2</char></note>let none of them remain or escape. <verse number="23" style="v" />But the king of Ai they took alive, and brought him to Joshua.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />And it came to pass when Israel had made an end of slaying all the inhabitants of Ai in the field, in the wilderness where they pursued them, and when they all had fallen by the edge of the sword until they were consumed, that all the Israelites returned to Ai and struck it with the edge of the sword. <verse number="25" style="v" />So it was <char style="it">that</char> all who fell that day, both men and women, <char style="it">were</char> twelve thousand—all the people of Ai. <verse number="26" style="v" />For Joshua did not draw back his hand, with which he stretched out the spear, until he had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:21</char></note>utterly destroyed all the inhabitants of Ai. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 31:22, 26</char></note>Only the livestock and the spoil of that city Israel took as booty for themselves, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:2</char></note>commanded Joshua. <verse number="28" style="v" />So Joshua burned Ai and made it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:16</char></note>a heap forever, a desolation to this day. <verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:26</char></note>And the king of Ai he hanged on a tree until evening. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 21:22, 23; Josh. 10:27</char></note>And as soon as the sun was down, Joshua commanded that they should take his corpse down from the tree, cast it at the entrance of the gate of the city, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:26; 10:27</char></note>raise over it a great heap of stones <char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">remains</char> to this day.</para>
	<para style="s">Joshua Renews the Covenant</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Now Joshua built an altar to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 27:4–8</char></note>in Mount Ebal, <verse number="31" style="v" />as Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded the children of Israel, as it is written in the Book of the Law of Moses: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:25; Deut. 27:5, 6</char></note>“an altar of whole stones over which no man has wielded an iron <char style="it">tool.</char>” And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:24</char></note>they offered on it burnt offerings to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and sacrificed peace offerings. <verse number="32" style="v" />And there, in the presence of the children of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 27:2, 3, 8</char></note>he wrote on the stones a copy of the law of Moses, which he had written. <verse number="33" style="v" />Then all Israel, with their elders and officers and judges, stood on either side of the ark before the priests, the Levites, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:9, 25</char></note>who bore the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:12</char></note>the stranger as well as he who was born among them. Half of them <char style="it">were</char> in front of Mount Gerizim and half of them in front of Mount Ebal, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 11:29; 27:12</char></note>as Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded before, that they should bless the people of Israel. <verse number="34" style="v" />And afterward <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:11; Neh. 8:3</char></note>he read all the words of the law, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:2, 15, 45; 29:20, 21; 30:19</char></note>the blessings and the cursings, according to all that is written in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:8</char></note>Book of the Law. <verse number="35" style="v" />There was not a word of all that Moses had commanded which Joshua did not read before all the assembly of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:38; Deut. 31:12</char></note>with the women, the little ones, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:33</char></note>and the strangers who were living among them.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Treaty with the Gibeonites</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:29; Josh. 3:10</char></note>all the kings who <char style="it">were</char> on this side of the Jordan, in the hills and in the lowland and in all the coasts of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:6</char></note>the Great Sea toward Lebanon—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:17; 23:23</char></note>the Hittite, the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite—heard <char style="it">about</char> <char style="it">it,</char> <verse number="2" style="v" />that they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:5; Ps. 83:3, 5</char></note>gathered together to fight with Joshua and Israel with one accord.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />But when the inhabitants of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:17, 22; 10:2; 21:17; 2 Sam. 21:1, 2</char></note>Gibeon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:27</char></note>heard what Joshua had done to Jericho and Ai, <verse number="4" style="v" />they worked craftily, and went and pretended to be ambassadors. And they took old sacks on their donkeys, old wineskins torn and mended, <verse number="5" style="v" />old and patched sandals on their feet, and old garments on themselves; and all the bread of their provision was dry <char style="it">and</char> moldy. <verse number="6" style="v" />And they went to Joshua, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:10</char></note>to the camp at Gilgal, and said to him and to the men of Israel, “We have come from a far country; now therefore, make a covenant with us.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Then the men of Israel said to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:1; 11:19</char></note>Hivites, “Perhaps you dwell among us; so <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:32; Deut. 7:2</char></note>how can we make a covenant with you?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />But they said to Joshua, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:11; 2 Kin. 10:5</char></note>“We <char style="it">are</char> your servants.”</para>
	<para style="p">And Joshua said to them, “Who <char style="it">are</char> you, and where do you come from?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So they said to him: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:15</char></note>“From a very far country your servants have come, because of the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God; for we have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:14; Josh. 2:9, 10; 5:1</char></note>heard of His fame, and all that He did in Egypt, <verse number="10" style="v" />and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24, 33</char></note>all that He did to the two kings of the Amorites who <char style="it">were</char> beyond the Jordan—to Sihon king of Heshbon, and Og king of Bashan, who was at Ashtaroth. <verse number="11" style="v" />Therefore our elders and all the inhabitants of our country spoke to us, saying, ‘Take provisions with you for the journey, and go to meet them, and say to them, “We <char style="it">are</char> your servants; now therefore, make a covenant with us.” ’ <verse number="12" style="v" />This bread of ours we took hot <char style="it">for</char> our provision from our houses on the day we departed to come to you. But now look, it is dry and moldy. <verse number="13" style="v" />And these wineskins which we filled <char style="it">were</char> new, and see, they are torn; and these our garments and our sandals have become old because of the very long journey.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then the men of Israel took some of their provisions; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:21; Is. 30:1</char></note>but they did not ask counsel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="15" style="v" />So Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 21:2</char></note>made peace with them, and made a covenant with them to let them live; and the rulers of the congregation swore to them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And it happened at the end of three days, after they had made a covenant with them, that they heard that they <char style="it">were</char> their neighbors who dwelt near them. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then the children of Israel journeyed and came to their cities on the third day. Now their cities <char style="it">were</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:25</char></note>Gibeon, Chephirah, Beeroth, and Kirjath Jearim. <verse number="18" style="v" />But the children of Israel did not attack them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 15:4</char></note>because the rulers of the congregation had sworn to them by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. And all the congregation complained against the rulers.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />Then all the rulers said to all the congregation, “We have sworn to them by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel; now therefore, we may not touch them. <verse number="20" style="v" />This we will do to them: We will let them live, lest <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 21:1, 2, 6; Ezek. 17:13, 15</char></note>wrath be upon us because of the oath which we swore to them.” <verse number="21" style="v" />And the rulers said to them, “Let them live, but let them be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 29:11</char></note>woodcutters and water carriers for all the congregation, as the rulers had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:15</char></note>promised them.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then Joshua called for them, and he spoke to them, saying, “Why have you deceived us, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:6, 9</char></note>‘We <char style="it">are</char> very far from you,’ when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:16</char></note>you dwell near us? <verse number="23" style="v" />Now therefore, you <char style="it">are</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:25</char></note>cursed, and none of you shall be freed from being slaves—woodcutters and water carriers for the house of my God.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So they answered Joshua and said, “Because your servants were clearly told that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:31–33; Deut. 7:1, 2</char></note>commanded His servant Moses to give you all the land, and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land from before you; therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:14</char></note>we were very much afraid for our lives because of you, and have done this thing. <verse number="25" style="v" />And now, here we are, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 16:6</char></note>in your hands; do with us as it seems good and right to do to us.” <verse number="26" style="v" />So he did to them, and delivered them out of the hand of the children of Israel, so that they did not kill them. <verse number="27" style="v" />And that day Joshua made them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:21, 23</char></note>woodcutters and water carriers for the congregation and for the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5</char></note>in the place which He would choose, even to this day.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Sun Stands Still</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now it came to pass when Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:1</char></note>heard how Joshua had taken <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:1</char></note>Ai and had utterly destroyed it—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:21</char></note>as he had done to Jericho and its king, so he had done to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:22, 26, 28</char></note>Ai and its king—and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:15</char></note>how the inhabitants of Gibeon had made peace with Israel and were among them, <verse number="2" style="v" />that they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:14–16; Deut. 11:25; 1 Chr. 14:17</char></note>feared greatly, because Gibeon <char style="it">was</char> a great city, like one of the royal cities, and because it <char style="it">was</char> greater than Ai, and all its men <char style="it">were</char> mighty. <verse number="3" style="v" />Therefore Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem sent to Hoham king of Hebron, Piram king of Jarmuth, Japhia king of Lachish, and Debir king of Eglon, saying, <verse number="4" style="v" />“Come up to me and help me, that we may attack Gibeon, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:15; 10:1</char></note>it has made peace with Joshua and with the children of Israel.” <verse number="5" style="v" />Therefore the five kings of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:29</char></note>Amorites, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, <char style="it">and</char> the king of Eglon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:2</char></note>gathered together and went up, they and all their armies, and camped before Gibeon and made war against it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And the men of Gibeon sent to Joshua at the camp <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:10; 9:6</char></note>at Gilgal, saying, “Do not forsake your servants; come up to us quickly, save us and help us, for all the kings of the Amorites who dwell in the mountains have gathered together against us.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So Joshua ascended from Gilgal, he and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:1</char></note>all the people of war with him, and all the mighty men of valor. <verse number="8" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:6; Judg. 4:14</char></note>“Do not fear them, for I have delivered them into your hand; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:5, 9</char></note>not a man of them shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:44</char></note>stand before you.” <verse number="9" style="v" />Joshua therefore came upon them suddenly, having marched all night from Gilgal. <verse number="10" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 4:15; 1 Sam. 7:10, 12; Is. 28:21</char></note>routed them before Israel, killed them with a great slaughter at Gibeon, chased them along the road that goes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:3, 5</char></note>to Beth Horon, and struck them down as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:35</char></note>Azekah and Makkedah. <verse number="11" style="v" />And it happened, as they fled before Israel <char style="it">and</char> were on the descent of Beth Horon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 30:30; Rev. 16:21</char></note>that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> cast down large hailstones from heaven on them as far as Azekah, and they died. <char style="it">There</char> <char style="it">were</char> more who died from the hailstones than the children of Israel killed with the sword.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />Then Joshua spoke to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in the day when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered up the Amorites before the children of Israel, and he said in the sight of Israel:</para>
	<para style="q1"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 28:21; Hab. 3:11</char></note>“Sun, stand still over Gibeon;</para>
	<para style="q2">And Moon, in the Valley of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 12:12</char></note>Aijalon.”</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="13" style="v" />So the sun stood still,</para>
	<para style="q2">And the moon stopped,</para>
	<para style="q2">Till the people had revenge</para>
	<para style="q2">Upon their enemies.</para>
	<para style="p"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 1:18</char></note><char style="it">Is</char> this not written in the Book of Jasher? So the sun stood still in the midst of heaven, and did not hasten to go <char style="it">down</char> for about a whole day. <verse number="14" style="v" />And there has been <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 38:7, 8</char></note>no day like that, before it or after it, that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> heeded the voice of a man; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:14; Deut. 1:30; 20:4; Josh. 10:42; 23:3</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> fought for Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:43</char></note>Then Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to the camp at Gilgal.</para>
	<para style="s">The Amorite Kings Executed</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />But these five kings had fled and hidden themselves in a cave at Makkedah. <verse number="17" style="v" />And it was told Joshua, saying, “The five kings have been found hidden in the cave at Makkedah.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />So Joshua said, “Roll large stones against the mouth of the cave, and set men by it to guard them. <verse number="19" style="v" />And do not stay <char style="it">there</char> yourselves, <char style="it">but</char> pursue your enemies, and attack their rear <char style="it">guard.</char> Do not allow them to enter their cities, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has delivered them into your hand.” <verse number="20" style="v" />Then it happened, while Joshua and the children of Israel made an end of slaying them with a very great slaughter, till they had finished, that those who escaped entered fortified cities. <verse number="21" style="v" />And all the people returned to the camp, to Joshua at Makkedah, in peace.</para>
	<para style="p"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 11:7</char></note>No one moved his tongue against any of the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then Joshua said, “Open the mouth of the cave, and bring out those five kings to me from the cave.” <verse number="23" style="v" />And they did so, and brought out those five kings to him from the cave: the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, <char style="it">and</char> the king of Eglon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />So it was, when they brought out those kings to Joshua, that Joshua called for all the men of Israel, and said to the captains of the men of war who went with him, “Come near, put your feet on the necks of these kings.” And they drew near and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 107:40; Is. 26:5, 6; Mal. 4:3</char></note>put their feet on their necks. <verse number="25" style="v" />Then Joshua said to them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:6–8; Josh. 1:9</char></note>“Do not be afraid, nor be dismayed; be strong and of good courage, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:21; 7:19</char></note>thus the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will do to all your enemies against whom you fight.” <verse number="26" style="v" />And afterward Joshua struck them and killed them, and hanged them on five trees; and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:29; 2 Sam. 21:9</char></note>were hanging on the trees until evening. <verse number="27" style="v" />So it was at the time of the going down of the sun <char style="it">that</char> Joshua commanded, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 21:22, 23; Josh. 8:29</char></note>took them down from the trees, cast them into the cave where they had been hidden, and laid large stones against the cave’s mouth, <char style="it">which</char> <char style="it">remain</char> until this very day.</para>
	<para style="s">Conquest of the Southland</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />On that day Joshua took Makkedah, and struck it and its king with the edge of the sword. He utterly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:2, 16</char></note>destroyed them—all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it. He let none remain. He also did to the king of Makkedah <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:21</char></note>as he had done to the king of Jericho.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />Then Joshua passed from Makkedah, and all Israel with him, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:42; 21:13; 2 Kin. 8:22; 19:8</char></note>Libnah; and they fought against Libnah. <verse number="30" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> also delivered it and its king into the hand of Israel; he struck it and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it with the edge of the sword. He let none remain in it, but did to its king as he had done to the king of Jericho.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />Then Joshua passed from Libnah, and all Israel with him, to Lachish; and they encamped against it and fought against it. <verse number="32" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered Lachish into the hand of Israel, who took it on the second day, and struck it and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it with the edge of the sword, according to all that he had done to Libnah. <verse number="33" style="v" />Then Horam king of Gezer came up to help Lachish; and Joshua struck him and his people, until he left him none remaining.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />From Lachish Joshua passed to Eglon, and all Israel with him; and they encamped against it and fought against it. <verse number="35" style="v" />They took it on that day and struck it with the edge of the sword; all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it he utterly destroyed that day, according to all that he had done to Lachish.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" />So Joshua went up from Eglon, and all Israel with him, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:22; Josh. 14:13–15; 15:13; Judg. 1:10, 20; 2 Sam. 5:1, 3, 5, 13; 2 Chr. 11:10</char></note>Hebron; and they fought against it. <verse number="37" style="v" />And they took it and struck it with the edge of the sword—its king, all its cities, and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it; he left none remaining, according to all that he had done to Eglon, but utterly destroyed it and all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />Then Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:15; Judg. 1:11; 1 Chr. 6:58</char></note>Debir; and they fought against it. <verse number="39" style="v" />And he took it and its king and all its cities; they struck them with the edge of the sword and utterly destroyed all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it. He left none remaining; as he had done to Hebron, so he did to Debir and its king, as he had done also to Libnah and its king.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" />So Joshua conquered all the land: the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 1:7</char></note>mountain country and the South and the lowland and the wilderness slopes, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:24</char></note>all their kings; he left none remaining, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:16, 17</char></note>utterly destroyed all that breathed, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel had commanded. <verse number="41" style="v" />And Joshua conquered them from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:26; Deut. 9:23</char></note>Kadesh Barnea as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 10:19; Josh. 11:22</char></note>Gaza, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:16; 15:51</char></note>and all the country of Goshen, even as far as Gibeon. <verse number="42" style="v" />All these kings and their land Joshua took at one time, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:14</char></note>because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel fought for Israel. <verse number="43" style="v" />Then Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to the camp at Gilgal.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Northern Conquest</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And it came to pass, when Jabin king of Hazor heard <char style="it">these</char> <char style="it">things,</char> that he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:3</char></note>sent to Jobab king of Madon, to the king <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:15</char></note>of Shimron, to the king of Achshaph, <verse number="2" style="v" />and to the kings who <char style="it">were</char> from the north, in the mountains, in the plain south of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:11</char></note>Chinneroth, in the lowland, and in the heights <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:11; Judg. 1:27; 1 Kin. 4:11</char></note>of Dor on the west, <verse number="3" style="v" />to the Canaanites in the east and in the west, the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:1</char></note>Amorite, the Hittite, the Perizzite, the Jebusite in the mountains, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:1; Judg. 3:3, 5; 1 Kin. 9:20</char></note>and the Hivite below <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:17; 13:5, 11</char></note>Hermon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 31:49</char></note>in the land of Mizpah. <verse number="4" style="v" />So they went out, they and all their armies with them, <char style="it">as</char> many people <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 22:17; 32:12; Judg. 7:12; 1 Sam. 13:5</char></note><char style="it">as</char> the sand that <char style="it">is</char> on the seashore in multitude, with very many horses and chariots. <verse number="5" style="v" />And when all these kings had met together, they came and camped together at the waters of Merom to fight against Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:8</char></note>“Do not be afraid because of them, for tomorrow about this time I will deliver all of them slain before Israel. You shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 8:4</char></note>hamstring their horses and burn their chariots with fire.” <verse number="7" style="v" />So Joshua and all the people of war with him came against them suddenly by the waters of Merom, and they attacked them. <verse number="8" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered them into the hand of Israel, who defeated them and chased them to Greater <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 49:13</char></note>Sidon, to the Brook <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:6</char></note>Misrephoth, and to the Valley of Mizpah eastward; they attacked them until they left none of them remaining. <verse number="9" style="v" />So Joshua did to them as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had told him: he hamstrung their horses and burned their chariots with fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Joshua turned back at that time and took Hazor, and struck its king with the sword; for Hazor was formerly the head of all those kingdoms. <verse number="11" style="v" />And they struck all the people who <char style="it">were</char> in it with the edge of the sword, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:16</char></note>utterly destroying <char style="it">them.</char> There was none left <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:40</char></note>breathing. Then he burned Hazor with fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />So all the cities of those kings, and all their kings, Joshua took and struck with the edge of the sword. He utterly destroyed them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:50–56; Deut. 7:2; 20:16</char></note>as Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded. <verse number="13" style="v" />But <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">for</char> the cities that stood on their mounds, Israel burned none of them, except Hazor only, <char style="it">which</char> Joshua burned. <verse number="14" style="v" />And all the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:14–18</char></note>spoil of these cities and the livestock, the children of Israel took as booty for themselves; but they struck every man with the edge of the sword until they had destroyed them, and they left none breathing. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:10–17</char></note>As the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses his servant, so <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:7, 8</char></note>Moses commanded Joshua, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:7</char></note>so Joshua did. He left nothing undone of all that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.</para>
	<para style="s">Summary of Joshua’s Conquests</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Thus Joshua took all this land: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:8</char></note>the mountain country, all the South, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:40, 41</char></note>all the land of Goshen, the lowland, and the Jordan plain—the mountains of Israel and its lowlands, <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:7</char></note>from Mount Halak and the ascent to Seir, even as far as Baal Gad in the Valley of Lebanon below Mount Hermon. He captured <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:24</char></note>all their kings, and struck them down and killed them. <verse number="18" style="v" />Joshua made war a long time with all those kings. <verse number="19" style="v" />There was not a city that made peace with the children of Israel, except <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:3–7</char></note>the Hivites, the inhabitants of Gibeon. All <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">others</char> they took in battle. <verse number="20" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:30</char></note>it was of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to harden their hearts, that they should come against Israel in battle, that He might utterly destroy them, <char style="it">and</char> that they might receive no mercy, but that He might destroy them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:16, 17</char></note>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And at that time Joshua came and cut off <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:22, 33; Deut. 1:28; 9:2; Josh. 15:13, 14</char></note>the Anakim from the mountains: from Hebron, from Debir, from Anab, from all the mountains of Judah, and from all the mountains of Israel; Joshua utterly destroyed them with their cities. <verse number="22" style="v" />None of the Anakim were left in the land of the children of Israel; they remained only <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 17:4</char></note>in Gaza, in Gath, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:46; 1 Sam. 5:1; Is. 20:1</char></note>and in Ashdod.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />So Joshua took the whole land, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 33:2; Num. 34:2–15</char></note>according to all that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said to Moses; and Joshua gave it as an inheritance to Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 26:53; Josh. 14; 15</char></note>according to their divisions by their tribes. Then the land <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:9, 10; 25:19; (Heb. 4:8)</char></note>rested from war.</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Kings Conquered by Moses</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />These <char style="it">are</char> the kings of the land whom the children of Israel defeated, and whose land they possessed on the other side of the Jordan toward the rising of the sun, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24</char></note>from the River Arnon <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:8</char></note>to Mount Hermon, and all the eastern Jordan plain: <verse number="2" style="v" /><char style="it">One</char> <char style="it">king</char> <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24; Deut. 2:24–27</char></note>Sihon king of the Amorites, who dwelt in Heshbon <char style="it">and</char> ruled half of Gilead, from Aroer, which is on the bank of the River Arnon, from the middle of that river, even as far as the River Jabbok, <char style="it">which</char> <char style="it">is</char> the border of the Ammonites, <verse number="3" style="v" />and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:17</char></note>the eastern Jordan plain from the Sea of Chinneroth as far as the Sea of the Arabah (the Salt Sea), <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:20</char></note>the road to Beth Jeshimoth, and southward below <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:17; 4:49</char></note>the slopes of Pisgah. <verse number="4" style="v" /><char style="it">The</char> <char style="it">other</char> <char style="it">king</char> <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:33; Deut. 3:4, 10</char></note>Og king of Bashan and his territory, <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">was</char> of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:11; Josh. 13:12</char></note>the remnant of the giants, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 1:4</char></note>who dwelt at Ashtaroth and at Edrei, <verse number="5" style="v" />and reigned over <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:8</char></note>Mount Hermon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:10; Josh. 13:11; 1 Chr. 5:11</char></note>over Salcah, over all Bashan, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:14; 1 Sam. 27:8</char></note>as far as the border of the Geshurites and the Maachathites, and over half of Gilead <char style="it">to</char> the border of Sihon king of Heshbon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24, 35</char></note>These Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the children of Israel had conquered; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:29–33; Deut. 3:12; Josh. 13:8</char></note>Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had given it <char style="it">as</char> a possession to the Reubenites, the Gadites, and half the tribe of Manasseh.</para>
	<para style="s">The Kings Conquered by Joshua</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And these <char style="it">are</char> the kings of the country <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:17</char></note>which Joshua and the children of Israel conquered on this side of the Jordan, on the west, from Baal Gad in the Valley of Lebanon as far as Mount Halak and the ascent to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 14:6; 32:3; Deut. 2:1, 4</char></note>Seir, which Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:23</char></note>gave to the tribes of Israel <char style="it">as</char> a possession according to their divisions, <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:40; 11:16</char></note>in the mountain country, in the lowlands, in the <char style="it">Jordan</char> plain, in the slopes, in the wilderness, and in the South—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:8; 23:23; Josh. 9:1</char></note>the Hittites, the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites: <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:2</char></note>the king of Jericho, one; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:29</char></note>the king of Ai, which <char style="it">is</char> beside Bethel, one; <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:23</char></note>the king of Jerusalem, one; the king of Hebron, one; <verse number="11" style="v" />the king of Jarmuth, one; the king of Lachish, one; <verse number="12" style="v" />the king of Eglon, one; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:33</char></note>the king of Gezer, one; <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:38, 39</char></note>the king of Debir, one; the king of Geder, one; <verse number="14" style="v" />the king of Hormah, one; the king of Arad, one; <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:29, 30</char></note>the king of Libnah, one; the king of Adullam, one; <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:28</char></note>the king of Makkedah, one; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:17; Judg. 1:22</char></note>the king of Bethel, one; <verse number="17" style="v" />the king of Tappuah, one; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 4:10</char></note>the king of Hepher, one; <verse number="18" style="v" />the king of Aphek, one; the king of Lasharon, one; <verse number="19" style="v" />the king of Madon, one; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:10</char></note>the king of Hazor, one; <verse number="20" style="v" />the king of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:1; 19:15</char></note>Shimron Meron, one; the king of Achshaph, one; <verse number="21" style="v" />the king of Taanach, one; the king of Megiddo, one; <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:37; 20:7; 21:32</char></note>the king of Kedesh, one; the king of Jokneam in Carmel, one; <verse number="23" style="v" />the king of Dor in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:2</char></note>heights of Dor, one; the king of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 14:1, 2; Is. 9:1</char></note>the people of Gilgal, one; <verse number="24" style="v" />the king of Tirzah, one—<note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:24</char></note>all the kings, thirty-one.</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Remaining Land to Be Conquered</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:10; 23:1, 2</char></note>was old, advanced in years. And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him: “You are old, advanced in years, and there remains very much land yet to be possessed. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:1–3</char></note>This is the land that yet remains: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Joel 3:4</char></note>all the territory of the Philistines and all <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:13; 2 Sam. 3:3</char></note><char style="it">that</char> <char style="it">of</char> the Geshurites, <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 13:5; Jer. 2:18</char></note>from Sihor, which <char style="it">is</char> east of Egypt, as far as the border of Ekron northward (<char style="it">which</char> is counted as Canaanite); the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 3:3</char></note>five lords of the Philistines—the Gazites, the Ashdodites, the Ashkelonites, the Gittites, and the Ekronites; also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 2:23</char></note>the Avites; <verse number="4" style="v" />from the south, all the land of the Canaanites, and Mearah that belongs to the Sidonians <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:18; 19:30; 1 Sam. 4:1; 1 Kin. 20:26, 30</char></note>as far as Aphek, to the border of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:34</char></note>the Amorites; <verse number="5" style="v" />the land of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 5:18; Ezek. 27:9</char></note>the Gebalites, and all Lebanon, toward the sunrise, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:7</char></note>from Baal Gad below Mount Hermon as far as the entrance to Hamath; <verse number="6" style="v" />all the inhabitants of the mountains from Lebanon as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:8</char></note>the Brook Misrephoth, <char style="it">and</char> all the Sidonians—them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 23:13; Judg. 2:21, 23</char></note>I will drive out from before the children of Israel; only <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:1, 2</char></note>divide it by lot to Israel as an inheritance, as I have commanded you. <verse number="7" style="v" />Now therefore, divide this land as an inheritance to the nine tribes and half the tribe of Manasseh.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Land Divided East of the Jordan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />With the other half-tribe the Reubenites and the Gadites received their inheritance, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:33; Deut. 3:12, 13; Josh. 22:4</char></note>which Moses had given them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:1–6</char></note>beyond the Jordan eastward, as Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had given them: <verse number="9" style="v" />from Aroer which <char style="it">is</char> on the bank of the River Arnon, and the town that <char style="it">is</char> in the midst of the ravine, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:30; Josh. 13:16</char></note>and all the plain of Medeba as far as Dibon; <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24, 25</char></note>all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, as far as the border of the children of Ammon; <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:1; Josh. 12:5</char></note>Gilead, and the border of the Geshurites and Maachathites, all Mount Hermon, and all Bashan as far as Salcah; <verse number="12" style="v" />all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and Edrei, who remained of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:11; Josh. 12:4</char></note>the remnant of the giants; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24, 34, 35</char></note>for Moses had defeated and cast out these.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Nevertheless the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:11</char></note>did not drive out the Geshurites or the Maachathites, but the Geshurites and the Maachathites dwell among the Israelites until this day.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:20, 23, 24; Deut. 18:1; Josh. 14:3, 4</char></note>Only to the tribe of Levi he had given no inheritance; the sacrifices of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel made by fire <char style="it">are</char> their inheritance, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:33</char></note>as He said to them.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Reuben</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:14; Josh. 13:15–23</char></note>And Moses had given to the tribe of the children of Reuben <char style="it">an</char> <char style="it">inheritance</char> according to their families. <verse number="16" style="v" />Their territory was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:2</char></note>from Aroer, which <char style="it">is</char> on the bank of the River Arnon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:28</char></note>and the city that <char style="it">is</char> in the midst of the ravine, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:30; Josh. 13:9</char></note>and all the plain by Medeba; <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:28, 30</char></note>Heshbon and all its cities that <char style="it">are</char> in the plain: Dibon, Bamoth Baal, Beth Baal Meon, <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:23; Judg. 11:20; Is. 15:4; Jer. 48:34</char></note>Jahaza, Kedemoth, Mephaath, <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:37; Jer. 48:1, 23; Ezek. 25:9</char></note>Kirjathaim, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:38</char></note>Sibmah, Zereth Shahar on the mountain of the valley, <verse number="20" style="v" />Beth Peor, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:17; Josh. 12:3</char></note>the slopes of Pisgah, and Beth Jeshimoth— <verse number="21" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:10</char></note>all the cities of the plain and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:24</char></note>whom Moses had struck <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 31:8</char></note>with the princes of Midian: Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur, and Reba, who <char style="it">were</char> princes of Sihon dwelling in the country. <verse number="22" style="v" />The children of Israel also killed with the sword <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:5; 31:8</char></note>Balaam the son of Beor, the soothsayer, among those who were killed by them. <verse number="23" style="v" />And the border of the children of Reuben was the bank of the Jordan. This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the children of Reuben according to their families, the cities and their villages.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Gad</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:14; 1 Chr. 5:11</char></note>Moses also had given <char style="it">an</char> <char style="it">inheritance</char> to the tribe of Gad, to the children of Gad according to their families. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:1, 35</char></note>Their territory was Jazer, and all the cities of Gilead, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:13, 15</char></note>and half the land of the Ammonites as far as Aroer, which <char style="it">is</char> before <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:11; 2 Sam. 11:1; 12:26</char></note>Rabbah, <verse number="26" style="v" />and from Heshbon to Ramath Mizpah and Betonim, and from Mahanaim to the border of Debir, <verse number="27" style="v" />and in the valley <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:36</char></note>Beth Haram, Beth Nimrah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 33:17; 1 Kin. 7:46</char></note>Succoth, and Zaphon, the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, with the Jordan as <char style="it">its</char> border, as far as the edge <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:11; Deut. 3:17</char></note>of the Sea of Chinnereth, on the other side of the Jordan eastward. <verse number="28" style="v" />This <char style="it">is</char> the inheritance of the children of Gad according to their families, the cities and their villages.</para>
	<para style="s">Half the Tribe of Manasseh (East)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:14; 1 Chr. 5:23</char></note>Moses also had given <char style="it">an</char> <char style="it">inheritance</char> to half the tribe of Manasseh; it was for half the tribe of the children of Manasseh according to their families: <verse number="30" style="v" />Their territory was from Mahanaim, all Bashan, all the kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:41; 1 Chr. 2:23</char></note>all the towns of Jair which are in Bashan, sixty cities; <verse number="31" style="v" />half of Gilead, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 9:10; 12:4; 13:12; 1 Chr. 6:71</char></note>Ashtaroth and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan, <char style="it">were</char> for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:39, 40; Josh. 17:1</char></note>children of Machir the son of Manasseh, for half of the children of Machir according to their families.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />These <char style="it">are</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">areas</char> which Moses had distributed as an inheritance in the plains of Moab on the other side of the Jordan, by Jericho eastward. <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 18:1; Josh. 13:14; 18:7</char></note>But to the tribe of Levi Moses had given no inheritance; the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel <char style="it">was</char> their inheritance, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:20; Deut. 10:9; 18:1, 2</char></note>as He had said to them.</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Land Divided West of the Jordan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />These <char style="it">are</char> <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">areas</char> which the children of Israel inherited in the land of Canaan, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:16–29</char></note>which Eleazar the priest, Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the children of Israel distributed as an inheritance to them. <verse number="2" style="v" />Their inheritance <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 26:55; 33:54; 34:13; Ps. 16:5</char></note>by lot, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded by the hand of Moses, for the nine tribes and the half-tribe. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:33; Josh. 13:8, 32, 33</char></note>For Moses had given the inheritance of the two tribes and the half-tribe on the other side of the Jordan; but to the Levites he had given no inheritance among them. <verse number="4" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:51; 46:20; 48:1, 5; Num. 26:28; 2 Chr. 30:1</char></note>the children of Joseph were two tribes: Manasseh and Ephraim. And they gave no part to the Levites in the land, except <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:2–8; Josh. 21:1–42</char></note>cities to dwell <char style="it">in,</char> with their common-lands for their livestock and their property. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:2; Josh. 21:2</char></note>As the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses, so the children of Israel did; and they divided the land.</para>
	<para style="s">Caleb Inherits Hebron</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then the children of Judah came to Joshua in Gilgal. And Caleb the son of Jephunneh the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:11, 12</char></note>Kenizzite said to him: “You know <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:24, 30</char></note>the word which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Moses the man of God concerning <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:26</char></note>you and me in Kadesh Barnea. <verse number="7" style="v" />I <char style="it">was</char> forty years old when Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:6, 17; 14:6</char></note>sent me from Kadesh Barnea to spy out the land, and I brought back word to him as <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> in my heart. <verse number="8" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:31, 32; Deut. 1:28</char></note>my brethren who went up with me made the heart of the people melt, but I wholly <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:24; Deut. 1:36</char></note>followed the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God. <verse number="9" style="v" />So Moses swore on that day, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:23, 24</char></note>‘Surely the land <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:22; Deut. 1:36</char></note>where your foot has trodden shall be your inheritance and your children’s forever, because you have wholly followed the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God.’ <verse number="10" style="v" />And now, behold, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has kept me <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 14:24, 30, 38</char></note>alive, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:6; Neh. 9:21</char></note>as He said, these forty-five years, ever since the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke this word to Moses while Israel wandered in the wilderness; and now, here I am this day, eighty-five years old. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 34:7</char></note>As yet I <char style="it">am</char> <char style="it">as</char> strong this day as on the day that Moses sent me; just as my strength <char style="it">was</char> then, so now <char style="it">is</char> my strength for war, both <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:2</char></note>for going out and for coming in. <verse number="12" style="v" />Now therefore, give me this mountain of which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke in that day; for you heard in that day how <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:28, 33</char></note>the Anakim <char style="it">were</char> there, and <char style="it">that</char> the cities <char style="it">were</char> great <char style="it">and</char> fortified. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rom. 8:31</char></note>It may be that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">be</char> with me, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:14; Judg. 1:20</char></note>I shall be able to drive them out as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:6</char></note>blessed him, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:37; 15:13</char></note>and gave Hebron to Caleb the son of Jephunneh as an inheritance. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:12</char></note>Hebron therefore became the inheritance of Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite to this day, because he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:8, 9</char></note>wholly followed the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel. <verse number="15" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 23:2; Josh. 15:13</char></note>the name of Hebron formerly was Kirjath Arba (<char style="it">Arba</char> <char style="it">was</char> the greatest man among the Anakim).</para>
	<para style="p"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:23</char></note>Then the land had rest from war.</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Land of Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />So <char style="it">this</char> was the lot of the tribe of the children of Judah according to their families:</para>
	<para style="p"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:3</char></note>The border of Edom at the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:36</char></note>Wilderness of Zin southward <char style="it">was</char> the extreme southern boundary. <verse number="2" style="v" />And their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:3, 4</char></note>southern border began at the shore of the Salt Sea, from the bay that faces southward. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then it went out to the southern side of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:4</char></note>the Ascent of Akrabbim, passed along to Zin, ascended on the south side of Kadesh Barnea, passed along to Hezron, went up to Adar, and went around to Karkaa. <verse number="4" style="v" /><char style="it">From</char> <char style="it">there</char> it passed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:5</char></note>toward Azmon and went out to the Brook of Egypt; and the border ended at the sea. This shall be your southern border.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />The east border <char style="it">was</char> the Salt Sea as far as the mouth of the Jordan.</para>
	<para style="p">And the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:15–19</char></note>border on the northern quarter <char style="it">began</char> at the bay of the sea at the mouth of the Jordan. <verse number="6" style="v" />The border went up to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:19, 21</char></note>Beth Hoglah and passed north of Beth Arabah; and the border went up <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:17</char></note>to the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then the border went up toward <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:26</char></note>Debir from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:26</char></note>the Valley of Achor, and it turned northward toward Gilgal, which <char style="it">is</char> before the Ascent of Adummim, which <char style="it">is</char> on the south side of the valley. The border continued toward the waters of En Shemesh and ended at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 17:17; 1 Kin. 1:9</char></note>En Rogel. <verse number="8" style="v" />And the border went up <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:16; 2 Kin. 23:10; Jer. 19:2, 6</char></note>by the Valley of the Son of Hinnom to the southern slope of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:63; 18:28; Judg. 1:21; 19:10</char></note>Jebusite <char style="it">city</char> (which <char style="it">is</char> Jerusalem). The border went up to the top of the mountain that <char style="it">lies</char> before the Valley of Hinnom westward, which <char style="it">is</char> at the end of the Valley <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:16</char></note>of Rephaim northward. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then the border went around from the top of the hill to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:15</char></note>the fountain of the water of Nephtoah, and extended to the cities of Mount Ephron. And the border went around <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 13:6</char></note>to Baalah (which <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:12</char></note>Kirjath Jearim). <verse number="10" style="v" />Then the border turned westward from Baalah to Mount Seir, passed along to the side of Mount Jearim on the north (which <char style="it">is</char> Chesalon), went down to Beth Shemesh, and passed on to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 38:13; Judg. 14:1</char></note>Timnah. <verse number="11" style="v" />And the border went out to the side of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:43</char></note>Ekron northward. Then the border went around to Shicron, passed along to Mount Baalah, and extended to Jabneel; and the border ended at the sea.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />The west border <char style="it">was</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:6, 7; Josh. 15:47</char></note>the coastline of the Great Sea. This <char style="it">is</char> the boundary of the children of Judah all around according to their families.</para>
	<para style="s">Caleb Occupies Hebron and Debir</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:13</char></note>Now to Caleb the son of Jephunneh he gave a share among the children of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:6</char></note>Judah, according to the commandment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to Joshua, <char style="it">namely,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:15</char></note>Kirjath Arba, which <char style="it">is</char> Hebron (<char style="it">Arba</char> <char style="it">was</char> the father of Anak). <verse number="14" style="v" />Caleb drove out <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:10, 20</char></note>the three sons of Anak from there: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 13:22</char></note>Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai, the children of Anak. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:38; Judg. 1:11</char></note>he went up from there to the inhabitants of Debir (formerly the name of Debir <char style="it">was</char> Kirjath Sepher).</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:12</char></note>And Caleb said, “He who attacks Kirjath Sepher and takes it, to him I will give Achsah my daughter as wife.” <verse number="17" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:13; 3:9</char></note>Othniel the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:12; Josh. 14:6</char></note>son of Kenaz, the brother of Caleb, took it; and he gave him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:12</char></note>Achsah his daughter as wife. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:14</char></note>Now it was so, when she came <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">him,</char> that she persuaded him to ask her father for a field. So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 24:64; 1 Sam. 25:23</char></note>she dismounted from <char style="it">her</char> donkey, and Caleb said to her, “What do you wish?” <verse number="19" style="v" />She answered, “Give me a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 33:11</char></note>blessing; since you have given me land in the South, give me also springs of water.” So he gave her the upper springs and the lower springs.</para>
	<para style="s">The Cities of Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Judah according to their families:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />The cities at the limits of the tribe of the children of Judah, toward the border of Edom in the South, were Kabzeel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:21</char></note>Eder, Jagur, <verse number="22" style="v" />Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah, <verse number="23" style="v" />Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan, <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 23:14</char></note>Ziph, Telem, Bealoth, <verse number="25" style="v" />Hazor, Hadattah, Kerioth, Hezron (which <char style="it">is</char> Hazor), <verse number="26" style="v" />Amam, Shema, Moladah, <verse number="27" style="v" />Hazar Gaddah, Heshmon, Beth Pelet, <verse number="28" style="v" />Hazar Shual, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 21:31; Josh. 19:2</char></note>Beersheba, Bizjothjah, <verse number="29" style="v" />Baalah, Ijim, Ezem, <verse number="30" style="v" />Eltolad, Chesil, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:4</char></note>Hormah, <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:5; 1 Sam. 27:6; 30:1</char></note>Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah, <verse number="32" style="v" />Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 20:45, 47</char></note>Rimmon: all the cities <char style="it">are</char> twenty-nine, with their villages.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />In the lowland: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 13:25; 16:31</char></note>Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah, <verse number="34" style="v" />Zanoah, En Gannim, Tappuah, Enam, <verse number="35" style="v" />Jarmuth, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 22:1</char></note>Adullam, Socoh, Azekah, <verse number="36" style="v" />Sharaim, Adithaim, Gederah, and Gederothaim: fourteen cities with their villages; <verse number="37" style="v" />Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal Gad, <verse number="38" style="v" />Dilean, Mizpah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:7</char></note>Joktheel, <verse number="39" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:19</char></note>Lachish, Bozkath, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:3</char></note>Eglon, <verse number="40" style="v" />Cabbon, Lahmas, Kithlish, <verse number="41" style="v" />Gederoth, Beth Dagon, Naamah, and Makkedah: sixteen cities with their villages; <verse number="42" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:13</char></note>Libnah, Ether, Ashan, <verse number="43" style="v" />Jiphtah, Ashnah, Nezib, <verse number="44" style="v" />Keilah, Achzib, and Mareshah: nine cities with their villages; <verse number="45" style="v" />Ekron, with its towns and villages; <verse number="46" style="v" />from Ekron to the sea, all that <char style="it">lay</char> near <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:22</char></note>Ashdod, with their villages; <verse number="47" style="v" />Ashdod with its towns and villages, Gaza with its towns and villages—as far as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:4</char></note>the Brook of Egypt and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:6</char></note>the Great Sea with <char style="it">its</char> coastline.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" />And in the mountain country: Shamir, Jattir, Sochoh, <verse number="49" style="v" />Dannah, Kirjath Sannah (which <char style="it">is</char> Debir), <verse number="50" style="v" />Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim, <verse number="51" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:41; 11:16</char></note>Goshen, Holon, and Giloh: eleven cities with their villages; <verse number="52" style="v" />Arab, Dumah, Eshean, <verse number="53" style="v" />Janum, Beth Tappuah, Aphekah, <verse number="54" style="v" />Humtah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:15</char></note>Kirjath Arba (which <char style="it">is</char> Hebron), and Zior: nine cities with their villages; <verse number="55" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 23:24, 25</char></note>Maon, Carmel, Ziph, Juttah, <verse number="56" style="v" />Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah, <verse number="57" style="v" />Kain, Gibeah, and Timnah: ten cities with their villages; <verse number="58" style="v" />Halhul, Beth Zur, Gedor, <verse number="59" style="v" />Maarath, Beth Anoth, and Eltekon: six cities with their villages; <verse number="60" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:14; 1 Sam. 7:1, 2</char></note>Kirjath Baal (which <char style="it">is</char> Kirjath Jearim) and Rabbah: two cities with their villages.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="61" style="v" />In the wilderness: Beth Arabah, Middin, Secacah, <verse number="62" style="v" />Nibshan, the City of Salt, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 23:29; Ezek. 47:10</char></note>En Gedi: six cities with their villages.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="63" style="v" />As for the Jebusites, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:8, 21; 2 Sam. 5:6; 1 Chr. 11:4</char></note>the children of Judah could not drive them out; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:21</char></note>but the Jebusites dwell with the children of Judah at Jerusalem to this day.</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Ephraim and West Manasseh</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />The lot fell to the children of Joseph from the Jordan, by Jericho, to the waters of Jericho on the east, to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 8:15; 18:12</char></note>wilderness that goes up from Jericho through the mountains to Bethel, <verse number="2" style="v" />then went out from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:13; Judg. 1:26</char></note>Bethel to Luz, passed along to the border of the Archites at Ataroth, <verse number="3" style="v" />and went down westward to the boundary of the Japhletites, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:13; 1 Kin. 9:17; 2 Chr. 8:5</char></note>as far as the boundary of Lower Beth Horon to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:21; 1 Kin. 9:15; 1 Chr. 7:28</char></note>Gezer; and it ended at the sea.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:14</char></note>So the children of Joseph, Manasseh and Ephraim, took their inheritance.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Ephraim</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:29; 1 Chr. 7:28, 29</char></note>The border of the children of Ephraim, according to their families, was <char style="it">thus:</char> The border of their inheritance on the east side was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:13</char></note>Ataroth Addar <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 8:5</char></note>as far as Upper Beth Horon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And the border went out toward the sea on the north side of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:7</char></note>Michmethath; then the border went around eastward to Taanath Shiloh, and passed by it on the east of Janohah. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then it went down from Janohah to Ataroth and Naarah, reached to Jericho, and came out at the Jordan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />The border went out from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:8</char></note>Tappuah westward to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:9</char></note>Brook Kanah, and it ended at the sea. This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Ephraim according to their families. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:9</char></note>The separate cities for the children of Ephraim <char style="it">were</char> among the inheritance of the children of Manasseh, all the cities with their villages.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:63; 17:12, 13; Judg. 1:29; 1 Kin. 9:16</char></note>And they did not drive out the Canaanites who dwelt in Gezer; but the Canaanites dwell among the Ephraimites to this day and have become forced laborers.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Other Half-Tribe of Manasseh (West)</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />There was also a lot for the tribe of Manasseh, for he <char style="it">was</char> the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 41:51; 46:20; 48:18</char></note>firstborn of Joseph: <char style="it">namely</char> for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 50:23; Judg. 5:14</char></note>Machir the firstborn of Manasseh, the father of Gilead, because he was a man of war; therefore he was given <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 3:15</char></note>Gilead and Bashan. <verse number="2" style="v" />And there was <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">lot</char> for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 26:29–33</char></note>the rest of the children of Manasseh according to their families: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 7:18</char></note>for the children of Abiezer, the children of Helek, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 26:31</char></note>the children of Asriel, the children of Shechem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 26:32</char></note>the children of Hepher, and the children of Shemida; these <char style="it">were</char> the male children of Manasseh the son of Joseph according to their families.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 26:33; 27:1; 36:2</char></note>Zelophehad the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, had no sons, but only daughters. And these <char style="it">are</char> the names of his daughters: Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. <verse number="4" style="v" />And they came near before <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:1</char></note>Eleazar the priest, before Joshua the son of Nun, and before the rulers, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:2–11</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded Moses to give us an inheritance among our brothers.” Therefore, according to the commandment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, he gave them an inheritance among their father’s brothers. <verse number="5" style="v" />Ten shares fell to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:7</char></note>Manasseh, besides the land of Gilead and Bashan, which <char style="it">were</char> on the other side of the Jordan, <verse number="6" style="v" />because the daughters of Manasseh received an inheritance among his sons; and the rest of Manasseh’s sons had the land of Gilead.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />And the territory of Manasseh was from Asher to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:6</char></note>Michmethath, that <char style="it">lies</char> east of Shechem; and the border went along south to the inhabitants of En Tappuah. <verse number="8" style="v" />Manasseh had the land of Tappuah, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:8</char></note>Tappuah on the border of Manasseh <char style="it">belonged</char> to the children of Ephraim. <verse number="9" style="v" />And the border descended to the Brook Kanah, southward to the brook. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:9</char></note>These cities of Ephraim <char style="it">are</char> among the cities of Manasseh. The border of Manasseh <char style="it">was</char> on the north side of the brook; and it ended at the sea.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Southward <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> Ephraim’s, northward <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">was</char> Manasseh’s, and the sea was its border. Manasseh’s territory was adjoining Asher on the north and Issachar on the east. <verse number="11" style="v" />And in Issachar and in Asher, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 7:29</char></note>Manasseh had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:27; 1 Sam. 31:10; 1 Kin. 4:12</char></note>Beth Shean and its towns, Ibleam and its towns, the inhabitants of Dor and its towns, the inhabitants of En Dor and its towns, the inhabitants of Taanach and its towns, and the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns—three hilly regions. <verse number="12" style="v" />Yet <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:19, 27, 28</char></note>the children of Manasseh could not drive out <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">inhabitants</char> <char style="it">of</char> those cities, but the Canaanites were determined to dwell in that land. <verse number="13" style="v" />And it happened, when the children of Israel grew strong, that they put the Canaanites to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:10</char></note>forced labor, but did not utterly drive them out.</para>
	<para style="s">More Land for Ephraim and Manasseh</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:4</char></note>Then the children of Joseph spoke to Joshua, saying, “Why have you given us <char style="it">only</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 48:22</char></note>one lot and one share to inherit, since we <char style="it">are</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 48:19; Num. 26:34, 37</char></note>a great people, inasmuch as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has blessed us until now?”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />So Joshua answered them, “If you <char style="it">are</char> a great people, <char style="it">then</char> go up to the forest <char style="it">country</char> and clear a place for yourself there in the land of the Perizzites and the giants, since the mountains of Ephraim are too confined for you.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />But the children of Joseph said, “The mountain country is not enough for us; and all the Canaanites who dwell in the land of the valley have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:18; Judg. 1:19; 4:3</char></note>chariots of iron, <char style="it">both</char> <char style="it">those</char> who <char style="it">are</char> of Beth Shean and its towns and <char style="it">those</char> who <char style="it">are</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:18; 1 Kin. 4:12</char></note>of the Valley of Jezreel.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And Joshua spoke to the house of Joseph—to Ephraim and Manasseh—saying, “You <char style="it">are</char> a great people and have great power; you shall not have <char style="it">only</char> one lot, <verse number="18" style="v" />but the mountain country shall be yours. Although it <char style="it">is</char> wooded, you shall cut it down, and its farthest extent shall be yours; for you shall drive out the Canaanites, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 20:1</char></note>though they have iron chariots <char style="it">and</char> are strong.”</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Remainder of the Land Divided</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now the whole congregation of the children of Israel assembled together <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:51; 21:2; 22:9; Jer. 7:12</char></note>at Shiloh, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:31; 1 Sam. 1:3, 24; 4:3, 4</char></note>set up the tabernacle of meeting there. And the land was subdued before them. <verse number="2" style="v" />But there remained among the children of Israel seven tribes which had not yet received their inheritance.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />Then Joshua said to the children of Israel: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:9</char></note>“How long will you neglect to go and possess the land which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of your fathers has given you? <verse number="4" style="v" />Pick out from among you three men for <char style="it">each</char> tribe, and I will send them; they shall rise and go through the land, survey it according to their inheritance, and come <char style="it">back</char> to me. <verse number="5" style="v" />And they shall divide it into seven parts. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:1</char></note>Judah shall remain in their territory on the south, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:1—17:18</char></note>house of Joseph shall remain in their territory on the north. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall therefore survey the land in seven parts and bring <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">survey</char> here to me, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:2; 18:10</char></note>that I may cast lots for you here before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:7, 20; Josh. 13:33</char></note>But the Levites have no part among you, for the priesthood of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> their inheritance. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:8</char></note>And Gad, Reuben, and half the tribe of Manasseh have received their inheritance beyond the Jordan on the east, which Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave them.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then the men arose to go away; and Joshua charged those who went to survey the land, saying, “Go, walk <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 13:17</char></note>through the land, survey it, and come back to me, that I may cast lots for you here before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Shiloh.” <verse number="9" style="v" />So the men went, passed through the land, and wrote the survey in a book in seven parts by cities; and they came to Joshua at the camp in Shiloh. <verse number="10" style="v" />Then Joshua cast <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 13:19</char></note>lots for them in Shiloh before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and there <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:16–29; Josh. 19:51</char></note>Joshua divided the land to the children of Israel according to their divisions.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Benjamin</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:21</char></note>Now the lot of the tribe of the children of Benjamin came up according to their families, and the territory of their lot came out between the children of Judah and the children of Joseph. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:1</char></note>Their border on the north side began at the Jordan, and the border went up to the side of Jericho on the north, and went up through the mountains westward; it ended at the Wilderness of Beth Aven. <verse number="13" style="v" />The border went over from there toward Luz, to the side of Luz <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 28:19; Josh. 16:2; Judg. 1:23</char></note>(which <char style="it">is</char> Bethel) southward; and the border descended to Ataroth Addar, near the hill that <char style="it">lies</char> on the south side <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 16:3</char></note>of Lower Beth Horon.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then the border extended around the west side to the south, from the hill that <char style="it">lies</char> before Beth Horon southward; and it ended at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:9</char></note>Kirjath Baal (which <char style="it">is</char> Kirjath Jearim), a city of the children of Judah. This <char style="it">was</char> the west side.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />The south side <char style="it">began</char> at the end of Kirjath Jearim, and the border extended on the west and went out to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:9</char></note>the spring of the waters of Nephtoah. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then the border came down to the end of the mountain that <char style="it">lies</char> before <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:8</char></note>the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, which <char style="it">is</char> in the Valley of the Rephaim on the north, descended to the Valley of Hinnom, to the side of the Jebusite <char style="it">city</char> on the south, and descended to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:7</char></note>En Rogel. <verse number="17" style="v" />And it went around from the north, went out to En Shemesh, and extended toward Geliloth, which is before the Ascent of Adummim, and descended to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:6</char></note>the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben. <verse number="18" style="v" />Then it passed along toward the north side of Arabah, and went down to Arabah. <verse number="19" style="v" />And the border passed along to the north side of Beth Hoglah; then the border ended at the north bay at the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:2, 5</char></note>Salt Sea, at the south end of the Jordan. This <char style="it">was</char> the southern boundary.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />The Jordan was its border on the east side. This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the children of Benjamin, according to its boundaries all around, according to their families.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Now the cities of the tribe of the children of Benjamin, according to their families, were Jericho, Beth Hoglah, Emek Keziz, <verse number="22" style="v" />Beth Arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel, <verse number="23" style="v" />Avim, Parah, Ophrah, <verse number="24" style="v" />Chephar Haammoni, Ophni, and Gaba: twelve cities with their villages; <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 11:19; 21:17; 1 Kin. 3:4, 5</char></note>Gibeon, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 31:15</char></note>Ramah, Beeroth, <verse number="26" style="v" />Mizpah, Chephirah, Mozah, <verse number="27" style="v" />Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah, <verse number="28" style="v" />Zelah, Eleph, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:8, 63</char></note>Jebus (which <char style="it">is</char> Jerusalem), Gibeath, <char style="it">and</char> Kirjath: fourteen cities with their villages. This was the inheritance of the children of Benjamin according to their families.</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Simeon’s Inheritance with Judah</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />The <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:3</char></note>second lot came out for Simeon, for the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:9</char></note>And their inheritance was within the inheritance of the children of Judah. <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 4:28</char></note>They had in their inheritance Beersheba (Sheba), Moladah, <verse number="3" style="v" />Hazar Shual, Balah, Ezem, <verse number="4" style="v" />Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah, <verse number="5" style="v" />Ziklag, Beth Marcaboth, Hazar Susah, <verse number="6" style="v" />Beth Lebaoth, and Sharuhen: thirteen cities and their villages; <verse number="7" style="v" />Ain, Rimmon, Ether, and Ashan: four cities and their villages; <verse number="8" style="v" />and all the villages that <char style="it">were</char> all around these cities as far as Baalath Beer, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 30:27</char></note>Ramah of the South. This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Simeon according to their families.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />The inheritance of the children of Simeon <char style="it">was</char> <char style="it">included</char> in the share of the children of Judah, for the share of the children of Judah was too much for them. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:1</char></note>Therefore the children of Simeon had <char style="it">their</char> inheritance within the inheritance of that people.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Zebulun</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />The third lot came out for the children of Zebulun according to their families, and the border of their inheritance was as far as Sarid. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 49:13</char></note>Their border went toward the west and to Maralah, went to Dabbasheth, and extended along the brook that is <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 12:22</char></note>east of Jokneam. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then from Sarid it went eastward toward the sunrise along the border of Chisloth Tabor, and went out toward <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:72</char></note>Daberath, bypassing Japhia. <verse number="13" style="v" />And from there it passed along on the east of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 14:25</char></note>Gath Hepher, toward Eth Kazin, and extended to Rimmon, which borders on Neah. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then the border went around it on the north side of Hannathon, and it ended in the Valley of Jiphthah El. <verse number="15" style="v" />Included were Kattath, Nahallal, Shimron, Idalah, and Bethlehem: twelve cities with their villages. <verse number="16" style="v" />This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the children of Zebulun according to their families, these cities with their villages.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Issachar</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />The fourth lot came out to Issachar, for the children of Issachar according to their families. <verse number="18" style="v" />And their territory went to Jezreel, and <char style="it">included</char> Chesulloth, Shunem, <verse number="19" style="v" />Haphraim, Shion, Anaharath, <verse number="20" style="v" />Rabbith, Kishion, Abez, <verse number="21" style="v" />Remeth, En Gannim, En Haddah, and Beth Pazzez. <verse number="22" style="v" />And the border reached to Tabor, Shahazimah, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:10; Judg. 1:33</char></note>Beth Shemesh; their border ended at the Jordan: sixteen cities with their villages. <verse number="23" style="v" />This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Issachar according to their families, the cities and their villages.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Asher</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:31, 32</char></note>The fifth lot came out for the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families. <verse number="25" style="v" />And their territory included Helkath, Hali, Beten, Achshaph, <verse number="26" style="v" />Alammelech, Amad, and Mishal; it reached to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 15:12; 1 Kin. 18:20; Is. 33:9; 35:2; Jer. 46:18</char></note>Mount Carmel westward, along <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">Brook</char> Shihor Libnath. <verse number="27" style="v" />It turned toward the sunrise to Beth Dagon; and it reached to Zebulun and to the Valley of Jiphthah El, then northward beyond Beth Emek and Neiel, bypassing <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 9:13</char></note>Cabul <char style="it">which</char> <char style="it">was</char> on the left, <verse number="28" style="v" />including Ebron, Rehob, Hammon, and Kanah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 10:19; Josh. 11:8; Judg. 1:31; Acts 27:3</char></note>as far as Greater Sidon. <verse number="29" style="v" />And the border turned to Ramah and to the fortified city of Tyre; then the border turned to Hosah, and ended at the sea by the region of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:31</char></note>Achzib. <verse number="30" style="v" />Also Ummah, Aphek, and Rehob <char style="it">were</char> <char style="it">included:</char> twenty-two cities with their villages. <verse number="31" style="v" />This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Asher according to their families, these cities with their villages.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Naphtali</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:32–39; Judg. 1:33</char></note>The sixth lot came out to the children of Naphtali, for the children of Naphtali according to their families. <verse number="33" style="v" />And their border began at Heleph, enclosing the territory from the terebinth tree in Zaanannim, Adami Nekeb, and Jabneel, as far as Lakkum; it ended at the Jordan. <verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 33:23</char></note>From Heleph the border extended westward to Aznoth Tabor, and went out from there toward Hukkok; it adjoined Zebulun on the south side and Asher on the west side, and ended at Judah by the Jordan toward the sunrise. <verse number="35" style="v" />And the fortified cities <char style="it">are</char> Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, Chinnereth, <verse number="36" style="v" />Adamah, Ramah, Hazor, <verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:7</char></note>Kedesh, Edrei, En Hazor, <verse number="38" style="v" />Iron, Migdal El, Horem, Beth Anath, and Beth Shemesh: nineteen cities with their villages. <verse number="39" style="v" />This <char style="it">was</char> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Naphtali according to their families, the cities and their villages.</para>
	<para style="s">The Land of Dan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:40–48; Judg. 1:34–36</char></note>The seventh lot came out for the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families. <verse number="41" style="v" />And the territory of their inheritance was Zorah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:33</char></note>Eshtaol, Ir Shemesh, <verse number="42" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:35; 1 Kin. 4:9</char></note>Shaalabbin, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:12; 21:24</char></note>Aijalon, Jethlah, <verse number="43" style="v" />Elon, Timnah, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:11; Judg. 1:18</char></note>Ekron, <verse number="44" style="v" />Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath, <verse number="45" style="v" />Jehud, Bene Berak, Gath Rimmon, <verse number="46" style="v" />Me Jarkon, and Rakkon, with the region near Joppa. <verse number="47" style="v" />And the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18</char></note>border of the children of Dan went beyond these, because the children of Dan went up to fight against Leshem and took it; and they struck it with the edge of the sword, took possession of it, and dwelt in it. They called Leshem, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 18:29</char></note>Dan, after the name of Dan their father. <verse number="48" style="v" />This <char style="it">is</char> the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Dan according to their families, these cities with their villages.</para>
	<para style="s">Joshua’s Inheritance</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" />When they had made an end of dividing the land as an inheritance according to their borders, the children of Israel gave an inheritance among them to Joshua the son of Nun. <verse number="50" style="v" />According to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> they gave him the city which he asked for, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:30</char></note>Timnath <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 7:24</char></note>Serah in the mountains of Ephraim; and he built the city and dwelt in it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:17; Josh. 14:1</char></note>These <char style="it">were</char> the inheritances which Eleazar the priest, Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the children of Israel divided as an inheritance by lot <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:1, 10</char></note>in Shiloh before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, at the door of the tabernacle of meeting. So they made an end of dividing the country.</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Cities of Refuge</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />The <char style="sc">Lord</char> also spoke to Joshua, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 21:13; Num. 35:6–34; Deut. 19:2, 9</char></note>‘Appoint for yourselves cities of refuge, of which I spoke to you through Moses, <verse number="3" style="v" />that the slayer who kills a person accidentally <char style="it">or</char> unintentionally may flee there; and they shall be your refuge from the avenger of blood. <verse number="4" style="v" />And when he flees to one of those cities, and stands at the entrance of the gate of the city, and declares his case in the hearing of the elders of that city, they shall take him into the city as one of them, and give him a place, that he may dwell among them. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:12</char></note>Then if the avenger of blood pursues him, they shall not deliver the slayer into his hand, because he struck his neighbor unintentionally, but did not hate him beforehand. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he shall dwell in that city <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:12, 24, 25</char></note>until he stands before the congregation for judgment, <char style="it">and</char> until the death of the one who is high priest in those days. Then the slayer may return and come to his own city and his own house, to the city from which he fled.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />So they appointed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:32; 1 Chr. 6:76</char></note>Kedesh in Galilee, in the mountains of Naphtali, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:21; 2 Chr. 10:1</char></note>Shechem in the mountains of Ephraim, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:15; 21:11, 13</char></note>Kirjath Arba (which <char style="it">is</char> Hebron) in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 1:39</char></note>the mountains of Judah. <verse number="8" style="v" />And on the other side of the Jordan, by Jericho eastward, they assigned <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:43; Josh. 21:36; 1 Chr. 6:78</char></note>Bezer in the wilderness on the plain, from the tribe of Reuben, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:38; 1 Kin. 22:3</char></note>Ramoth in Gilead, from the tribe of Gad, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:27</char></note>Golan in Bashan, from the tribe of Manasseh. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:15</char></note>These were the cities appointed for all the children of Israel and for the stranger who dwelt among them, that whoever killed a person accidentally might flee there, and not die by the hand of the avenger of blood <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:6</char></note>until he stood before the congregation.</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Cities of the Levites</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the heads of the fathers’ <char style="it">houses</char> of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:1–8</char></note>Levites came near to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 34:16–29; Josh. 14:1; 17:4</char></note>Eleazar the priest, to Joshua the son of Nun, and to the heads of the fathers’ <char style="it">houses</char> of the tribes of the children of Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />And they spoke to them at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:1</char></note>Shiloh in the land of Canaan, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:2</char></note>“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded through Moses to give us cities to dwell in, with their common-lands for our livestock.” <verse number="3" style="v" />So the children of Israel gave to the Levites from their inheritance, at the commandment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, these cities and their common-lands:</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Now the lot came out for the families of the Kohathites. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:8, 19</char></note>the children of Aaron the priest, <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> of the Levites, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:51</char></note>had thirteen cities by lot from the tribe of Judah, from the tribe of Simeon, and from the tribe of Benjamin. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:20</char></note>The rest of the children of Kohath had ten cities by lot from the families of the tribe of Ephraim, from the tribe of Dan, and from the half-tribe of Manasseh.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:27</char></note>the children of Gershon had thirteen cities by lot from the families of the tribe of Issachar, from the tribe of Asher, from the tribe of Naphtali, and from the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:34</char></note>The children of Merari according to their families had twelve cities from the tribe of Reuben, from the tribe of Gad, and from the tribe of Zebulun.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:3</char></note>And the children of Israel gave these cities with their common-lands by lot to the Levites, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:2</char></note>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded by the hand of Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So they gave from the tribe of the children of Judah and from the tribe of the children of Simeon these cities which are designated by name, <verse number="10" style="v" />which were for the children of Aaron, one of the families of the Kohathites, <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">were</char> of the children of Levi; for the lot was theirs first. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:7; 1 Chr. 6:55</char></note>And they gave them Kirjath Arba (<char style="it">Arba</char> <char style="it">was</char> the father of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:15; 15:13, 14</char></note>Anak), <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:7; Luke 1:39</char></note>which <char style="it">is</char> Hebron, in the mountains of Judah, with the common-land surrounding it. <verse number="12" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 14:14; 1 Chr. 6:56</char></note>the fields of the city and its villages they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh as his possession.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Thus <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:57</char></note>to the children of Aaron the priest they gave <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:54; 20:2, 7</char></note>Hebron with its common-land (a city of refuge for the slayer), <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:42; 2 Kin. 8:22</char></note>Libnah with its common-land, <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:48</char></note>Jattir with its common-land, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:50</char></note>Eshtemoa with its common-land, <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:58</char></note>Holon with its common-land, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:49</char></note>Debir with its common-land, <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:59</char></note>Ain with its common-land, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:55</char></note>Juttah with its common-land, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 15:10</char></note>Beth Shemesh with its common-land: nine cities from those two tribes; <verse number="17" style="v" />and from the tribe of Benjamin, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:25</char></note>Gibeon with its common-land, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:24</char></note>Geba with its common-land, <verse number="18" style="v" />Anathoth with its common-land, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:60</char></note>Almon with its common-land: four cities. <verse number="19" style="v" />All the cities of the children of Aaron, the priests, <char style="it">were</char> thirteen cities with their common-lands.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 6:66</char></note>And the families of the children of Kohath, the Levites, the rest of the children of Kohath, even they had the cities of their lot from the tribe of Ephraim. <verse number="21" style="v" />For they gave them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:7</char></note>Shechem with its common-land in the mountains of Ephraim (a city of refuge for the slayer), <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 1:29</char></note>Gezer with its common-land, <verse number="22" style="v" />Kibzaim with its common-land, and Beth Horon with its common-land: four cities; <verse number="23" style="v" />and from the tribe of Dan, Eltekeh with its common-land, Gibbethon with its common-land, <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 10:12</char></note>Aijalon with its common-land, <char style="it">and</char> Gath Rimmon with its common-land: four cities; <verse number="25" style="v" />and from the half-tribe of Manasseh, Tanach with its common-land and Gath Rimmon with its common-land: two cities. <verse number="26" style="v" />All the ten cities with their common-lands were for the rest of the families of the children of Kohath.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:6; 1 Chr. 6:71</char></note>Also to the children of Gershon, of the families of the Levites, from the <char style="it">other</char> half-tribe of Manasseh, <char style="it">they</char> <char style="it">gave</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:8</char></note>Golan in Bashan with its common-land (a city of refuge for the slayer), and Be Eshterah with its common-land: two cities; <verse number="28" style="v" />and from the tribe of Issachar, Kishion with its common-land, Daberath with its common-land, <verse number="29" style="v" />Jarmuth with its common-land, <char style="it">and</char> En Gannim with its common-land: four cities; <verse number="30" style="v" />and from the tribe of Asher, Mishal with its common-land, Abdon with its common-land, <verse number="31" style="v" />Helkath with its common-land, and Rehob with its common-land: four cities; <verse number="32" style="v" />and from the tribe of Naphtali, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:7</char></note>Kedesh in Galilee with its common-land (a city of refuge for the slayer), Hammoth Dor with its common-land, and Kartan with its common-land: three cities. <verse number="33" style="v" />All the cities of the Gershonites according to their families <char style="it">were</char> thirteen cities with their common-lands.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:7; 1 Chr. 6:77–81</char></note>And to the families of the children of Merari, the rest of the Levites, from the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam with its common-land, Kartah with its common-land, <verse number="35" style="v" />Dimnah with its common-land, <char style="it">and</char> Nahalal with its common-land: four cities; <verse number="36" style="v" />and from the tribe of Reuben, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:43; Josh. 20:8</char></note>Bezer with its common-land, Jahaz with its common-land, <verse number="37" style="v" />Kedemoth with its common-land, and Mephaath with its common-land: four cities; <verse number="38" style="v" />and from the tribe of Gad, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 20:8</char></note>Ramoth in Gilead with its common-land (a city of refuge for the slayer), Mahanaim with its common-land, <verse number="39" style="v" />Heshbon with its common-land, <char style="it">and</char> Jazer with its common-land: four cities in all. <verse number="40" style="v" />So all the cities for the children of Merari according to their families, the rest of the families of the Levites, were <char style="it">by</char> their lot twelve cities.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:7</char></note>All the cities of the Levites within the possession of the children of Israel <char style="it">were</char> forty-eight cities with their common-lands. <verse number="42" style="v" />Every one of these cities had its common-land surrounding it; thus <char style="it">were</char> all these cities.</para>
	<para style="s">The Promise Fulfilled</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" />So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave to Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 12:7; 26:3, 4; 28:4, 13, 14</char></note>all the land of which He had sworn to give to their fathers, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:53; Josh. 1:11</char></note>took possession of it and dwelt in it. <verse number="44" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:23, 24; Josh. 11:23; 22:4</char></note>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:13, 15; 11:23</char></note>rest all around, according to all that He had sworn to their fathers. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:24</char></note>not a man of all their enemies stood against them; the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered all their enemies into their hand. <verse number="45" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Num. 23:19); Josh. 23:14; 1 Kin. 8:56</char></note>Not a word failed of any good thing which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had spoken to the house of Israel. All came to pass.</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Eastern Tribes Return to Their Lands</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Joshua called the Reubenites, the Gadites, and half the tribe of Manasseh, <verse number="2" style="v" />and said to them: “You have kept <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:20–22; Deut. 3:18</char></note>all that Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:12–18</char></note>and have obeyed my voice in all that I commanded you. <verse number="3" style="v" />You have not left your brethren these many days, up to this day, but have kept the charge of the commandment of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. <verse number="4" style="v" />And now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has given <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:44</char></note>rest to your brethren, as He promised them; now therefore, return and go to your tents <char style="it">and</char> to the land of your possession, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:33</char></note>which Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave you on the other side of the Jordan. <verse number="5" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 6:6, 17; 11:22; Jer. 12:16</char></note>take careful heed to do the commandment and the law which Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 10:12; 11:13, 22</char></note>to love the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, to walk in all His ways, to keep His commandments, to hold fast to Him, and to serve Him with all your heart and with all your soul.” <verse number="6" style="v" />So Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 47:7; Ex. 39:43; Josh. 14:13; 2 Sam. 6:18; Luke 24:50</char></note>blessed them and sent them away, and they went to their tents.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />Now to half the tribe of Manasseh Moses had given a possession in Bashan, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 17:1–13</char></note>but to the <char style="it">other</char> half of it Joshua gave <char style="it">a</char> <char style="it">possession</char> among their brethren on this side of the Jordan, westward. And indeed, when Joshua sent them away to their tents, he blessed them, <verse number="8" style="v" />and spoke to them, saying, “Return with much riches to your tents, with very much livestock, with silver, with gold, with bronze, with iron, and with very much clothing. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 31:27; 1 Sam. 30:24</char></note>Divide the spoil of your enemies with your brethren.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />So the children of Reuben, the children of Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh returned, and departed from the children of Israel at Shiloh, which <char style="it">is</char> in the land of Canaan, to go to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 32:1, 26, 29</char></note>the country of Gilead, to the land of their possession, which they had obtained according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by the hand of Moses.</para>
	<para style="s">An Altar by the Jordan</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />And when they came to the region of the Jordan which <char style="it">is</char> in the land of Canaan, the children of Reuben, the children of Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh built an altar there by the Jordan—a great, impressive altar. <verse number="11" style="v" />Now the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:12–18; Judg. 20:12, 13</char></note>heard <char style="it">someone</char> say, “Behold, the children of Reuben, the children of Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh have built an altar on the frontier of the land of Canaan, in the region of the Jordan—on the children of Israel’s side.” <verse number="12" style="v" />And when the children of Israel heard <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">it,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:1; Judg. 20:1</char></note>the whole congregation of the children of Israel gathered together at Shiloh to go to war against them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />Then the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:14; Judg. 20:12</char></note>sent <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 6:25; Num. 25:7, 11–13</char></note>Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest to the children of Reuben, to the children of Gad, and to half the tribe of Manasseh, into the land of Gilead, <verse number="14" style="v" />and with him ten rulers, one ruler each from the chief house of every tribe of Israel; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 1:4</char></note>each one <char style="it">was</char> the head of the house of his father among the divisions of Israel. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then they came to the children of Reuben, to the children of Gad, and to half the tribe of Manasseh, to the land of Gilead, and they spoke with them, saying, <verse number="16" style="v" />“Thus says the whole congregation of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘What <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5–14</char></note>treachery <char style="it">is</char> this that you have committed against the God of Israel, to turn away this day from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, in that you have built for yourselves an altar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 17:8, 9</char></note>that you might rebel this day against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>? <verse number="17" style="v" /><char style="it">Is</char> the iniquity <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 25:1–9; Deut. 4:3</char></note>of Peor not enough for us, from which we are not cleansed till this day, although there was a plague in the congregation of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse number="18" style="v" />but that you must turn away this day from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char>? And it shall be, if you rebel today against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that tomorrow <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 16:22</char></note>He will be angry with the whole congregation of Israel. <verse number="19" style="v" />Nevertheless, if the land of your possession <char style="it">is</char> unclean, <char style="it">then</char> cross over to the land of the possession of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 18:1</char></note>where the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s tabernacle stands, and take possession among us; but do not rebel against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, nor rebel against us, by building yourselves an altar besides the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:1–26</char></note>Did not Achan the son of Zerah commit a trespass in the accursed thing, and wrath fell on all the congregation of Israel? And that man did not perish alone in his iniquity.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />Then the children of Reuben, the children of Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh answered and said to the heads of the divisions of Israel: <verse number="22" style="v" />“The <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:35; 10:17; Is. 44:8; 45:5; 46:9; (1 Cor. 8:5, 6)</char></note>God of gods, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of gods, He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Job 10:7; 23:10; Jer. 12:3; 2 Cor. 11:11, 31)</char></note>knows, and let Israel itself know—if <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> in rebellion, or if in treachery against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, do not save us this day. <verse number="23" style="v" />If we have built ourselves an altar to turn from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, or if to offer on it burnt offerings or grain offerings, or if to offer peace offerings on it, let the <char style="sc">Lord</char> Himself <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 18:19; 1 Sam. 20:16</char></note>require <char style="it">an</char> <char style="it">account.</char> <verse number="24" style="v" />But in fact we have done it for fear, for a reason, saying, ‘In time to come your descendants may speak to our descendants, saying, “What have you to do with the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel? <verse number="25" style="v" />For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has made the Jordan a border between you and us, <char style="it">you</char> children of Reuben and children of Gad. You have no part in the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” So your descendants would make our descendants cease fearing the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ <verse number="26" style="v" />Therefore we said, ‘Let us now prepare to build ourselves an altar, not for burnt offering nor for sacrifice, <verse number="27" style="v" />but <char style="it">that</char> it <char style="it">may</char> <char style="it">be</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 31:48; Josh. 22:34; 24:27</char></note>a witness between you and us and our generations after us, that we may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5, 14</char></note>perform the service of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> before Him with our burnt offerings, with our sacrifices, and with our peace offerings; that your descendants may not say to our descendants in time to come, “You have no part in the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” ’ <verse number="28" style="v" />Therefore we said that it will be, when they say <char style="it">this</char> to us or to our generations in time to come, that we may say, ‘Here is the replica of the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which our fathers made, though not for burnt offerings nor for sacrifices; but it <char style="it">is</char> a witness between you and us.’ <verse number="29" style="v" />Far be it from us that we should rebel against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and turn from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char> this day, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:13, 14</char></note>to build an altar for burnt offerings, for grain offerings, or for sacrifices, besides the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God which <char style="it">is</char> before His tabernacle.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Now when Phinehas the priest and the rulers of the congregation, the heads of the divisions of Israel who <char style="it">were</char> with him, heard the words that the children of Reuben, the children of Gad, and the children of Manasseh spoke, it pleased them. <verse number="31" style="v" />Then Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest said to the children of Reuben, the children of Gad, and the children of Manasseh, “This day we perceive that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:8; Lev. 26:11, 12; 2 Chr. 15:2; Zech. 8:23</char></note>among us, because you have not committed this treachery against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Now you have delivered the children of Israel out of the hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />And Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, and the rulers, returned from the children of Reuben and the children of Gad, from the land of Gilead to the land of Canaan, to the children of Israel, and brought back word to them. <verse number="33" style="v" />So the thing pleased the children of Israel, and the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 29:20; Neh. 8:6; Dan. 2:19; Luke 2:28</char></note>blessed God; they spoke no more of going against them in battle, to destroy the land where the children of Reuben and Gad dwelt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" />The children of Reuben and the children of Gad called the altar, <char style="it">Witness,</char> “For <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">is</char> a witness between us that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> God.”</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Joshua’s Farewell Address</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now it came to pass, a long time after the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:44; 22:4</char></note>had given rest to Israel from all their enemies round about, that Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:1; 24:29</char></note>was old, advanced in age. <verse number="2" style="v" />And Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:28</char></note>called for all Israel, for their elders, for their heads, for their judges, and for their officers, and said to them:</para>
	<para style="p">“I am old, advanced in age. <verse number="3" style="v" />You have seen all that the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 44:3</char></note><char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has done to all these nations because of you, for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:14; Deut. 1:30; Josh. 10:14, 42</char></note><char style="sc">Lord</char> your God <char style="it">is</char> He who has fought for you. <verse number="4" style="v" />See, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 13:2, 6; 18:10</char></note>I have divided to you by lot these nations that remain, to be an inheritance for your tribes, from the Jordan, with all the nations that I have cut off, as far as the Great Sea westward. <verse number="5" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:30; 33:2</char></note>will expel them from before you and drive them out of your sight. So you shall possess their land, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 33:53</char></note>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God promised you. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 1:7</char></note>Therefore be very courageous to keep and to do all that is written in the Book of the Law of Moses, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 5:32</char></note>lest you turn aside from it to the right hand or to the left, <verse number="7" style="v" /><char style="it">and</char> lest you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:33; Deut. 7:2, 3; (Prov. 4:14; Eph. 5:11)</char></note>go among these nations, these who remain among you. You shall not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:13; Ps. 16:4; Jer. 5:7; Hos. 2:17</char></note>make mention of the name of their gods, nor cause <char style="it">anyone</char> to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 6:13; 10:20</char></note>swear <char style="it">by</char> <char style="it">them;</char> you shall not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:5</char></note>serve them nor bow down to them, <verse number="8" style="v" />but you shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 10:20</char></note>hold fast to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, as you have done to this day. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:24; 11:23; Josh. 1:5</char></note>For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has driven out from before you great and strong nations; but <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">for</char> you, no one has been able to stand against you to this day. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:8; Deut. 28:7; Is. 30:17</char></note>One man of you shall chase a thousand, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God <char style="it">is</char> He who fights for you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:14</char></note>as He promised you. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 22:5</char></note>Therefore take careful heed to yourselves, that you love the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. <verse number="12" style="v" />Or else, if indeed you do <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(2 Pet. 2:20, 21)</char></note>go back, and cling to the remnant of these nations—these that remain among you—and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 7:3, 4; Ezra 9:2; Neh. 13:25</char></note>make marriages with them, and go in to them and they to you, <verse number="13" style="v" />know for certain that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:3</char></note>the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will no longer drive out these nations from before you. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:33; 34:12; Deut. 7:16</char></note>But they shall be snares and traps to you, and scourges on your sides and thorns in your eyes, until you perish from this good land which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has given you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />“Behold, this day <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 2:2</char></note>I <char style="it">am</char> going the way of all the earth. And you know in all your hearts and in all your souls that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 21:45; (Luke 21:33)</char></note>not one thing has failed of all the good things which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God spoke concerning you. All have come to pass for you; not one word of them has failed. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:63</char></note>Therefore it shall come to pass, that as all the good things have come upon you which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God promised you, so the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will bring upon you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:14–39; Deut. 28:15–68</char></note>all harmful things, until He has destroyed you from this good land which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has given you. <verse number="16" style="v" />When you have transgressed the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, which He commanded you, and have gone and served other gods, and bowed down to them, then the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:24–28</char></note>anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will burn against you, and you shall perish quickly from the good land which He has given you.”</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Covenant at Shechem</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then Joshua gathered all the tribes of Israel to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:4</char></note>Shechem and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 23:2</char></note>called for the elders of Israel, for their heads, for their judges, and for their officers; and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 10:19</char></note>presented themselves before God. <verse number="2" style="v" />And Joshua said to all the people, “Thus says the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 11:7–32</char></note>‘Your fathers, <char style="it">including</char> Terah, the father of Abraham and the father of Nahor, dwelt on the other side of the River in old times; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:14</char></note>they served other gods. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 12:1; Acts 7:2, 3</char></note>Then I took your father Abraham from the other side of the River, led him throughout all the land of Canaan, and multiplied his descendants and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 21:1–8; (Ps. 127:3)</char></note>gave him Isaac. <verse number="4" style="v" />To Isaac I gave <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 25:24–26</char></note>Jacob and Esau. To <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 36:8; Deut. 2:5</char></note>Esau I gave the mountains of Seir to possess, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 46:1, 3, 6</char></note>but Jacob and his children went down to Egypt. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:10</char></note>Also I sent Moses and Aaron, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 7—10</char></note>I plagued Egypt, according to what I did among them. Afterward I brought you out.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />‘Then I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:37, 51; 14:2–31</char></note>brought your fathers out of Egypt, and you came to the sea; and the Egyptians pursued your fathers with chariots and horsemen to the Red Sea. <verse number="7" style="v" />So they cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and He put <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 14:20</char></note>darkness between you and the Egyptians, brought the sea upon them, and covered them. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:34</char></note>your eyes saw what I did in Egypt. Then you dwelt in the wilderness <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 5:6</char></note>a long time. <verse number="8" style="v" />And I brought you into the land of the Amorites, who dwelt on the other side of the Jordan, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:21–35</char></note>and they fought with you. But I gave them into your hand, that you might possess their land, and I destroyed them from before you. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 11:25</char></note>Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, arose to make war against Israel, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 22:2–14</char></note>sent and called Balaam the son of Beor to curse you. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 23:5</char></note>But I would not listen to Balaam; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 23:11, 20; 24:10</char></note>therefore he continued to bless you. So I delivered you out of his hand. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 3:14, 17</char></note>you went over the Jordan and came to Jericho. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 6:1; 10:1</char></note>the men of Jericho fought against you—<char style="it">also</char> the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Girgashites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites. But I delivered them into your hand. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:28; Deut. 7:20</char></note>I sent the hornet before you which drove them out from before you, <char style="it">also</char> the two kings of the Amorites, <char style="it">but</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 44:3</char></note>not with your sword or with your bow. <verse number="13" style="v" />I have given you a land for which you did not labor, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 6:10, 11</char></note>cities which you did not build, and you dwell in them; you eat of the vineyards and olive groves which you did not plant.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 10:12, 13; 1 Sam. 12:24</char></note>“Now therefore, fear the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, serve Him in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Cor. 1:12</char></note>sincerity and in truth, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:2, 23; Ezek. 20:18</char></note>put away the gods which your fathers served on the other side of the River and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 20:7, 8</char></note>in Egypt. Serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>! <verse number="15" style="v" />And if it seems evil to you to serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ruth 1:15; 1 Kin. 18:21</char></note>choose for yourselves this day whom you will serve, whether <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:2; Ezek. 20:39</char></note>the gods which your fathers served that <char style="it">were</char> on the other side of the River, or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:24, 32</char></note>the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you dwell. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 18:19; Ps. 101:2; (1 Tim. 3:4, 5)</char></note>But as for me and my house, we will serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />So the people answered and said: “Far be it from us that we should forsake the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to serve other gods; <verse number="17" style="v" />for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God <char style="it">is</char> He who brought us and our fathers up out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage, who did those great signs in our sight, and preserved us in all the way that we went and among all the people through whom we passed. <verse number="18" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> drove out from before us all the people, including the Amorites who dwelt in the land. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 116:16</char></note>We also will serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, for He <char style="it">is</char> our God.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />But Joshua said to the people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 6:24</char></note>“You cannot serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, for He <char style="it">is</char> a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:44, 45; 1 Sam. 6:20</char></note>holy God. He <char style="it">is</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:5</char></note>a jealous God; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:21</char></note>He will not forgive your transgressions nor your sins. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Chr. 28:9; Ezra 8:22; Is. 1:28; 63:10; 65:11, 12; Jer. 17:13</char></note>If you forsake the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and serve foreign gods, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:24–26; Josh. 23:15</char></note>then He will turn and do you harm and consume you, after He has done you good.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />And the people said to Joshua, “No, but we will serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />So Joshua said to the people, “You <char style="it">are</char> witnesses against yourselves that <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 119:173</char></note>you have chosen the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for yourselves, to serve Him.”</para>
	<para style="p">And they said, “<char style="it">We</char> <char style="it">are</char> witnesses!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />“Now therefore,” <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">said,</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:2; Josh. 24:14; Judg. 10:15, 16; 1 Sam. 7:3</char></note>“put away the foreign gods which <char style="it">are</char> among you, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:57, 58; Ps. 119:36; 141:4</char></note>incline your heart to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God of Israel.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />And the people <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:8; 24:3, 7; Deut. 5:24–27</char></note>said to Joshua, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God we will serve, and His voice we will obey!”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />So Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 15:25</char></note>made a covenant with the people that day, and made for them a statute and an ordinance <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:1</char></note>in Shechem.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />Then Joshua <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 31:24</char></note>wrote these words in the Book of the Law of God. And he took <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 9:6</char></note>a large stone, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 28:18</char></note>set it up there <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:4</char></note>under the oak that <char style="it">was</char> by the sanctuary of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="27" style="v" />And Joshua said to all the people, “Behold, this stone shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 31:48</char></note>a witness to us, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:1</char></note>it has heard all the words of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He spoke to us. It shall therefore be a witness to you, lest you deny your God.” <verse number="28" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:6, 7</char></note>Joshua let the people depart, each to his own inheritance.</para>
	<para style="s">Death of Joshua and Eleazar</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:8</char></note>Now it came to pass after these things that Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, died, <char style="it">being</char> one hundred and ten years old. <verse number="30" style="v" />And they buried him within the border of his inheritance at <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 19:50; Judg. 2:9</char></note>Timnath Serah, which <char style="it">is</char> in the mountains of Ephraim, on the north side of Mount Gaash.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 2:7</char></note>Israel served the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua, who had <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 11:2</char></note>known all the works of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which He had done for Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 50:25; Ex. 13:19; Heb. 11:22</char></note>The bones of Joseph, which the children of Israel had brought up out of Egypt, they buried at Shechem, in the plot of ground <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 33:19; John 4:5</char></note>which Jacob had bought from the sons of Hamor the father of Shechem for one hundred pieces of silver, and which had become an inheritance of the children of Joseph.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:1; Num. 20:28; Josh. 14:1</char></note>Eleazar the son of Aaron died. They buried him in a hill <char style="it">belonging</char> <char style="it">to</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 6:25</char></note>Phinehas his son, which was given to him in the mountains of Ephraim.</para>
	
</usx>