<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="2.0">
    <book code="LEV" style="id">The Third Book of Moses Called Leviticus</book>
    <para style="mt">The Third Book of Moses Called Leviticus</para>
    <chapter number="1" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Burnt Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:3; 25:22; Num. 7:89</char></note>called to Moses, and spoke to him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:34</char></note>from the tabernacle of meeting, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:18, 19</char></note>‘When any one of you brings an offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, you shall bring your offering of the livestock—of the herd and of the flock.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />‘If his offering <char style="it">is</char> a burnt sacrifice of the herd, let him offer a male <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:5; Lev. 22:20–24; Deut. 15:21; Eph. 5:27; Heb. 9:14; 1 Pet. 1:19</char></note>without blemish; he shall offer it of his own free will at the door of the tabernacle of meeting before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:10, 15, 19; Lev. 3:2, 8, 13; 4:15</char></note>Then he shall put his hand on the head of the burnt offering, and it will be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rom. 12:1); Phil. 4:18</char></note>accepted on his behalf <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:20, 26, 31; 2 Chr. 29:23, 24</char></note>to make atonement for him. <verse number="5" style="v" />He shall kill the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Mic. 6:6</char></note>bull before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:11</char></note>and the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall bring the blood <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:11; 3:2, 8, 13; (Heb. 12:24; 1 Pet. 1:2)</char></note>and sprinkle the blood all around on the altar that <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">by</char> the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:8</char></note>skin the burnt offering and cut it into its pieces. <verse number="7" style="v" />The sons of Aaron the priest shall put <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:8–13; Mal. 1:10</char></note>fire on the altar, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 22:9</char></note>lay the wood in order on the fire. <verse number="8" style="v" />Then the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall lay the parts, the head, and the fat in order on the wood that <char style="it">is</char> on the fire upon the altar; <verse number="9" style="v" />but he shall wash its entrails and its legs with water. And the priest shall burn all on the altar as a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 8:21; (Ezek. 20:28, 41; 2 Cor. 2:15)</char></note>sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />‘If his offering <char style="it">is</char> of the flocks—of the sheep or of the goats—as a burnt sacrifice, he shall bring a male <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:5; Lev. 1:3; Ezek. 43:22; (1 Pet. 1:19)</char></note>without blemish. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 24:6; 40:22; Lev. 1:5; Ezek. 8:5</char></note>He shall kill it on the north side of the altar before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and the priests, Aaron’s sons, shall sprinkle its blood all around on the altar. <verse number="12" style="v" />And he shall cut it into its pieces, with its head and its fat; and the priest shall lay them in order on the wood that <char style="it">is</char> on the fire upon the altar; <verse number="13" style="v" />but he shall wash the entrails and the legs with water. Then the priest shall bring <char style="it">it</char> all and burn <char style="it">it</char> on the altar; it <char style="it">is</char> a burnt sacrifice, an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:4–7; 28:12–14</char></note>offering made by fire, a sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />‘And if the burnt sacrifice of his offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <char style="it">is</char> of birds, then he shall bring his offering of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:9; Lev. 5:7, 11; 12:8; Luke 2:24</char></note>turtledoves or young pigeons. <verse number="15" style="v" />The priest shall bring it to the altar, wring off its head, and burn <char style="it">it</char> on the altar; its blood shall be drained out at the side of the altar. <verse number="16" style="v" />And he shall remove its crop with its feathers and cast it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:10</char></note>beside the altar on the east side, into the place for ashes. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then he shall split it at its wings, <char style="it">but</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 15:10; Lev. 5:8</char></note>shall not divide <char style="it">it</char> completely; and the priest shall burn it on the altar, on the wood that <char style="it">is</char> on the fire. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:9, 13</char></note>It <char style="it">is</char> a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, a sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<chapter number="2" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Grain Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />‘When anyone offers <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:14; 9:17; Num. 15:4</char></note>a grain offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, his offering shall be <char style="it">of</char> fine flour. And he shall pour oil on it, and put <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:11</char></note>frankincense on it. <verse number="2" style="v" />He shall bring it to Aaron’s sons, the priests, one of whom shall take from it his handful of fine flour and oil with all the frankincense. And the priest shall burn <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:9; 5:12; 6:15; 24:7; Acts 10:4</char></note><char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">as</char> a memorial on the altar, an offering made by fire, a sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:9</char></note>The rest of the grain offering <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> Aaron’s and his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:6; 10:12, 13</char></note>sons’. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:37; Num. 18:9</char></note><char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> most holy of the offerings to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made by fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />‘And if you bring as an offering a grain offering baked in the oven, <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> unleavened cakes of fine flour mixed with oil, or unleavened wafers <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:2</char></note>anointed with oil. <verse number="5" style="v" />But if your offering <char style="it">is</char> a grain offering <char style="it">baked</char> in a pan, <char style="it">it</char> <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> <char style="it">of</char> fine flour, unleavened, mixed with oil. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall break it in pieces and pour oil on it; it <char style="it">is</char> a grain offering.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" />‘If your offering <char style="it">is</char> a grain offering <char style="it">baked</char> in a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:9</char></note>covered pan, it shall be made <char style="it">of</char> fine flour with oil. <verse number="8" style="v" />You shall bring the grain offering that is made of these things to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And when it is presented to the priest, he shall bring it to the altar. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then the priest shall take from the grain offering <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:2, 16; 5:12; 6:15</char></note>a memorial portion, and burn <char style="it">it</char> on the altar. <char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:18</char></note>offering made by fire, a sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="10" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:3; 6:16</char></note>what is left of the grain offering <char style="it">shall</char> <char style="it">be</char> Aaron’s and his sons’. <char style="it">It</char> <char style="it">is</char> most holy of the offerings to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made by fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />‘No grain offering which you bring to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> shall be made with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:18; 34:25; Lev. 6:16, 17; (Matt. 16:12; Mark 8:15; Luke 12:1; 1 Cor. 5:8; Gal. 5:9)</char></note>leaven, for you shall burn no leaven nor any honey in any offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made by fire. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:29; 34:22; Lev. 23:10, 11, 17, 18</char></note>As for the offering of the firstfruits, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Mark 9:49, 50; Col. 4:6)</char></note>you shall offer them to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but they shall not be burned on the altar for a sweet aroma. <verse number="13" style="v" />And every offering of your grain offering you shall season with salt; you shall not allow <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:19; 2 Chr. 13:5</char></note>the salt of the covenant of your God to be lacking from your grain offering. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 43:24</char></note>With all your offerings <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:10, 14</char></note>you shall offer salt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />‘If you offer a grain offering of your firstfruits to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, you shall offer for the grain offering of your firstfruits green heads of grain roasted on the fire, grain beaten from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 4:42</char></note>full heads. <verse number="15" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:1</char></note>you shall put oil on it, and lay frankincense on it. It <char style="it">is</char> a grain offering. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then the priest shall burn <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:2</char></note>the memorial portion: <char style="it">part</char> of its beaten grain and <char style="it">part</char> of its oil, with all the frankincense, as an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<chapter number="3" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Peace Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />‘When his offering <char style="it">is</char> a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:11, 29</char></note>sacrifice of a peace offering, if he offers <char style="it">it</char> of the herd, whether male or female, he shall offer it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:3; 22:20–24</char></note>without blemish before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="2" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:10, 11, 16, 20; Lev. 1:4, 5; 16:21</char></note>he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it at the door of the tabernacle of meeting; and Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:5</char></note>sprinkle the blood all around on the altar. <verse number="3" style="v" />Then he shall offer from the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:13, 22; Lev. 1:8; 3:16; 4:8, 9</char></note>The fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails, <verse number="4" style="v" />the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove; <verse number="5" style="v" />and Aaron’s sons <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:13; Lev. 6:12; 7:28–34</char></note>shall burn it on the altar upon the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 35:14</char></note>burnt sacrifice, which is on the wood that is on the fire, as an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 28:3–10</char></note>offering made by fire, a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:8–10</char></note>sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />‘If his offering as a sacrifice of a peace offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is of the flock, whether male or female, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1; 22:20–24</char></note>he shall offer it without blemish. <verse number="7" style="v" />If he offers a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:4, 5</char></note>lamb as his offering, then he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 8:62</char></note>offer it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 17:8, 9</char></note>before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="8" style="v" />And he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it before the tabernacle of meeting; and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle its blood all around on the altar.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />‘Then he shall offer from the sacrifice of the peace offering, as an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, its fat and the whole fat tail which he shall remove close to the backbone. And the fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails, <verse number="10" style="v" />the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove; <verse number="11" style="v" />and the priest shall burn them on the altar as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 21:6, 8, 17, 21, 22; 22:25; Num. 28:2; (Ezek. 44:7; Mal. 1:7, 12)</char></note>food, an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />‘And if his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:6–11</char></note>offering is a goat, then he shall offer it before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />He shall lay his hand on its head and kill it before the tabernacle of meeting; and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle its blood all around on the altar. <verse number="14" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1, 7</char></note>he shall offer from it his offering, as an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. The fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails, <verse number="15" style="v" />the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove; <verse number="16" style="v" />and the priest shall burn them on the altar as food, an offering made by fire for a sweet aroma; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:23–25; 1 Sam. 2:15; 2 Chr. 7:7</char></note>all the fat is the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />‘This shall be a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:18; 7:36; 17:7; 23:14</char></note>perpetual statute throughout your generations in all your dwellings: you shall eat neither fat nor <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:4; Lev. 7:23, 26; 17:10, 14; 1 Sam. 14:33</char></note>blood.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="4" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Sin Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:15–18; Num. 15:22–30; 1 Sam. 14:27; Acts 3:17</char></note>‘If a person sins unintentionally against any of the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in anything which ought not to be done, and does any of them, <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:15; Lev. 8:12</char></note>if the anointed priest sins, bringing guilt on the people, then let him offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for his sin which he has sinned <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1; 9:2</char></note>a young bull without blemish as a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 9:7</char></note>sin offering. <verse number="4" style="v" />He shall bring the bull <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:3, 4; 4:15; Num. 8:12</char></note>to the door of the tabernacle of meeting before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, lay his hand on the bull’s head, and kill the bull before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="5" style="v" />Then the anointed priest shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:14; Num. 19:4</char></note>take some of the bull’s blood and bring it to the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="6" style="v" />The priest shall dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle some of the blood seven times before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, in front of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:21, 26</char></note>veil of the sanctuary. <verse number="7" style="v" />And the priest shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:18, 25, 30, 34; 8:15; 9:9; 16:18</char></note>put some of the blood on the horns of the altar of sweet incense before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which is in the tabernacle of meeting; and he shall pour <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:5, 6; Lev. 5:9</char></note>the remaining blood of the bull at the base of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="8" style="v" />He shall take from it all the fat of the bull as the sin offering. The fat that covers the entrails and all the fat which is on the entrails, <verse number="9" style="v" />the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove, <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:3–5</char></note>as it was taken from the bull of the sacrifice of the peace offering; and the priest shall burn them on the altar of the burnt offering. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:14; Lev. 9:11; Num. 19:5</char></note>But the bull’s hide and all its flesh, with its head and legs, its entrails and offal— <verse number="12" style="v" />the whole bull he shall carry outside the camp to a clean place, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:21; 6:10, 11; 16:27</char></note>where the ashes are poured out, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 13:11, 12)</char></note>burn it on wood with fire; where the ashes are poured out it shall be burned.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />‘Now <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:24–26; Josh. 7:11</char></note>if the whole congregation of Israel sins unintentionally, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:2–4, 17</char></note>and the thing is hidden from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done something against any of the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in anything which should not be done, and are guilty; <verse number="14" style="v" />when the sin which they have committed becomes known, then the assembly shall offer a young bull for the sin, and bring it before the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="15" style="v" />And the elders of the congregation <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:3, 4</char></note>shall lay their hands on the head of the bull before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Then the bull shall be killed before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:5; (Heb. 9:12–14)</char></note>The anointed priest shall bring some of the bull’s blood to the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then the priest shall dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle it seven times before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, in front of the veil. <verse number="18" style="v" />And he shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar which is before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which is in the tabernacle of meeting; and he shall pour the remaining blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="19" style="v" />He shall take all the fat from it and burn it on the altar. <verse number="20" style="v" />And he shall do <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:3</char></note>with the bull as he did with the bull as a sin offering; thus he shall do with it. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:4; Num. 15:25</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for them, and it shall be forgiven them. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then he shall carry the bull outside the camp, and burn it as he burned the first bull. It is a sin offering for the assembly.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />‘When a ruler has sinned, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:2, 13, 27</char></note>done something unintentionally against any of the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God in anything which should not be done, and is guilty, <verse number="23" style="v" />or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:14; 5:4</char></note>if his sin which he has committed comes to his knowledge, he shall bring as his offering a kid of the goats, a male without blemish. <verse number="24" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:4; (Is. 53:6)</char></note>he shall lay his hand on the head of the goat, and kill it at the place where they kill the burnt offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. It is a sin offering. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:7, 18, 30, 34</char></note>The priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and pour its blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering. <verse number="26" style="v" />And he shall burn all its fat on the altar, like <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:3–5</char></note>the fat of the sacrifice of the peace offering. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:20; Num. 15:28</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin, and it shall be forgiven him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:2; Num. 15:27</char></note>‘If anyone of the common people sins unintentionally by doing something against any of the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in anything which ought not to be done, and is guilty, <verse number="28" style="v" />or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:23</char></note>if his sin which he has committed comes to his knowledge, then he shall bring as his offering a kid of the goats, a female without blemish, for his sin which he has committed. <verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:4; 4:4, 24</char></note>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill the sin offering at the place of the burnt offering. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then the priest shall take some of its blood with his finger, put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and pour all the remaining blood at the base of the altar. <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:14</char></note>He shall remove all its fat, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:3, 4</char></note>as fat is removed from the sacrifice of the peace offering; and the priest shall burn it on the altar for a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 8:21; Ex. 29:18; Lev. 1:9, 13; 2:2, 9, 12</char></note>sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:26</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for him, and it shall be forgiven him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" />‘If he brings a lamb as his sin offering, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:28</char></note>he shall bring a female without blemish. <verse number="33" style="v" />Then he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:4; Num. 8:12</char></note>lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill it as a sin offering at the place where they kill the burnt offering. <verse number="34" style="v" />The priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and pour all the remaining blood at the base of the altar. <verse number="35" style="v" />He shall remove all its fat, as the fat of the lamb is removed from the sacrifice of the peace offering. Then the priest shall burn it on the altar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:5</char></note>according to the offerings made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:26, 31</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for his sin that he has committed, and it shall be forgiven him.</para>
	<chapter number="5" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Trespass Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />‘If a person sins in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 29:24; (Jer. 23:10)</char></note>hearing the utterance of an oath, and is a witness, whether he has seen or known of the matter—if he does not tell it, he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:17; 7:18; 17:16; 19:8; 20:17; Num. 9:13</char></note>bears guilt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" />‘Or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:24, 28, 31, 39; Num. 19:11–16; Deut. 14:8</char></note>if a person touches any unclean thing, whether it is the carcass of an unclean beast, or the carcass of unclean livestock, or the carcass of unclean creeping things, and he is unaware of it, he also shall be unclean and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:17</char></note>guilty. <verse number="3" style="v" />Or if he touches <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:12, 13, 15</char></note>human uncleanness—whatever uncleanness with which a man may be defiled, and he is unaware of it—when he realizes it, then he shall be guilty.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />‘Or if a person swears, speaking thoughtlessly with his lips <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 25:22; Acts 23:12</char></note>to do evil or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 5:33–37); Mark 6:23; (James 5:12)</char></note>to do good, whatever it is that a man may pronounce by an oath, and he is unaware of it—when he realizes it, then he shall be guilty in any of these matters.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />‘And it shall be, when he is guilty in any of these matters, that he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:21; 26:40; Num. 5:7; Ezra 10:11, 12; Ps. 32:5; Prov. 28:13</char></note>confess that he has sinned in that thing; <verse number="6" style="v" />and he shall bring his trespass offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for his sin which he has committed, a female from the flock, a lamb or a kid of the goats as a sin offering. So the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 12:6, 8; 14:21</char></note>‘If he is not able to bring a lamb, then he shall bring to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, for his trespass which he has committed, two <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:14</char></note>turtledoves or two young pigeons: one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering. <verse number="8" style="v" />And he shall bring them to the priest, who shall offer that which is for the sin offering first, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:15–17</char></note>wring off its head from its neck, but shall not divide it completely. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then he shall sprinkle some of the blood of the sin offering on the side of the altar, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:7, 18, 30, 34</char></note>rest of the blood shall be drained out at the base of the altar. It is a sin offering. <verse number="10" style="v" />And he shall offer the second as a burnt offering according to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:14–17</char></note>prescribed manner. So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:20, 26; 5:13, 16</char></note>the priest shall make atonement on his behalf for his sin which he has committed, and it shall be forgiven him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />‘But if he is <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:21–32</char></note>not able to bring two turtledoves or two young pigeons, then he who sinned shall bring for his offering one-tenth of an ephah of fine flour as a sin offering. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:1, 2; 6:15; Num. 5:15</char></note>He shall put no oil on it, nor shall he put frankincense on it, for it is a sin offering. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then he shall bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his handful of it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:2</char></note>as a memorial portion, and burn it on the altar <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:35</char></note>according to the offerings made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. It is a sin offering. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:26</char></note>The priest shall make atonement for him, for his sin that he has committed in any of these matters; and it shall be forgiven him. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:3; 6:17, 26</char></note>The rest shall be the priest’s as a grain offering.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Offerings with Restitution</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying: <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:2; 22:14; Num. 5:5–8</char></note>“If a person commits a trespass, and sins unintentionally in regard to the holy things of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 10:19</char></note>he shall bring to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> as his trespass offering a ram without blemish from the flocks, with your valuation in shekels of silver according to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:13; Lev. 27:25</char></note>the shekel of the sanctuary, as a trespass offering. <verse number="16" style="v" />And he shall make restitution for the harm that he has done in regard to the holy thing, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:5; 22:14; 27:13, 15, 27, 31; Num. 5:7</char></note>and shall add one-fifth to it and give it to the priest. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:26</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering, and it shall be forgiven him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />“If a person sins, and commits any of these things which are forbidden to be done by the commandments of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:2, 13, 22, 27</char></note>though he does not know it, yet he is <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:1, 2</char></note>guilty and shall bear his iniquity. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:15</char></note>And he shall bring to the priest a ram without blemish from the flock, with your valuation, as a trespass offering. So the priest shall make atonement for him regarding his ignorance in which he erred and did not know it, and it shall be forgiven him. <verse number="19" style="v" />It is a trespass offering; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 10:2</char></note>he has certainly trespassed against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<chapter number="6" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" />“If a person sins and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 5:6</char></note>commits a trespass against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:11; Acts 5:4; Col. 3:9</char></note>lying to his neighbor about <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:7, 10</char></note>what was delivered to him for safekeeping, or about a pledge, or about a robbery, or if he has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 24:28</char></note>extorted from his neighbor, <verse number="3" style="v" />or if he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:4; Deut. 22:1–4</char></note>has found what was lost and lies concerning it, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:11; Lev. 19:12; Jer. 7:9; Zech. 5:4</char></note>swears falsely—in any one of these things that a man may do in which he sins: <verse number="4" style="v" />then it shall be, because he has sinned and is guilty, that he shall restore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 24:18, 21</char></note>what he has stolen, or the thing which he has extorted, or what was delivered to him for safekeeping, or the lost thing which he found, <verse number="5" style="v" />or all that about which he has sworn falsely. He shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:16; Num. 5:7, 8; 2 Sam. 12:6</char></note>restore its full value, add one-fifth more to it, and give it to whomever it belongs, on the day of his trespass offering. <verse number="6" style="v" />And he shall bring his trespass offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:3; 5:15</char></note>a ram without blemish from the flock, with your valuation, as a trespass offering, to the priest. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:26</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for him before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and he shall be forgiven for any one of these things that he may have done in which he trespasses.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Law of the Burnt Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="9" style="v" />“Command Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘This is the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:38–42; Num. 28:3–10</char></note>law of the burnt offering: The burnt offering shall be on the hearth upon the altar all night until morning, and the fire of the altar shall be kept burning on it. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:39–43; Lev. 16:4; Ezek. 44:17, 18</char></note>And the priest shall put on his linen garment, and his linen trousers he shall put on his body, and take up the ashes of the burnt offering which the fire has consumed on the altar, and he shall put them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:16</char></note>beside the altar. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 44:19</char></note>he shall take off his garments, put on other garments, and carry the ashes outside the camp <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:12</char></note>to a clean place. <verse number="12" style="v" />And the fire on the altar shall be kept burning on it; it shall not be put out. And the priest shall burn wood on it every morning, and lay the burnt offering in order on it; and he shall burn on it the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:3, 5, 9, 14</char></note>fat of the peace offerings. <verse number="13" style="v" />A fire shall always be burning on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:7</char></note>altar; it shall never go out.</para>
	<para style="s">The Law of the Grain Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />‘This is the law of the grain offering: The sons of Aaron shall offer it on the altar before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="15" style="v" />He shall take from it his handful of the fine flour of the grain offering, with its oil, and all the frankincense which is on the grain offering, and shall burn it on the altar for a sweet aroma, as a memorial to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="16" style="v" />And the remainder of it Aaron and his sons shall eat; with unleavened bread it shall be eaten in a holy place; in the court of the tabernacle of meeting they shall eat it. <verse number="17" style="v" />It shall not be baked with leaven. I have given it as their portion of My offerings made by fire; it is most holy, like the sin offering and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:7</char></note>trespass offering. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:29; 7:6; Num. 18:10; 1 Cor. 9:13</char></note>All the males among the children of Aaron may eat it. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:17</char></note>It shall be a statute forever in your generations concerning the offerings made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:37; Lev. 22:3–7; Num. 4:15; Hag. 2:11–13</char></note>Everyone who touches them must be holy.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:2</char></note>“This is the offering of Aaron and his sons, which they shall offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, beginning on the day when he is anointed: one-tenth of an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 16:36</char></note>ephah of fine flour as a daily grain offering, half of it in the morning and half of it at night. <verse number="21" style="v" />It shall be made in a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:5; 7:9</char></note>pan with oil. When it is mixed, you shall bring it in. The baked pieces of the grain offering you shall offer for a sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="22" style="v" />The priest from among his sons, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:3</char></note>who is anointed in his place, shall offer it. It is a statute forever to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:25</char></note>It shall be wholly burned. <verse number="23" style="v" />For every grain offering for the priest shall be wholly burned. It shall not be eaten.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Law of the Sin Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />Also the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="25" style="v" />“Speak to Aaron and to his sons, saying, ‘This is the law of the sin offering: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:1, 3, 5, 11</char></note>In the place where the burnt offering is killed, the sin offering shall be killed before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. It is most holy. <verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Lev. 10:17, 18); Num. 18:9, 10; (Ezek. 44:28, 29)</char></note>The priest who offers it for sin shall eat it. In a holy place it shall be eaten, in the court of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:37; Num. 4:15; Hag. 2:11–13</char></note>Everyone who touches its flesh must be holy. And when its blood is sprinkled on any garment, you shall wash that on which it was sprinkled, in a holy place. <verse number="28" style="v" />But the earthen vessel in which it is boiled <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:33; 15:12</char></note>shall be broken. And if it is boiled in a bronze pot, it shall be both scoured and rinsed in water. <verse number="29" style="v" />All the males among the priests may eat it. It is most holy. <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:7, 11, 12, 18, 21; 10:18; 16:27; (Heb. 13:11, 12)</char></note>But no sin offering from which any of the blood is brought into the tabernacle of meeting, to make atonement in the holy <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 26:33</char></note>place, shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:16, 23, 26</char></note>eaten. It shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:27</char></note>burned in the fire.</para>
	<chapter number="7" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Law of the Trespass Offering</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />‘Likewise <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:14—6:7</char></note>this is the law of the trespass offering (it is most holy): <verse number="2" style="v" />In the place where they kill the burnt offering they shall kill the trespass offering. And its blood he shall sprinkle all around on the altar. <verse number="3" style="v" />And he shall offer from it all its fat. The fat tail and the fat that covers the entrails, <verse number="4" style="v" />the two kidneys and the fat that is on them by the flanks, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver above the kidneys, he shall remove; <verse number="5" style="v" />and the priest shall burn them on the altar as an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. It is a trespass offering. <verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:16–18, 29; Num. 18:9</char></note>Every male among the priests may eat it. It shall be eaten in a holy place. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:3</char></note>It is most holy. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:24–30; 14:13</char></note>The trespass offering is like the sin offering; there is one law for them both: the priest who makes atonement with it shall have it. <verse number="8" style="v" />And the priest who offers anyone’s burnt offering, that priest shall have for himself the skin of the burnt offering which he has offered. <verse number="9" style="v" />Also <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:3, 10; Num. 18:9; Ezek. 44:29</char></note>every grain offering that is baked in the oven and all that is prepared in the covered pan, or in a pan, shall be the priest’s who offers it. <verse number="10" style="v" />Every grain offering, whether mixed with oil or dry, shall belong to all the sons of Aaron, to one as much as the other.</para>
	<para style="s">The Law of Peace Offerings</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1; 22:18, 21; Ezek. 45:15</char></note>‘This is the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings which he shall offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <verse number="12" style="v" />If he offers it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer, with the sacrifice of thanksgiving, unleavened cakes mixed with oil, unleavened wafers <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:4; Num. 6:15</char></note>anointed with oil, or cakes of blended flour mixed with oil. <verse number="13" style="v" />Besides the cakes, as his offering he shall offer <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:12; 23:17, 18; Amos 4:5</char></note>leavened bread with the sacrifice of thanksgiving of his peace offering. <verse number="14" style="v" />And from it he shall offer one cake from each offering as a heave offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:8, 11, 19</char></note>It shall belong to the priest who sprinkles the blood of the peace offering.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:29, 30</char></note>‘The flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offering for thanksgiving shall be eaten the same day it is offered. He shall not leave any of it until morning. <verse number="16" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:5–8</char></note>if the sacrifice of his offering is a vow or a voluntary offering, it shall be eaten the same day that he offers his sacrifice; but on the next day the remainder of it also may be eaten; <verse number="17" style="v" />the remainder of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day must be burned with fire. <verse number="18" style="v" />And if any of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offering is eaten at all on the third day, it shall not be accepted, nor shall it be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:27</char></note>imputed to him; it shall be an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:10, 11, 41; 19:7; (Prov. 15:8)</char></note>abomination to him who offers it, and the person who eats of it shall bear guilt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />‘The flesh that touches any unclean thing shall not be eaten. It shall be burned with fire. And as for the clean flesh, all who are clean may eat of it. <verse number="20" style="v" />But the person who eats the flesh of the sacrifice of the peace offering that belongs to the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 2:17)</char></note><char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:3; 15:3; 22:3–7; Num. 19:13; (1 Cor. 11:28)</char></note>while he is unclean, that person <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:14; Ex. 31:14</char></note>shall be cut off from his people. <verse number="21" style="v" />Moreover the person who touches any unclean thing, such as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:2, 3, 5</char></note>human uncleanness, an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:24, 28</char></note>unclean animal, or any <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 4:14</char></note>abominable unclean thing, and who eats the flesh of the sacrifice of the peace offering that belongs to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that person <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:20</char></note>shall be cut off from his people.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Fat and Blood May Not Be Eaten</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="23" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:17; 17:10–15; Deut. 14:21; Ezek. 4:14; 44:31</char></note>‘You shall not eat any fat, of ox or sheep or goat. <verse number="24" style="v" />And the fat of an animal that dies naturally, and the fat of what is torn by wild beasts, may be used in any other way; but you shall by no means eat it. <verse number="25" style="v" />For whoever eats the fat of the animal of which men offer an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the person who eats it shall be cut off from his people. <verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:4; Lev. 3:17; 17:10–16; 19:26; Deut. 12:23; 1 Sam. 14:33; Ezek. 33:25; Acts 15:20, 29</char></note>Moreover you shall not eat any blood in any of your dwellings, whether of bird or beast. <verse number="27" style="v" />Whoever eats any blood, that person shall be cut off from his people.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">The Portion of Aaron and His Sons</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="29" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1; 22:21; Ezek. 45:15</char></note>‘He who offers the sacrifice of his peace offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> shall bring his offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> from the sacrifice of his peace offering. <verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:3, 4, 9, 14</char></note>His own hands shall bring the offerings made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. The fat with the breast he shall bring, that the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:24, 27; Lev. 8:27; 9:21; Num. 6:20</char></note>breast may be waved as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:5, 11, 16</char></note>And the priest shall burn the fat on the altar, but the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:11; Deut. 18:3</char></note>breast shall be Aaron’s and his sons’. <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:27; Lev. 7:34; 9:21; Num. 6:20</char></note>Also the right thigh you shall give to the priest as a heave offering from the sacrifices of your peace offerings. <verse number="33" style="v" />He among the sons of Aaron, who offers the blood of the peace offering and the fat, shall have the right thigh for his part. <verse number="34" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:28; Lev. 10:14, 15; Num. 18:18, 19; Deut. 18:3</char></note>the breast of the wave offering and the thigh of the heave offering I have taken from the children of Israel, from the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and I have given them to Aaron the priest and to his sons from the children of Israel by a statute forever.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />This is the consecrated portion for Aaron and his sons, from the offerings made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, on the day when Moses presented them to minister to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> as priests. <verse number="36" style="v" />The <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded this to be given to them by the children of Israel, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 40:13–15; Lev. 8:12, 30</char></note>on the day that He anointed them, by a statute forever throughout their generations.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" />This is the law <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:9</char></note>of the burnt offering, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:14</char></note>the grain offering, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:25</char></note>the sin offering, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:1</char></note>the trespass offering, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:1; Lev. 6:20</char></note>the consecrations, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:11</char></note>the sacrifice of the peace offering, <verse number="38" style="v" />which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded Moses on Mount Sinai, on the day when He commanded the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:1, 2; Deut. 4:5</char></note>to offer their offerings to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in the Wilderness of Sinai.</para>
	<chapter number="8" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Aaron and His Sons Consecrated</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:1–3</char></note>“Take Aaron and his sons with him, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:2, 4</char></note>the garments, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:24, 25</char></note>the anointing oil, a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:10</char></note>bull as the sin offering, two <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:15, 19</char></note>rams, and a basket of unleavened bread; <verse number="3" style="v" />and gather all the congregation together at the door of the tabernacle of meeting.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />So Moses did as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded him. And the congregation was gathered together at the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="5" style="v" />And Moses said to the congregation, “This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded to be done.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />Then Moses brought Aaron and his sons and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:20; Heb. 10:22</char></note>washed them with water. <verse number="7" style="v" />And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 39:1–31</char></note>put the tunic on him, girded him with the sash, clothed him with the robe, and put the ephod on him; and he girded him with the intricately woven band of the ephod, and with it tied the ephod on him. <verse number="8" style="v" />Then he put the breastplate on him, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:30; Num. 27:21; Deut. 33:8; 1 Sam. 28:6; Ezra 2:63; Neh. 7:65</char></note>put the Urim and the Thummim in the breastplate. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:36, 37; 29:6</char></note>And he put the turban on his head. Also on the turban, on its front, he put the golden plate, the holy crown, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:26–29; 40:10, 11; Lev. 8:2</char></note>Also Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was in it, and consecrated them. <verse number="11" style="v" />He sprinkled some of it on the altar seven times, anointed the altar and all its utensils, and the laver and its base, to consecrate them. <verse number="12" style="v" />And he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:7; 30:30; Lev. 21:10, 12; Ps. 133:2</char></note>poured some of the anointing oil on Aaron’s head and anointed him, to consecrate him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:8, 9</char></note>Then Moses brought Aaron’s sons and put tunics on them, girded them with sashes, and put hats on them, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:10; Ps. 66:15; Ezek. 43:19</char></note>And he brought the bull for the sin offering. Then Aaron and his sons <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:4</char></note>laid their hands on the head of the bull for the sin offering, <verse number="15" style="v" />and Moses killed it. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:12, 36; Lev. 4:7; Ezek. 43:20, 26; (Heb. 9:22)</char></note>Then he took the blood, and put some on the horns of the altar all around with his finger, and purified the altar. And he poured the blood at the base of the altar, and consecrated it, to make atonement for it. <verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:13; Lev. 4:8</char></note>Then he took all the fat that was on the entrails, the fatty lobe attached to the liver, and the two kidneys with their fat, and Moses burned them on the altar. <verse number="17" style="v" />But the bull, its hide, its flesh, and its offal, he burned with fire outside the camp, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:14; Lev. 4:11, 12</char></note>had commanded Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:15</char></note>Then he brought the ram as the burnt offering. And Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram, <verse number="19" style="v" />and Moses killed it. Then he sprinkled the blood all around on the altar. <verse number="20" style="v" />And he cut the ram into pieces; and Moses <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:8</char></note>burned the head, the pieces, and the fat. <verse number="21" style="v" />Then he washed the entrails and the legs in water. And Moses burned the whole ram on the altar. It was a burnt sacrifice for a sweet aroma, an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:18</char></note>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:19, 31; Lev. 8:2</char></note>he brought the second ram, the ram of consecration. Then Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram, <verse number="23" style="v" />and Moses killed it. Also he took some of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:20, 21; Lev. 14:14</char></note>its blood and put it on the tip of Aaron’s right ear, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot. <verse number="24" style="v" />Then he brought Aaron’s sons. And Moses put some of the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 9:13, 14, 18–23)</char></note>blood on the tips of their right ears, on the thumbs of their right hands, and on the big toes of their right feet. And Moses sprinkled the blood all around on the altar. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:22</char></note>Then he took the fat and the fat tail, all the fat that was on the entrails, the fatty lobe attached to the liver, the two kidneys and their fat, and the right thigh; <verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:23</char></note>and from the basket of unleavened bread that was before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> he took one unleavened cake, a cake of bread anointed with oil, and one wafer, and put them on the fat and on the right thigh; <verse number="27" style="v" />and he put all these <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:24; Lev. 7:30, 34</char></note>in Aaron’s hands and in his sons’ hands, and waved them as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="28" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:25</char></note>Then Moses took them from their hands and burned them on the altar, on the burnt offering. They were consecration offerings for a sweet aroma. That was an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="29" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 99:6</char></note>Moses took the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:27</char></note>breast and waved it as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. It was Moses’ <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:26</char></note>part of the ram of consecration, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:21; 30:30; Num. 3:3</char></note>Moses took some of the anointing oil and some of the blood which was on the altar, and sprinkled it on Aaron, on his garments, on his sons, and on the garments of his sons with him; and he consecrated Aaron, his garments, his sons, and the garments of his sons with him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />And Moses said to Aaron and his sons, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:31, 32</char></note>“Boil the flesh at the door of the tabernacle of meeting, and eat it there with the bread that is in the basket of consecration offerings, as I commanded, saying, ‘Aaron and his sons shall eat it.’ <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:34</char></note>What remains of the flesh and of the bread you shall burn with fire. <verse number="33" style="v" />And you shall not go outside the door of the tabernacle of meeting for seven days, until the days of your consecration are ended. For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:30, 35; Lev. 10:7; Ezek. 43:25, 26</char></note>seven days he shall consecrate you. <verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 7:16)</char></note>As he has done this day, so the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has commanded to do, to make atonement for you. <verse number="35" style="v" />Therefore you shall stay at the door of the tabernacle of meeting day and night for seven days, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 1:53; 3:7; 9:19; Deut. 11:1; 1 Kin. 2:3; Ezek. 48:11</char></note>keep the charge of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, so that you may not die; for so I have been commanded.” <verse number="36" style="v" />So Aaron and his sons did all the things that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded by the hand of Moses.</para>
	<chapter number="9" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Priestly Ministry Begins</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />It came to pass on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 43:27</char></note>eighth day that Moses called Aaron and his sons and the elders of Israel. <verse number="2" style="v" />And he said to Aaron, “Take for yourself a young <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:21; Lev. 4:1–12</char></note>bull as a sin offering and a ram as a burnt offering, without blemish, and offer them before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="3" style="v" />And to the children of Israel you shall speak, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:23, 28; Ezra 6:17; 10:19</char></note>‘Take a kid of the goats as a sin offering, and a calf and a lamb, both of the first year, without blemish, as a burnt offering, <verse number="4" style="v" />also a bull and a ram as peace offerings, to sacrifice before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:4</char></note>a grain offering mixed with oil; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:43; Lev. 9:6, 23</char></note>today the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will appear to you.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />So they brought what Moses commanded before the tabernacle of meeting. And all the congregation drew near and stood before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then Moses said, “This is the thing which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded you to do, and the glory of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will appear to you.” <verse number="7" style="v" />And Moses said to Aaron, “Go to the altar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:3; 1 Sam. 3:14; (Heb. 5:3–5; 7:27)</char></note>offer your sin offering and your burnt offering, and make atonement for yourself and for the people. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:16, 20; Heb. 5:1</char></note>Offer the offering of the people, and make atonement for them, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Aaron therefore went to the altar and killed the calf of the sin offering, which was for himself. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then the sons of Aaron brought the blood to him. And he dipped his finger in the blood, put it on the horns of the altar, and poured the blood at the base of the altar. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:18; Lev. 8:16</char></note>But the fat, the kidneys, and the fatty lobe from the liver of the sin offering he burned on the altar, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses. <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:11, 12; 8:17</char></note>The flesh and the hide he burned with fire outside the camp.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And he killed the burnt offering; and Aaron’s sons presented to him the blood, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:5; 8:19</char></note>which he sprinkled all around on the altar. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:20</char></note>Then they presented the burnt offering to him, with its pieces and head, and he burned them on the altar. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:21</char></note>And he washed the entrails and the legs, and burned them with the burnt offering on the altar.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 53:10; Heb. 2:17; 5:3)</char></note>Then he brought the people’s offering, and took the goat, which was the sin offering for the people, and killed it and offered it for sin, like the first one. <verse number="16" style="v" />And he brought the burnt offering and offered it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:1–13</char></note>according to the prescribed manner. <verse number="17" style="v" />Then he brought the grain offering, took a handful of it, and burned it on the altar, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:38, 39</char></note>besides the burnt sacrifice of the morning.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />He also killed the bull and the ram as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1–11</char></note>sacrifices of peace offerings, which were for the people. And Aaron’s sons presented to him the blood, which he sprinkled all around on the altar, <verse number="19" style="v" />and the fat from the bull and the ram—the fatty tail, what covers the entrails and the kidneys, and the fatty lobe attached to the liver; <verse number="20" style="v" />and they put the fat on the breasts. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:5, 16</char></note>Then he burned the fat on the altar; <verse number="21" style="v" />but the breasts and the right thigh Aaron waved <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:24, 26, 27; Lev. 7:30–34</char></note>as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as Moses had commanded.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />Then Aaron lifted his hand toward the people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:22–26; Deut. 21:5; Luke 24:50</char></note>blessed them, and came down from offering the sin offering, the burnt offering, and peace offerings. <verse number="23" style="v" />And Moses and Aaron went into the tabernacle of meeting, and came out and blessed the people. Then the glory of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared to all the people, <verse number="24" style="v" />and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 4:4; Judg. 6:21; 2 Chr. 7:1; Ps. 20:3</char></note>fire came out from before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and consumed the burnt offering and the fat on the altar. When all the people saw it, they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezra 3:11</char></note>shouted and fell on their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:38, 39</char></note>faces.</para>
	<chapter number="10" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Profane Fire of Nadab and Abihu</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 24:1, 9; Num. 3:2–4; 1 Chr. 24:2</char></note>Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:12</char></note>each took his censer and put fire in it, put incense on it, and offered <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:9; 1 Sam. 2:17</char></note>profane fire before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which He had not commanded them. <verse number="2" style="v" />So <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 19:24; Num. 11:1; 16:35; Rev. 20:9</char></note>fire went out from the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and devoured them, and they died before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="3" style="v" />And Moses said to Aaron, “This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke, saying:</para>
	<para style="q1">‘By those <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:22; Lev. 21:6; Is. 52:11; Ezek. 20:41</char></note>who come near Me</para>
	<para style="q2">I must be regarded as holy;</para>
	<para style="q2">And before all the people</para>
	<para style="q2">I must be glorified.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p">So Aaron held his peace.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />Then Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said to them, “Come near, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 5:6, 10</char></note>carry your brethren from before the sanctuary out of the camp.” <verse number="5" style="v" />So they went near and carried them by their tunics out of the camp, as Moses had said.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />And Moses said to Aaron, and to Eleazar and Ithamar, his sons, “Do not uncover your heads nor tear your clothes, lest you die, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 1:53; 16:22, 46; 18:5; Josh. 7:1; 22:18, 20; 2 Sam. 24:1</char></note>wrath come upon all the people. But let your brethren, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has kindled. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:33; 21:12</char></note>You shall not go out from the door of the tabernacle of meeting, lest you die, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:30</char></note>for the anointing oil of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is upon you.” And they did according to the word of Moses.</para>
	<para style="s">Conduct Prescribed for Priests</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Aaron, saying: <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:21; (Prov. 20:1; 31:5); Is. 28:7; Ezek. 44:21; Hos. 4:11; Luke 1:15; (Eph. 5:18); 1 Tim. 3:3; Titus 1:7</char></note>“Do not drink wine or intoxicating drink, you, nor your sons with you, when you go into the tabernacle of meeting, lest you die. It shall be a statute forever throughout your generations, <verse number="10" style="v" />that you may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:47; 20:25; Ezek. 22:26; 44:23</char></note>distinguish between holy and unholy, and between unclean and clean, <verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 24:8; Neh. 8:2, 8; Jer. 18:18; Mal. 2:7</char></note>and that you may teach the children of Israel all the statutes which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has spoken to them by the hand of Moses.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />And Moses spoke to Aaron, and to Eleazar and Ithamar, his sons who were left: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:9</char></note>“Take the grain offering that remains of the offerings made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and eat it without leaven beside the altar; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 21:22</char></note>for it is most holy. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall eat it in a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:10</char></note>holy place, because it is your due and your sons’ due, of the sacrifices made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:3; 6:16</char></note>so I have been commanded. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:24, 26, 27; Lev. 7:30–34; Num. 18:11</char></note>The breast of the wave offering and the thigh of the heave offering you shall eat in a clean place, you, your sons, and your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:13</char></note>daughters with you; for they are your due and your sons’ <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:10</char></note>due, which are given from the sacrifices of peace offerings of the children of Israel. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:29, 30, 34</char></note>The thigh of the heave offering and the breast of the wave offering they shall bring with the offerings of fat made by fire, to offer as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And it shall be yours and your sons’ with you, by a statute forever, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has commanded.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />Then Moses made careful inquiry about <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 9:3, 15</char></note>the goat of the sin offering, and there it was—burned up. And he was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, the sons of Aaron who were left, saying, <verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:24–30</char></note>“Why have you not eaten the sin offering in a holy place, since it is most holy, and God has given it to you to bear <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:38; Lev. 22:16; Num. 18:1</char></note>the guilt of the congregation, to make atonement for them before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>? <verse number="18" style="v" />See! <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:30</char></note>Its blood was not brought inside the holy place; indeed you should have eaten it in a holy place, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:26, 30</char></note>as I commanded.”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />And Aaron said to Moses, “Look, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 9:8, 12</char></note>this day they have offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and such things have befallen me! If I had eaten the sin offering today, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 1:11–15); Jer. 6:20; 14:12; Hos. 9:4; (Mal. 1:10, 13; 3:1–4)</char></note>would it have been accepted in the sight of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?” <verse number="20" style="v" />So when Moses heard that, he was content.</para>
	<chapter number="11" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Foods Permitted and Forbidden</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying to them, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 14:4; Ezek. 4:14; Dan. 1:8; (Matt. 15:11); Acts 10:12, 14; (Rom. 14:14; Heb. 9:10; 13:9)</char></note>‘These are the animals which you may eat among all the animals that are on the earth: <verse number="3" style="v" />Among the animals, whatever divides the hoof, having cloven hooves and chewing the cud—that you may eat. <verse number="4" style="v" />Nevertheless these you shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 10:14</char></note>not eat among those that chew the cud or those that have cloven hooves: the camel, because it chews the cud but does not have cloven hooves, is unclean to you; <verse number="5" style="v" />the rock hyrax, because it chews the cud but does not have cloven hooves, is unclean to you; <verse number="6" style="v" />the hare, because it chews the cud but does not have cloven hooves, is unclean to you; <verse number="7" style="v" />and the swine, though it divides the hoof, having cloven hooves, yet does not chew the cud, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 65:4; 66:3, 17; Mark 5:1–17</char></note>is unclean to you. <verse number="8" style="v" />Their flesh you shall not eat, and their carcasses you shall not touch. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 52:11; (Mark 7:2, 15, 18); Acts 10:14, 15; 15:29</char></note>They are unclean to you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 14:9</char></note>‘These you may eat of all that are in the water: whatever in the water has fins and scales, whether in the seas or in the rivers—that you may eat. <verse number="10" style="v" />But all in the seas or in the rivers that do not have fins and scales, all that move in the water or any living thing which is in the water, they are an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:18, 21; Deut. 14:3</char></note>abomination to you. <verse number="11" style="v" />They shall be an abomination to you; you shall not eat their flesh, but you shall regard their carcasses as an abomination. <verse number="12" style="v" />Whatever in the water does not have fins or scales—that shall be an abomination to you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 14:12–19; Is. 66:17</char></note>‘And these you shall regard as an abomination among the birds; they shall not be eaten, they are an abomination: the eagle, the vulture, the buzzard, <verse number="14" style="v" />the kite, and the falcon after its kind; <verse number="15" style="v" />every raven after its kind, <verse number="16" style="v" />the ostrich, the short-eared owl, the sea gull, and the hawk after its kind; <verse number="17" style="v" />the little owl, the fisher owl, and the screech owl; <verse number="18" style="v" />the white owl, the jackdaw, and the carrion vulture; <verse number="19" style="v" />the stork, the heron after its kind, the hoopoe, and the bat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />‘All flying insects that creep on all fours shall be an abomination to you. <verse number="21" style="v" />Yet these you may eat of every flying insect that creeps on all fours: those which have jointed legs above their feet with which to leap on the earth. <verse number="22" style="v" />These you may eat: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 3:4; Mark 1:6</char></note>the locust after its kind, the destroying locust after its kind, the cricket after its kind, and the grasshopper after its kind. <verse number="23" style="v" />But all other flying insects which have four feet shall be an abomination to you.</para>
	<para style="s">Unclean Animals</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />‘By these you shall become unclean; whoever touches the carcass of any of them shall be unclean until evening; <verse number="25" style="v" />whoever carries part of the carcass of any of them <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:8; 15:5; Num. 19:10, 21, 22; 31:24; Zech. 13:1; (Heb. 9:10; 10:22; Rev. 7:14)</char></note>shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening: <verse number="26" style="v" />The carcass of any animal which divides the foot, but is not cloven-hoofed or does not chew the cud, is unclean to you. Everyone who touches it shall be unclean. <verse number="27" style="v" />And whatever goes on its paws, among all kinds of animals that go on all fours, those are unclean to you. Whoever touches any such carcass shall be unclean until evening. <verse number="28" style="v" />Whoever carries any such carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening. It is unclean to you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />‘These also shall be unclean to you among the creeping things that creep on the earth: the mole, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 66:17</char></note>the mouse, and the large lizard after its kind; <verse number="30" style="v" />the gecko, the monitor lizard, the sand reptile, the sand lizard, and the chameleon. <verse number="31" style="v" />These are unclean to you among all that creep. Whoever <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Hag. 2:13</char></note>touches them when they are dead shall be unclean until evening. <verse number="32" style="v" />Anything on which any of them falls, when they are dead shall be unclean, whether it is any item of wood or clothing or skin or sack, whatever item it is, in which any work is done, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:12</char></note>it must be put in water. And it shall be unclean until evening; then it shall be clean. <verse number="33" style="v" />Any <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:28</char></note>earthen vessel into which any of them falls <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:12; Ps. 2:9; Jer. 48:38; (2 Tim. 2:21); Rev. 2:27</char></note>you shall break; and whatever is in it shall be unclean: <verse number="34" style="v" />in such a vessel, any edible food upon which water falls becomes unclean, and any drink that may be drunk from it becomes unclean. <verse number="35" style="v" />And everything on which a part of any such carcass falls shall be unclean; whether it is an oven or cooking stove, it shall be broken down; for they are unclean, and shall be unclean to you. <verse number="36" style="v" />Nevertheless a spring or a cistern, in which there is plenty of water, shall be clean, but whatever touches any such carcass becomes unclean. <verse number="37" style="v" />And if a part of any such carcass falls on any planting seed which is to be sown, it remains clean. <verse number="38" style="v" />But if water is put on the seed, and if a part of any such carcass falls on it, it becomes unclean to you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />‘And if any animal which you may eat dies, he who touches its carcass shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Hag. 2:11–13</char></note>unclean until evening. <verse number="40" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:31; Lev. 17:15; 22:8; Deut. 14:21; Ezek. 4:14; 44:31</char></note>He who eats of its carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening. He also who carries its carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until evening.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" />‘And every creeping thing that creeps on the earth shall be an abomination. It shall not be eaten. <verse number="42" style="v" />Whatever crawls on its belly, whatever goes on all fours, or whatever has many feet among all creeping things that creep on the earth—these you shall not eat, for they are an abomination. <verse number="43" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:25</char></note>You shall not make yourselves abominable with any creeping thing that creeps; nor shall you make yourselves unclean with them, lest you be defiled by them. <verse number="44" style="v" />For I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 6:7; Lev. 22:33; 25:38; 26:45</char></note>God. You shall therefore consecrate yourselves, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:6; Lev. 19:2; 20:7, 26; (Amos 3:3); Matt. 5:48; 1 Thess. 4:7; 1 Pet. 1:15, 16; (Rev. 22:11, 14)</char></note>you shall be holy; for I am holy. Neither shall you defile yourselves with any creeping thing that creeps on the earth. <verse number="45" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 6:7; 20:2; Lev. 22:33; 25:38; 26:45; Ps. 105:43–45; Hos. 11:1</char></note>For I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> who brings you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:44</char></note>You shall therefore be holy, for I am holy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" />‘This is the law of the animals and the birds and every living creature that moves in the waters, and of every creature that creeps on the earth, <verse number="47" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:10; Ezek. 44:23; Mal. 3:18</char></note>to distinguish between the unclean and the clean, and between the animal that may be eaten and the animal that may not be eaten.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="12" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Ritual After Childbirth</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying: ‘If a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:19; (Job 14:4; Ps. 51:5)</char></note>woman has conceived, and borne a male child, then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:30; Lev. 8:33; 13:4; Luke 2:22</char></note>she shall be unclean seven days; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:19</char></note>as in the days of her customary impurity she shall be unclean. <verse number="3" style="v" />And on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:12; Luke 1:59; 2:21; John 7:22, 23; Gal. 5:3</char></note>eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised. <verse number="4" style="v" />She shall then continue in the blood of her purification thirty-three days. She shall not touch any hallowed thing, nor come into the sanctuary until the days of her purification are fulfilled.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />‘But if she bears a female child, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her customary impurity, and she shall continue in the blood of her purification sixty-six days.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Luke 2:22</char></note>‘When the days of her purification are fulfilled, whether for a son or a daughter, she shall bring to the priest a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(John 1:29; 1 Pet. 1:18, 19)</char></note>lamb of the first year as a burnt offering, and a young pigeon or a turtledove as a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:7</char></note>sin offering, to the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="7" style="v" />Then he shall offer it before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and make atonement for her. And she shall be clean from the flow of her blood. This is the law for her who has borne a male or a female.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:7; Luke 2:22–24</char></note>‘And if she is not able to bring a lamb, then she may bring two turtledoves or two young pigeons—one as a burnt offering and the other as a sin offering. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:26</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for her, and she will be clean.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="13" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Law Concerning Leprosy</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" />“When a man has on the skin of his body a swelling, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:27; Is. 3:17</char></note>a scab, or a bright spot, and it becomes on the skin of his body like a leprous sore, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:8, 9; 24:8; Mal. 2:7; Luke 17:14</char></note>then he shall be brought to Aaron the priest or to one of his sons the priests. <verse number="3" style="v" />The priest shall examine the sore on the skin of the body; and if the hair on the sore has turned white, and the sore appears to be deeper than the skin of his body, it is a leprous sore. Then the priest shall examine him, and pronounce him unclean. <verse number="4" style="v" />But if the bright spot is white on the skin of his body, and does not appear to be deeper than the skin, and its hair has not turned white, then the priest shall isolate the one who has the sore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:8</char></note>seven days. <verse number="5" style="v" />And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day; and indeed if the sore appears to be as it was, and the sore has not spread on the skin, then the priest shall isolate him another seven days. <verse number="6" style="v" />Then the priest shall examine him again on the seventh day; and indeed if the sore has faded, and the sore has not spread on the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean; it is only a scab, and he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:25; 14:8; (John 13:8, 10)</char></note>shall wash his clothes and be clean. <verse number="7" style="v" />But if the scab should at all spread over the skin, after he has been seen by the priest for his cleansing, he shall be seen by the priest again. <verse number="8" style="v" />And if the priest sees that the scab has indeed spread on the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is leprosy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />“When the leprous sore is on a person, then he shall be brought to the priest. <verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 12:10, 12; 2 Kin. 5:27; 2 Chr. 26:19, 20</char></note>And the priest shall examine him; and indeed if the swelling on the skin is white, and it has turned the hair white, and there is a spot of raw flesh in the swelling, <verse number="11" style="v" />it is an old leprosy on the skin of his body. The priest shall pronounce him unclean, and shall not isolate him, for he is unclean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" />“And if leprosy breaks out all over the skin, and the leprosy covers all the skin of the one who has the sore, from his head to his foot, wherever the priest looks, <verse number="13" style="v" />then the priest shall consider; and indeed if the leprosy has covered all his body, he shall pronounce him clean who has the sore. It has all turned <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 4:6</char></note>white. He is clean. <verse number="14" style="v" />But when raw flesh appears on him, he shall be unclean. <verse number="15" style="v" />And the priest shall examine the raw flesh and pronounce him to be unclean; for the raw flesh is unclean. It is leprosy. <verse number="16" style="v" />Or if the raw flesh changes and turns white again, he shall come to the priest. <verse number="17" style="v" />And the priest shall examine him; and indeed if the sore has turned white, then the priest shall pronounce him clean who has the sore. He is clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" />“If the body develops a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 9:9; 15:26</char></note>boil in the skin, and it is healed, <verse number="19" style="v" />and in the place of the boil there comes a white swelling or a bright spot, reddish-white, then it shall be shown to the priest; <verse number="20" style="v" />and if, when the priest sees it, it indeed appears deeper than the skin, and its hair has turned white, the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a leprous sore which has broken out of the boil. <verse number="21" style="v" />But if the priest examines it, and indeed there are no white hairs in it, and it is not deeper than the skin, but has faded, then the priest shall isolate him seven days; <verse number="22" style="v" />and if it should at all spread over the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a leprous sore. <verse number="23" style="v" />But if the bright spot stays in one place, and has not spread, it is the scar of the boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />“Or if the body receives a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 3:24</char></note>burn on its skin by fire, and the raw flesh of the burn becomes a bright spot, reddish-white or white, <verse number="25" style="v" />then the priest shall examine it; and indeed if the hair of the bright spot has turned white, and it appears deeper than the skin, it is leprosy broken out in the burn. Therefore the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a leprous sore. <verse number="26" style="v" />But if the priest examines it, and indeed there are no white hairs in the bright spot, and it is not deeper than the skin, but has faded, then the priest shall isolate him seven days. <verse number="27" style="v" />And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day. If it has at all spread over the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a leprous sore. <verse number="28" style="v" />But if the bright spot stays in one place, and has not spread on the skin, but has faded, it is a swelling from the burn. The priest shall pronounce him clean, for it is the scar from the burn.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />“If a man or woman has a sore on the head or the beard, <verse number="30" style="v" />then the priest shall examine the sore; and indeed if it appears deeper than the skin, and there is in it thin yellow hair, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a scaly leprosy of the head or beard. <verse number="31" style="v" />But if the priest examines the scaly sore, and indeed it does not appear deeper than the skin, and there is no black hair in it, then the priest shall isolate the one who has the scale seven days. <verse number="32" style="v" />And on the seventh day the priest shall examine the sore; and indeed if the scale has not spread, and there is no yellow hair in it, and the scale does not appear deeper than the skin, <verse number="33" style="v" />he shall shave himself, but the scale he shall not shave. And the priest shall isolate the one who has the scale another seven days. <verse number="34" style="v" />On the seventh day the priest shall examine the scale; and indeed if the scale has not spread over the skin, and does not appear deeper than the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. He shall wash his clothes and be clean. <verse number="35" style="v" />But if the scale should at all spread over the skin after his cleansing, <verse number="36" style="v" />then the priest shall examine him; and indeed if the scale has spread over the skin, the priest need not seek for yellow hair. He is unclean. <verse number="37" style="v" />But if the scale appears to be at a standstill, and there is black hair grown up in it, the scale has healed. He is clean, and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" />“If a man or a woman has bright spots on the skin of the body, specifically white bright spots, <verse number="39" style="v" />then the priest shall look; and indeed if the bright spots on the skin of the body are dull white, it is a white spot that grows on the skin. He is clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" />“As for the man whose hair has fallen from his head, he is bald, but he is clean. <verse number="41" style="v" />He whose hair has fallen from his forehead, he is bald on the forehead, but he is clean. <verse number="42" style="v" />And if there is on the bald head or bald <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 26:19</char></note>forehead a reddish-white sore, it is leprosy breaking out on his bald head or his bald forehead. <verse number="43" style="v" />Then the priest shall examine it; and indeed if the swelling of the sore is reddish-white on his bald head or on his bald forehead, as the appearance of leprosy on the skin of the body, <verse number="44" style="v" />he is a leprous man. He is unclean. The priest shall surely pronounce him unclean; his sore is on his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 1:5</char></note>head.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" />“Now the leper on whom the sore is, his clothes shall be torn and his head <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:6; 21:10</char></note>bare; and he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 24:17, 22; Mic. 3:7</char></note>cover his mustache, and cry, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 6:5; 64:6; Lam. 4:15; Luke 5:8</char></note>‘Unclean! Unclean!’ <verse number="46" style="v" />He shall be unclean. All the days he has the sore he shall be unclean. He is unclean, and he shall dwell alone; his dwelling shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 5:1–4; 12:14; 2 Kin. 7:3; 15:5; 2 Chr. 26:21; Ps. 38:11; Luke 17:12</char></note>outside the camp.</para>
	<para style="s">The Law Concerning Leprous Garments</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" />“Also, if a garment has a leprous plague in it, whether it is a woolen garment or a linen garment, <verse number="48" style="v" />whether it is in the warp or woof of linen or wool, whether in leather or in anything made of leather, <verse number="49" style="v" />and if the plague is greenish or reddish in the garment or in the leather, whether in the warp or in the woof, or in anything made of leather, it is a leprous plague and shall be shown to the priest. <verse number="50" style="v" />The priest shall examine the plague and isolate that which has the plague seven days. <verse number="51" style="v" />And he shall examine the plague on the seventh day. If the plague has spread in the garment, either in the warp or in the woof, in the leather or in anything made of leather, the plague is an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:44</char></note>active leprosy. It is unclean. <verse number="52" style="v" />He shall therefore burn that garment in which is the plague, whether warp or woof, in wool or in linen, or anything of leather, for it is an active leprosy; the garment shall be burned in the fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="53" style="v" />“But if the priest examines it, and indeed the plague has not spread in the garment, either in the warp or in the woof, or in anything made of leather, <verse number="54" style="v" />then the priest shall command that they wash the thing in which is the plague; and he shall isolate it another seven days. <verse number="55" style="v" />Then the priest shall examine the plague after it has been washed; and indeed if the plague has not changed its color, though the plague has not spread, it is unclean, and you shall burn it in the fire; it continues eating away, whether the damage is outside or inside. <verse number="56" style="v" />If the priest examines it, and indeed the plague has faded after washing it, then he shall tear it out of the garment, whether out of the warp or out of the woof, or out of the leather. <verse number="57" style="v" />But if it appears again in the garment, either in the warp or in the woof, or in anything made of leather, it is a spreading plague; you shall burn with fire that in which is the plague. <verse number="58" style="v" />And if you wash the garment, either warp or woof, or whatever is made of leather, if the plague has disappeared from it, then it shall be washed a second time, and shall be clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="59" style="v" />“This is the law of the leprous plague in a garment of wool or linen, either in the warp or woof, or in anything made of leather, to pronounce it clean or to pronounce it unclean.”</para>
	<chapter number="14" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Ritual for Cleansing Healed Lepers</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“This shall be the law of the leper for the day of his cleansing: He <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 8:2, 4; Mark 1:40, 44; Luke 5:12, 14; 17:14</char></note>shall be brought to the priest. <verse number="3" style="v" />And the priest shall go out of the camp, and the priest shall examine him; and indeed, if the leprosy is healed in the leper, <verse number="4" style="v" />then the priest shall command to take for him who is to be cleansed two living and clean birds, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:6, 49, 51, 52; Num. 19:6; Heb. 9:19</char></note>cedar wood, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:4</char></note>scarlet, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:22; Ps. 51:7</char></note>hyssop. <verse number="5" style="v" />And the priest shall command that one of the birds be killed in an earthen vessel over running water. <verse number="6" style="v" />As for the living bird, he shall take it, the cedar wood and the scarlet and the hyssop, and dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the running water. <verse number="7" style="v" />And he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 19:18, 19; (Heb. 9:13, 21; 12:24)</char></note>sprinkle it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 5:10, 14; Ps. 51:2</char></note>seven times on him who is to be cleansed from the leprosy, and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird loose in the open field. <verse number="8" style="v" />He who is to be cleansed <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:25; 13:6; Num. 8:7</char></note>shall wash his clothes, shave off all his hair, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:25; (Eph. 5:26; Heb. 10:22; Rev. 1:5, 6)</char></note>wash himself in water, that he may be clean. After that he shall come into the camp, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 13:5; Num. 5:2, 3; 12:14, 15; 2 Chr. 26:21</char></note>shall stay outside his tent seven days. <verse number="9" style="v" />But on the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 19:19</char></note>seventh day he shall shave all the hair off his head and his beard and his eyebrows—all his hair he shall shave off. He shall wash his clothes and wash his body in water, and he shall be clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />“And on the eighth day <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 8:4; Mark 1:44; Luke 5:14</char></note>he shall take two male lambs without blemish, one ewe lamb of the first year without blemish, three-tenths of an ephah of fine flour mixed with oil as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:1; Num. 15:4</char></note>a grain offering, and one log of oil. <verse number="11" style="v" />Then the priest who makes him clean shall present the man who is to be made clean, and those things, before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, at the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="12" style="v" />And the priest shall take one male lamb and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:6, 18; 6:6; 14:19</char></note>offer it as a trespass offering, and the log of oil, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:22–24, 26</char></note>wave them as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />Then he shall kill the lamb <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:11; Lev. 1:5, 11; 4:4, 24</char></note>in the place where he kills the sin offering and the burnt offering, in a holy place; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:24–30; 7:7</char></note>as the sin offering is the priest’s, so is the trespass offering. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:3; 7:6; 21:22</char></note>It is most holy. <verse number="14" style="v" />The priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and the priest shall put it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:20; Lev. 8:23, 24</char></note>on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot. <verse number="15" style="v" />And the priest shall take some of the log of oil, and pour it into the palm of his own left hand. <verse number="16" style="v" />Then the priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand, and shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:6</char></note>sprinkle some of the oil with his finger seven times before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="17" style="v" />And of the rest of the oil in his hand, the priest shall put some on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, on the blood of the trespass offering. <verse number="18" style="v" />The rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:26; 5:6; Num. 15:28; (Heb. 2:17)</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for him before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />“Then the priest shall offer <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:1, 6; 12:7; (2 Cor. 5:21)</char></note>the sin offering, and make atonement for him who is to be cleansed from his uncleanness. Afterward he shall kill the burnt offering. <verse number="20" style="v" />And the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the grain offering on the altar. So the priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:8, 9</char></note>clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" />“But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:7, 11; 12:8; 27:8</char></note>if he is poor and cannot afford it, then he shall take one male lamb as a trespass offering to be waved, to make atonement for him, one-tenth of an ephah of fine flour mixed with oil as a grain offering, a log of oil, <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 12:8; 15:14, 15</char></note>and two turtledoves or two young pigeons, such as he is able to afford: one shall be a sin offering and the other a burnt offering. <verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:10, 11</char></note>He shall bring them to the priest on the eighth day for his cleansing, to the door of the tabernacle of meeting, before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:12</char></note>And the priest shall take the lamb of the trespass offering and the log of oil, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:14, 17</char></note>and the priest shall wave them as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="25" style="v" />Then he shall kill the lamb of the trespass offering, and the priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering and put it on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot. <verse number="26" style="v" />And the priest shall pour some of the oil into the palm of his own left hand. <verse number="27" style="v" />Then the priest shall sprinkle with his right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="28" style="v" />And the priest shall put some of the oil that is in his hand on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, on the thumb of the right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, on the place of the blood of the trespass offering. <verse number="29" style="v" />The rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed, to make atonement for him before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="30" style="v" />And he shall offer one of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:22; 15:14, 15</char></note>the turtledoves or young pigeons, such as he can afford— <verse number="31" style="v" />such as he is able to afford, the one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering, with the grain offering. So the priest shall make atonement for him who is to be cleansed before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="32" style="v" />This is the law for one who had a leprous sore, who cannot afford <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:10</char></note>the usual cleansing.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Law Concerning Leprous Houses</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying: <verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 12:7; 13:17; 17:8; Num. 32:22; Deut. 7:1; 32:49</char></note>“When you have come into the land of Canaan, which I give you as a possession, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 3:33)</char></note>I put the leprous plague in a house in the land of your possession, <verse number="35" style="v" />and he who owns the house comes and tells the priest, saying, ‘It seems to me that there is <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ps. 91:9, 10; Prov. 3:33; Zech. 5:4)</char></note>some plague in the house,’ <verse number="36" style="v" />then the priest shall command that they empty the house, before the priest goes into it to examine the plague, that all that is in the house may not be made unclean; and afterward the priest shall go in to examine the house. <verse number="37" style="v" />And he shall examine the plague; and indeed if the plague is on the walls of the house with ingrained streaks, greenish or reddish, which appear to be deep in the wall, <verse number="38" style="v" />then the priest shall go out of the house, to the door of the house, and shut up the house seven days. <verse number="39" style="v" />And the priest shall come again on the seventh day and look; and indeed if the plague has spread on the walls of the house, <verse number="40" style="v" />then the priest shall command that they take away the stones in which is the plague, and they shall cast them into an unclean place outside the city. <verse number="41" style="v" />And he shall cause the house to be scraped inside, all around, and the dust that they scrape off they shall pour out in an unclean place outside the city. <verse number="42" style="v" />Then they shall take other stones and put them in the place of those stones, and he shall take other mortar and plaster the house.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" />“Now if the plague comes back and breaks out in the house, after he has taken away the stones, after he has scraped the house, and after it is plastered, <verse number="44" style="v" />then the priest shall come and look; and indeed if the plague has spread in the house, it is <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 13:51; (Zech. 5:4)</char></note>an active leprosy in the house. It is unclean. <verse number="45" style="v" />And he shall break down the house, its stones, its timber, and all the plaster of the house, and he shall carry them outside the city to an unclean place. <verse number="46" style="v" />Moreover he who goes into the house at all while it is shut up shall be unclean until <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:24; 15:5</char></note>evening. <verse number="47" style="v" />And he who lies down in the house shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:8</char></note>wash his clothes, and he who eats in the house shall wash his clothes.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" />“But if the priest comes in and examines it, and indeed the plague has not spread in the house after the house was plastered, then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the plague is healed. <verse number="49" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:4</char></note>he shall take, to cleanse the house, two birds, cedar wood, scarlet, and hyssop. <verse number="50" style="v" />Then he shall kill one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water; <verse number="51" style="v" />and he shall take the cedar wood, the hyssop, the scarlet, and the living bird, and dip them in the blood of the slain bird and in the running water, and sprinkle the house seven times. <verse number="52" style="v" />And he shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird and the running water and the living bird, with the cedar wood, the hyssop, and the scarlet. <verse number="53" style="v" />Then he shall let the living bird loose outside the city in the open field, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:20</char></note>make atonement for the house, and it shall be clean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v" />“This is the law for any <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 13:30; 26:21</char></note>leprous sore and scale, <verse number="55" style="v" />for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 13:47–52</char></note>leprosy of a garment <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:34</char></note>and of a house, <verse number="56" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 13:2</char></note>for a swelling and a scab and a bright spot, <verse number="57" style="v" />to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:47; 20:25; Deut. 24:8; Ezek. 44:23</char></note>teach when it is unclean and when it is clean. This is the law of leprosy.”</para>
	<chapter number="15" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Law Concerning Bodily Discharges</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:4; Num. 5:2; 2 Sam. 3:29</char></note>‘When any man has a discharge from his body, his discharge is unclean. <verse number="3" style="v" />And this shall be his uncleanness in regard to his discharge—whether his body runs with his discharge, or his body is stopped up by his discharge, it is his uncleanness. <verse number="4" style="v" />Every bed is unclean on which he who has the discharge lies, and everything on which he sits shall be unclean. <verse number="5" style="v" />And whoever <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:2; 14:46</char></note>touches his bed shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:8, 47</char></note>wash his clothes and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:25; 17:15</char></note>bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="6" style="v" />He who sits on anything on which he who has the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:10; Deut. 23:10</char></note>discharge sat shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="7" style="v" />And he who touches the body of him who has the discharge shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="8" style="v" />If he who has the discharge <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 12:14</char></note>spits on him who is clean, then he shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="9" style="v" />Any saddle on which he who has the discharge rides shall be unclean. <verse number="10" style="v" />Whoever touches anything that was under him shall be unclean until evening. He who carries any of those things shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="11" style="v" />And whomever the one who has the discharge touches, and has not rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="12" style="v" />The <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:28; 11:32, 33</char></note>vessel of earth that he who has the discharge touches shall be broken, and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />‘And when he who has a discharge is cleansed of his discharge, then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:8; 15:28; Num. 19:11, 12</char></note>he shall count for himself seven days for his cleansing, wash his clothes, and bathe his body in running water; then he shall be clean. <verse number="14" style="v" />On the eighth day he shall take for himself <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:22, 23, 30, 31</char></note>two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and come before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to the door of the tabernacle of meeting, and give them to the priest. <verse number="15" style="v" />Then the priest shall offer them, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:30, 31</char></note>the one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:19, 31</char></note>So the priest shall make atonement for him before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> because of his discharge.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:4; Deut. 23:10, 11</char></note>‘If any man has an emission of semen, then he shall wash all his body in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="17" style="v" />And any garment and any leather on which there is semen, it shall be washed with water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="18" style="v" />Also, when a woman lies with a man, and there is an emission of semen, they shall bathe in water, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Ex. 19:15; 1 Sam. 21:4; 1 Cor. 6:18)</char></note>be unclean until evening.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 12:2</char></note>‘If a woman has a discharge, and the discharge from her body is blood, she shall be set apart seven days; and whoever touches her shall be unclean until evening. <verse number="20" style="v" />Everything that she lies on during her impurity shall be unclean; also everything that she sits on shall be unclean. <verse number="21" style="v" />Whoever touches her bed shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="22" style="v" />And whoever touches anything that she sat on shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. <verse number="23" style="v" />If anything is on her bed or on anything on which she sits, when he touches it, he shall be unclean until evening. <verse number="24" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:19; 20:18</char></note>if any man lies with her at all, so that her impurity is on him, he shall be unclean seven days; and every bed on which he lies shall be unclean.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" />‘If <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 9:20; Mark 5:25; Luke 8:43</char></note>a woman has a discharge of blood for many days, other than at the time of her customary impurity, or if it runs beyond her usual time of impurity, all the days of her unclean discharge shall be as the days of her customary impurity. She shall be unclean. <verse number="26" style="v" />Every bed on which she lies all the days of her discharge shall be to her as the bed of her impurity; and whatever she sits on shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her impurity. <verse number="27" style="v" />Whoever touches those things shall be unclean; he shall wash his clothes and bathe in water, and be unclean until evening.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" />‘But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:13–15</char></note>if she is cleansed of her discharge, then she shall count for herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean. <verse number="29" style="v" />And on the eighth day she shall take for herself two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and bring them to the priest, to the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="30" style="v" />Then the priest shall offer the one as a sin offering and the other as a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:7</char></note>burnt offering, and the priest shall make atonement for her before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for the discharge of her uncleanness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />‘Thus you shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:47; 14:57; 22:2; Deut. 24:8; Ezek. 44:23; (Heb. 12:15)</char></note>separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness, lest they die in their uncleanness when they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:3; Num. 5:3; 19:13, 20; Ezek. 5:11; 23:38; 36:17</char></note>defile My tabernacle that is among them. <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:2</char></note>This is the law for one who has a discharge, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:16</char></note>and for him who emits semen and is unclean thereby, <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:19</char></note>and for her who is indisposed because of her customary impurity, and for one who has a discharge, either man <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:25</char></note>or woman, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:24</char></note>and for him who lies with her who is unclean.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="16" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Day of Atonement</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses after <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:1, 2; 2 Sam. 6:6–8</char></note>the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they offered profane fire before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and died; <verse number="2" style="v" />and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Moses: “Tell Aaron your brother <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:10; Lev. 16:34; 23:27; (Heb. 6:19; 9:7, 8, 12; 10:19)</char></note>not to come at just any time into the Holy Place inside the veil, before the mercy seat which is on the ark, lest he die; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:21, 22; 40:34; 1 Kin. 8:10–12</char></note>I will appear in the cloud above the mercy seat.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" />“Thus Aaron shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:1–12; 16:6; (Heb. 9:7, 12, 24, 25)</char></note>come into the Holy Place: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:3</char></note>with the blood of a young bull as a sin offering, and of a ram as a burnt offering. <verse number="4" style="v" />He shall put the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:39, 42, 43; Lev. 6:10; Ezek. 44:17, 18</char></note>holy linen tunic and the linen trousers on his body; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:20; Lev. 8:6, 7</char></note>he shall be girded with a linen sash, and with the linen turban he shall be attired. These are holy garments. Therefore he shall wash his body in water, and put them on. <verse number="5" style="v" />And he shall take from <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:14; Num. 29:11; 2 Chr. 29:21; Ezra 6:17; Ezek. 45:22, 23</char></note>the congregation of the children of Israel two kids of the goats as a sin offering, and one ram as a burnt offering.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />“Aaron shall offer the bull as a sin offering, which is for himself, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 9:7; (Heb. 5:3; 7:27, 28; 9:7)</char></note>make atonement for himself and for his house. <verse number="7" style="v" />He shall take the two goats and present them before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at the door of the tabernacle of meeting. <verse number="8" style="v" />Then Aaron shall cast lots for the two goats: one lot for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the other lot for the scapegoat. <verse number="9" style="v" />And Aaron shall bring the goat on which the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s lot fell, and offer it as a sin offering. <verse number="10" style="v" />But the goat on which the lot fell to be the scapegoat shall be presented alive before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to make <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 53:5, 6; Rom. 3:25; Heb. 7:27; 9:23, 24; 1 John 2:2)</char></note>atonement upon it, and to let it go as the scapegoat into the wilderness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" />“And Aaron shall bring the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself, and make atonement for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 7:27; 9:7)</char></note>himself and for his house, and shall kill the bull as the sin offering which is for himself. <verse number="12" style="v" />Then he shall take <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:1; Num. 16:7, 18; Is. 6:6, 7; Rev. 8:5</char></note>a censer full of burning coals of fire from the altar before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, with his hands full of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:34–38</char></note>sweet incense beaten fine, and bring it inside the veil. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:7, 8; Num. 16:7, 18, 46</char></note>And he shall put the incense on the fire before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that the cloud of incense may cover the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:21</char></note>mercy seat that is on the Testimony, lest he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:43; Lev. 22:9; Num. 4:15, 20</char></note>die. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:5; (Heb. 9:25; 10:4)</char></note>He shall take some of the blood of the bull and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:6, 17</char></note>sprinkle it with his finger on the mercy seat on the east side; and before the mercy seat he shall sprinkle some of the blood with his finger seven times.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 2:17)</char></note>“Then he shall kill the goat of the sin offering, which is for the people, bring its blood <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 6:19; 7:27; 9:3, 7, 12)</char></note>inside the veil, do with that blood as he did with the blood of the bull, and sprinkle it on the mercy seat and before the mercy seat. <verse number="16" style="v" />So he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:36; 30:10; Ezek. 45:18; (Heb. 9:22–24)</char></note>make atonement for the Holy Place, because of the uncleanness of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions, for all their sins; and so he shall do for the tabernacle of meeting which remains among them in the midst of their uncleanness. <verse number="17" style="v" />There shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:3; Luke 1:10</char></note>no man in the tabernacle of meeting when he goes in to make atonement in the Holy Place, until he comes out, that he may make atonement for himself, for his household, and for all the assembly of Israel. <verse number="18" style="v" />And he shall go out to the altar that is before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and make atonement for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:36</char></note>it, and shall take some of the blood of the bull and some of the blood of the goat, and put it on the horns of the altar all around. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then he shall sprinkle some of the blood on it with his finger seven times, cleanse it, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:14; Ezek. 43:20</char></note>consecrate it from the uncleanness of the children of Israel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />“And when he has made an end of atoning for the Holy Place, the tabernacle of meeting, and the altar, he shall bring the live goat. <verse number="21" style="v" />Aaron shall lay both his hands on the head of the live goat, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:5; 26:40</char></note>confess over it all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions, concerning all their sins, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 53:6)</char></note>putting them on the head of the goat, and shall send it away into the wilderness by the hand of a suitable man. <verse number="22" style="v" />The goat shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:14; (Is. 53:6, 11, 12; John 1:29; Heb. 9:28; 1 Pet. 2:24)</char></note>bear on itself all their iniquities to an uninhabited land; and he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:7</char></note>release the goat in the wilderness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />“Then Aaron shall come into the tabernacle of meeting, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:11; 16:4; Ezek. 42:14; 44:19</char></note>shall take off the linen garments which he put on when he went into the Holy Place, and shall leave them there. <verse number="24" style="v" />And he shall wash his body with water in a holy place, put on his garments, come out and offer his burnt offering and the burnt offering of the people, and make atonement for himself and for the people. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:8; 4:10</char></note>The fat of the sin offering he shall burn on the altar. <verse number="26" style="v" />And he who released the goat as the scapegoat shall wash his clothes <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:5</char></note>and bathe his body in water, and afterward he may come into the camp. <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:12, 21; 6:30; Heb. 13:11</char></note>The bull for the sin offering and the goat for the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the Holy Place, shall be carried outside the camp. And they shall burn in the fire their skins, their flesh, and their offal. <verse number="28" style="v" />Then he who burns them shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water, and afterward he may come into the camp.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />“This shall be a statute forever for you: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:10; Lev. 23:27–32; Num. 29:7</char></note>In the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, you shall afflict your souls, and do no work at all, whether a native of your own country or a stranger who dwells among you. <verse number="30" style="v" />For on that day the priest shall make atonement for you, to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 51:2; Jer. 33:8; (Eph. 5:26; Heb. 9:13, 14; 1 John 1:7, 9)</char></note>cleanse you, that you may be clean from all your sins before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:27, 32; Ezra 8:21; Is. 58:3, 5; Dan. 10:12</char></note>It is a sabbath of solemn rest for you, and you shall afflict your souls. It is a statute forever. <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:3, 5, 16; 21:10</char></note>And the priest, who is anointed and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:29, 30; Num. 20:26, 28</char></note>consecrated to minister as priest in his father’s place, shall make atonement, and put on the linen clothes, the holy garments; <verse number="33" style="v" />then he shall make atonement for the Holy Sanctuary, and he shall make atonement for the tabernacle of meeting and for the altar, and he shall make atonement for the priests and for all the people of the assembly. <verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:31; Num. 29:7</char></note>This shall be an everlasting statute for you, to make atonement for the children of Israel, for all their sins, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:10; (Heb. 9:7, 25, 28)</char></note>once a year.” And he did as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded Moses.</para>
	<chapter number="17" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Sanctity of Blood</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to Aaron, to his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and say to them, ‘This is the thing which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has commanded, saying: <verse number="3" style="v" />“Whatever man of the house of Israel who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:5, 15, 21</char></note>kills an ox or lamb or goat in the camp, or who kills it outside the camp, <verse number="4" style="v" />and does not bring it to the door of the tabernacle of meeting to offer an offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> before the tabernacle of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the guilt of bloodshed shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Rom. 5:13</char></note>imputed to that man. He has shed blood; and that man shall be cut off from among his people, <verse number="5" style="v" />to the end that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 21:33; 22:2; 31:54; Deut. 12:1–27; Ezek. 20:28</char></note>which they offer in the open field, that they may bring them to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at the door of the tabernacle of meeting, to the priest, and offer them as peace offerings to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="6" style="v" />And the priest <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:2</char></note>shall sprinkle the blood on the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at the door of the tabernacle of meeting, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:13, 18; Num. 18:17</char></note>burn the fat for a sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="7" style="v" />They shall no more offer their sacrifices <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:20; 32:8; 34:15; Deut. 32:17; 2 Chr. 11:15; Ps. 106:37; 1 Cor. 10:20</char></note>to demons, after whom they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:15; Deut. 31:16; Ezek. 23:8</char></note>have played the harlot. This shall be a statute forever for them throughout their generations.” ’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />“Also you shall say to them: ‘Whatever man of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who dwell among you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:2, 3; 18:26</char></note>who offers a burnt offering or sacrifice, <verse number="9" style="v" />and does not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:23</char></note>bring it to the door of the tabernacle of meeting, to offer it to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that man shall be cut off from among his people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:4; Lev. 3:17; 7:26, 27; Deut. 12:16, 23–25; 15:23; 1 Sam. 14:33</char></note>‘And whatever man of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who dwell among you, who eats any blood, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:3, 5, 6</char></note>I will set My face against that person who eats blood, and will cut him off from among his people. <verse number="11" style="v" />For the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:4; Lev. 17:14</char></note>life of the flesh is in the blood, and I have given it to you upon the altar <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 26:28; Rom. 3:25; Eph. 1:7; Col. 1:14, 20; 1 Pet. 1:2; 1 John 1:7)</char></note>to make atonement for your souls; for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 9:22)</char></note>it is the blood that makes atonement for the soul.’ <verse number="12" style="v" />Therefore I said to the children of Israel, ‘No one among you shall eat blood, nor shall any stranger who dwells among you eat blood.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />“Whatever man of the children of Israel, or of the strangers who dwell among you, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:26</char></note>hunts and catches any animal or bird that may be eaten, he shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:16, 24</char></note>pour out its blood and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 24:7</char></note>cover it with dust; <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:4; Lev. 17:11; Deut. 12:23</char></note>for it is the life of all flesh. Its blood sustains its life. Therefore I said to the children of Israel, ‘You shall not eat the blood of any flesh, for the life of all flesh is its blood. Whoever eats it shall be cut off.’</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:31; Lev. 7:24; 22:8; Deut. 14:21; Ezek. 4:14; 44:31</char></note>“And every person who eats what died naturally or what was torn by beasts, whether he is a native of your own country or a stranger, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:25</char></note>he shall both wash his clothes and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:5</char></note>bathe in water, and be unclean until evening. Then he shall be clean. <verse number="16" style="v" />But if he does not wash them or bathe his body, then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:1</char></note>he shall bear his guilt.”</para>
	<chapter number="18" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Laws of Sexual Morality</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 6:7; Lev. 11:44, 45; 19:3; Ezek. 20:5, 7, 19, 20</char></note>‘I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 24:14; Ezek. 20:7, 8</char></note>According to the doings of the land of Egypt, where you dwelt, you shall not do; and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:24; Lev. 18:24–30; 20:23; Deut. 12:30, 31</char></note>according to the doings of the land of Canaan, where I am bringing you, you shall not do; nor shall you walk in their ordinances. <verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 20:19</char></note>You shall observe My judgments and keep My ordinances, to walk in them: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. <verse number="5" style="v" />You shall therefore keep My statutes and My judgments, which if a man does, he shall live by them: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />‘None of you shall approach anyone who is near of kin to him, to uncover his nakedness: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="7" style="v" />The nakedness of your father or the nakedness of your mother you shall not uncover. She is your mother; you shall not uncover her nakedness. <verse number="8" style="v" />The nakedness of your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 35:22</char></note>father’s wife you shall not uncover; it is your father’s nakedness. <verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:11; 20:17; Deut. 27:22</char></note>The nakedness of your sister, the daughter of your father, or the daughter of your mother, whether born at home or elsewhere, their nakedness you shall not uncover. <verse number="10" style="v" />The nakedness of your son’s daughter or your daughter’s daughter, their nakedness you shall not uncover; for theirs is your own nakedness. <verse number="11" style="v" />The nakedness of your father’s wife’s daughter, begotten by your father—she is your sister—you shall not uncover her nakedness. <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:19</char></note>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s sister; she is near of kin to your father. <verse number="13" style="v" />You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother’s sister, for she is near of kin to your mother. <verse number="14" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:20</char></note>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s brother. You shall not approach his wife; she is your aunt. <verse number="15" style="v" />You shall not uncover the nakedness of your daughter-in-law—she is your son’s wife—you shall not uncover her nakedness. <verse number="16" style="v" />You shall not uncover the nakedness of your brother’s wife; it is your brother’s nakedness. <verse number="17" style="v" />You shall not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:14</char></note>daughter, nor shall you take her son’s daughter or her daughter’s daughter, to uncover her nakedness. They are near of kin to her. It is wickedness. <verse number="18" style="v" />Nor shall you take a woman <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 1:6, 8</char></note>as a rival to her sister, to uncover her nakedness while the other is alive.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />‘Also you shall not approach a woman to uncover her nakedness as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 18:6</char></note>long as she is in her <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:24; 20:18</char></note>customary impurity. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Prov. 6:25–33)</char></note>Moreover you shall not lie carnally with your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:14; Lev. 20:10; (Matt. 5:27, 28; 1 Cor. 6:9; Heb. 13:4)</char></note>neighbor’s wife, to defile yourself with her. <verse number="21" style="v" />And you shall not let any of your descendants <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:2–5; Deut. 12:31</char></note>pass through <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 16:3</char></note>the fire to <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 11:7, 33; Acts 7:43</char></note>Molech, nor shall you profane the name of your God: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="22" style="v" />You shall not lie with <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:13; Rom. 1:27</char></note>a male as with a woman. It is an abomination. <verse number="23" style="v" />Nor shall you mate with any <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:19; Lev. 20:15, 16; Deut. 27:21</char></note>animal, to defile yourself with it. Nor shall any woman stand before an animal to mate with it. It is perversion.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 15:18–20; 1 Cor. 3:17</char></note>‘Do not defile yourselves with any of these things; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:3; 20:23; Deut. 18:12</char></note>for by all these the nations are defiled, which I am casting out before you. <verse number="25" style="v" />For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:33, 34; Ezek. 36:17</char></note>the land is defiled; therefore I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 26:21; Jer. 5:9</char></note>visit the punishment of its iniquity upon it, and the land <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:28; 20:22</char></note>vomits out its inhabitants. <verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:5, 30</char></note>You shall therefore keep My statutes and My judgments, and shall not commit any of these abominations, either any of your own nation or any stranger who dwells among you <verse number="27" style="v" />(for all these abominations the men of the land have done, who were before you, and thus the land is defiled), <verse number="28" style="v" />lest <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 9:19</char></note>the land vomit you out also when you defile it, as it vomited out the nations that were before you. <verse number="29" style="v" />For whoever commits any of these abominations, the persons who commit them shall be cut off from among their people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />‘Therefore you shall keep My ordinance, so <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:3; 22:9</char></note>that you do not commit any of these abominable customs which were committed before you, and that you do not defile yourselves by them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:2</char></note>I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="19" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Moral and Ceremonial Laws</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to all the congregation of the children of Israel, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:6; Lev. 11:44; 20:7, 26; (Eph. 1:4); 1 Pet. 1:16</char></note>‘You shall be holy, for I the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God am holy.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:12; Deut. 5:16; Matt. 15:4; Eph. 6:2</char></note>‘Every one of you shall revere his mother and his father, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 16:23; 20:8; 31:13</char></note>keep My Sabbaths: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:4; Ps. 96:5; 115:4–7; 1 Cor. 10:14; (Col. 3:5)</char></note>‘Do not turn to idols, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:17</char></note>nor make for yourselves molded gods: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />‘And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:16</char></note>if you offer a sacrifice of a peace offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, you shall offer it of your own free will. <verse number="6" style="v" />It shall be eaten the same day you offer it, and on the next day. And if any remains until the third day, it shall be burned in the fire. <verse number="7" style="v" />And if it is eaten at all on the third day, it is an abomination. It shall not be accepted. <verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore everyone who eats it shall bear his iniquity, because he has profaned the hallowed offering of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; and that person shall be cut off from his people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:22; Deut. 24:19–22</char></note>‘When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not wholly reap the corners of your field, nor shall you gather the gleanings of your harvest. <verse number="10" style="v" />And you shall not glean your vineyard, nor shall you gather every grape of your vineyard; you shall leave them for the poor and the stranger: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:15, 16</char></note>‘You shall not steal, nor deal falsely, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 9:3–5; Eph. 4:25</char></note>nor lie to one another. <verse number="12" style="v" />And you shall not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:7; Deut. 5:11; (Matt. 5:33–37; James 5:12)</char></note>swear by My name falsely, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:21</char></note>nor shall you profane the name of your God: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:7–15, 21–27; Mark 10:19</char></note>‘You shall not cheat your neighbor, nor rob him. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 24:15; Mal. 3:5; James 5:4</char></note>The wages of him who is hired shall not remain with you all night until morning. <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall not curse the deaf, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 27:18</char></note>nor put a stumbling block before the blind, but shall fear your God: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />‘You shall do no injustice in <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 16:19</char></note>judgment. You shall not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:3, 6; Deut. 1:17; 10:17; Ps. 82:2</char></note>be partial to the poor, nor honor the person of the mighty. In righteousness you shall judge your neighbor. <verse number="16" style="v" />You shall not go about as a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 11:13; 18:8; 20:19</char></note>talebearer among your people; nor shall you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:7; Deut. 27:25; 1 Kin. 21:7–19</char></note>take a stand against the life of your neighbor: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(1 John 2:9, 11; 3:15)</char></note>‘You shall not hate your brother in your heart. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 18:15; (Luke 17:3); Eph. 5:11</char></note>You shall surely rebuke your neighbor, and not bear sin because of him. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Deut. 32:35; 1 Sam. 24:12; Rom. 12:19; Heb. 10:30)</char></note>You shall not take vengeance, nor bear any grudge against the children of your people, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 5:43; 19:19; Mark 12:31; Luke 10:27; (Rom. 13:9; Gal. 5:14); James 2:8</char></note>but you shall love your neighbor as yourself: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />‘You shall keep My statutes. You shall not let your livestock breed with another kind. You shall not sow your field with mixed seed. Nor shall a garment of mixed linen and wool come upon you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />‘Whoever lies carnally with a woman who is <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 22:23–27</char></note>betrothed to a man as a concubine, and who has not at all been redeemed nor given her freedom, for this there shall be scourging; but they shall not be put to death, because she was not free. <verse number="21" style="v" />And he shall bring his trespass offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to the door of the tabernacle of meeting, a ram as a trespass offering. <verse number="22" style="v" />The priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for his sin which he has committed. And the sin which he has committed shall be forgiven him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />‘When you come into the land, and have planted all kinds of trees for food, then you shall count their fruit as uncircumcised. Three years it shall be as uncircumcised to you. It shall not be eaten. <verse number="24" style="v" />But in the fourth year all its fruit shall be holy, a praise to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="25" style="v" />And in the fifth year you may eat its fruit, that it may yield to you its increase: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />‘You shall not eat anything with the blood, nor shall you practice divination or soothsaying. <verse number="27" style="v" />You shall not shave around the sides of your head, nor shall you disfigure the edges of your beard. <verse number="28" style="v" />You shall not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 18:28; Jer. 16:6</char></note>make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor tattoo any marks on you: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 21:9; Deut. 22:21; 23:17, 18</char></note>‘Do not prostitute your daughter, to cause her to be a harlot, lest the land fall into harlotry, and the land become full of wickedness.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" />‘You shall keep My Sabbaths and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:2; Eccl. 5:1</char></note>reverence My sanctuary: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" />‘Give no regard to mediums and familiar spirits; do not seek after <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:6, 27; Deut. 18:11; 1 Sam. 28:3; Is. 8:19</char></note>them, to be defiled by them: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 23:22; Lam. 5:12; 1 Tim. 5:1</char></note>‘You shall rise before the gray headed and honor the presence of an old man, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:14</char></note>fear your God: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />‘And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:21; Deut. 24:17, 18</char></note>if a stranger dwells with you in your land, you shall not mistreat him. <verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:48</char></note>The stranger who dwells among you shall be to you as one born among you, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 10:19</char></note>you shall love him as yourself; for you were strangers in the land of Egypt: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />‘You shall do no injustice in judgment, in measurement of length, weight, or volume. <verse number="36" style="v" />You shall have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 25:13–15; Prov. 20:10</char></note>honest scales, honest weights, an honest ephah, and an honest hin: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:4, 5; Deut. 4:5, 6; 5:1; 6:25</char></note>‘Therefore you shall observe all My statutes and all My judgments, and perform them: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="20" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Penalties for Breaking the Law</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:2</char></note>“Again, you shall say to the children of Israel: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:21; 2 Kin. 23:10; 2 Chr. 33:6; Jer. 7:31</char></note>‘Whoever of the children of Israel, or of the strangers who dwell in Israel, who gives any of his descendants to Molech, he shall surely be put to death. The people of the land shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 17:2–5</char></note>stone him with stones. <verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 17:10</char></note>I will set My face against that man, and will cut him off from his people, because he has given some of his descendants to Molech, to defile My sanctuary and profane My holy name. <verse number="4" style="v" />And if the people of the land should in any way hide their eyes from the man, when he gives some of his descendants to Molech, and they do not kill him, <verse number="5" style="v" />then I will set My face against that man and against his family; and I will cut him off from his people, and all who prostitute themselves with him to commit harlotry with Molech.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" />‘And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:31; 1 Sam. 28:7–25</char></note>the person who turns to mediums and familiar spirits, to prostitute himself with them, I will set My face against that person and cut him off from his people. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:2; Heb. 12:14</char></note>Consecrate yourselves therefore, and be holy, for I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. <verse number="8" style="v" />And you shall keep <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:19, 37</char></note>My statutes, and perform them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 31:13; Deut. 14:2; Ezek. 37:28</char></note>I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> who sanctifies you.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />‘For <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 21:17; Deut. 27:16; Prov. 20:20; Matt. 15:4</char></note>everyone who curses his father or his mother shall surely be put to death. He has cursed his father or his mother. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Sam. 1:16</char></note>His blood shall be upon him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:14; Lev. 18:20; Deut. 5:18; 22:22; John 8:4, 5</char></note>‘The man who commits adultery with another man’s wife, he who commits adultery with his neighbor’s wife, the adulterer and the adulteress, shall surely be put to death. <verse number="11" style="v" />The man who lies with his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:7, 8; Deut. 27:20</char></note>father’s wife has uncovered his father’s nakedness; both of them shall surely be put to death. Their blood shall be upon them. <verse number="12" style="v" />If a man lies with his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:15</char></note>daughter-in-law, both of them shall surely be put to death. They have committed perversion. Their blood shall be upon them. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:22; Deut. 23:17; Judg. 19:22</char></note>If a man lies with a male as he lies with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination. They shall surely be put to death. Their blood shall be upon them. <verse number="14" style="v" />If a man marries a woman and her <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:17</char></note>mother, it is wickedness. They shall be burned with fire, both he and they, that there may be no wickedness among you. <verse number="15" style="v" />If a man mates with an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:23; Deut. 27:21</char></note>animal, he shall surely be put to death, and you shall kill the animal. <verse number="16" style="v" />If a woman approaches any animal and mates with it, you shall kill the woman and the animal. They shall surely be put to death. Their blood is upon them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />‘If a man takes his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:9; Deut. 27:22</char></note>sister, his father’s daughter or his mother’s daughter, and sees her nakedness and she sees his nakedness, it is a wicked thing. And they shall be cut off in the sight of their people. He has uncovered his sister’s nakedness. He shall bear his guilt. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:24; 18:19</char></note>If a man lies with a woman during her sickness and uncovers her nakedness, he has exposed her flow, and she has uncovered the flow of her blood. Both of them shall be cut off from their people.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />‘You shall not uncover the nakedness of your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:13</char></note>mother’s sister nor of your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:12</char></note>father’s sister, for that would uncover his near of kin. They shall bear their guilt. <verse number="20" style="v" />If a man lies with his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:14</char></note>uncle’s wife, he has uncovered his uncle’s nakedness. They shall bear their sin; they shall die childless. <verse number="21" style="v" />If a man takes his <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:16; Matt. 14:3, 4</char></note>brother’s wife, it is an unclean thing. He has uncovered his brother’s nakedness. They shall be childless.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />‘You shall therefore keep all My <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:26; 19:37</char></note>statutes and all My judgments, and perform them, that the land where I am bringing you to dwell <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:25, 28; 2 Chr. 36:14–16</char></note>may not vomit you out. <verse number="23" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:3, 24</char></note>And you shall not walk in the statutes of the nation which I am casting out before you; for they commit all these things, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 9:5</char></note>therefore I abhor them. <verse number="24" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 3:17; 6:8; 13:5; 33:1–3</char></note>I have said to you, “You shall inherit their land, and I will give it to you to possess, a land flowing with milk and honey.” I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:5; 33:16; Lev. 20:26; Deut. 7:6; 14:2; 1 Kin. 8:53</char></note>who has separated you from the peoples. <verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:10; 11:1–47; Deut. 14:3–21</char></note>You shall therefore distinguish between clean animals and unclean, between unclean birds and clean, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:43</char></note>and you shall not make yourselves abominable by beast or by bird, or by any kind of living thing that creeps on the ground, which I have separated from you as unclean. <verse number="26" style="v" />And you shall be holy to Me, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:2; 1 Pet. 1:16</char></note>for I the <char style="sc">Lord</char> am holy, and have separated you from the peoples, that you should be Mine.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:31; 1 Sam. 28:9</char></note>‘A man or a woman who is a medium, or who has familiar spirits, shall surely be put to death; they shall stone them with stones. Their blood shall be upon them.’ ”</para>
	<chapter number="21" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Regulations for Conduct of Priests</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Moses, “Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:28; Ezek. 44:25</char></note>‘None shall defile himself for the dead among his people, <verse number="2" style="v" />except for his relatives who are nearest to him: his mother, his father, his son, his daughter, and his brother; <verse number="3" style="v" />also his virgin sister who is near to him, who has had no husband, for her he may defile himself. <verse number="4" style="v" />Otherwise he shall not defile himself, being a chief man among his people, to profane himself.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:27; Deut. 14:1; Ezek. 44:20</char></note>‘They shall not make any bald place on their heads, nor shall they shave the edges of their beards nor make any cuttings in their flesh. <verse number="6" style="v" />They shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:31</char></note>holy to their God and not profane the name of their God, for they offer the offerings of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made by fire, and the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:11</char></note>bread of their God; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 52:11</char></note>therefore they shall be holy. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 44:22</char></note>They shall not take a wife who is a harlot or a defiled woman, nor shall they take a woman <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 24:1, 2</char></note>divorced from her husband; for the priest is holy to his God. <verse number="8" style="v" />Therefore you shall consecrate him, for he offers the bread of your God. He shall be holy to you, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:44, 45</char></note>I the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:12, 30</char></note>sanctify you, am holy. <verse number="9" style="v" />The daughter of any priest, if she profanes herself by playing the harlot, she profanes her father. She shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 22:21</char></note>burned with fire.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />‘He who is the high priest among his brethren, on whose head the anointing oil was <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 8:12</char></note>poured and who is consecrated to wear the garments, shall not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:6, 7</char></note>uncover his head nor tear his clothes; <verse number="11" style="v" />nor shall he go <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 19:14</char></note>near any dead body, nor defile himself for his father or his mother; <verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:7</char></note>nor shall he go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:6, 7</char></note>consecration of the anointing oil of his God is upon him: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />And he shall take a wife in her virginity. <verse number="14" style="v" />A widow or a divorced woman or a defiled woman or a harlot—these he shall not marry; but he shall take a virgin of his own people as wife. <verse number="15" style="v" />Nor shall he profane his posterity among his people, for I the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sanctify him.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="17" style="v" />“Speak to Aaron, saying: ‘No man of your descendants in succeeding generations, who has any defect, may approach to offer the bread of his God. <verse number="18" style="v" />For any man who has a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:19–25</char></note>defect shall not approach: a man blind or lame, who has a marred face or any limb <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:23</char></note>too long, <verse number="19" style="v" />a man who has a broken foot or broken hand, <verse number="20" style="v" />or is a hunchback or a dwarf, or a man who has a defect in his eye, or eczema or scab, or is a eunuch. <verse number="21" style="v" />No man of the descendants of Aaron the priest, who has a defect, shall come near to offer the offerings made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He has a defect; he shall not come near to offer the bread of his God. <verse number="22" style="v" />He may eat the bread of his God, both the most holy and the holy; <verse number="23" style="v" />only he shall not go near the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:2</char></note>veil or approach the altar, because he has a defect, lest <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 21:12</char></note>he profane My sanctuaries; for I the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sanctify them.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />And Moses told it to Aaron and his sons, and to all the children of Israel.</para>
	<chapter number="22" style="c" />
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to Aaron and his sons, that they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 6:3</char></note>separate themselves from the holy things of the children of Israel, and that they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:21</char></note>do not profane My holy name by what they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:38; Lev. 16:19; 25:10; Num. 18:32; Deut. 15:19</char></note>dedicate to Me: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="3" style="v" />Say to them: ‘Whoever of all your descendants throughout your generations, who goes near the holy things which the children of Israel dedicate to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:20, 21; Num. 19:13</char></note>while he has uncleanness upon him, that person shall be cut off from My presence: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" />‘Whatever man of the descendants of Aaron, who is a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 5:2</char></note>leper or has <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:2</char></note>a discharge, shall not eat the holy offerings <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:2; 15:13</char></note>until he is clean. And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:24–28, 39, 40; Num. 19:11</char></note>whoever touches anything made unclean by a corpse, or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:16, 17</char></note>a man who has had an emission of semen, <verse number="5" style="v" />or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:23–28</char></note>whoever touches any creeping thing by which he would be made unclean, or <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:7, 19</char></note>any person by whom he would become unclean, whatever his uncleanness may be— <verse number="6" style="v" />the person who has touched any such thing shall be unclean until evening, and shall not eat the holy offerings unless he <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 15:5</char></note>washes his body with water. <verse number="7" style="v" />And when the sun goes down he shall be clean; and afterward he may eat the holy offerings, because <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 21:22; Num. 18:11, 13</char></note>it is his food. <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:31; Lev. 7:24; 11:39, 40; 17:15; Ezek. 44:31</char></note>Whatever dies naturally or is torn by beasts he shall not eat, to defile himself with it: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />‘They shall therefore keep <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:30</char></note>My ordinance, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 28:43; Lev. 22:16; Num. 18:22</char></note>lest they bear sin for it and die thereby, if they profane it: I the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sanctify them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:33; Lev. 22:13; Num. 3:10</char></note>‘No outsider shall eat the holy offering; one who dwells with the priest, or a hired servant, shall not eat the holy thing. <verse number="11" style="v" />But if the priest <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:44</char></note>buys a person with his money, he may eat it; and one who is born in his house may eat his food. <verse number="12" style="v" />If the priest’s daughter is married to an outsider, she may not eat of the holy offerings. <verse number="13" style="v" />But if the priest’s daughter is a widow or divorced, and has no child, and has returned to her father’s house as in her youth, she may eat her father’s food; but no outsider shall eat it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />‘And if a man eats the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:32</char></note>holy offering unintentionally, then he shall restore a holy offering to the priest, and add one-fifth to it. <verse number="15" style="v" />They shall not profane the holy offerings of the children of Israel, which they offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse number="16" style="v" />or allow them to bear the guilt of trespass when they eat their holy offerings; for I the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sanctify them.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">Offerings Accepted and Not Accepted</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="18" style="v" />“Speak to Aaron and his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:2, 3, 10</char></note>‘Whatever man of the house of Israel, or of the strangers in Israel, who offers his sacrifice for any of his vows or for any of his freewill offerings, which they offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> as a burnt offering— <verse number="19" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:3; Deut. 15:21</char></note>you shall offer of your own free will a male without blemish from the cattle, from the sheep, or from the goats. <verse number="20" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 15:21; 17:1; Mal. 1:8, 14; (Eph. 5:27; Heb. 9:14; 1 Pet. 1:19)</char></note>Whatever has a defect, you shall not offer, for it shall not be acceptable on your behalf. <verse number="21" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1, 6</char></note>whoever offers a sacrifice of a peace offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:3, 8; Ps. 61:8; 65:1; Eccl. 5:4, 5</char></note>to fulfill his vow, or a freewill offering from the cattle or the sheep, it must be perfect to be accepted; there shall be no defect in it. <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:20; Mal. 1:8</char></note>Those that are blind or broken or maimed, or have an ulcer or eczema or scabs, you shall not offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, nor make <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 1:9, 13; 3:3, 5</char></note>an offering by fire of them on the altar to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="23" style="v" />Either a bull or a lamb that has any limb <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 21:18</char></note>too long or too short you may offer as a freewill offering, but for a vow it shall not be accepted.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" />‘You shall not offer to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> what is bruised or crushed, or torn or cut; nor shall you make any offering of them in your land. <verse number="25" style="v" />Nor <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:15, 16</char></note>from a foreigner’s hand shall you offer any of these as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 21:6, 17</char></note>the bread of your God, because their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Mal. 1:14</char></note>corruption is in them, and defects are in them. They shall not be accepted on your behalf.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying: <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:30</char></note>“When a bull or a sheep or a goat is born, it shall be seven days with its mother; and from the eighth day and thereafter it shall be accepted as an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="28" style="v" />Whether it is a cow or ewe, do not kill both her <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 22:6, 7</char></note>and her young on the same day. <verse number="29" style="v" />And when you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:12; Ps. 107:22; 116:17; Amos 4:5</char></note>offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, offer it of your own free will. <verse number="30" style="v" />On the same day it shall be eaten; you shall leave <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:15</char></note>none of it until morning: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:37; Num. 15:40; Deut. 4:40</char></note>“Therefore you shall keep My commandments, and perform them: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 18:21</char></note>You shall not profane My holy name, but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 10:3; Matt. 6:9; Luke 11:2</char></note>I will be hallowed among the children of Israel. I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> who <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:8</char></note>sanctifies you, <verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:36, 37; Num. 15:40; Deut. 4:40</char></note>who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”</para>
	<chapter number="23" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Feasts of the <char style="sc">Lord</char></para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: ‘The feasts of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which you shall proclaim to be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:16</char></note>holy convocations, these are My feasts.</para>
	<para style="s">The Sabbath</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:9; 23:12; 31:15; Lev. 19:3; Deut. 5:13, 14; Luke 13:14</char></note>‘Six days shall work be done, but the seventh day is a Sabbath of solemn rest, a holy convocation. You shall do no work on it; it is the Sabbath of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in all your dwellings.</para>
	<para style="s">The Passover and Unleavened Bread</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:14–16; Lev. 23:2, 37</char></note>‘These are the feasts of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, holy convocations which you shall proclaim at their appointed times. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:1–28; Num. 9:1–5; 28:16–25; Deut. 16:1–8; Josh. 5:10</char></note>On the fourteenth day of the first month at twilight is the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s Passover. <verse number="6" style="v" />And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the Feast of Unleavened Bread to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; seven days you must eat unleavened bread. <verse number="7" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:16; Num. 28:18, 25</char></note>On the first day you shall have a holy convocation; you shall do no customary work on it. <verse number="8" style="v" />But you shall offer an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for seven days. The seventh day shall be a holy convocation; you shall do no customary work on it.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">The Feast of Firstfruits</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="10" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:19; 34:26</char></note>‘When you come into the land which I give to you, and reap its harvest, then you shall bring a sheaf of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rom. 11:16); James 1:18; Rev. 14:4</char></note>the firstfruits of your harvest to the priest. <verse number="11" style="v" />He shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:24</char></note>wave the sheaf before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, to be accepted on your behalf; on the day after the Sabbath the priest shall wave it. <verse number="12" style="v" />And you shall offer on that day, when you wave the sheaf, a male lamb of the first year, without blemish, as a burnt offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="13" style="v" />Its grain offering shall be two-tenths of an ephah of fine flour mixed with oil, an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, for a sweet aroma; and its drink offering shall be of wine, one-fourth of a hin. <verse number="14" style="v" />You shall eat neither bread nor parched grain nor fresh grain until the same day that you have brought an offering to your God; it shall be a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</para>
	<para style="s">The Feast of Weeks</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />‘And you shall count for yourselves from the day after the Sabbath, from the day that you brought the sheaf of the wave offering: seven Sabbaths shall be completed. <verse number="16" style="v" />Count <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 2:1</char></note>fifty days to the day after the seventh Sabbath; then you shall offer <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 28:26</char></note>a new grain offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="17" style="v" />You shall bring from your dwellings two wave loaves of two-tenths of an ephah. They shall be of fine flour; they shall be baked with leaven. They are <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:16, 19; Num. 15:17–21</char></note>the firstfruits to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="18" style="v" />And you shall offer with the bread seven lambs of the first year, without blemish, one young bull, and two rams. They shall be as a burnt offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, with their grain offering and their drink offerings, an offering made by fire for a sweet aroma to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then you shall sacrifice <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 4:23, 28; Num. 28:30; (2 Cor. 5:21)</char></note>one kid of the goats as a sin offering, and two male lambs of the first year as a sacrifice of a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 3:1</char></note>peace offering. <verse number="20" style="v" />The priest shall wave them with the bread of the firstfruits as a wave offering before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, with the two lambs. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 14:13; Num. 18:12; Deut. 18:4</char></note>They shall be holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for the priest. <verse number="21" style="v" />And you shall proclaim on the same day that it is a holy convocation to you. You shall do no customary work on it. It shall be a statute forever in all your dwellings throughout your generations.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:9, 10; Deut. 24:19–22; Ruth 2:2, 15</char></note>‘When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not wholly reap the corners of your field when you reap, nor shall you gather any gleaning from your harvest. You shall leave them for the poor and for the stranger: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">The Feast of Trumpets</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="24" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying: ‘In the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 29:1</char></note>seventh month, on the first day of the month, you shall have a sabbath-rest, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:9</char></note>a memorial of blowing of trumpets, a holy convocation. <verse number="25" style="v" />You shall do no customary work on it; and you shall offer an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ ”</para>
	<para style="s">The Day of Atonement</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying: <verse number="27" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:1–34; 25:9; Num. 29:7</char></note>“Also the tenth day of this seventh month shall be the Day of Atonement. It shall be a holy convocation for you; you shall afflict your souls, and offer an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="28" style="v" />And you shall do no work on that same day, for it is the Day of Atonement, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 16:34</char></note>to make atonement for you before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. <verse number="29" style="v" />For any person who is not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 22:12; Jer. 31:9; Ezek. 7:16</char></note>afflicted in soul on that same day <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:14; Lev. 13:46; Num. 5:2</char></note>shall be cut off from his people. <verse number="30" style="v" />And any person who does any work on that same day, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:3–6</char></note>that person I will destroy from among his people. <verse number="31" style="v" />You shall do no manner of work; it shall be a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwellings. <verse number="32" style="v" />It shall be to you a sabbath of solemn rest, and you shall afflict your souls; on the ninth day of the month at evening, from evening to evening, you shall celebrate your sabbath.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Feast of Tabernacles</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="34" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, saying: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:16; Num. 29:12; Deut. 16:13–16; Ezra 3:4; Neh. 8:14; Zech. 14:16–19; John 7:2</char></note>‘The fifteenth day of this seventh month shall be the Feast of Tabernacles for seven days to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="35" style="v" />On the first day there shall be a holy convocation. You shall do no customary work on it. <verse number="36" style="v" />For seven days you shall offer an <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 29:12–34</char></note>offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 29:35–38; Neh. 8:18; John 7:37</char></note>On the eighth day you shall have a holy convocation, and you shall offer an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. It is a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 16:8; 2 Chr. 7:8</char></note>sacred assembly, and you shall do no customary work on it.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:2, 4</char></note>‘These are the feasts of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> which you shall proclaim to be holy convocations, to offer an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, a burnt offering and a grain offering, a sacrifice and drink offerings, everything on its day— <verse number="38" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 29:39</char></note>besides the Sabbaths of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, besides your gifts, besides all your vows, and besides all your freewill offerings which you give to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />‘Also on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 23:16; Deut. 16:13</char></note>gathered in the fruit of the land, you shall keep the feast of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for seven days; on the first day there shall be a sabbath-rest, and on the eighth day a sabbath-rest. <verse number="40" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 8:15</char></note>you shall take for yourselves on the first day the fruit of beautiful trees, branches of palm trees, the boughs of leafy trees, and willows of the brook; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 12:7; 16:14, 15</char></note>and you shall rejoice before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God for seven days. <verse number="41" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 29:12; Neh. 8:18</char></note>You shall keep it as a feast to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for seven days in the year. It shall be a statute forever in your generations. You shall celebrate it in the seventh month. <verse number="42" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 4:6)</char></note>You shall dwell in booths for seven days. <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 8:14–16</char></note>All who are native Israelites shall dwell in booths, <verse number="43" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 13:14; Deut. 31:13; Ps. 78:5</char></note>that your generations may <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 10:2</char></note>know that I made the children of Israel dwell in booths when <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:33</char></note>I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" />So Moses <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:2</char></note>declared to the children of Israel the feasts of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<chapter number="24" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Care of the Tabernacle Lamps</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying: <verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 27:20, 21</char></note>“Command the children of Israel that they bring to you pure oil of pressed olives for the light, to make the lamps burn continually. <verse number="3" style="v" />Outside the veil of the Testimony, in the tabernacle of meeting, Aaron shall be in charge of it from evening until morning before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> continually; it shall be a statute forever in your generations. <verse number="4" style="v" />He shall be in charge of the lamps on <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:31; 31:8; 37:17</char></note>the pure gold lampstand before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> continually.</para>
	<para style="s">The Bread of the Tabernacle</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" />“And you shall take fine flour and bake twelve <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:30; 39:36; 40:23</char></note>cakes with it. Two-tenths of an ephah shall be in each cake. <verse number="6" style="v" />You shall set them in two rows, six in a row, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:23, 24; 1 Kin. 7:48; 2 Chr. 4:19; 13:11; Heb. 9:2</char></note>on the pure gold table before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="7" style="v" />And you shall put pure frankincense on each row, that it may be on the bread for a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 2:2, 9, 16</char></note>memorial, an offering made by fire to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 4:7; 1 Chr. 9:32; 2 Chr. 2:4; Matt. 12:4, 5</char></note>Every Sabbath he shall set it in order before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> continually, being taken from the children of Israel by an everlasting covenant. <verse number="9" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 21:6; Matt. 12:4; Mark 2:26; Luke 6:4</char></note>it shall be for Aaron and his sons, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 29:33; Lev. 8:31</char></note>and they shall eat it in a holy place; for it is most holy to him from the offerings of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made by fire, by a perpetual statute.”</para>
	<para style="s">The Penalty for Blasphemy</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" />Now the son of an Israelite woman, whose father was an Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel; and this Israelite woman’s son and a man of Israel fought each other in the camp. <verse number="11" style="v" />And the Israelite woman’s son <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:28</char></note>blasphemed the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 1:5, 11, 22; Is. 8:21</char></note>cursed; and so they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 18:22, 26</char></note>brought him to Moses. (His mother’s name was Shelomith the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan.) <verse number="12" style="v" />Then they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 15:34</char></note>put him in custody, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 27:5</char></note>that the mind of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> might be shown to them.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="14" style="v" />“Take outside the camp him who has cursed; then let all who heard him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 13:9; 17:7</char></note>lay their hands on his head, and let all the congregation stone him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" />“Then you shall speak to the children of Israel, saying: ‘Whoever curses his God <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 20:17; Num. 9:13</char></note>shall bear his sin. <verse number="16" style="v" />And whoever <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:7; 1 Kin. 21:10, 13; (Matt. 12:31; Mark 3:28, 29)</char></note>blasphemes the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> shall surely be put to death. All the congregation shall certainly stone him, the stranger as well as him who is born in the land. When he blasphemes the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, he shall be put to death.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 9:6; Ex. 21:12; Num. 35:30, 31; Deut. 19:11, 12; 27:24</char></note>‘Whoever kills any man shall surely be put to death. <verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 24:21</char></note>Whoever kills an animal shall make it good, animal for animal.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" />‘If a man causes disfigurement of his neighbor, as <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 21:24</char></note>he has done, so shall it be done to him— <verse number="20" style="v" />fracture for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 21:23; Deut. 19:21</char></note>fracture, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Matt. 5:38, 39)</char></note>eye for eye, tooth for tooth; as he has caused disfigurement of a man, so shall it be done to him. <verse number="21" style="v" />And whoever kills an animal shall restore it; but whoever kills a man shall be put to death. <verse number="22" style="v" />You shall have <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 12:49; Lev. 19:33–37; Num. 9:14; 15:15, 16, 29</char></note>the same law for the stranger and for one from your own country; for I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />Then Moses spoke to the children of Israel; and they took outside the camp him who had cursed, and stoned him with stones. So the children of Israel did as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded Moses.</para>
	<chapter number="25" style="c" />
	<para style="s">The Sabbath of the Seventh Year</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses on Mount <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:46</char></note>Sinai, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: ‘When you come into the land which I give you, then the land shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:34, 35</char></note>keep a sabbath to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="3" style="v" />Six years you shall sow your field, and six years you shall prune your vineyard, and gather its fruit; <verse number="4" style="v" />but in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 15:1; Neh. 10:31</char></note>seventh year there shall be a sabbath of solemn <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Heb. 4:9)</char></note>rest for the land, a sabbath to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. You shall neither sow your field nor prune your vineyard. <verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:29</char></note>What grows of its own accord of your harvest you shall not reap, nor gather the grapes of your untended vine, for it is a year of rest for the land. <verse number="6" style="v" />And the sabbath produce of the land shall be food for you: for you, your male and female servants, your hired man, and the stranger who dwells with you, <verse number="7" style="v" />for your livestock and the beasts that are in your land—all its produce shall be for food.</para>
	<para style="s">The Year of Jubilee</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />‘And you shall count seven sabbaths of years for yourself, seven times seven years; and the time of the seven sabbaths of years shall be to you forty-nine years. <verse number="9" style="v" />Then you shall cause the trumpet of the Jubilee to sound on the tenth day of the seventh month; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 23:24, 27</char></note>on the Day of Atonement you shall make the trumpet to sound throughout all your land. <verse number="10" style="v" />And you shall consecrate the fiftieth year, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 61:2; 63:4; Jer. 34:8, 15, 17; (Luke 4:19)</char></note>proclaim liberty throughout all the land to all its inhabitants. It shall be a Jubilee for you; and each of you shall return to his possession, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:13, 28, 54; Num. 36:4</char></note>and each of you shall return to his family. <verse number="11" style="v" />That fiftieth year shall be a Jubilee to you; in it <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:5</char></note>you shall neither sow nor reap what grows of its own accord, nor gather the grapes of your untended vine. <verse number="12" style="v" />For it is the Jubilee; it shall be holy to you; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:6, 7</char></note>you shall eat its produce from the field.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:10; 27:24; Num. 36:4</char></note>‘In this Year of Jubilee, each of you shall return to his possession. <verse number="14" style="v" />And if you sell anything to your neighbor or buy from your neighbor’s hand, you shall not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:13</char></note>oppress one another. <verse number="15" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:18, 23</char></note>According to the number of years after the Jubilee you shall buy from your neighbor, and according to the number of years of crops he shall sell to you. <verse number="16" style="v" />According to the multitude of years you shall increase its price, and according to the fewer number of years you shall diminish its price; for he sells to you according to the number of the years of the crops. <verse number="17" style="v" />Therefore <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:14; Prov. 14:31; 22:22; Jer. 7:5, 6; 1 Thess. 4:6</char></note>you shall not oppress one another, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:14, 32; 25:43</char></note>but you shall fear your God; for I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="s">Provisions for the Seventh Year</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:37</char></note>‘So you shall observe My statutes and keep My judgments, and perform them; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:5; Deut. 12:10; Ps. 4:8; Jer. 23:6</char></note>and you will dwell in the land in safety. <verse number="19" style="v" />Then the land will yield its fruit, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:5; Ezek. 34:25</char></note>you will eat your fill, and dwell there in safety.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" />‘And if you say, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Matt. 6:25, 31</char></note>“What shall we eat in the seventh year, since <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:4, 5</char></note>we shall not sow nor gather in our produce?” <verse number="21" style="v" />Then I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:8</char></note>command My blessing on you in the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 16:29</char></note>sixth year, and it will bring forth produce enough for three years. <verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 19:29</char></note>And you shall sow in the eighth year, and eat <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:10; Josh. 5:11</char></note>old produce until the ninth year; until its produce comes in, you shall eat of the old harvest.</para>
	<para style="s">Redemption of Property</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" />‘The land shall not be sold permanently, for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:5; 2 Chr. 7:20</char></note>the land is Mine; for you are <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 23:4; Ex. 6:4; 1 Chr. 29:15; Ps. 39:12; Heb. 11:13; 1 Pet. 2:11</char></note>strangers and sojourners with Me. <verse number="24" style="v" />And in all the land of your possession you shall grant redemption of the land.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ruth 2:20; 4:4, 6</char></note>‘If one of your brethren becomes poor, and has sold some of his possession, and if <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 5:8; Ruth 3:2, 9, 12; (Job 19:25); Jer. 32:7, 8</char></note>his redeeming relative comes to redeem it, then he may redeem what his brother sold. <verse number="26" style="v" />Or if the man has no one to redeem it, but he himself becomes able to redeem it, <verse number="27" style="v" />then <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:50–52</char></note>let him count the years since its sale, and restore the remainder to the man to whom he sold it, that he may return to his possession. <verse number="28" style="v" />But if he is not able to have it restored to himself, then what was sold shall remain in the hand of him who bought it until the Year of Jubilee; <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:10, 13</char></note>and in the Jubilee it shall be released, and he shall return to his possession.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" />‘If a man sells a house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it is sold; within a full year he may redeem it. <verse number="30" style="v" />But if it is not redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house in the walled city shall belong permanently to him who bought it, throughout his generations. It shall not be released in the Jubilee. <verse number="31" style="v" />However the houses of villages which have no wall around them shall be counted as the fields of the country. They may be redeemed, and they shall be released in the Jubilee. <verse number="32" style="v" />Nevertheless <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:1–8; Josh. 21:2</char></note>the cities of the Levites, and the houses in the cities of their possession, the Levites may redeem at any time. <verse number="33" style="v" />And if a man purchases a house from the Levites, then the house that was sold in the city of his possession shall be released in the Jubilee; for the houses in the cities of the Levites are their possession among the children of Israel. <verse number="34" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 35:2–5</char></note>the field of the common-land of their cities may not be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 4:36, 37</char></note>sold, for it is their perpetual possession.</para>
	<para style="s">Lending to the Poor</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" />‘If one of your brethren becomes poor, and falls into poverty among you, then you shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 15:7–11; 24:14, 15; Luke 6:35; 1 John 3:17</char></note>help him, like a stranger or a sojourner, that he may live with you. <verse number="36" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 22:25; Deut. 23:19, 20</char></note>Take no usury or interest from him; but <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Neh. 5:9</char></note>fear your God, that your brother may live with you. <verse number="37" style="v" />You shall not lend him your money for usury, nor lend him your food at a profit. <verse number="38" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 11:45; 22:32, 33</char></note>I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan and to be your God.</para>
	<para style="s">The Law Concerning Slavery</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" />‘And if one of your brethren who dwells by you becomes poor, and sells himself to you, you shall not compel him to serve as a slave. <verse number="40" style="v" />As a hired servant and a sojourner he shall be with you, and shall serve you until the Year of Jubilee. <verse number="41" style="v" />And then he shall depart from you—he and his children <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 21:3</char></note>with him—and shall return to his own family. He shall return to the possession of his fathers. <verse number="42" style="v" />For they are <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:55; (Rom. 6:22; 1 Cor. 7:22, 23)</char></note>My servants, whom I brought out of the land of Egypt; they shall not be sold as slaves. <verse number="43" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Eph. 6:9; Col. 4:1</char></note>You shall not rule over him <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 1:13, 14; Lev. 25:46, 53; Ezek. 34:4</char></note>with rigor, but you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 1:17; Deut. 25:18; Mal. 3:5</char></note>shall fear your God. <verse number="44" style="v" />And as for your male and female slaves whom you may have—from the nations that are around you, from them you may buy male and female slaves. <verse number="45" style="v" />Moreover you may buy <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Is. 56:3, 6, 7)</char></note>the children of the strangers who dwell among you, and their families who are with you, which they beget in your land; and they shall become your property. <verse number="46" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 14:2</char></note>you may take them as an inheritance for your children after you, to inherit them as a possession; they shall be your permanent slaves. But regarding your brethren, the children of Israel, you shall not rule over one another with rigor.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" />‘Now if a sojourner or stranger close to you becomes rich, and one of your brethren who dwells by him becomes poor, and sells himself to the stranger or sojourner close to you, or to a member of the stranger’s family, <verse number="48" style="v" />after he is sold he may be redeemed again. One of his brothers may redeem him; <verse number="49" style="v" />or his uncle or his uncle’s son may redeem him; or anyone who is near of kin to him in his family may redeem him; or if he is able he may redeem himself. <verse number="50" style="v" />Thus he shall reckon with him who bought him: The price of his release shall be according to the number of years, from the year that he was sold to him until the Year of Jubilee; it shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 7:1; Is. 16:14</char></note>according to the time of a hired servant for him. <verse number="51" style="v" />If there are still many years remaining, according to them he shall repay the price of his redemption from the money with which he was bought. <verse number="52" style="v" />And if there remain but a few years until the Year of Jubilee, then he shall reckon with him, and according to his years he shall repay him the price of his redemption. <verse number="53" style="v" />He shall be with him as a yearly hired servant, and he shall not rule with rigor over him in your sight. <verse number="54" style="v" />And if he is not redeemed in these years, then he shall be released in the Year of Jubilee—he and his children with him. <verse number="55" style="v" />For the children of Israel are servants to Me; they are My servants whom I brought out of the land of Egypt: I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<chapter number="26" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Promise of Blessing and Retribution</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="1" style="v" />‘You shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 20:4, 5; Deut. 4:15–18; 5:8</char></note>not make idols for yourselves;</para>
	<para style="q2">neither a carved image nor a sacred pillar shall you rear up for yourselves;</para>
	<para style="q2">nor shall you set up an engraved stone in your land, to bow down to it;</para>
	<para style="q2">for I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="2" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 19:30</char></note>You shall keep My Sabbaths and reverence My sanctuary:</para>
	<para style="q2">I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="3" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:1–14</char></note>‘If you walk in My statutes and keep My commandments, and perform them,</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="4" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 30:23</char></note>then I will give you rain in its season, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 67:6</char></note>the land shall yield its produce, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="5" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 11:15; Joel 2:19, 26; Amos 9:13</char></note>Your threshing shall last till the time of vintage, and the vintage shall last till the time of sowing;</para>
	<para style="q2">you shall eat your bread to the full, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:18, 19; Ezek. 34:25</char></note>dwell in your land safely.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="6" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 45:7</char></note>I will give peace in the land, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Job 11:19; Ps. 4:8; Zeph. 3:13</char></note>you shall lie down, and none will make you afraid;</para>
	<para style="q2">I will rid the land of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 17:25; Hos. 2:18</char></note>evil beasts,</para>
	<para style="q2">and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 14:17</char></note>the sword will not go through your land.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="7" style="v" />You will chase your enemies, and they shall fall by the sword before you.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="8" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:30; Judg. 7:7–12</char></note>Five of you shall chase a hundred, and a hundred of you shall put ten thousand to flight;</para>
	<para style="q2">your enemies shall fall by the sword before you.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="9" style="v" />‘For I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 2:25; 2 Kin. 13:23</char></note>look on you favorably and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:6, 7; Ps. 107:38</char></note>make you fruitful, multiply you and confirm My <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 17:1–7</char></note>covenant with you.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="10" style="v" />You shall eat the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:22</char></note>old harvest, and clear out the old because of the new.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="11" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 25:8; 29:45, 46; Josh. 22:19; Ps. 76:2; Ezek. 37:26; Rev. 21:3</char></note>I will set My tabernacle among you, and My soul shall not abhor you.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="12" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 23:14; (2 Cor. 6:16)</char></note>I will walk among you and be your God, and you shall be My people.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="13" style="v" />I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, that you should not be their slaves;</para>
	<para style="q2">I have broken the bands of your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 27:40</char></note>yoke and made you walk upright.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="14" style="v" />‘But if you do not obey Me, and do not observe all these commandments,</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="15" style="v" />and if you despise My statutes, or if your soul abhors My judgments, so that you do not perform all My commandments, but break My covenant,</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="16" style="v" />I also will do this to you:</para>
	<para style="q2">I will even appoint terror over you, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:22</char></note>wasting disease and fever which shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:33</char></note>consume the eyes and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 24:23; 33:10</char></note>cause sorrow of heart.</para>
	<para style="q2">And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 6:3–6; Job 31:8; Mic. 6:15</char></note>you shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="17" style="v" />I will set <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 34:16</char></note>My face against you, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:25; 1 Sam. 4:10; 31:1</char></note>you shall be defeated by your enemies.</para>
	<para style="q2"><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 106:41</char></note>Those who hate you shall reign over you, and you shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Prov. 28:1</char></note>flee when no one pursues you.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="18" style="v" />‘And after all this, if you do not obey Me, then I will punish you <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Sam. 2:5</char></note>seven times more for your sins.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="19" style="v" />I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 25:11</char></note>break the pride of your power;</para>
	<para style="q2">I <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:23</char></note>will make your heavens like iron and your earth like bronze.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="20" style="v" />And your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 127:1; Is. 17:10, 11; 49:4; Jer. 12:13</char></note>strength shall be spent in vain;</para>
	<para style="q2">for your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 4:12; Deut. 11:17</char></note>land shall not yield its produce, nor shall the trees of the land yield their fruit.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="21" style="v" />‘Then, if you walk contrary to Me, and are not willing to obey Me, I will bring on you seven times more plagues, according to your sins.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="22" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 32:24; Ezek. 14:21</char></note>I will also send wild beasts among you, which shall rob you of your children, destroy your livestock, and make you few in number;</para>
	<para style="q2">and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 5:6; 2 Chr. 15:5; Zech. 7:14</char></note>your highways shall be desolate.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="23" style="v" />‘And if <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 2:30; Amos 4:6–12</char></note>by these things you are not reformed by Me, but walk contrary to Me,</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:28, 41; Ps. 18:26</char></note>then I also will walk contrary to you, and I will punish you yet seven times for your sins.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="25" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ezek. 5:17</char></note>I will bring a sword against you that will execute the vengeance of the covenant;</para>
	<para style="q2">when you are gathered together within your cities <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 16:49; Deut. 28:21; 2 Sam. 24:15</char></note>I will send pestilence among you;</para>
	<para style="q2">and you shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="26" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 105:16; Is. 3:1; Ezek. 4:16, 17; 5:16</char></note>When I have cut off your supply of bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall bring back your bread by weight, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Mic. 6:14; Hag. 1:6</char></note>and you shall eat and not be satisfied.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="27" style="v" />‘And after all this, if you do not obey Me, but walk contrary to Me,</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="28" style="v" />then I also will walk contrary to you in fury;</para>
	<para style="q2">and I, even I, will chastise you seven times for your sins.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:53; 2 Kin. 6:28, 29</char></note>You shall eat the flesh of your sons, and you shall eat the flesh of your daughters.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="30" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">1 Kin. 13:2; 2 Chr. 34:3; Is. 27:9; Ezek. 6:3–6, 13</char></note>I will destroy your high places, cut down your incense altars, and cast your carcasses on the lifeless forms of your idols;</para>
	<para style="q2">and My soul shall abhor you.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="31" style="v" />I will lay your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Kin. 25:4, 10</char></note>cities waste and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 36:19; Ps. 74:7</char></note>bring your sanctuaries to desolation, and I will not <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 1:11–15</char></note>smell the fragrance of your sweet aromas.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="32" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 9:11; 18:16</char></note>I will bring the land to desolation, and your enemies who dwell in it shall be astonished at it.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="33" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:27; Ps. 44:11; Ezek. 12:15; 20:23; 22:15; Zech. 7:14</char></note>I will scatter you among the nations and draw out a sword after you;</para>
	<para style="q2">your land shall be desolate and your cities waste.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:43; 2 Chr. 36:21</char></note>Then the land shall enjoy its sabbaths as long as it lies desolate and you are in your enemies’ land;</para>
	<para style="q2">then the land shall rest and enjoy its sabbaths.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="35" style="v" />As long as it lies desolate it shall rest—</para>
	<para style="q2">for the time it did not rest on your <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:2</char></note>sabbaths when you dwelt in it.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="36" style="v" />‘And as for those of you who are left, I will send <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Is. 30:17; Lam. 1:3, 6; 4:19; Ezek. 21:7, 12, 15</char></note>faintness into their hearts in the lands of their enemies;</para>
	<para style="q2">the sound of a shaken leaf shall cause them to flee;</para>
	<para style="q2">they shall flee as though fleeing from a sword, and they shall fall when no one pursues.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="37" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Judg. 7:22; 1 Sam. 14:15, 16; Is. 10:4</char></note>They shall stumble over one another, as it were before a sword, when no one pursues;</para>
	<para style="q2">and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Josh. 7:12, 13; Judg. 2:14</char></note>you shall have no power to stand before your enemies.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="38" style="v" />You shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:26</char></note>perish among the nations, and the land of your enemies shall eat you up.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="39" style="v" />And those of you who are left <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 28:65; Ezek. 4:17; 33:10; Zech. 10:9</char></note>shall waste away in their iniquity in your enemies’ lands;</para>
	<para style="q2">also in their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 34:7</char></note>fathers’ iniquities, which are with them, they shall waste away.</para>
	<para style="q1"><verse number="40" style="v" />‘But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 5:7; 1 Kin. 8:33, 34; Neh. 9:2; Luke 15:18; (1 John 1:9)</char></note>if they confess their iniquity and the iniquity of their fathers, with their unfaithfulness in which they were unfaithful to Me, and that they also have walked contrary to Me,</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="41" style="v" />and that I also have walked contrary to them and have brought them into the land of their enemies;</para>
	<para style="q2">if their <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Acts 7:51; Rom. 2:29</char></note>uncircumcised hearts are <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">2 Chr. 12:6, 7, 12; 1 Pet. 5:5, 6</char></note>humbled, and they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 39:9; 51:3, 4; Dan. 9:7</char></note>accept their guilt—</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="42" style="v" />then I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 2:24; 6:5; Ps. 106:45; Ezek. 16:60</char></note>remember My covenant with Jacob, and My covenant with Isaac and My covenant with Abraham I will remember;</para>
	<para style="q2">I will <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 136:23</char></note>remember the land.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="43" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:34, 35</char></note>The land also shall be left empty by them, and will enjoy its sabbaths while it lies desolate without them;</para>
	<para style="q2">they will accept their guilt, because they <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:15</char></note>despised My judgments and because their soul abhorred My statutes.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="44" style="v" />Yet for all that, when they are in the land of their enemies, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Deut. 4:31; 2 Kin. 13:23; Jer. 30:11; (Rom. 11:1–36)</char></note>I will not cast them away, nor shall I abhor them, to utterly destroy them and break My covenant with them;</para>
	<para style="q2">for I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God.</para>
	<para style="q2"><verse number="45" style="v" />But <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">(Rom. 11:28)</char></note>for their sake I will remember the covenant of their ancestors, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 22:33; 25:38</char></note>whom I brought out of the land of Egypt <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ps. 98:2; Ezek. 20:9, 14, 22</char></note>in the sight of the nations, that I might be their God:</para>
	<para style="q2">I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:34; Deut. 6:1; 12:1; (John 1:17)</char></note>These are the statutes and judgments and laws which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made between Himself and the children of Israel <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:1</char></note>on Mount Sinai by the hand of Moses.</para>
	<chapter number="27" style="c" />
	<para style="s">Redeeming Persons and Property Dedicated to God</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" />Now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke to Moses, saying, <verse number="2" style="v" />“Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 7:16; Num. 6:2; Deut. 23:21–23; Judg. 11:30, 31, 39</char></note>‘When a man consecrates by a vow certain persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, according to your valuation, <verse number="3" style="v" />if your valuation is of a male from twenty years old up to sixty years old, then your valuation shall be fifty shekels of silver, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:13; Lev. 27:25; Num. 3:47; 18:16</char></note>according to the shekel of the sanctuary. <verse number="4" style="v" />If it is a female, then your valuation shall be thirty shekels; <verse number="5" style="v" />and if from five years old up to twenty years old, then your valuation for a male shall be twenty shekels, and for a female ten shekels; <verse number="6" style="v" />and if from a month old up to five years old, then your valuation for a male shall be five shekels of silver, and for a female your valuation shall be three shekels of silver; <verse number="7" style="v" />and if from sixty years old and above, if it is a male, then your valuation shall be fifteen shekels, and for a female ten shekels.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" />‘But if he is too poor to pay your valuation, then he shall present himself before the priest, and the priest shall set a value for <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 5:11; 14:21–24</char></note>him; according to the ability of him who vowed, the priest shall value him.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" />‘If it is an animal that men may bring as an offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, all that anyone gives to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> shall be holy. <verse number="10" style="v" />He shall not substitute it or exchange it, good for bad or bad for good; and if he at all exchanges animal for animal, then both it and the one exchanged for it shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:33</char></note>holy. <verse number="11" style="v" />If it is an unclean animal which they do not offer as a sacrifice to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, then he shall present the animal before the priest; <verse number="12" style="v" />and the priest shall set a value for it, whether it is good or bad; as you, the priest, value it, so it shall be. <verse number="13" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 6:5; 22:14; 27:15, 19</char></note>But if he wants at all to redeem it, then he must add one-fifth to your valuation.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" />‘And when a man dedicates his house to be holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, then the priest shall set a value for it, whether it is good or bad; as the priest values it, so it shall stand. <verse number="15" style="v" />If he who dedicated it wants to redeem his house, then he must add one-fifth of the money of your valuation to it, and it shall be his.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" />‘If a man dedicates to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> part of a field of his possession, then your valuation shall be according to the seed for it. A homer of barley seed shall be valued at fifty shekels of silver. <verse number="17" style="v" />If he dedicates his field from the Year of Jubilee, according to your valuation it shall stand. <verse number="18" style="v" />But if he dedicates his field after the Jubilee, then the priest shall <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:15, 16, 28</char></note>reckon to him the money due according to the years that remain till the Year of Jubilee, and it shall be deducted from your valuation. <verse number="19" style="v" />And if he who dedicates the field ever wishes to redeem it, then he must add one-fifth of the money of your valuation to it, and it shall belong to him. <verse number="20" style="v" />But if he does not want to redeem the field, or if he has sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed anymore; <verse number="21" style="v" />but the field, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:10, 28, 31</char></note>when it is released in the Jubilee, shall be holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as a <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:28</char></note>devoted field; it shall be <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 18:14; Ezek. 44:29</char></note>the possession of the priest.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" />‘And if a man dedicates to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> a field which he has bought, which is not the field of <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:10, 25</char></note>his possession, <verse number="23" style="v" />then the priest shall reckon to him the worth of your valuation, up to the Year of Jubilee, and he shall give your valuation on that day as a holy offering to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="24" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 25:10–13, 28</char></note>In the Year of Jubilee the field shall return to him from whom it was bought, to the one who owned the land as a possession. <verse number="25" style="v" />And all your valuations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 30:13; Lev. 27:3; Num. 3:47; 18:16; Ezek. 45:12</char></note>twenty gerahs to the shekel.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" />‘But the <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 13:2, 12; 22:30</char></note>firstborn of the animals, which should be the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s firstborn, no man shall dedicate; whether it is an ox or sheep, it is the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s. <verse number="27" style="v" />And if it is an unclean animal, then he shall redeem it according to your valuation, and <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:11, 12</char></note>shall add one-fifth to it; or if it is not redeemed, then it shall be sold according to your valuation.</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:21; Num. 18:14; Josh. 6:17–19</char></note>‘Nevertheless no devoted offering that a man may devote to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> of all that he has, both man and beast, or the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed; every devoted offering is most holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="29" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Num. 21:2</char></note>No person under the ban, who may become doomed to destruction among men, shall be redeemed, but shall surely be put to death. <verse number="30" style="v" />And <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Gen. 28:22; Num. 18:21, 24; 2 Chr. 31:5, 6, 12; Neh. 13:12; Mal. 3:8</char></note>all the tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land or of the fruit of the tree, is the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s. It is holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="31" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:13</char></note>If a man wants at all to redeem any of his tithes, he shall add one-fifth to it. <verse number="32" style="v" />And concerning the tithe of the herd or the flock, of whatever <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Jer. 33:13; Ezek. 20:37; Mic. 7:14</char></note>passes under the rod, the tenth one shall be holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse number="33" style="v" />He shall not inquire whether it is good or bad, <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 27:10</char></note>nor shall he exchange it; and if he exchanges it at all, then both it and the one exchanged for it shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed.’ ”</para>
	<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" /><note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Lev. 26:46; Deut. 4:5; Mal. 4:4</char></note>These are the commandments which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded Moses for the children of Israel on Mount <note style="x" caller="-"><char style="xt" closed="false">Ex. 19:1–6, 25; (Heb. 12:18–29)</char></note>Sinai.</para>
	
</usx>