<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2KI" style="id">- English-UK: New International Version® (Anglicised) NIV® 2011 (Revised format)</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1973, 1978, 1984, 2011 by Biblica, Inc.®</para>
  <para style="h">2 Kings</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 Kings</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Kings</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Ki</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 Kings</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">See the Invitation to Samuel-Kings.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2KI 1"/>
  <para style="s1">The <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s judgment on Ahaziah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 1:1"/>After Ahab’s death, Moab rebelled against Israel. <verse eid="2KI 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 1:2"/>Now Ahaziah had fallen through the lattice of his upper room in Samaria and injured himself. So he sent messengers, saying to them, ‘Go and consult Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron, to see if I will recover from this injury.’<verse eid="2KI 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 1:3"/>But the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Elijah the Tishbite, ‘Go up and meet the messengers of the king of Samaria and ask them, “Is it because there is no God in Israel that you are going off to consult Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron?” <verse eid="2KI 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 1:4"/>Therefore this is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: “You will not leave the bed you are lying on. You will certainly die!” ’ So Elijah went.<verse eid="2KI 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 1:5"/>When the messengers returned to the king, he asked them, ‘Why have you come back?’<verse eid="2KI 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 1:6"/>‘A man came to meet us,’ they replied. ‘And he said to us, “Go back to the king who sent you and tell him, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: is it because there is no God in Israel that you are sending messengers to consult Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron? Therefore you will not leave the bed you are lying on. You will certainly die!’ ” ’<verse eid="2KI 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 1:7"/>The king asked them, ‘What kind of man was it who came to meet you and told you this?’<verse eid="2KI 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 1:8"/>They replied, ‘He had a garment of hair<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">He was a hairy man</char></note> and had a leather belt round his waist.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 1:8">The king said, ‘That was Elijah the Tishbite.’<verse eid="2KI 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 1:9"/>Then he sent to Elijah a captain with his company of fifty men. The captain went up to Elijah, who was sitting on the top of a hill, and said to him, ‘Man of God, the king says, “Come down!” ’<verse eid="2KI 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 1:10"/>Elijah answered the captain, ‘If I am a man of God, may fire come down from heaven and consume you and your fifty men!’ Then the fire fell from heaven and consumed the captain and his men.<verse eid="2KI 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 1:11"/>At this the king sent to Elijah another captain with his fifty men. The captain said to him, ‘Man of God, this is what the king says, “Come down at once!” ’<verse eid="2KI 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 1:12"/>‘If I am a man of God,’ Elijah replied, ‘may fire come down from heaven and consume you and your fifty men!’ Then the fire of God fell from heaven and consumed him and his fifty men.<verse eid="2KI 1:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 1:13"/>So the king sent a third captain with his fifty men. This third captain went up and fell on his knees before Elijah. ‘Man of God,’ he begged, ‘please have respect for my life and the lives of these fifty men, your servants! <verse eid="2KI 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 1:14"/>See, fire has fallen from heaven and consumed the first two captains and all their men. But now have respect for my life!’<verse eid="2KI 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 1:15"/>The angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Elijah, ‘Go down with him; do not be afraid of him.’ So Elijah got up and went down with him to the king.<verse eid="2KI 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 1:16"/>He told the king, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: is it because there is no God in Israel for you to consult that you have sent messengers to consult Baal-Zebub, the god of Ekron? Because you have done this, you will never leave the bed you are lying on. You will certainly die!’ <verse eid="2KI 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 1:17"/>So he died, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that Elijah had spoken.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 1:17">Because Ahaziah had no son, Joram<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jehoram, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Joram</char></note> succeeded him as king in the second year of Jehoram son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah. <verse eid="2KI 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 1:18"/>As for all the other events of Ahaziah’s reign, and what he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel?<verse eid="2KI 1:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2KI 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Elijah taken up to heaven</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 2:1"/>When the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was about to take Elijah up to heaven in a whirlwind, Elijah and Elisha were on their way from Gilgal. <verse eid="2KI 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 2:2"/>Elijah said to Elisha, ‘Stay here; the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has sent me to Bethel.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 2:2">But Elisha said, ‘As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives and as you live, I will not leave you.’ So they went down to Bethel.<verse eid="2KI 2:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 2:3"/>The company of the prophets at Bethel came out to Elisha and asked, ‘Do you know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is going to take your master from you today?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 2:3">‘Yes, I know,’ Elisha replied, ‘so be quiet.’<verse eid="2KI 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 2:4"/>Then Elijah said to him, ‘Stay here, Elisha; the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has sent me to Jericho.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 2:4">And he replied, ‘As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives and as you live, I will not leave you.’ So they went to Jericho.<verse eid="2KI 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 2:5"/>The company of the prophets at Jericho went up to Elisha and asked him, ‘Do you know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is going to take your master from you today?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 2:5">‘Yes, I know,’ he replied, ‘so be quiet.’<verse eid="2KI 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 2:6"/>Then Elijah said to him, ‘Stay here; the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has sent me to the Jordan.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 2:6">And he replied, ‘As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives and as you live, I will not leave you.’ So the two of them walked on.<verse eid="2KI 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 2:7"/>Fifty men from the company of the prophets went and stood at a distance, facing the place where Elijah and Elisha had stopped at the Jordan. <verse eid="2KI 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 2:8"/>Elijah took his cloak, rolled it up and struck the water with it. The water divided to the right and to the left, and the two of them crossed over on dry ground.<verse eid="2KI 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 2:9"/>When they had crossed, Elijah said to Elisha, ‘Tell me, what can I do for you before I am taken from you?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 2:9">‘Let me inherit a double portion of your spirit,’ Elisha replied.<verse eid="2KI 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 2:10"/>‘You have asked a difficult thing,’ Elijah said, ‘yet if you see me when I am taken from you, it will be yours – otherwise, it will not.’<verse eid="2KI 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 2:11"/>As they were walking along and talking together, suddenly a chariot of fire and horses of fire appeared and separated the two of them, and Elijah went up to heaven in a whirlwind. <verse eid="2KI 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 2:12"/>Elisha saw this and cried out, ‘My father! My father! The chariots and horsemen of Israel!’ And Elisha saw him no more. Then he took hold of his garment and tore it in two.<verse eid="2KI 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 2:13"/>Elisha then picked up Elijah’s cloak that had fallen from him and went back and stood on the bank of the Jordan. <verse eid="2KI 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 2:14"/>He took the cloak that had fallen from Elijah and struck the water with it. ‘Where now is the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Elijah?’ he asked. When he struck the water, it divided to the right and to the left, and he crossed over.<verse eid="2KI 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 2:15"/>The company of the prophets from Jericho, who were watching, said, ‘The spirit of Elijah is resting on Elisha.’ And they went to meet him and bowed to the ground before him. <verse eid="2KI 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 2:16"/>‘Look,’ they said, ‘we your servants have fifty able men. Let them go and look for your master. Perhaps the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has picked him up and set him down on some mountain or in some valley.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 2:16">‘No,’ Elisha replied, ‘do not send them.’<verse eid="2KI 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 2:17"/>But they persisted until he was too embarrassed to refuse. So he said, ‘Send them.’ And they sent fifty men, who searched for three days but did not find him. <verse eid="2KI 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 2:18"/>When they returned to Elisha, who was staying in Jericho, he said to them, ‘Didn’t I tell you not to go?’<verse eid="2KI 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Healing of the water</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 2:19"/>The people of the city said to Elisha, ‘Look, our lord, this town is well situated, as you can see, but the water is bad and the land is unproductive.’<verse eid="2KI 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 2:20"/>‘Bring me a new bowl,’ he said, ‘and put salt in it.’ So they brought it to him.<verse eid="2KI 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 2:21"/>Then he went out to the spring and threw the salt into it, saying, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: “I have healed this water. Never again will it cause death or make the land unproductive.” ’ <verse eid="2KI 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 2:22"/>And the water has remained pure to this day, according to the word Elisha had spoken.<verse eid="2KI 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Elisha is jeered</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 2:23"/>From there Elisha went up to Bethel. As he was walking along the road, some boys came out of the town and jeered at him. ‘Get out of here, baldy!’ they said. ‘Get out of here, baldy!’ <verse eid="2KI 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 2:24"/>He turned round, looked at them and called down a curse on them in the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Then two bears came out of the woods and mauled forty-two of the boys. <verse eid="2KI 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 2:25"/>And he went on to Mount Carmel and from there returned to Samaria.<verse eid="2KI 2:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2KI 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Moab revolts</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 3:1"/>Joram<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jehoram, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Joram</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verse 6</char></note> son of Ahab became king of Israel in Samaria in the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and he reigned for twelve years. <verse eid="2KI 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 3:2"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but not as his father and mother had done. He got rid of the sacred stone of Baal that his father had made. <verse eid="2KI 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 3:3"/>Nevertheless he clung to the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit; he did not turn away from them.<verse eid="2KI 3:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 3:4"/>Now Mesha king of Moab raised sheep, and he had to pay the king of Israel a tribute of a hundred thousand lambs and the wool of a hundred thousand rams. <verse eid="2KI 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 3:5"/>But after Ahab died, the king of Moab rebelled against the king of Israel. <verse eid="2KI 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 3:6"/>So at that time King Joram set out from Samaria and mobilised all Israel. <verse eid="2KI 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 3:7"/>He also sent this message to Jehoshaphat king of Judah: ‘The king of Moab has rebelled against me. Will you go with me to fight against Moab?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 3:7">‘I will go with you,’ he replied. ‘I am as you are, my people as your people, my horses as your horses.’<verse eid="2KI 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 3:8"/>‘By what route shall we attack?’ he asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 3:8">‘Through the Desert of Edom,’ he answered.<verse eid="2KI 3:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 3:9"/>So the king of Israel set out with the king of Judah and the king of Edom. After a roundabout march of seven days, the army had no more water for themselves or for the animals with them.<verse eid="2KI 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 3:10"/>‘What!’ exclaimed the king of Israel. ‘Has the <char style="sc">Lord</char> called us three kings together only to deliver us into the hands of Moab?’<verse eid="2KI 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 3:11"/>But Jehoshaphat asked, ‘Is there no prophet of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> here, through whom we may enquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 3:11">An officer of the king of Israel answered, ‘Elisha son of Shaphat is here. He used to pour water on the hands of Elijah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, he was Elijah’s personal servant.</char></note>’<verse eid="2KI 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 3:12"/>Jehoshaphat said, ‘The word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is with him.’ So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom went down to him.<verse eid="2KI 3:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 3:13"/>Elisha said to the king of Israel, ‘Why do you want to involve me? Go to the prophets of your father and the prophets of your mother.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 3:13">‘No,’ the king of Israel answered, ‘because it was the <char style="sc">Lord</char> who called us three kings together to deliver us into the hands of Moab.’<verse eid="2KI 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 3:14"/>Elisha said, ‘As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> Almighty lives, whom I serve, if I did not have respect for the presence of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, I would not pay any attention to you. <verse eid="2KI 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 3:15"/>But now bring me a harpist.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 3:15">While the harpist was playing, the hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came on Elisha <verse eid="2KI 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 3:16"/>and he said, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: I will fill this valley with pools of water. <verse eid="2KI 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 3:17"/>For this is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: you will see neither wind nor rain, yet this valley will be filled with water, and you, your cattle and your other animals will drink. <verse eid="2KI 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 3:18"/>This is an easy thing in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; he will also deliver Moab into your hands. <verse eid="2KI 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 3:19"/>You will overthrow every fortified city and every major town. You will cut down every good tree, block up all the springs, and ruin every good field with stones.’<verse eid="2KI 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 3:20"/>The next morning, about the time for offering the sacrifice, there it was – water flowing from the direction of Edom! And the land was filled with water.<verse eid="2KI 3:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 3:21"/>Now all the Moabites had heard that the kings had come to fight against them; so every man, young and old, who could bear arms was called up and stationed on the border. <verse eid="2KI 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 3:22"/>When they got up early in the morning, the sun was shining on the water. To the Moabites across the way, the water looked red – like blood. <verse eid="2KI 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 3:23"/>‘That’s blood!’ they said. ‘Those kings must have fought and slaughtered each other. Now to the plunder, Moab!’<verse eid="2KI 3:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 3:24"/>But when the Moabites came to the camp of Israel, the Israelites rose up and fought them until they fled. And the Israelites invaded the land and slaughtered the Moabites. <verse eid="2KI 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 3:25"/>They destroyed the towns, and each man threw a stone on every good field until it was covered. They stopped up all the springs and cut down every good tree. Only Kir Hareseth was left with its stones in place, but men armed with slings surrounded it and attacked it.<verse eid="2KI 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 3:26"/>When the king of Moab saw that the battle had gone against him, he took with him seven hundred swordsmen to break through to the king of Edom, but they failed. <verse eid="2KI 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 3:27"/>Then he took his firstborn son, who was to succeed him as king, and offered him as a sacrifice on the city wall. The fury against Israel was great; they withdrew and returned to their own land.<verse eid="2KI 3:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2KI 4"/>
  <para style="s1">The widow’s olive oil</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 4:1"/>The wife of a man from the company of the prophets cried out to Elisha, ‘Your servant my husband is dead, and you know that he revered the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. But now his creditor is coming to take my two boys as his slaves.’<verse eid="2KI 4:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 4:2"/>Elisha replied to her, ‘How can I help you? Tell me, what do you have in your house?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:2">‘Your servant has nothing there at all,’ she said, ‘except a small jar of olive oil.’<verse eid="2KI 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 4:3"/>Elisha said, ‘Go round and ask all your neighbours for empty jars. Don’t ask for just a few. <verse eid="2KI 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 4:4"/>Then go inside and shut the door behind you and your sons. Pour oil into all the jars, and as each is filled, put it to one side.’<verse eid="2KI 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 4:5"/>She left him and shut the door behind her and her sons. They brought the jars to her and she kept pouring. <verse eid="2KI 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 4:6"/>When all the jars were full, she said to her son, ‘Bring me another one.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:6">But he replied, ‘There is not a jar left.’ Then the oil stopped flowing.<verse eid="2KI 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 4:7"/>She went and told the man of God, and he said, ‘Go, sell the oil and pay your debts. You and your sons can live on what is left.’<verse eid="2KI 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Shunammite’s son restored to life</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 4:8"/>One day Elisha went to Shunem. And a well-to-do woman was there, who urged him to stay for a meal. So whenever he passed by, he stopped there to eat. <verse eid="2KI 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 4:9"/>She said to her husband, ‘I know that this man who often comes our way is a holy man of God. <verse eid="2KI 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 4:10"/>Let’s make a small room on the roof and put in it a bed and a table, a chair and a lamp for him. Then he can stay there whenever he comes to us.’<verse eid="2KI 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 4:11"/>One day when Elisha came, he went up to his room and lay down there. <verse eid="2KI 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 4:12"/>He said to his servant Gehazi, ‘Call the Shunammite.’ So he called her, and she stood before him. <verse eid="2KI 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 4:13"/>Elisha said to him, ‘Tell her, “You have gone to all this trouble for us. Now what can be done for you? Can we speak on your behalf to the king or the commander of the army?” ’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:13">She replied, ‘I have a home among my own people.’<verse eid="2KI 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 4:14"/>‘What can be done for her?’ Elisha asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:14">Gehazi said, ‘She has no son, and her husband is old.’<verse eid="2KI 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 4:15"/>Then Elisha said, ‘Call her.’ So he called her, and she stood in the doorway. <verse eid="2KI 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 4:16"/>‘About this time next year,’ Elisha said, ‘you will hold a son in your arms.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:16">‘No, my lord!’ she objected. ‘Please, man of God, don’t mislead your servant!’<verse eid="2KI 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 4:17"/>But the woman became pregnant, and the next year about that same time she gave birth to a son, just as Elisha had told her.<verse eid="2KI 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 4:18"/>The child grew, and one day he went out to his father, who was with the reapers. <verse eid="2KI 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 4:19"/>He said to his father, ‘My head! My head!’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:19">His father told a servant, ‘Carry him to his mother.’ <verse eid="2KI 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 4:20"/>After the servant had lifted him up and carried him to his mother, the boy sat on her lap until noon, and then he died. <verse eid="2KI 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 4:21"/>She went up and laid him on the bed of the man of God, then shut the door and went out.<verse eid="2KI 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 4:22"/>She called her husband and said, ‘Please send me one of the servants and a donkey so I can go to the man of God quickly and return.’<verse eid="2KI 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 4:23"/>‘Why go to him today?’ he asked. ‘It’s not the New Moon or the Sabbath.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:23">‘That’s all right,’ she said.<verse eid="2KI 4:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 4:24"/>She saddled the donkey and said to her servant, ‘Lead on; don’t slow down for me unless I tell you.’ <verse eid="2KI 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 4:25"/>So she set out and came to the man of God at Mount Carmel.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:25">When he saw her in the distance, the man of God said to his servant Gehazi, ‘Look! There’s the Shunammite! <verse eid="2KI 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 4:26"/>Run to meet her and ask her, “Are you all right? Is your husband all right? Is your child all right?” ’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:26">‘Everything is all right,’ she said.<verse eid="2KI 4:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 4:27"/>When she reached the man of God at the mountain, she took hold of his feet. Gehazi came over to push her away, but the man of God said, ‘Leave her alone! She is in bitter distress, but the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has hidden it from me and has not told me why.’<verse eid="2KI 4:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 4:28"/>‘Did I ask you for a son, my lord?’ she said. ‘Didn’t I tell you, “Don’t raise my hopes”?’<verse eid="2KI 4:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 4:29"/>Elisha said to Gehazi, ‘Tuck your cloak into your belt, take my staff in your hand and run. Don’t greet anyone you meet, and if anyone greets you, do not answer. Lay my staff on the boy’s face.’<verse eid="2KI 4:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 4:30"/>But the child’s mother said, ‘As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives and as you live, I will not leave you.’ So he got up and followed her.<verse eid="2KI 4:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 4:31"/>Gehazi went on ahead and laid the staff on the boy’s face, but there was no sound or response. So Gehazi went back to meet Elisha and told him, ‘The boy has not awakened.’<verse eid="2KI 4:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 4:32"/>When Elisha reached the house, there was the boy lying dead on his couch. <verse eid="2KI 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 4:33"/>He went in, shut the door on the two of them and prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 4:34"/>Then he got on the bed and lay on the boy, mouth to mouth, eyes to eyes, hands to hands. As he stretched himself out on him, the boy’s body grew warm. <verse eid="2KI 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 4:35"/>Elisha turned away and walked back and forth in the room and then got onto the bed and stretched out on him once more. The boy sneezed seven times and opened his eyes.<verse eid="2KI 4:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 4:36"/>Elisha summoned Gehazi and said, ‘Call the Shunammite.’ And he did. When she came, he said, ‘Take your son.’ <verse eid="2KI 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2KI 4:37"/>She came in, fell at his feet and bowed to the ground. Then she took her son and went out.<verse eid="2KI 4:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Death in the pot</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="2KI 4:38"/>Elisha returned to Gilgal and there was a famine in that region. While the company of the prophets was meeting with him, he said to his servant, ‘Put on the large pot and cook some stew for these prophets.’<verse eid="2KI 4:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="2KI 4:39"/>One of them went out into the fields to gather herbs and found a wild gourd plant and picked as many of its gourds as his garment could hold. When he returned, he cut them up into the pot of stew, though no-one knew what they were. <verse eid="2KI 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="2KI 4:40"/>The stew was poured out for the men, but as they began to eat it, they cried out, ‘Man of God, there is death in the pot!’ And they could not eat it.<verse eid="2KI 4:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="2KI 4:41"/>Elisha said, ‘Get some flour.’ He put it into the pot and said, ‘Serve it to the people to eat.’ And there was nothing harmful in the pot.<verse eid="2KI 4:41"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Feeding of a hundred</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="2KI 4:42"/>A man came from Baal Shalishah, bringing the man of God twenty loaves of barley bread baked from the first ripe corn, along with some ears of new corn. ‘Give it to the people to eat,’ Elisha said.<verse eid="2KI 4:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="2KI 4:43"/>‘How can I set this before a hundred men?’ his servant asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 4:43">But Elisha answered, ‘Give it to the people to eat. For this is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: “They will eat and have some left over.” ’ <verse eid="2KI 4:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="2KI 4:44"/>Then he set it before them, and they ate and had some left over, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="2KI 4:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="2KI 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Naaman healed of leprosy</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 5:1"/>Now Naaman was commander of the army of the king of Aram. He was a great man in the sight of his master and highly regarded, because through him the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had given victory to Aram. He was a valiant soldier, but he had leprosy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew for </char><char style="fq" closed="false">leprosy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was used for various diseases affecting the skin; also in verses 3, 6, 7, 11 and 27.</char></note><verse eid="2KI 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 5:2"/>Now bands of raiders from Aram had gone out and had taken captive a young girl from Israel, and she served Naaman’s wife. <verse eid="2KI 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 5:3"/>She said to her mistress, ‘If only my master would see the prophet who is in Samaria! He would cure him of his leprosy.’<verse eid="2KI 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 5:4"/>Naaman went to his master and told him what the girl from Israel had said. <verse eid="2KI 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 5:5"/>‘By all means, go,’ the king of Aram replied. ‘I will send a letter to the king of Israel.’ So Naaman left, taking with him ten talents<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 340 kilograms</char></note> of silver, six thousand shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 69 kilograms</char></note> of gold and ten sets of clothing. <verse eid="2KI 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 5:6"/>The letter that he took to the king of Israel read: ‘With this letter I am sending my servant Naaman to you so that you may cure him of his leprosy.’<verse eid="2KI 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 5:7"/>As soon as the king of Israel read the letter, he tore his robes and said, ‘Am I God? Can I kill and bring back to life? Why does this fellow send someone to me to be cured of his leprosy? See how he is trying to pick a quarrel with me!’<verse eid="2KI 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 5:8"/>When Elisha the man of God heard that the king of Israel had torn his robes, he sent him this message: ‘Why have you torn your robes? Make the man come to me and he will know that there is a prophet in Israel.’ <verse eid="2KI 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 5:9"/>So Naaman went with his horses and chariots and stopped at the door of Elisha’s house. <verse eid="2KI 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 5:10"/>Elisha sent a messenger to say to him, ‘Go, wash yourself seven times in the Jordan, and your flesh will be restored and you will be cleansed.’<verse eid="2KI 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 5:11"/>But Naaman went away angry and said, ‘I thought that he would surely come out to me and stand and call on the name of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God, wave his hand over the spot and cure me of my leprosy. <verse eid="2KI 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 5:12"/>Are not Abana and Pharpar, the rivers of Damascus, better than all the waters of Israel? Couldn’t I wash in them and be cleansed?’ So he turned and went off in a rage.<verse eid="2KI 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 5:13"/>Naaman’s servants went to him and said, ‘My father, if the prophet had told you to do some great thing, would you not have done it? How much more, then, when he tells you, “Wash and be cleansed”!’ <verse eid="2KI 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 5:14"/>So he went down and dipped himself in the Jordan seven times, as the man of God had told him, and his flesh was restored and became clean like that of a young boy.<verse eid="2KI 5:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 5:15"/>Then Naaman and all his attendants went back to the man of God. He stood before him and said, ‘Now I know that there is no God in all the world except in Israel. So please accept a gift from your servant.’<verse eid="2KI 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 5:16"/>The prophet answered, ‘As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, whom I serve, I will not accept a thing.’ And even though Naaman urged him, he refused.<verse eid="2KI 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 5:17"/>‘If you will not,’ said Naaman, ‘please let me, your servant, be given as much earth as a pair of mules can carry, for your servant will never again make burnt offerings and sacrifices to any other god but the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 5:18"/>But may the <char style="sc">Lord</char> forgive your servant for this one thing: when my master enters the temple of Rimmon to bow down and he is leaning on my arm and I have to bow there also – when I bow down in the temple of Rimmon, may the <char style="sc">Lord</char> forgive your servant for this.’<verse eid="2KI 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 5:19"/>‘Go in peace,’ Elisha said.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 5:19">After Naaman had travelled some distance, <verse eid="2KI 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 5:20"/>Gehazi, the servant of Elisha the man of God, said to himself, ‘My master was too easy on Naaman, this Aramean, by not accepting from him what he brought. As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, I will run after him and get something from him.’<verse eid="2KI 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 5:21"/>So Gehazi hurried after Naaman. When Naaman saw him running towards him, he got down from the chariot to meet him. ‘Is everything all right?’ he asked.<verse eid="2KI 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 5:22"/>‘Everything is all right,’ Gehazi answered. ‘My master sent me to say, “Two young men from the company of the prophets have just come to me from the hill country of Ephraim. Please give them a talent<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 34 kilograms</char></note> of silver and two sets of clothing.” ’<verse eid="2KI 5:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 5:23"/>‘By all means, take two talents,’ said Naaman. He urged Gehazi to accept them, and then tied up the two talents of silver in two bags, with two sets of clothing. He gave them to two of his servants, and they carried them ahead of Gehazi. <verse eid="2KI 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 5:24"/>When Gehazi came to the hill, he took the things from the servants and put them away in the house. He sent the men away and they left.<verse eid="2KI 5:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 5:25"/>When he went in and stood before his master, Elisha asked him, ‘Where have you been, Gehazi?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 5:25">‘Your servant didn’t go anywhere,’ Gehazi answered.<verse eid="2KI 5:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 5:26"/>But Elisha said to him, ‘Was not my spirit with you when the man got down from his chariot to meet you? Is this the time to take money or to accept clothes – or olive groves and vineyards, or flocks and herds, or male and female slaves? <verse eid="2KI 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 5:27"/>Naaman’s leprosy will cling to you and to your descendants for ever.’ Then Gehazi went from Elisha’s presence and his skin was leprous – it had become as white as snow.<verse eid="2KI 5:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="2KI 6"/>
  <para style="s1">An axe-head floats</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 6:1"/>The company of the prophets said to Elisha, ‘Look, the place where we meet with you is too small for us. <verse eid="2KI 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 6:2"/>Let us go to the Jordan, where each of us can get a pole; and let us build a place there for us to meet.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 6:2">And he said, ‘Go.’<verse eid="2KI 6:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 6:3"/>Then one of them said, ‘Won’t you please come with your servants?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 6:3">‘I will,’ Elisha replied. <verse eid="2KI 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 6:4"/>And he went with them.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 6:4">They went to the Jordan and began to cut down trees. <verse eid="2KI 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 6:5"/>As one of them was cutting down a tree, the iron axe-head fell into the water. ‘Oh no, my lord!’ he cried out. ‘It was borrowed!’<verse eid="2KI 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 6:6"/>The man of God asked, ‘Where did it fall?’ When he showed him the place, Elisha cut a stick and threw it there, and made the iron float. <verse eid="2KI 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 6:7"/>‘Lift it out,’ he said. Then the man reached out his hand and took it.<verse eid="2KI 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Elisha traps blinded Arameans</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 6:8"/>Now the king of Aram was at war with Israel. After conferring with his officers, he said, ‘I will set up my camp in such and such a place.’<verse eid="2KI 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 6:9"/>The man of God sent word to the king of Israel: ‘Beware of passing that place, because the Arameans are going down there.’ <verse eid="2KI 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 6:10"/>So the king of Israel checked on the place indicated by the man of God. Time and again Elisha warned the king, so that he was on his guard in such places.<verse eid="2KI 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 6:11"/>This enraged the king of Aram. He summoned his officers and demanded of them, ‘Tell me! Which of us is on the side of the king of Israel?’<verse eid="2KI 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 6:12"/>‘None of us, my lord the king,’ said one of his officers, ‘but Elisha, the prophet who is in Israel, tells the king of Israel the very words you speak in your bedroom.’<verse eid="2KI 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 6:13"/>‘Go, find out where he is,’ the king ordered, ‘so that I can send men and capture him.’ The report came back: ‘He is in Dothan.’ <verse eid="2KI 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 6:14"/>Then he sent horses and chariots and a strong force there. They went by night and surrounded the city.<verse eid="2KI 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 6:15"/>When the servant of the man of God got up and went out early the next morning, an army with horses and chariots had surrounded the city. ‘Oh no, my lord! What shall we do?’ the servant asked.<verse eid="2KI 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 6:16"/>‘Don’t be afraid,’ the prophet answered. ‘Those who are with us are more than those who are with them.’<verse eid="2KI 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 6:17"/>And Elisha prayed, ‘Open his eyes, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, so that he may see.’ Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> opened the servant’s eyes, and he looked and saw the hills full of horses and chariots of fire all round Elisha.<verse eid="2KI 6:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 6:18"/>As the enemy came down towards him, Elisha prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘Strike this army with blindness.’ So he struck them with blindness, as Elisha had asked.<verse eid="2KI 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 6:19"/>Elisha told them, ‘This is not the road and this is not the city. Follow me, and I will lead you to the man you are looking for.’ And he led them to Samaria.<verse eid="2KI 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 6:20"/>After they entered the city, Elisha said, ‘<char style="sc">Lord</char>, open the eyes of these men so that they can see.’ Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> opened their eyes and they looked, and there they were, inside Samaria.<verse eid="2KI 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 6:21"/>When the king of Israel saw them, he asked Elisha, ‘Shall I kill them, my father? Shall I kill them?’<verse eid="2KI 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 6:22"/>‘Do not kill them,’ he answered. ‘Would you kill those you have captured with your own sword or bow? Set food and water before them so that they may eat and drink and then go back to their master.’ <verse eid="2KI 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 6:23"/>So he prepared a great feast for them, and after they had finished eating and drinking, he sent them away, and they returned to their master. So the bands from Aram stopped raiding Israel’s territory.<verse eid="2KI 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Famine in besieged Samaria</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 6:24"/>Some time later, Ben-Hadad king of Aram mobilised his entire army and marched up and laid siege to Samaria. <verse eid="2KI 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 6:25"/>There was a great famine in the city; the siege lasted so long that a donkey’s head sold for eighty shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 920 grams</char></note> of silver, and a quarter of a cab<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, probably about 100 grams</char></note> of seed pods<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">of doves’ dung</char></note> for five shekels.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 58 grams</char></note><verse eid="2KI 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 6:26"/>As the king of Israel was passing by on the wall, a woman cried to him, ‘Help me, my lord the king!’<verse eid="2KI 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 6:27"/>The king replied, ‘If the <char style="sc">Lord</char> does not help you, where can I get help for you? From the threshing-floor? From the winepress?’ <verse eid="2KI 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 6:28"/>Then he asked her, ‘What’s the matter?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 6:28">She answered, ‘This woman said to me, “Give up your son so that we may eat him today, and tomorrow we’ll eat my son.” <verse eid="2KI 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 6:29"/>So we cooked my son and ate him. The next day I said to her, “Give up your son so that we may eat him,” but she had hidden him.’<verse eid="2KI 6:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 6:30"/>When the king heard the woman’s words, he tore his robes. As he went along the wall, the people looked, and they saw that, under his robes, he had sackcloth on his body. <verse eid="2KI 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 6:31"/>He said, ‘May God deal with me, be it ever so severely, if the head of Elisha son of Shaphat remains on his shoulders today!’<verse eid="2KI 6:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 6:32"/>Now Elisha was sitting in his house, and the elders were sitting with him. The king sent a messenger ahead, but before he arrived, Elisha said to the elders, ‘Don’t you see how this murderer is sending someone to cut off my head? Look, when the messenger comes, shut the door and hold it shut against him. Is not the sound of his master’s footsteps behind him?’ <verse eid="2KI 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 6:33"/>While he was still talking to them, the messenger came down to him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 6:33">The king said, ‘This disaster is from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Why should I wait for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> any longer?’<verse eid="2KI 6:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="2KI 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 7:1"/>Elisha replied, ‘Hear the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: about this time tomorrow, a seah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, probably about 5.5 kilograms of flour; also in verses 16 and 18</char></note> of the finest flour will sell for a shekel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 12 grams; also in verses 16 and 18</char></note> and two seahs<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, probably about 9 kilograms of barley; also in verses 16 and 18</char></note> of barley for a shekel at the gate of Samaria.’<verse eid="2KI 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 7:2"/>The officer on whose arm the king was leaning said to the man of God, ‘Look, even if the <char style="sc">Lord</char> should open the floodgates of the heavens, could this happen?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 7:2">‘You will see it with your own eyes,’ answered Elisha, ‘but you will not eat any of it!’<verse eid="2KI 7:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The siege lifted</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 7:3"/>Now there were four men with leprosy<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew for </char><char style="fq" closed="false">leprosy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was used for various diseases affecting the skin; also in verse 8.</char></note> at the entrance of the city gate. They said to each other, ‘Why stay here until we die? <verse eid="2KI 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 7:4"/>If we say, “We’ll go into the city” – the famine is there, and we will die. And if we stay here, we will die. So let’s go over to the camp of the Arameans and surrender. If they spare us, we live; if they kill us, then we die.’<verse eid="2KI 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 7:5"/>At dusk they got up and went to the camp of the Arameans. When they reached the edge of the camp, no-one was there, <verse eid="2KI 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 7:6"/>for the Lord had caused the Arameans to hear the sound of chariots and horses and a great army, so that they said to one another, ‘Look, the king of Israel has hired the Hittite and Egyptian kings to attack us!’ <verse eid="2KI 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 7:7"/>So they got up and fled in the dusk and abandoned their tents and their horses and donkeys. They left the camp as it was and ran for their lives.<verse eid="2KI 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 7:8"/>The men who had leprosy reached the edge of the camp, entered one of the tents and ate and drank. Then they took silver, gold and clothes, and went off and hid them. They returned and entered another tent and took some things from it and hid them also.<verse eid="2KI 7:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 7:9"/>Then they said to each other, ‘What we’re doing is not right. This is a day of good news and we are keeping it to ourselves. If we wait until daylight, punishment will overtake us. Let’s go at once and report this to the royal palace.’<verse eid="2KI 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 7:10"/>So they went and called out to the city gatekeepers and told them, ‘We went into the Aramean camp and no-one was there – not a sound of anyone – only tethered horses and donkeys, and the tents left just as they were.’ <verse eid="2KI 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 7:11"/>The gatekeepers shouted the news, and it was reported within the palace.<verse eid="2KI 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 7:12"/>The king got up in the night and said to his officers, ‘I will tell you what the Arameans have done to us. They know we are starving; so they have left the camp to hide in the countryside, thinking, “They will surely come out, and then we will take them alive and get into the city.” ’<verse eid="2KI 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 7:13"/>One of his officers answered, ‘Make some men take five of the horses that are left in the city. Their plight will be like that of all the Israelites left here – yes, they will only be like all these Israelites who are doomed. So let us send them to find out what happened.’<verse eid="2KI 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 7:14"/>So they selected two chariots with their horses, and the king sent them after the Aramean army. He commanded the drivers, ‘Go and find out what has happened.’ <verse eid="2KI 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 7:15"/>They followed them as far as the Jordan, and they found the whole road strewn with the clothing and equipment the Arameans had thrown away in their headlong flight. So the messengers returned and reported to the king. <verse eid="2KI 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 7:16"/>Then the people went out and plundered the camp of the Arameans. So a seah of the finest flour sold for a shekel, and two seahs of barley sold for a shekel, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said.<verse eid="2KI 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 7:17"/>Now the king had put the officer on whose arm he leaned in charge of the gate, and the people trampled him in the gateway, and he died, just as the man of God had foretold when the king came down to his house. <verse eid="2KI 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 7:18"/>It happened as the man of God had said to the king: ‘About this time tomorrow, a seah of the finest flour will sell for a shekel and two seahs of barley for a shekel at the gate of Samaria.’<verse eid="2KI 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 7:19"/>The officer had said to the man of God, ‘Look, even if the <char style="sc">Lord</char> should open the floodgates of the heavens, could this happen?’ The man of God had replied, ‘You will see it with your own eyes, but you will not eat any of it!’ <verse eid="2KI 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 7:20"/>And that is exactly what happened to him, for the people trampled him in the gateway, and he died.<verse eid="2KI 7:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="2KI 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The Shunammite’s land restored</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 8:1"/>Now Elisha had said to the woman whose son he had restored to life, ‘Go away with your family and stay for a while wherever you can, because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has decreed a famine in the land that will last seven years.’ <verse eid="2KI 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 8:2"/>The woman proceeded to do as the man of God said. She and her family went away and stayed in the land of the Philistines for seven years.<verse eid="2KI 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 8:3"/>At the end of the seven years she came back from the land of the Philistines and went to appeal to the king for her house and land. <verse eid="2KI 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 8:4"/>The king was talking to Gehazi, the servant of the man of God, and had said, ‘Tell me about all the great things Elisha has done.’ <verse eid="2KI 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 8:5"/>Just as Gehazi was telling the king how Elisha had restored the dead to life, the woman whose son Elisha had brought back to life came to appeal to the king for her house and land.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 8:5">Gehazi said, ‘This is the woman, my lord the king, and this is her son whom Elisha restored to life.’ <verse eid="2KI 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 8:6"/>The king asked the woman about it, and she told him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 8:6">Then he assigned an official to her case and said to him, ‘Give back everything that belonged to her, including all the income from her land from the day she left the country until now.’<verse eid="2KI 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hazael murders Ben-Hadad</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 8:7"/>Elisha went to Damascus, and Ben-Hadad king of Aram was ill. When the king was told, ‘The man of God has come all the way up here,’ <verse eid="2KI 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 8:8"/>he said to Hazael, ‘Take a gift with you and go to meet the man of God. Consult the <char style="sc">Lord</char> through him; ask him, “Will I recover from this illness?” ’<verse eid="2KI 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 8:9"/>Hazael went to meet Elisha, taking with him as a gift forty camel-loads of all the finest wares of Damascus. He went in and stood before him, and said, ‘Your son Ben-Hadad king of Aram has sent me to ask, “Will I recover from this illness?” ’<verse eid="2KI 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 8:10"/>Elisha answered, ‘Go and say to him, “You will certainly recover.” Nevertheless,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew may also be read </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Go and say, “You will certainly not recover,” for.</char></note> the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has revealed to me that he will in fact die.’ <verse eid="2KI 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 8:11"/>He stared at him with a fixed gaze until Hazael was embarrassed. Then the man of God began to weep.<verse eid="2KI 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 8:12"/>‘Why is my lord weeping?’ asked Hazael.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 8:12">‘Because I know the harm you will do to the Israelites,’ he answered. ‘You will set fire to their fortified places, kill their young men with the sword, dash their little children to the ground, and rip open their pregnant women.’<verse eid="2KI 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 8:13"/>Hazael said, ‘How could your servant, a mere dog, accomplish such a feat?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 8:13">‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has shown me that you will become king of Aram,’ answered Elisha.<verse eid="2KI 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 8:14"/>Then Hazael left Elisha and returned to his master. When Ben-Hadad asked, ‘What did Elisha say to you?’ Hazael replied, ‘He told me that you would certainly recover.’ <verse eid="2KI 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 8:15"/>But the next day he took a thick cloth, soaked it in water and spread it over the king’s face, so that he died. Then Hazael succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 8:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoram king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 8:16"/>In the fifth year of Joram son of Ahab king of Israel, when Jehoshaphat was king of Judah, Jehoram son of Jehoshaphat began his reign as king of Judah. <verse eid="2KI 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 8:17"/>He was thirty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for eight years. <verse eid="2KI 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 8:18"/>He followed the ways of the kings of Israel, as the house of Ahab had done, for he married a daughter of Ahab. He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 8:19"/>Nevertheless, for the sake of his servant David, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was not willing to destroy Judah. He had promised to maintain a lamp for David and his descendants for ever.<verse eid="2KI 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 8:20"/>In the time of Jehoram, Edom rebelled against Judah and set up its own king. <verse eid="2KI 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 8:21"/>So Jehoram<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Joram, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Jehoram</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 23 and 24</char></note> went to Zair with all his chariots. The Edomites surrounded him and his chariot commanders, but he rose up and broke through by night; his army, however, fled back home. <verse eid="2KI 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 8:22"/>To this day Edom has been in rebellion against Judah. Libnah revolted at the same time.<verse eid="2KI 8:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 8:23"/>As for the other events of Jehoram’s reign, and all he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 8:24"/>Jehoram rested with his ancestors and was buried with them in the City of David. And Ahaziah his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 8:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ahaziah king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 8:25"/>In the twelfth year of Joram son of Ahab king of Israel, Ahaziah son of Jehoram king of Judah began to reign. <verse eid="2KI 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 8:26"/>Ahaziah was twenty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for one year. His mother’s name was Athaliah, a granddaughter of Omri king of Israel. <verse eid="2KI 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 8:27"/>He followed the ways of the house of Ahab and did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as the house of Ahab had done, for he was related by marriage to Ahab’s family.<verse eid="2KI 8:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 8:28"/>Ahaziah went with Joram son of Ahab to war against Hazael king of Aram at Ramoth Gilead. The Arameans wounded Joram; <verse eid="2KI 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 8:29"/>so King Joram returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds the Arameans had inflicted on him at Ramoth<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ramah, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Ramoth</char></note> in his battle with Hazael king of Aram.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 8:29">Then Ahaziah son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to Jezreel to see Joram son of Ahab, because he had been wounded.<verse eid="2KI 8:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="2KI 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Jehu anointed king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 9:1"/>The prophet Elisha summoned a man from the company of the prophets and said to him, ‘Tuck your cloak into your belt, take this flask of olive oil with you and go to Ramoth Gilead. <verse eid="2KI 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 9:2"/>When you get there, look for Jehu son of Jehoshaphat, the son of Nimshi. Go to him, get him away from his companions and take him into an inner room. <verse eid="2KI 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 9:3"/>Then take the flask and pour the oil on his head and declare, “This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: I anoint you king over Israel.” Then open the door and run; don’t delay!’<verse eid="2KI 9:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 9:4"/>So the young prophet went to Ramoth Gilead. <verse eid="2KI 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 9:5"/>When he arrived, he found the army officers sitting together. ‘I have a message for you, commander,’ he said.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:5">‘For which of us?’ asked Jehu.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:5">‘For you, commander,’ he replied.<verse eid="2KI 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 9:6"/>Jehu got up and went into the house. Then the prophet poured the oil on Jehu’s head and declared, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says: “I anoint you king over the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s people Israel. <verse eid="2KI 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 9:7"/>You are to destroy the house of Ahab your master, and I will avenge the blood of my servants the prophets and the blood of all the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s servants shed by Jezebel. <verse eid="2KI 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 9:8"/>The whole house of Ahab will perish. I will cut off from Ahab every last male in Israel – slave or free.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Israel – every ruler or leader</char></note> <verse eid="2KI 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 9:9"/>I will make the house of Ahab like the house of Jeroboam son of Nebat and like the house of Baasha son of Ahijah. <verse eid="2KI 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 9:10"/>As for Jezebel, dogs will devour her on the plot of ground at Jezreel, and no-one will bury her.” ’ Then he opened the door and ran.<verse eid="2KI 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 9:11"/>When Jehu went out to his fellow officers, one of them asked him, ‘Is everything all right? Why did this maniac come to you?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:11">‘You know the man and the sort of things he says,’ Jehu replied.<verse eid="2KI 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 9:12"/>‘That’s not true!’ they said. ‘Tell us.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:12">Jehu said, ‘Here is what he told me: “This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: I anoint you king over Israel.” ’<verse eid="2KI 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 9:13"/>They quickly took their cloaks and spread them under him on the bare steps. Then they blew the trumpet and shouted, ‘Jehu is king!’<verse eid="2KI 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehu kills Joram and Ahaziah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 9:14"/>So Jehu son of Jehoshaphat, the son of Nimshi, conspired against Joram. (Now Joram and all Israel had been defending Ramoth Gilead against Hazael king of Aram, <verse eid="2KI 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 9:15"/>but King Joram<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jehoram, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Joram</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 17 and 21-24</char></note> had returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds the Arameans had inflicted on him in the battle with Hazael king of Aram.) Jehu said, ‘If you desire to make me king, don’t let anyone slip out of the city to go and tell the news in Jezreel.’ <verse eid="2KI 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 9:16"/>Then he got into his chariot and rode to Jezreel, because Joram was resting there and Ahaziah king of Judah had gone down to see him.<verse eid="2KI 9:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 9:17"/>When the lookout standing on the tower in Jezreel saw Jehu’s troops approaching, he called out, ‘I see some troops coming.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:17">‘Get a horseman,’ Joram ordered. ‘Send him to meet them and ask, “Do you come in peace?” ’<verse eid="2KI 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 9:18"/>The horseman rode off to meet Jehu and said, ‘This is what the king says: “Do you come in peace?” ’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:18">‘What do you have to do with peace?’ Jehu replied. ‘Fall in behind me.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:18">The lookout reported, ‘The messenger has reached them, but he isn’t coming back.’<verse eid="2KI 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 9:19"/>So the king sent out a second horseman. When he came to them he said, ‘This is what the king says: “Do you come in peace?” ’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:19">Jehu replied, ‘What do you have to do with peace? Fall in behind me.’<verse eid="2KI 9:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 9:20"/>The lookout reported, ‘He has reached them, but he isn’t coming back either. The driving is like that of Jehu son of Nimshi – he drives like a maniac.’<verse eid="2KI 9:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 9:21"/>‘Hitch up my chariot,’ Joram ordered. And when it was hitched up, Joram king of Israel and Ahaziah king of Judah rode out, each in his own chariot, to meet Jehu. They met him at the plot of ground that had belonged to Naboth the Jezreelite. <verse eid="2KI 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 9:22"/>When Joram saw Jehu he asked, ‘Have you come in peace, Jehu?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 9:22">‘How can there be peace,’ Jehu replied, ‘as long as all the idolatry and witchcraft of your mother Jezebel abound?’<verse eid="2KI 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 9:23"/>Joram turned about and fled, calling out to Ahaziah, ‘Treachery, Ahaziah!’<verse eid="2KI 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 9:24"/>Then Jehu drew his bow and shot Joram between the shoulders. The arrow pierced his heart and he slumped down in his chariot. <verse eid="2KI 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 9:25"/>Jehu said to Bidkar, his chariot officer, ‘Pick him up and throw him on the field that belonged to Naboth the Jezreelite. Remember how you and I were riding together in chariots behind Ahab his father when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoke this prophecy against him: <verse eid="2KI 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 9:26"/>“Yesterday I saw the blood of Naboth and the blood of his sons, declares the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and I will surely make you pay for it on this plot of ground, declares the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 21:19">1 Kings 21:19</ref></char>.</char></note> Now then, pick him up and throw him on that plot, in accordance with the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’<verse eid="2KI 9:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 9:27"/>When Ahaziah king of Judah saw what had happened, he fled up the road to Beth Haggan.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">fled by way of the garden house</char></note> Jehu chased him, shouting, ‘Kill him too!’ They wounded him in his chariot on the way up to Gur near Ibleam, but he escaped to Megiddo and died there. <verse eid="2KI 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 9:28"/>His servants took him by chariot to Jerusalem and buried him with his ancestors in his tomb in the City of David. <verse eid="2KI 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 9:29"/>(In the eleventh year of Joram son of Ahab, Ahaziah had become king of Judah.)<verse eid="2KI 9:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jezebel killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 9:30"/>Then Jehu went to Jezreel. When Jezebel heard about it, she put on eye makeup, arranged her hair and looked out of a window. <verse eid="2KI 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 9:31"/>As Jehu entered the gate, she asked, ‘Have you come in peace, you Zimri, you murderer of your master?’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">‘Was there peace for Zimri, who murdered his master?’</char></note><verse eid="2KI 9:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 9:32"/>He looked up at the window and called out, ‘Who is on my side? Who?’ Two or three eunuchs looked down at him. <verse eid="2KI 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 9:33"/>‘Throw her down!’ Jehu said. So they threw her down, and some of her blood spattered the wall and the horses as they trampled her underfoot.<verse eid="2KI 9:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 9:34"/>Jehu went in and ate and drank. ‘Take care of that cursed woman,’ he said, ‘and bury her, for she was a king’s daughter.’ <verse eid="2KI 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 9:35"/>But when they went out to bury her, they found nothing except her skull, her feet and her hands. <verse eid="2KI 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 9:36"/>They went back and told Jehu, who said, ‘This is the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that he spoke through his servant Elijah the Tishbite: on the plot of ground at Jezreel dogs will devour Jezebel’s flesh.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See <char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 21:23">1 Kings 21:23</ref></char>.</char></note> <verse eid="2KI 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2KI 9:37"/>Jezebel’s body will be like dung on the ground in the plot at Jezreel, so that no-one will be able to say, “This is Jezebel.” ’<verse eid="2KI 9:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="2KI 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Ahab’s family killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 10:1"/>Now there were in Samaria seventy sons of the house of Ahab. So Jehu wrote letters and sent them to Samaria: to the officials of Jezreel,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; some Septuagint manuscripts and Vulgate </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">of the city</char></note> to the elders and to the guardians of Ahab’s children. He said, <verse eid="2KI 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 10:2"/>‘You have your master’s sons with you and you have chariots and horses, a fortified city and weapons. Now as soon as this letter reaches you, <verse eid="2KI 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 10:3"/>choose the best and most worthy of your master’s sons and set him on his father’s throne. Then fight for your master’s house.’<verse eid="2KI 10:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 10:4"/>But they were terrified and said, ‘If two kings could not resist him, how can we?’<verse eid="2KI 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 10:5"/>So the palace administrator, the city governor, the elders and the guardians sent this message to Jehu: ‘We are your servants and we will do anything you say. We will not appoint anyone as king; you do whatever you think best.’<verse eid="2KI 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 10:6"/>Then Jehu wrote them a second letter, saying, ‘If you are on my side and will obey me, take the heads of your master’s sons and come to me in Jezreel by this time tomorrow.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 10:6">Now the royal princes, seventy of them, were with the leading men of the city, who were bringing them up. <verse eid="2KI 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 10:7"/>When the letter arrived, these men took the princes and slaughtered all seventy of them. They put their heads in baskets and sent them to Jehu in Jezreel. <verse eid="2KI 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 10:8"/>When the messenger arrived, he told Jehu, ‘They have brought the heads of the princes.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 10:8">Then Jehu ordered, ‘Put them in two piles at the entrance of the city gate until morning.’<verse eid="2KI 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 10:9"/>The next morning Jehu went out. He stood before all the people and said, ‘You are innocent. It was I who conspired against my master and killed him, but who killed all these? <verse eid="2KI 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 10:10"/>Know, then, that not a word the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has spoken against the house of Ahab will fail. The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has done what he announced through his servant Elijah.’ <verse eid="2KI 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 10:11"/>So Jehu killed everyone in Jezreel who remained of the house of Ahab, as well as all his chief men, his close friends and his priests, leaving him no survivor.<verse eid="2KI 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 10:12"/>Jehu then set out and went towards Samaria. At Beth Eked of the Shepherds, <verse eid="2KI 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 10:13"/>he met some relatives of Ahaziah king of Judah and asked, ‘Who are you?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 10:13">They said, ‘We are relatives of Ahaziah, and we have come down to greet the families of the king and of the queen mother.’<verse eid="2KI 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 10:14"/>‘Take them alive!’ he ordered. So they took them alive and slaughtered them by the well of Beth Eked – forty-two of them. He left no survivor.<verse eid="2KI 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 10:15"/>After he left there, he came upon Jehonadab son of Rekab, who was on his way to meet him. Jehu greeted him and said, ‘Are you in accord with me, as I am with you?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 10:15">‘I am,’ Jehonadab answered.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 10:15">‘If so,’ said Jehu, ‘give me your hand.’ So he did, and Jehu helped him up into the chariot. <verse eid="2KI 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 10:16"/>Jehu said, ‘Come with me and see my zeal for the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ Then he made him ride in his chariot.<verse eid="2KI 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 10:17"/>When Jehu came to Samaria, he killed all who were left there of Ahab’s family; he destroyed them, according to the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoken to Elijah.<verse eid="2KI 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Servants of Baal killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 10:18"/>Then Jehu brought all the people together and said to them, ‘Ahab served Baal a little; Jehu will serve him much. <verse eid="2KI 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 10:19"/>Now summon all the prophets of Baal, all his servants and all his priests. See that no-one is missing, because I am going to hold a great sacrifice for Baal. Anyone who fails to come will no longer live.’ But Jehu was acting deceptively in order to destroy the servants of Baal.<verse eid="2KI 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 10:20"/>Jehu said, ‘Call an assembly in honour of Baal.’ So they proclaimed it. <verse eid="2KI 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 10:21"/>Then he sent word throughout Israel, and all the servants of Baal came; not one stayed away. They crowded into the temple of Baal until it was full from one end to the other. <verse eid="2KI 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 10:22"/>And Jehu said to the keeper of the wardrobe, ‘Bring robes for all the servants of Baal.’ So he brought out robes for them.<verse eid="2KI 10:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 10:23"/>Then Jehu and Jehonadab son of Rekab went into the temple of Baal. Jehu said to the servants of Baal, ‘Look around and see that no-one who serves the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is here with you – only servants of Baal.’ <verse eid="2KI 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 10:24"/>So they went in to make sacrifices and burnt offerings. Now Jehu had posted eighty men outside with this warning: ‘If one of you lets any of the men I am placing in your hands escape, it will be your life for his life.’<verse eid="2KI 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 10:25"/>As soon as Jehu had finished making the burnt offering, he ordered the guards and officers: ‘Go in and kill them; let no-one escape.’ So they cut them down with the sword. The guards and officers threw the bodies out and then entered the inner shrine of the temple of Baal. <verse eid="2KI 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 10:26"/>They brought the sacred stone out of the temple of Baal and burned it. <verse eid="2KI 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 10:27"/>They demolished the sacred stone of Baal and tore down the temple of Baal, and people have used it for a latrine to this day.<verse eid="2KI 10:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 10:28"/>So Jehu destroyed Baal worship in Israel. <verse eid="2KI 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 10:29"/>However, he did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit – the worship of the golden calves at Bethel and Dan.<verse eid="2KI 10:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 10:30"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Jehu, ‘Because you have done well in accomplishing what is right in my eyes and have done to the house of Ahab all I had in mind to do, your descendants will sit on the throne of Israel to the fourth generation.’ <verse eid="2KI 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 10:31"/>Yet Jehu was not careful to keep the law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, with all his heart. He did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam, which he had caused Israel to commit.<verse eid="2KI 10:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 10:32"/>In those days the <char style="sc">Lord</char> began to reduce the size of Israel. Hazael overpowered the Israelites throughout their territory <verse eid="2KI 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 10:33"/>east of the Jordan in all the land of Gilead (the region of Gad, Reuben and Manasseh), from Aroer by the Arnon Gorge through Gilead to Bashan.<verse eid="2KI 10:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 10:34"/>As for the other events of Jehu’s reign, all he did, and all his achievements, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel?<verse eid="2KI 10:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 10:35"/>Jehu rested with his ancestors and was buried in Samaria. And Jehoahaz his son succeeded him as king. <verse eid="2KI 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 10:36"/>The time that Jehu reigned over Israel in Samaria was twenty-eight years.<verse eid="2KI 10:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="2KI 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Athaliah and Joash</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 11:1"/>When Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she proceeded to destroy the whole royal family. <verse eid="2KI 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 11:2"/>But Jehosheba, the daughter of King Jehoram<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Joram, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Jehoram</char></note> and sister of Ahaziah, took Joash son of Ahaziah and stole him away from among the royal princes, who were about to be murdered. She put him and his nurse in a bedroom to hide him from Athaliah; so he was not killed. <verse eid="2KI 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 11:3"/>He remained hidden with his nurse at the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for six years while Athaliah ruled the land.<verse eid="2KI 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 11:4"/>In the seventh year Jehoiada sent for the commanders of units of a hundred, the Carites and the guards and had them brought to him at the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He made a covenant with them and put them under oath at the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Then he showed them the king’s son. <verse eid="2KI 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 11:5"/>He commanded them, saying, ‘This is what you are to do: you who are in the three companies that are going on duty on the Sabbath – a third of you guarding the royal palace, <verse eid="2KI 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 11:6"/>a third at the Sur Gate, and a third at the gate behind the guard, who take turns guarding the temple – <verse eid="2KI 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 11:7"/>and you who are in the other two companies that normally go off Sabbath duty are all to guard the temple for the king. <verse eid="2KI 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 11:8"/>Station yourselves round the king, each of you with weapon in hand. Anyone who approaches your ranks<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">approaches the precincts</char></note> is to be put to death. Stay close to the king wherever he goes.’<verse eid="2KI 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 11:9"/>The commanders of units of a hundred did just as Jehoiada the priest ordered. Each one took his men – those who were going on duty on the Sabbath and those who were going off duty – and came to Jehoiada the priest. <verse eid="2KI 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 11:10"/>Then he gave the commanders the spears and shields that had belonged to King David and that were in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 11:11"/>The guards, each with weapon in hand, stationed themselves round the king – near the altar and the temple, from the south side to the north side of the temple.<verse eid="2KI 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 11:12"/>Jehoiada brought out the king’s son and put the crown on him; he presented him with a copy of the covenant and proclaimed him king. They anointed him, and the people clapped their hands and shouted, ‘Long live the king!’<verse eid="2KI 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 11:13"/>When Athaliah heard the noise made by the guards and the people, she went to the people at the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 11:14"/>She looked and there was the king, standing by the pillar, as the custom was. The officers and the trumpeters were beside the king, and all the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing trumpets. Then Athaliah tore her robes and called out, ‘Treason! Treason!’<verse eid="2KI 11:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 11:15"/>Jehoiada the priest ordered the commanders of units of a hundred, who were in charge of the troops: ‘Bring her out between the ranks<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">out from the precincts</char></note> and put to the sword anyone who follows her.’ For the priest had said, ‘She must not be put to death in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ <verse eid="2KI 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 11:16"/>So they seized her as she reached the place where the horses enter the palace grounds, and there she was put to death.<verse eid="2KI 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 11:17"/>Jehoiada then made a covenant between the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the king and people that they would be the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s people. He also made a covenant between the king and the people. <verse eid="2KI 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 11:18"/>All the people of the land went to the temple of Baal and tore it down. They smashed the altars and idols to pieces and killed Mattan the priest of Baal in front of the altars.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 11:18">Then Jehoiada the priest posted guards at the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 11:19"/>He took with him the commanders of hundreds, the Carites, the guards and all the people of the land, and together they brought the king down from the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and went into the palace, entering by way of the gate of the guards. The king then took his place on the royal throne. <verse eid="2KI 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 11:20"/>All the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was calm, because Athaliah had been slain with the sword at the palace.<verse eid="2KI 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 11:21"/>Joash<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jehoash, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Joash</char></note> was seven years old when he began his reign.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">In Hebrew texts this verse (11:21) is numbered 12:1.</char></note><verse eid="2KI 11:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="2KI 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Joash repairs the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="ft" closed="false">In Hebrew texts 12:1-21 is numbered 12:2-22</char>
    </note> <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 12:1"/>In the seventh year of Jehu, Joash<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Jehoash, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Joash</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 2, 4, 6, 7 and 18</char></note> became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for forty years. His mother’s name was Zibiah; she was from Beersheba. <verse eid="2KI 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 12:2"/>Joash did what was right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all the years Jehoiada the priest instructed him. <verse eid="2KI 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 12:3"/>The high places, however, were not removed; the people continued to offer sacrifices and burn incense there.<verse eid="2KI 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 12:4"/>Joash said to the priests, ‘Collect all the money that is brought as sacred offerings to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> – the money collected in the census, the money received from personal vows and the money brought voluntarily to the temple. <verse eid="2KI 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 12:5"/>Let every priest receive the money from one of the treasurers, then use it to repair whatever damage is found in the temple.’<verse eid="2KI 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 12:6"/>But by the twenty-third year of King Joash the priests still had not repaired the temple. <verse eid="2KI 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 12:7"/>Therefore King Joash summoned Jehoiada the priest and the other priests and asked them, ‘Why aren’t you repairing the damage done to the temple? Take no more money from your treasurers, but hand it over for repairing the temple.’ <verse eid="2KI 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 12:8"/>The priests agreed that they would not collect any more money from the people and that they would not repair the temple themselves.<verse eid="2KI 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 12:9"/>Jehoiada the priest took a chest and bored a hole in its lid. He placed it beside the altar, on the right side as one enters the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. The priests who guarded the entrance put into the chest all the money that was brought to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 12:10"/>Whenever they saw that there was a large amount of money in the chest, the royal secretary and the high priest came, counted the money that had been brought into the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and put it into bags. <verse eid="2KI 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 12:11"/>When the amount had been determined, they gave the money to the men appointed to supervise the work on the temple. With it they paid those who worked on the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> – the carpenters and builders, <verse eid="2KI 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 12:12"/>the masons and stonecutters. They purchased timber and blocks of dressed stone for the repair of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and met all the other expenses of restoring the temple.<verse eid="2KI 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 12:13"/>The money brought into the temple was not spent for making silver basins, wick trimmers, sprinkling bowls, trumpets or any other articles of gold or silver for the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; <verse eid="2KI 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 12:14"/>it was paid to the workers, who used it to repair the temple. <verse eid="2KI 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 12:15"/>They did not require an accounting from those to whom they gave the money to pay the workers, because they acted with complete honesty. <verse eid="2KI 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 12:16"/>The money from the guilt offerings and sin offerings<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">purification offerings</char></note> was not brought into the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; it belonged to the priests.<verse eid="2KI 12:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 12:17"/>About this time Hazael king of Aram went up and attacked Gath and captured it. Then he turned to attack Jerusalem. <verse eid="2KI 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 12:18"/>But Joash king of Judah took all the sacred objects dedicated by his predecessors – Jehoshaphat, Jehoram and Ahaziah, the kings of Judah – and the gifts he himself had dedicated and all the gold found in the treasuries of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and of the royal palace, and he sent them to Hazael king of Aram, who then withdrew from Jerusalem.<verse eid="2KI 12:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 12:19"/>As for the other events of the reign of Joash, and all he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 12:20"/>His officials conspired against him and assassinated him at Beth Millo, on the road down to Silla. <verse eid="2KI 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 12:21"/>The officials who murdered him were Jozabad son of Shimeath and Jehozabad son of Shomer. He died and was buried with his ancestors in the City of David. And Amaziah his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 12:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="2KI 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Jehoahaz king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 13:1"/>In the twenty-third year of Joash son of Ahaziah king of Judah, Jehoahaz son of Jehu became king of Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for seventeen years. <verse eid="2KI 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 13:2"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> by following the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit, and he did not turn away from them. <verse eid="2KI 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 13:3"/>So the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger burned against Israel, and for a long time he kept them under the power of Hazael king of Aram and Ben-Hadad his son.<verse eid="2KI 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 13:4"/>Then Jehoahaz sought the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s favour, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> listened to him, for he saw how severely the king of Aram was oppressing Israel. <verse eid="2KI 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 13:5"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> provided a deliverer for Israel, and they escaped from the power of Aram. So the Israelites lived in their own homes as they had before. <verse eid="2KI 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 13:6"/>But they did not turn away from the sins of the house of Jeroboam, which he had caused Israel to commit; they continued in them. Also, the Asherah pole<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, a wooden symbol of the goddess Asherah; here and elsewhere in 2 Kings</char></note> remained standing in Samaria.<verse eid="2KI 13:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 13:7"/>Nothing had been left of the army of Jehoahaz except fifty horsemen, ten chariots and ten thousand foot soldiers, for the king of Aram had destroyed the rest and made them like the dust at threshing time.<verse eid="2KI 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 13:8"/>As for the other events of the reign of Jehoahaz, all he did and his achievements, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel? <verse eid="2KI 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 13:9"/>Jehoahaz rested with his ancestors and was buried in Samaria. And Jehoash<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Joash, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Jehoash</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 12-14 and 25</char></note> his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoash king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 13:10"/>In the thirty-seventh year of Joash king of Judah, Jehoash son of Jehoahaz became king of Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for sixteen years. <verse eid="2KI 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 13:11"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and did not turn away from any of the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit; he continued in them.<verse eid="2KI 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 13:12"/>As for the other events of the reign of Jehoash, all he did and his achievements, including his war against Amaziah king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel? <verse eid="2KI 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 13:13"/>Jehoash rested with his ancestors, and Jeroboam succeeded him on the throne. Jehoash was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel.<verse eid="2KI 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 13:14"/>Now Elisha had been suffering from the illness from which he died. Jehoash king of Israel went down to see him and wept over him. ‘My father! My father!’ he cried. ‘The chariots and horsemen of Israel!’<verse eid="2KI 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 13:15"/>Elisha said, ‘Get a bow and some arrows,’ and he did so. <verse eid="2KI 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 13:16"/>‘Take the bow in your hands,’ he said to the king of Israel. When he had taken it, Elisha put his hands on the king’s hands.<verse eid="2KI 13:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 13:17"/>‘Open the east window,’ he said, and he opened it. ‘Shoot!’ Elisha said, and he shot. ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s arrow of victory, the arrow of victory over Aram!’ Elisha declared. ‘You will completely destroy the Arameans at Aphek.’<verse eid="2KI 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 13:18"/>Then he said, ‘Take the arrows,’ and the king took them. Elisha told him, ‘Strike the ground.’ He struck it three times and stopped. <verse eid="2KI 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 13:19"/>The man of God was angry with him and said, ‘You should have struck the ground five or six times; then you would have defeated Aram and completely destroyed it. But now you will defeat it only three times.’<verse eid="2KI 13:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 13:20"/>Elisha died and was buried.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 13:20">Now Moabite raiders used to enter the country every spring. <verse eid="2KI 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 13:21"/>Once while some Israelites were burying a man, suddenly they saw a band of raiders; so they threw the man’s body into Elisha’s tomb. When the body touched Elisha’s bones, the man came to life and stood up on his feet.<verse eid="2KI 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 13:22"/>Hazael king of Aram oppressed Israel throughout the reign of Jehoahaz. <verse eid="2KI 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 13:23"/>But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was gracious to them and had compassion and showed concern for them because of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. To this day he has been unwilling to destroy them or banish them from his presence.<verse eid="2KI 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 13:24"/>Hazael king of Aram died, and Ben-Hadad his son succeeded him as king. <verse eid="2KI 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 13:25"/>Then Jehoash son of Jehoahaz recaptured from Ben-Hadad son of Hazael the towns he had taken in battle from his father Jehoahaz. Three times Jehoash defeated him, and so he recovered the Israelite towns.<verse eid="2KI 13:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="2KI 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Amaziah king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 14:1"/>In the second year of Jehoash<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Joash, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Jehoash</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 13, 23 and 27</char></note> son of Jehoahaz king of Israel, Amaziah son of Joash king of Judah began to reign. <verse eid="2KI 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 14:2"/>He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for twenty-nine years. His mother’s name was Jehoaddan; she was from Jerusalem. <verse eid="2KI 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 14:3"/>He did what was right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but not as his father David had done. In everything he followed the example of his father Joash. <verse eid="2KI 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 14:4"/>The high places, however, were not removed; the people continued to offer sacrifices and burn incense there.<verse eid="2KI 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 14:5"/>After the kingdom was firmly in his grasp, he executed the officials who had murdered his father the king. <verse eid="2KI 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 14:6"/>Yet he did not put the children of the assassins to death, in accordance with what is written in the Book of the Law of Moses where the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded: ‘Parents are not to be put to death for their children, nor children put to death for their parents; each will die for their own sin.’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 24:16">Deut. 24:16</ref></char></char></note><verse eid="2KI 14:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 14:7"/>He was the one who defeated ten thousand Edomites in the Valley of Salt and captured Sela in battle, calling it Joktheel, the name it has to this day.<verse eid="2KI 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 14:8"/>Then Amaziah sent messengers to Jehoash son of Jehoahaz, the son of Jehu, king of Israel, with the challenge: ‘Come, let us face each other in battle.’<verse eid="2KI 14:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 14:9"/>But Jehoash king of Israel replied to Amaziah king of Judah: ‘A thistle in Lebanon sent a message to a cedar in Lebanon, “Give your daughter to my son in marriage.” Then a wild beast in Lebanon came along and trampled the thistle underfoot. <verse eid="2KI 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 14:10"/>You have indeed defeated Edom and now you are arrogant. Glory in your victory, but stay at home! Why ask for trouble and cause your own downfall and that of Judah also?’<verse eid="2KI 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 14:11"/>Amaziah, however, would not listen, so Jehoash king of Israel attacked. He and Amaziah king of Judah faced each other at Beth Shemesh in Judah. <verse eid="2KI 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 14:12"/>Judah was routed by Israel, and every man fled to his home. <verse eid="2KI 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 14:13"/>Jehoash king of Israel captured Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash, the son of Ahaziah, at Beth Shemesh. Then Jehoash went to Jerusalem and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from the Ephraim Gate to the Corner Gate – a section about four hundred cubits long.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 180 metres</char></note> <verse eid="2KI 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 14:14"/>He took all the gold and silver and all the articles found in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in the treasuries of the royal palace. He also took hostages and returned to Samaria.<verse eid="2KI 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 14:15"/>As for the other events of the reign of Jehoash, what he did and his achievements, including his war against Amaziah king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel? <verse eid="2KI 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 14:16"/>Jehoash rested with his ancestors and was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel. And Jeroboam his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 14:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 14:17"/>Amaziah son of Joash king of Judah lived for fifteen years after the death of Jehoash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel. <verse eid="2KI 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 14:18"/>As for the other events of Amaziah’s reign, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah?<verse eid="2KI 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 14:19"/>They conspired against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to Lachish, but they sent men after him to Lachish and killed him there. <verse eid="2KI 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 14:20"/>He was brought back by horse and was buried in Jerusalem with his ancestors, in the City of David.<verse eid="2KI 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 14:21"/>Then all the people of Judah took Azariah,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Also called </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Uzziah</char></note> who was sixteen years old, and made him king in place of his father Amaziah. <verse eid="2KI 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 14:22"/>He was the one who rebuilt Elath and restored it to Judah after Amaziah rested with his ancestors.<verse eid="2KI 14:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jeroboam II king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 14:23"/>In the fifteenth year of Amaziah son of Joash king of Judah, Jeroboam son of Jehoash king of Israel became king in Samaria, and he reigned for forty-one years. <verse eid="2KI 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 14:24"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and did not turn away from any of the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit. <verse eid="2KI 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 14:25"/>He was the one who restored the boundaries of Israel from Lebo Hamath to the Dead Sea,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the Sea of the Arabah</char></note> in accordance with the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, spoken through his servant Jonah son of Amittai, the prophet from Gath Hepher.<verse eid="2KI 14:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 14:26"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> had seen how bitterly everyone in Israel, whether slave or free, was suffering;<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Israel was suffering. They were without a ruler or leader, and</char></note> there was no-one to help them. <verse eid="2KI 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 14:27"/>And since the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had not said he would blot out the name of Israel from under heaven, he saved them by the hand of Jeroboam son of Jehoash.<verse eid="2KI 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 14:28"/>As for the other events of Jeroboam’s reign, all he did, and his military achievements, including how he recovered for Israel both Damascus and Hamath, which had belonged to Judah, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel? <verse eid="2KI 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 14:29"/>Jeroboam rested with his ancestors, the kings of Israel. And Zechariah his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 14:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="2KI 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Azariah king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 15:1"/>In the twenty-seventh year of Jeroboam king of Israel, Azariah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Also called </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Uzziah</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 6, 7, 8, 17, 23 and 27</char></note> son of Amaziah king of Judah began to reign. <verse eid="2KI 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 15:2"/>He was sixteen years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for fifty-two years. His mother’s name was Jekoliah; she was from Jerusalem. <verse eid="2KI 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 15:3"/>He did what was right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, just as his father Amaziah had done. <verse eid="2KI 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 15:4"/>The high places, however, were not removed; the people continued to offer sacrifices and burn incense there.<verse eid="2KI 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 15:5"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> afflicted the king with leprosy<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew for </char><char style="fq" closed="false">leprosy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was used for various diseases affecting the skin.</char></note> until the day he died, and he lived in a separate house.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">in a house where he was relieved of responsibilities</char></note> Jotham the king’s son had charge of the palace and governed the people of the land.<verse eid="2KI 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 15:6"/>As for the other events of Azariah’s reign, and all he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 15:7"/>Azariah rested with his ancestors and was buried near them in the City of David. And Jotham his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 15:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Zechariah king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 15:8"/>In the thirty-eighth year of Azariah king of Judah, Zechariah son of Jeroboam became king of Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for six months. <verse eid="2KI 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 15:9"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as his predecessors had done. He did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit.<verse eid="2KI 15:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 15:10"/>Shallum son of Jabesh conspired against Zechariah. He attacked him in front of the people,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; some Septuagint manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">in Ibleam</char></note> assassinated him and succeeded him as king. <verse eid="2KI 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 15:11"/>The other events of Zechariah’s reign are written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel. <verse eid="2KI 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 15:12"/>So the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> spoken to Jehu was fulfilled: ‘Your descendants will sit on the throne of Israel to the fourth generation.’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="2KI 10:30">2 Kings 10:30</ref></char></char></note><verse eid="2KI 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Shallum king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 15:13"/>Shallum son of Jabesh became king in the thirty-ninth year of Uzziah king of Judah, and he reigned in Samaria for one month. <verse eid="2KI 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 15:14"/>Then Menahem son of Gadi went from Tirzah up to Samaria. He attacked Shallum son of Jabesh in Samaria, assassinated him and succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 15:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 15:15"/>The other events of Shallum’s reign, and the conspiracy he led, are written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel.<verse eid="2KI 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 15:16"/>At that time Menahem, starting out from Tirzah, attacked Tiphsah and everyone in the city and its vicinity, because they refused to open their gates. He sacked Tiphsah and ripped open all the pregnant women.<verse eid="2KI 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Menahem king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 15:17"/>In the thirty-ninth year of Azariah king of Judah, Menahem son of Gadi became king of Israel, and he reigned in Samaria for ten years. <verse eid="2KI 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 15:18"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. During his entire reign he did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit.<verse eid="2KI 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 15:19"/>Then Pul<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Also called </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Tiglath-Pileser</char></note> king of Assyria invaded the land, and Menahem gave him a thousand talents<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 34 metric tons</char></note> of silver to gain his support and strengthen his own hold on the kingdom. <verse eid="2KI 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 15:20"/>Menahem exacted this money from Israel. Every wealthy person had to contribute fifty shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 575 grams</char></note> of silver to be given to the king of Assyria. So the king of Assyria withdrew and stayed in the land no longer.<verse eid="2KI 15:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 15:21"/>As for the other events of Menahem’s reign, and all he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel? <verse eid="2KI 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 15:22"/>Menahem rested with his ancestors. And Pekahiah his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 15:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Pekahiah king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 15:23"/>In the fiftieth year of Azariah king of Judah, Pekahiah son of Menahem became king of Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for two years. <verse eid="2KI 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 15:24"/>Pekahiah did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit. <verse eid="2KI 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 15:25"/>One of his chief officers, Pekah son of Remaliah, conspired against him. Taking fifty men of Gilead with him, he assassinated Pekahiah, along with Argob and Arieh, in the citadel of the royal palace at Samaria. So Pekah killed Pekahiah and succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 15:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 15:26"/>The other events of Pekahiah’s reign, and all he did, are written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel.<verse eid="2KI 15:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Pekah king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 15:27"/>In the fifty-second year of Azariah king of Judah, Pekah son of Remaliah became king of Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for twenty years. <verse eid="2KI 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 15:28"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He did not turn away from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, which he had caused Israel to commit.<verse eid="2KI 15:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 15:29"/>In the time of Pekah king of Israel, Tiglath-Pileser king of Assyria came and took Ijon, Abel Beth Maakah, Janoah, Kedesh and Hazor. He took Gilead and Galilee, including all the land of Naphtali, and deported the people to Assyria. <verse eid="2KI 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 15:30"/>Then Hoshea son of Elah conspired against Pekah son of Remaliah. He attacked and assassinated him, and then succeeded him as king in the twentieth year of Jotham son of Uzziah.<verse eid="2KI 15:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 15:31"/>As for the other events of Pekah’s reign, and all he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Israel?<verse eid="2KI 15:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jotham king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 15:32"/>In the second year of Pekah son of Remaliah king of Israel, Jotham son of Uzziah king of Judah began to reign. <verse eid="2KI 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 15:33"/>He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for sixteen years. His mother’s name was Jerusha daughter of Zadok. <verse eid="2KI 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 15:34"/>He did what was right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, just as his father Uzziah had done. <verse eid="2KI 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 15:35"/>The high places, however, were not removed; the people continued to offer sacrifices and burn incense there. Jotham rebuilt the Upper Gate of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="2KI 15:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 15:36"/>As for the other events of Jotham’s reign, and what he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 15:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2KI 15:37"/>(In those days the <char style="sc">Lord</char> began to send Rezin king of Aram and Pekah son of Remaliah against Judah.) <verse eid="2KI 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="2KI 15:38"/>Jotham rested with his ancestors and was buried with them in the City of David, the city of his father. And Ahaz his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 15:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="2KI 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Ahaz king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 16:1"/>In the seventeenth year of Pekah son of Remaliah, Ahaz son of Jotham king of Judah began to reign. <verse eid="2KI 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 16:2"/>Ahaz was twenty years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for sixteen years. Unlike David his father, he did not do what was right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> his God. <verse eid="2KI 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 16:3"/>He followed the ways of the kings of Israel and even sacrificed his son in the fire, engaging in the detestable practices of the nations the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had driven out before the Israelites. <verse eid="2KI 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 16:4"/>He offered sacrifices and burned incense at the high places, on the hilltops and under every spreading tree.<verse eid="2KI 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 16:5"/>Then Rezin king of Aram and Pekah son of Remaliah king of Israel marched up to fight against Jerusalem and besieged Ahaz, but they could not overpower him. <verse eid="2KI 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 16:6"/>At that time, Rezin king of Aram recovered Elath for Aram by driving out the people of Judah. Edomites then moved into Elath and have lived there to this day.<verse eid="2KI 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 16:7"/>Ahaz sent messengers to say to Tiglath-Pileser king of Assyria, ‘I am your servant and vassal. Come up and save me out of the hand of the king of Aram and of the king of Israel, who are attacking me.’ <verse eid="2KI 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 16:8"/>And Ahaz took the silver and gold found in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in the treasuries of the royal palace and sent it as a gift to the king of Assyria. <verse eid="2KI 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 16:9"/>The king of Assyria complied by attacking Damascus and capturing it. He deported its inhabitants to Kir and put Rezin to death.<verse eid="2KI 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 16:10"/>Then King Ahaz went to Damascus to meet Tiglath-Pileser king of Assyria. He saw an altar in Damascus and sent to Uriah the priest a sketch of the altar, with detailed plans for its construction. <verse eid="2KI 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 16:11"/>So Uriah the priest built an altar in accordance with all the plans that King Ahaz had sent from Damascus and finished it before King Ahaz returned. <verse eid="2KI 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 16:12"/>When the king came back from Damascus and saw the altar, he approached it and presented offerings<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">and went up</char></note> on it. <verse eid="2KI 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 16:13"/>He offered up his burnt offering and grain offering, poured out his drink offering, and splashed the blood of his fellowship offerings against the altar. <verse eid="2KI 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 16:14"/>The bronze altar that stood before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> he brought from the front of the temple – from between the new altar and the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> – and put it on the north side of the new altar.<verse eid="2KI 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 16:15"/>King Ahaz then gave these orders to Uriah the priest: ‘On the large new altar, offer the morning burnt offering and the evening grain offering, the king’s burnt offering and his grain offering, and the burnt offering of all the people of the land, and their grain offering and their drink offering. Splash against this altar the blood of all the burnt offerings and sacrifices. But I will use the bronze altar for seeking guidance.’ <verse eid="2KI 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 16:16"/>And Uriah the priest did just as King Ahaz had ordered.<verse eid="2KI 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 16:17"/>King Ahaz cut off the side panels and removed the basins from the movable stands. He removed the Sea from the bronze bulls that supported it and set it on a stone base. <verse eid="2KI 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 16:18"/>He took away the Sabbath canopy<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the dais of his throne </char><char style="ft" closed="false">(see Septuagint)</char></note> that had been built at the temple and removed the royal entrance outside the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, in deference to the king of Assyria.<verse eid="2KI 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 16:19"/>As for the other events of the reign of Ahaz, and what he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 16:20"/>Ahaz rested with his ancestors and was buried with them in the City of David. And Hezekiah his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 16:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="2KI 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Hoshea last king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 17:1"/>In the twelfth year of Ahaz king of Judah, Hoshea son of Elah became king of Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for nine years. <verse eid="2KI 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 17:2"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but not like the kings of Israel who preceded him.<verse eid="2KI 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 17:3"/>Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up to attack Hoshea, who had been Shalmaneser’s vassal and had paid him tribute. <verse eid="2KI 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 17:4"/>But the king of Assyria discovered that Hoshea was a traitor, for he had sent envoys to So<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:4 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">So </char><char style="ft" closed="false">is probably an abbreviation for </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Osorkon.</char></note> king of Egypt, and he no longer paid tribute to the king of Assyria, as he had done year by year. Therefore Shalmaneser seized him and put him in prison. <verse eid="2KI 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 17:5"/>The king of Assyria invaded the entire land, marched against Samaria and laid siege to it for three years. <verse eid="2KI 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 17:6"/>In the ninth year of Hoshea, the king of Assyria captured Samaria and deported the Israelites to Assyria. He settled them in Halah, in Gozan on the River Habor and in the towns of the Medes.<verse eid="2KI 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Israel exiled because of sin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 17:7"/>All this took place because the Israelites had sinned against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, who had brought them up out of Egypt from under the power of Pharaoh king of Egypt. They worshipped other gods <verse eid="2KI 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 17:8"/>and followed the practices of the nations the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had driven out before them, as well as the practices that the kings of Israel had introduced. <verse eid="2KI 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 17:9"/>The Israelites secretly did things against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God that were not right. From watchtower to fortified city they built themselves high places in all their towns. <verse eid="2KI 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 17:10"/>They set up sacred stones and Asherah poles on every high hill and under every spreading tree. <verse eid="2KI 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 17:11"/>At every high place they burned incense, as the nations whom the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had driven out before them had done. They did wicked things that aroused the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger. <verse eid="2KI 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 17:12"/>They worshipped idols, though the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said, ‘You shall not do this.’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="EXO 20:4">Exodus 20:4</ref>,<ref loc="EXO 20:5">5</ref></char></char></note> <verse eid="2KI 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 17:13"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> warned Israel and Judah through all his prophets and seers: ‘Turn from your evil ways. Observe my commands and decrees, in accordance with the entire Law that I commanded your ancestors to obey and that I delivered to you through my servants the prophets.’<verse eid="2KI 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 17:14"/>But they would not listen and were as stiff-necked as their ancestors, who did not trust in the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God. <verse eid="2KI 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 17:15"/>They rejected his decrees and the covenant he had made with their ancestors and the statutes he had warned them to keep. They followed worthless idols and themselves became worthless. They imitated the nations around them although the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had ordered them, ‘Do not do as they do.’<verse eid="2KI 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 17:16"/>They forsook all the commands of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God and made for themselves two idols cast in the shape of calves, and an Asherah pole. They bowed down to all the starry hosts, and they worshipped Baal. <verse eid="2KI 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 17:17"/>They sacrificed their sons and daughters in the fire. They practised divination and sought omens and sold themselves to do evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, arousing his anger.<verse eid="2KI 17:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 17:18"/>So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was very angry with Israel and removed them from his presence. Only the tribe of Judah was left, <verse eid="2KI 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 17:19"/>and even Judah did not keep the commands of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God. They followed the practices Israel had introduced. <verse eid="2KI 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 17:20"/>Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> rejected all the people of Israel; he afflicted them and gave them into the hands of plunderers, until he thrust them from his presence.<verse eid="2KI 17:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 17:21"/>When he tore Israel away from the house of David, they made Jeroboam son of Nebat their king. Jeroboam enticed Israel away from following the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and caused them to commit a great sin. <verse eid="2KI 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 17:22"/>The Israelites persisted in all the sins of Jeroboam and did not turn away from them <verse eid="2KI 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 17:23"/>until the <char style="sc">Lord</char> removed them from his presence, as he had warned through all his servants the prophets. So the people of Israel were taken from their homeland into exile in Assyria, and they are still there.<verse eid="2KI 17:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Samaria resettled</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 17:24"/>The king of Assyria brought people from Babylon, Kuthah, Avva, Hamath and Sepharvaim and settled them in the towns of Samaria to replace the Israelites. They took over Samaria and lived in its towns. <verse eid="2KI 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 17:25"/>When they first lived there, they did not worship the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; so he sent lions among them and they killed some of the people. <verse eid="2KI 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 17:26"/>It was reported to the king of Assyria: ‘The people you deported and resettled in the towns of Samaria do not know what the god of that country requires. He has sent lions among them, which are killing them off, because the people do not know what he requires.’<verse eid="2KI 17:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 17:27"/>Then the king of Assyria gave this order: ‘Make one of the priests you took captive from Samaria go back to live there and teach the people what the god of the land requires.’ <verse eid="2KI 17:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 17:28"/>So one of the priests who had been exiled from Samaria came to live in Bethel and taught them how to worship the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="2KI 17:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 17:29"/>Nevertheless, each national group made its own gods in the several towns where they settled, and set them up in the shrines the people of Samaria had made at the high places. <verse eid="2KI 17:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 17:30"/>The people from Babylon made Sukkoth Benoth, those from Kuthah made Nergal, and those from Hamath made Ashima; <verse eid="2KI 17:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 17:31"/>the Avvites made Nibhaz and Tartak, and the Sepharvites burned their children in the fire as sacrifices to Adrammelek and Anammelek, the gods of Sepharvaim. <verse eid="2KI 17:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 17:32"/>They worshipped the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but they also appointed all sorts of their own people to officiate for them as priests in the shrines at the high places. <verse eid="2KI 17:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 17:33"/>They worshipped the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, but they also served their own gods in accordance with the customs of the nations from which they had been brought.<verse eid="2KI 17:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 17:34"/>To this day they persist in their former practices. They neither worship the <char style="sc">Lord</char> nor adhere to the decrees and regulations, the laws and commands that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave the descendants of Jacob, whom he named Israel. <verse eid="2KI 17:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 17:35"/>When the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made a covenant with the Israelites, he commanded them: ‘Do not worship any other gods or bow down to them, serve them or sacrifice to them. <verse eid="2KI 17:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 17:36"/>But the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, who brought you up out of Egypt with mighty power and outstretched arm, is the one you must worship. To him you shall bow down and to him offer sacrifices. <verse eid="2KI 17:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2KI 17:37"/>You must always be careful to keep the decrees and regulations, the laws and commands he wrote for you. Do not worship other gods. <verse eid="2KI 17:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="2KI 17:38"/>Do not forget the covenant I have made with you, and do not worship other gods. <verse eid="2KI 17:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="2KI 17:39"/>Rather, worship the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God; it is he who will deliver you from the hand of all your enemies.’<verse eid="2KI 17:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="2KI 17:40"/>They would not listen, however, but persisted in their former practices. <verse eid="2KI 17:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="2KI 17:41"/>Even while these people were worshipping the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, they were serving their idols. To this day their children and grandchildren continue to do as their ancestors did.<verse eid="2KI 17:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="2KI 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Hezekiah king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 18:1"/>In the third year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, Hezekiah son of Ahaz king of Judah began to reign. <verse eid="2KI 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 18:2"/>He was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for twenty-nine years. His mother’s name was Abijah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Abi, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Abijah</char></note> daughter of Zechariah. <verse eid="2KI 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 18:3"/>He did what was right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, just as his father David had done. <verse eid="2KI 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 18:4"/>He removed the high places, smashed the sacred stones and cut down the Asherah poles. He broke into pieces the bronze snake Moses had made, for up to that time the Israelites had been burning incense to it. (It was called Nehushtan.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:4 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Nehushtan </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sounds like the Hebrew for both </char><char style="fq" closed="false">bronze </char><char style="ft" closed="false">and </char><char style="fq" closed="false">snake</char><char style="fqa" closed="false">.</char></note>)<verse eid="2KI 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 18:5"/>Hezekiah trusted in the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel. There was no-one like him among all the kings of Judah, either before him or after him. <verse eid="2KI 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 18:6"/>He held fast to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and did not stop following him; he kept the commands the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had given Moses. <verse eid="2KI 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 18:7"/>And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with him; he was successful in whatever he undertook. He rebelled against the king of Assyria and did not serve him. <verse eid="2KI 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 18:8"/>From watchtower to fortified city, he defeated the Philistines, as far as Gaza and its territory.<verse eid="2KI 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 18:9"/>In King Hezekiah’s fourth year, which was the seventh year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, Shalmaneser king of Assyria marched against Samaria and laid siege to it. <verse eid="2KI 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 18:10"/>At the end of three years the Assyrians took it. So Samaria was captured in Hezekiah’s sixth year, which was the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel. <verse eid="2KI 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 18:11"/>The king of Assyria deported Israel to Assyria and settled them in Halah, in Gozan on the River Habor and in towns of the Medes. <verse eid="2KI 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 18:12"/>This happened because they had not obeyed the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, but had violated his covenant – all that Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded. They neither listened to the commands nor carried them out.<verse eid="2KI 18:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 18:13"/>In the fourteenth year of King Hezekiah’s reign, Sennacherib king of Assyria attacked all the fortified cities of Judah and captured them. <verse eid="2KI 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 18:14"/>So Hezekiah king of Judah sent this message to the king of Assyria at Lachish: ‘I have done wrong. Withdraw from me, and I will pay whatever you demand of me.’ The king of Assyria exacted from Hezekiah king of Judah three hundred talents<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 10 metric tons</char></note> of silver and thirty talents<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about one metric ton</char></note> of gold. <verse eid="2KI 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 18:15"/>So Hezekiah gave him all the silver that was found in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and in the treasuries of the royal palace.<verse eid="2KI 18:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 18:16"/>At this time Hezekiah king of Judah stripped off the gold with which he had covered the doors and doorposts of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and gave it to the king of Assyria.<verse eid="2KI 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Sennacherib threatens Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 18:17"/>The king of Assyria sent his supreme commander, his chief officer and his field commander with a large army, from Lachish to King Hezekiah at Jerusalem. They came up to Jerusalem and stopped at the aqueduct of the Upper Pool, on the road to the Washerman’s Field. <verse eid="2KI 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 18:18"/>They called for the king; and Eliakim son of Hilkiah the palace administrator, Shebna the secretary, and Joah son of Asaph the recorder went out to them.<verse eid="2KI 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 18:19"/>The field commander said to them, ‘Tell Hezekiah:</para>
  <para style="pm" vid="2KI 18:19">‘ “This is what the great king, the king of Assyria, says: on what are you basing this confidence of yours? <verse eid="2KI 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 18:20"/>You say you have the counsel and the might for war – but you speak only empty words. On whom are you depending, that you rebel against me? <verse eid="2KI 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 18:21"/>Look, I know you are depending on Egypt, that splintered reed of a staff, which pierces the hand of anyone who leans on it! Such is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all who depend on him. <verse eid="2KI 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 18:22"/>But if you say to me, ‘We are depending on the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God’ – isn’t he the one whose high places and altars Hezekiah removed, saying to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘You must worship before this altar in Jerusalem’?<verse eid="2KI 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 18:23"/>‘ “Come now, make a bargain with my master, the king of Assyria: I will give you two thousand horses – if you can put riders on them! <verse eid="2KI 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 18:24"/>How can you repulse one officer of the least of my master’s officials, even though you are depending on Egypt for chariots and horsemen<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">charioteers</char></note>? <verse eid="2KI 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 18:25"/>Furthermore, have I come to attack and destroy this place without word from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>? The <char style="sc">Lord</char> himself told me to march against this country and destroy it.” ’<verse eid="2KI 18:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 18:26"/>Then Eliakim son of Hilkiah, and Shebna and Joah said to the field commander, ‘Please speak to your servants in Aramaic, since we understand it. Don’t speak to us in Hebrew in the hearing of the people on the wall.’<verse eid="2KI 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 18:27"/>But the commander replied, ‘Was it only to your master and you that my master sent me to say these things, and not to the people sitting on the wall – who, like you, will have to eat their own excrement and drink their own urine?’<verse eid="2KI 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 18:28"/>Then the commander stood and called out in Hebrew, ‘Hear the word of the great king, the king of Assyria! <verse eid="2KI 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 18:29"/>This is what the king says: do not let Hezekiah deceive you. He cannot deliver you from my hand. <verse eid="2KI 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 18:30"/>Do not let Hezekiah persuade you to trust in the <char style="sc">Lord</char> when he says, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will surely deliver us; this city will not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.”<verse eid="2KI 18:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 18:31"/>‘Do not listen to Hezekiah. This is what the king of Assyria says: make peace with me and come out to me. Then each of you will eat fruit from your own vine and fig-tree and drink water from your own cistern, <verse eid="2KI 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 18:32"/>until I come and take you to a land like your own – a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive trees and honey. Choose life and not death!</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 18:32">‘Do not listen to Hezekiah, for he is misleading you when he says, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will deliver us.” <verse eid="2KI 18:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 18:33"/>Has the god of any nation ever delivered his land from the hand of the king of Assyria? <verse eid="2KI 18:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 18:34"/>Where are the gods of Hamath and Arpad? Where are the gods of Sepharvaim, Hena and Ivvah? Have they rescued Samaria from my hand? <verse eid="2KI 18:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 18:35"/>Who of all the gods of these countries has been able to save his land from me? How then can the <char style="sc">Lord</char> deliver Jerusalem from my hand?’<verse eid="2KI 18:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 18:36"/>But the people remained silent and said nothing in reply, because the king had commanded, ‘Do not answer him.’<verse eid="2KI 18:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="2KI 18:37"/>Then Eliakim son of Hilkiah the palace administrator, Shebna the secretary, and Joah son of Asaph the recorder went to Hezekiah, with their clothes torn, and told him what the field commander had said.<verse eid="2KI 18:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="2KI 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Jerusalem’s deliverance foretold</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 19:1"/>When King Hezekiah heard this, he tore his clothes and put on sackcloth and went into the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 19:2"/>He sent Eliakim the palace administrator, Shebna the secretary and the leading priests, all wearing sackcloth, to the prophet Isaiah son of Amoz. <verse eid="2KI 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 19:3"/>They told him, ‘This is what Hezekiah says: this day is a day of distress and rebuke and disgrace, as when children come to the moment of birth and there is no strength to deliver them. <verse eid="2KI 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 19:4"/>It may be that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will hear all the words of the field commander, whom his master, the king of Assyria, has sent to ridicule the living God, and that he will rebuke him for the words the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has heard. Therefore pray for the remnant that still survives.’<verse eid="2KI 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 19:5"/>When King Hezekiah’s officials came to Isaiah, <verse eid="2KI 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 19:6"/>Isaiah said to them, ‘Tell your master, “This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: do not be afraid of what you have heard – those words with which the underlings of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me. <verse eid="2KI 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 19:7"/>Listen! When he hears a certain report, I will make him want to return to his own country, and there I will have him cut down with the sword.” ’<verse eid="2KI 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 19:8"/>When the field commander heard that the king of Assyria had left Lachish, he withdrew and found the king fighting against Libnah.<verse eid="2KI 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 19:9"/>Now Sennacherib received a report that Tirhakah, the king of Cush,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, the upper Nile region</char></note> was marching out to fight against him. So he again sent messengers to Hezekiah with this word: <verse eid="2KI 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 19:10"/>‘Say to Hezekiah king of Judah: do not let the god you depend on deceive you when he says, “Jerusalem will not be given into the hands of the king of Assyria.” <verse eid="2KI 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 19:11"/>Surely you have heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all the countries, destroying them completely. And will you be delivered? <verse eid="2KI 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 19:12"/>Did the gods of the nations that were destroyed by my predecessors deliver them – the gods of Gozan, Harran, Rezeph and the people of Eden who were in Tel Assar? <verse eid="2KI 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 19:13"/>Where is the king of Hamath or the king of Arpad? Where are the kings of Lair, Sepharvaim, Hena and Ivvah?’<verse eid="2KI 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hezekiah’s prayer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 19:14"/>Hezekiah received the letter from the messengers and read it. Then he went up to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and spread it out before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 19:15"/>And Hezekiah prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘<char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, enthroned between the cherubim, you alone are God over all the kingdoms of the earth. You have made heaven and earth. <verse eid="2KI 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 19:16"/>Give ear, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and hear; open your eyes, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and see; listen to the words Sennacherib has sent to ridicule the living God.<verse eid="2KI 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 19:17"/>‘It is true, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, that the Assyrian kings have laid waste these nations and their lands. <verse eid="2KI 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 19:18"/>They have thrown their gods into the fire and destroyed them, for they were not gods but only wood and stone, fashioned by human hands. <verse eid="2KI 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 19:19"/>Now, <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, deliver us from his hand, so that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you alone, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, are God.’<verse eid="2KI 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Isaiah prophesies Sennacherib’s fall</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 19:20"/>Then Isaiah son of Amoz sent a message to Hezekiah: ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says: I have heard your prayer concerning Sennacherib king of Assyria. <verse eid="2KI 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 19:21"/>This is the word that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has spoken against him:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:21">‘ “Virgin Daughter Zion</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:21">despises you and mocks you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:21">Daughter Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:21">tosses her head as you flee.<verse eid="2KI 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 19:22"/>Who is it you have ridiculed and blasphemed?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:22">Against whom have you raised your voice</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:22">and lifted your eyes in pride?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:22">Against the Holy One of Israel!<verse eid="2KI 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 19:23"/>By your messengers</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:23">you have ridiculed the Lord.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:23">And you have said,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:23">‘With my many chariots</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:23">I have ascended the heights of the mountains,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:23">the utmost heights of Lebanon.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:23">I have cut down its tallest cedars,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:23">the choicest of its junipers.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:23">I have reached its remotest parts,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:23">the finest of its forests.<verse eid="2KI 19:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 19:24"/>I have dug wells in foreign lands</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:24">and drunk the water there.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:24">With the soles of my feet</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:24">I have dried up all the streams of Egypt.’<verse eid="2KI 19:24"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 19:25"/>‘ “Have you not heard?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:25">Long ago I ordained it.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:25">In days of old I planned it;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:25">now I have brought it to pass,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:25">that you have turned fortified cities</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:25">into piles of stone.<verse eid="2KI 19:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 19:26"/>Their people, drained of power,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:26">are dismayed and put to shame.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:26">They are like plants in the field,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:26">like tender green shoots,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:26">like grass sprouting on the roof,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:26">scorched before it grows up.<verse eid="2KI 19:26"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 19:27"/>‘ “But I know where you are</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:27">and when you come and go</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:27">and how you rage against me.<verse eid="2KI 19:27"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 19:28"/>Because you rage against me</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:28">and because your insolence has reached my ears,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:28">I will put my hook in your nose</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:28">and my bit in your mouth,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:28">and I will make you return</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:28">by the way you came.”<verse eid="2KI 19:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 19:29"/>‘This will be the sign for you, Hezekiah:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:29">‘This year you will eat what grows by itself,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:29">and the second year what springs from that.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:29">But in the third year sow and reap,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:29">plant vineyards and eat their fruit.<verse eid="2KI 19:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 19:30"/>Once more a remnant of the kingdom of Judah</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:30">will take root below and bear fruit above.<verse eid="2KI 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 19:31"/>For out of Jerusalem will come a remnant,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:31">and out of Mount Zion a band of survivors.</para>
  <para style="m" vid="2KI 19:31">‘The zeal of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> Almighty will accomplish this.<verse eid="2KI 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 19:32"/>‘Therefore this is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says concerning the king of Assyria:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:32">‘ “He will not enter this city</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:32">or shoot an arrow here.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2KI 19:32">He will not come before it with shield</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:32">or build a siege ramp against it.<verse eid="2KI 19:32"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 19:33"/>By the way that he came he will return;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:33">he will not enter this city,”</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:33">declares the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="2KI 19:33"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 19:34"/>“I will defend this city and save it,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2KI 19:34">for my sake and for the sake of David my servant.” ’<verse eid="2KI 19:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 19:35"/>That night the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> went out and put to death a hundred and eighty-five thousand in the Assyrian camp. When the people got up the next morning – there were all the dead bodies! <verse eid="2KI 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 19:36"/>So Sennacherib king of Assyria broke camp and withdrew. He returned to Nineveh and stayed there.<verse eid="2KI 19:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="2KI 19:37"/>One day, while he was worshipping in the temple of his god Nisrok, his sons Adrammelek and Sharezer killed him with the sword, and they escaped to the land of Ararat. And Esarhaddon his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 19:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="2KI 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Hezekiah’s illness</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 20:1"/>In those days Hezekiah became ill and was at the point of death. The prophet Isaiah son of Amoz went to him and said, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: put your house in order, because you are going to die; you will not recover.’<verse eid="2KI 20:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 20:2"/>Hezekiah turned his face to the wall and prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, <verse eid="2KI 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 20:3"/>‘Remember, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, how I have walked before you faithfully and with wholehearted devotion and have done what is good in your eyes.’ And Hezekiah wept bitterly.<verse eid="2KI 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 20:4"/>Before Isaiah had left the middle court, the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came to him: <verse eid="2KI 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 20:5"/>‘Go back and tell Hezekiah, the ruler of my people, “This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of your father David, says: I have heard your prayer and seen your tears; I will heal you. On the third day from now you will go up to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 20:6"/>I will add fifteen years to your life. And I will deliver you and this city from the hand of the king of Assyria. I will defend this city for my sake and for the sake of my servant David.” ’<verse eid="2KI 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 20:7"/>Then Isaiah said, ‘Prepare a poultice of figs.’ They did so and applied it to the boil, and he recovered.<verse eid="2KI 20:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 20:8"/>Hezekiah had asked Isaiah, ‘What will be the sign that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will heal me and that I will go up to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> on the third day from now?’<verse eid="2KI 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 20:9"/>Isaiah answered, ‘This is the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s sign to you that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will do what he has promised: shall the shadow go forward ten steps, or shall it go back ten steps?’<verse eid="2KI 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 20:10"/>‘It is a simple matter for the shadow to go forward ten steps,’ said Hezekiah. ‘Rather, let it go back ten steps.’<verse eid="2KI 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 20:11"/>Then the prophet Isaiah called on the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> made the shadow go back the ten steps it had gone down on the stairway of Ahaz.<verse eid="2KI 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Envoys from Babylon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 20:12"/>At that time Marduk-Baladan son of Baladan king of Babylon sent Hezekiah letters and a gift, because he had heard of Hezekiah’s illness. <verse eid="2KI 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 20:13"/>Hezekiah received the envoys and showed them all that was in his storehouses – the silver, the gold, the spices and the fine oil – his armoury and everything found among his treasures. There was nothing in his palace or in all his kingdom that Hezekiah did not show them.<verse eid="2KI 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 20:14"/>Then Isaiah the prophet went to King Hezekiah and asked, ‘What did those men say, and where did they come from?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 20:14">‘From a distant land,’ Hezekiah replied. ‘They came from Babylon.’<verse eid="2KI 20:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 20:15"/>The prophet asked, ‘What did they see in your palace?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 20:15">‘They saw everything in my palace,’ Hezekiah said. ‘There is nothing among my treasures that I did not show them.’<verse eid="2KI 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 20:16"/>Then Isaiah said to Hezekiah, ‘Hear the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: <verse eid="2KI 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 20:17"/>the time will surely come when everything in your palace, and all that your predecessors have stored up until this day, will be carried off to Babylon. Nothing will be left, says the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 20:18"/>And some of your descendants, your own flesh and blood who will be born to you, will be taken away, and they will become eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon.’<verse eid="2KI 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 20:19"/>‘The word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> you have spoken is good,’ Hezekiah replied. For he thought, ‘Will there not be peace and security in my lifetime?’<verse eid="2KI 20:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 20:20"/>As for the other events of Hezekiah’s reign, all his achievements and how he made the pool and the tunnel by which he brought water into the city, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 20:21"/>Hezekiah rested with his ancestors. And Manasseh his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 20:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="2KI 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Manasseh king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 21:1"/>Manasseh was twelve years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for fifty-five years. His mother’s name was Hephzibah. <verse eid="2KI 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 21:2"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, following the detestable practices of the nations the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had driven out before the Israelites. <verse eid="2KI 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 21:3"/>He rebuilt the high places his father Hezekiah had destroyed; he also erected altars to Baal and made an Asherah pole, as Ahab king of Israel had done. He bowed down to all the starry hosts and worshipped them. <verse eid="2KI 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 21:4"/>He built altars in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, of which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said, ‘In Jerusalem I will put my Name.’ <verse eid="2KI 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 21:5"/>In the two courts of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, he built altars to all the starry hosts. <verse eid="2KI 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 21:6"/>He sacrificed his own son in the fire, practised divination, sought omens, and consulted mediums and spiritists. He did much evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, arousing his anger.<verse eid="2KI 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 21:7"/>He took the carved Asherah pole he had made and put it in the temple, of which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had said to David and to his son Solomon, ‘In this temple and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I will put my Name for ever. <verse eid="2KI 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 21:8"/>I will not again make the feet of the Israelites wander from the land I gave their ancestors, if only they will be careful to do everything I commanded them and will keep the whole Law that my servant Moses gave them.’ <verse eid="2KI 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 21:9"/>But the people did not listen. Manasseh led them astray, so that they did more evil than the nations the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had destroyed before the Israelites.<verse eid="2KI 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 21:10"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said through his servants the prophets: <verse eid="2KI 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 21:11"/>‘Manasseh king of Judah has committed these detestable sins. He has done more evil than the Amorites who preceded him and has led Judah into sin with his idols. <verse eid="2KI 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 21:12"/>Therefore this is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says: I am going to bring such disaster on Jerusalem and Judah that the ears of everyone who hears of it will tingle. <verse eid="2KI 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 21:13"/>I will stretch out over Jerusalem the measuring line used against Samaria and the plumb-line used against the house of Ahab. I will wipe out Jerusalem as one wipes out a dish, wiping it and turning it upside down. <verse eid="2KI 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 21:14"/>I will forsake the remnant of my inheritance and give them into the hands of enemies. They will be looted and plundered by all their enemies; <verse eid="2KI 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 21:15"/>they have done evil in my eyes and have aroused my anger from the day their ancestors came out of Egypt until this day.’<verse eid="2KI 21:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 21:16"/>Moreover, Manasseh also shed so much innocent blood that he filled Jerusalem from end to end – besides the sin that he had caused Judah to commit, so that they did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="2KI 21:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 21:17"/>As for the other events of Manasseh’s reign, and all he did, including the sin he committed, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 21:18"/>Manasseh rested with his ancestors and was buried in his palace garden, the garden of Uzza. And Amon his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 21:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Amon king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 21:19"/>Amon was twenty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for two years. His mother’s name was Meshullemeth daughter of Haruz; she was from Jotbah. <verse eid="2KI 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 21:20"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, as his father Manasseh had done. <verse eid="2KI 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 21:21"/>He followed completely the ways of his father, worshipping the idols his father had worshipped, and bowing down to them. <verse eid="2KI 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 21:22"/>He forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of his ancestors, and did not walk in obedience to him.<verse eid="2KI 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 21:23"/>Amon’s officials conspired against him and assassinated the king in his palace. <verse eid="2KI 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 21:24"/>Then the people of the land killed all who had plotted against King Amon, and they made Josiah his son king in his place.<verse eid="2KI 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 21:25"/>As for the other events of Amon’s reign, and what he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 21:26"/>He was buried in his tomb in the garden of Uzza. And Josiah his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 21:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="2KI 22"/>
  <para style="s1">The Book of the Law found</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 22:1"/>Josiah was eight years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for thirty-one years. His mother’s name was Jedidah daughter of Adaiah; she was from Bozkath. <verse eid="2KI 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 22:2"/>He did what was right in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and followed completely the ways of his father David, not turning aside to the right or to the left.<verse eid="2KI 22:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 22:3"/>In the eighteenth year of his reign, King Josiah sent the secretary, Shaphan son of Azaliah, the son of Meshullam, to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He said: <verse eid="2KI 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 22:4"/>‘Go up to Hilkiah the high priest and make him get ready the money that has been brought into the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, which the doorkeepers have collected from the people. <verse eid="2KI 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 22:5"/>Make them entrust it to the men appointed to supervise the work on the temple. And make these men pay the workers who repair the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> – <verse eid="2KI 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 22:6"/>the carpenters, the builders and the masons. Also make them purchase timber and dressed stone to repair the temple. <verse eid="2KI 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 22:7"/>But they need not account for the money entrusted to them, because they are honest in their dealings.’<verse eid="2KI 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 22:8"/>Hilkiah the high priest said to Shaphan the secretary, ‘I have found the Book of the Law in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ He gave it to Shaphan, who read it. <verse eid="2KI 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 22:9"/>Then Shaphan the secretary went to the king and reported to him: ‘Your officials have paid out the money that was in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and have entrusted it to the workers and supervisors at the temple.’ <verse eid="2KI 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 22:10"/>Then Shaphan the secretary informed the king, ‘Hilkiah the priest has given me a book.’ And Shaphan read from it in the presence of the king.<verse eid="2KI 22:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 22:11"/>When the king heard the words of the Book of the Law, he tore his robes. <verse eid="2KI 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 22:12"/>He gave these orders to Hilkiah the priest, Ahikam son of Shaphan, Akbor son of Micaiah, Shaphan the secretary and Asaiah the king’s attendant: <verse eid="2KI 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 22:13"/>‘Go and enquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for me and for the people and for all Judah about what is written in this book that has been found. Great is the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger that burns against us because those who have gone before us have not obeyed the words of this book; they have not acted in accordance with all that is written there concerning us.’<verse eid="2KI 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 22:14"/>Hilkiah the priest, Ahikam, Akbor, Shaphan and Asaiah went to speak to the prophet Huldah, who was the wife of Shallum son of Tikvah, the son of Harhas, keeper of the wardrobe. She lived in Jerusalem, in the New Quarter.<verse eid="2KI 22:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 22:15"/>She said to them, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says: tell the man who sent you to me, <verse eid="2KI 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 22:16"/>“This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: I am going to bring disaster on this place and its people, according to everything written in the book the king of Judah has read. <verse eid="2KI 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 22:17"/>Because they have forsaken me and burned incense to other gods and aroused my anger by all the idols their hands have made,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">by everything they have done</char></note> my anger will burn against this place and will not be quenched.” <verse eid="2KI 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 22:18"/>Tell the king of Judah, who sent you to enquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, “This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says concerning the words you heard: <verse eid="2KI 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 22:19"/>because your heart was responsive and you humbled yourself before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> when you heard what I have spoken against this place and its people – that they would become a curse<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, their names would be used in cursing (see <char style="xt"><ref loc="JER 29:22">Jer. 29:22</ref></char>); or, others would see that they are cursed.</char></note> and be laid waste – and because you tore your robes and wept in my presence, I also have heard you, declares the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 22:20"/>Therefore I will gather you to your ancestors, and you will be buried in peace. Your eyes will not see all the disaster I am going to bring on this place.” ’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 22:20">So they took her answer back to the king.<verse eid="2KI 22:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="2KI 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Josiah renews the covenant</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 23:1"/>Then the king called together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. <verse eid="2KI 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 23:2"/>He went up to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with the people of Judah, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the priests and the prophets – all the people from the least to the greatest. He read in their hearing all the words of the Book of the Covenant, which had been found in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 23:3"/>The king stood by the pillar and renewed the covenant in the presence of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> – to follow the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and keep his commands, statutes and decrees with all his heart and all his soul, thus confirming the words of the covenant written in this book. Then all the people pledged themselves to the covenant.<verse eid="2KI 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 23:4"/>The king ordered Hilkiah the high priest, the priests next in rank and the doorkeepers to remove from the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> all the articles made for Baal and Asherah and all the starry hosts. He burned them outside Jerusalem in the fields of the Kidron Valley and took the ashes to Bethel. <verse eid="2KI 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 23:5"/>He did away with the idolatrous priests appointed by the kings of Judah to burn incense on the high places of the towns of Judah and on those around Jerusalem – those who burned incense to Baal, to the sun and moon, to the constellations and to all the starry hosts. <verse eid="2KI 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 23:6"/>He took the Asherah pole from the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to the Kidron Valley outside Jerusalem and burned it there. He ground it to powder and scattered the dust over the graves of the common people. <verse eid="2KI 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 23:7"/>He also tore down the quarters of the male shrine-prostitutes that were in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the quarters where women did weaving for Asherah.<verse eid="2KI 23:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 23:8"/>Josiah brought all the priests from the towns of Judah and desecrated the high places, from Geba to Beersheba, where the priests had burned incense. He broke down the gateway at the entrance of the Gate of Joshua, the city governor, which was on the left of the city gate. <verse eid="2KI 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 23:9"/>Although the priests of the high places did not serve at the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Jerusalem, they ate unleavened bread with their fellow priests.<verse eid="2KI 23:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 23:10"/>He desecrated Topheth, which was in the Valley of Ben Hinnom, so no-one could use it to sacrifice their son or daughter in the fire to Molek. <verse eid="2KI 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 23:11"/>He removed from the entrance to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> the horses that the kings of Judah had dedicated to the sun. They were in the court<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</char></note> near the room of an official named Nathan-Melek. Josiah then burned the chariots dedicated to the sun.<verse eid="2KI 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 23:12"/>He pulled down the altars the kings of Judah had erected on the roof near the upper room of Ahaz, and the altars Manasseh had built in the two courts of the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He removed them from there, smashed them to pieces and threw the rubble into the Kidron Valley. <verse eid="2KI 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 23:13"/>The king also desecrated the high places that were east of Jerusalem on the south of the Hill of Corruption – the ones Solomon king of Israel had built for Ashtoreth the vile goddess of the Sidonians, for Chemosh the vile god of Moab, and for Molek the detestable god of the people of Ammon. <verse eid="2KI 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 23:14"/>Josiah smashed the sacred stones and cut down the Asherah poles and covered the sites with human bones.<verse eid="2KI 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 23:15"/>Even the altar at Bethel, the high place made by Jeroboam son of Nebat, who had caused Israel to sin – even that altar and high place he demolished. He burned the high place and ground it to powder, and burned the Asherah pole also. <verse eid="2KI 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 23:16"/>Then Josiah looked around, and when he saw the tombs that were there on the hillside, he had the bones removed from them and burned on the altar to defile it, in accordance with the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> proclaimed by the man of God who foretold these things.<verse eid="2KI 23:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 23:17"/>The king asked, ‘What is that tombstone I see?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 23:17">The people of the city said, ‘It marks the tomb of the man of God who came from Judah and pronounced against the altar of Bethel the very things you have done to it.’<verse eid="2KI 23:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 23:18"/>‘Leave it alone,’ he said. ‘Don’t let anyone disturb his bones.’ So they spared his bones and those of the prophet who had come from Samaria.<verse eid="2KI 23:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 23:19"/>Just as he had done at Bethel, Josiah removed all the shrines at the high places that the kings of Israel had built in the towns of Samaria and that had aroused the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger. <verse eid="2KI 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 23:20"/>Josiah slaughtered all the priests of those high places on the altars and burned human bones on them. Then he went back to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2KI 23:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 23:21"/>The king gave this order to all the people: ‘Celebrate the Passover to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, as it is written in this Book of the Covenant.’ <verse eid="2KI 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 23:22"/>Neither in the days of the judges who led Israel nor in the days of the kings of Israel and the kings of Judah had any such Passover been observed. <verse eid="2KI 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 23:23"/>But in the eighteenth year of King Josiah, this Passover was celebrated to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Jerusalem.<verse eid="2KI 23:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 23:24"/>Furthermore, Josiah got rid of the mediums and spiritists, the household gods, the idols and all the other detestable things seen in Judah and Jerusalem. This he did to fulfil the requirements of the law written in the book that Hilkiah the priest had discovered in the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 23:25"/>Neither before nor after Josiah was there a king like him who turned to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> as he did – with all his heart and with all his soul and with all his strength, in accordance with all the Law of Moses.<verse eid="2KI 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 23:26"/>Nevertheless, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> did not turn away from the heat of his fierce anger, which burned against Judah because of all that Manasseh had done to arouse his anger. <verse eid="2KI 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 23:27"/>So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, ‘I will remove Judah also from my presence as I removed Israel, and I will reject Jerusalem, the city I chose, and this temple, about which I said, “My Name shall be there.”<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="1KI 8:29">1 Kings 8:29</ref></char></char></note>’<verse eid="2KI 23:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 23:28"/>As for the other events of Josiah’s reign, and all he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah?<verse eid="2KI 23:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 23:29"/>While Josiah was king, Pharaoh Necho king of Egypt went up to the River Euphrates to help the king of Assyria. King Josiah marched out to meet him in battle, but Necho faced him and killed him at Megiddo. <verse eid="2KI 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 23:30"/>Josiah’s servants brought his body in a chariot from Megiddo to Jerusalem and buried him in his own tomb. And the people of the land took Jehoahaz son of Josiah and anointed him and made him king in place of his father.<verse eid="2KI 23:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoahaz king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2KI 23:31"/>Jehoahaz was twenty-three years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for three months. His mother’s name was Hamutal daughter of Jeremiah; she was from Libnah. <verse eid="2KI 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2KI 23:32"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, just as his predecessors had done. <verse eid="2KI 23:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2KI 23:33"/>Pharaoh Necho put him in chains at Riblah in the land of Hamath so that he might not reign in Jerusalem, and he imposed on Judah a levy of a hundred talents<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 3.4 metric tons</char></note> of silver and a talent<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 34 kilograms</char></note> of gold. <verse eid="2KI 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2KI 23:34"/>Pharaoh Necho made Eliakim son of Josiah king in place of his father Josiah and changed Eliakim’s name to Jehoiakim. But he took Jehoahaz and carried him off to Egypt, and there he died. <verse eid="2KI 23:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2KI 23:35"/>Jehoiakim paid Pharaoh Necho the silver and gold he demanded. In order to do so, he taxed the land and exacted the silver and gold from the people of the land according to their assessments.<verse eid="2KI 23:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoiakim king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2KI 23:36"/>Jehoiakim was twenty-five years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for eleven years. His mother’s name was Zebidah daughter of Pedaiah; she was from Rumah. <verse eid="2KI 23:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2KI 23:37"/>And he did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, just as his predecessors had done.<verse eid="2KI 23:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="2KI 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 24:1"/>During Jehoiakim’s reign, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon invaded the land, and Jehoiakim became his vassal for three years. But then he turned against Nebuchadnezzar and rebelled. <verse eid="2KI 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 24:2"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> sent Babylonian,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Chaldean</char></note> Aramean, Moabite and Ammonite raiders against him to destroy Judah, in accordance with the word of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> proclaimed by his servants the prophets. <verse eid="2KI 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 24:3"/>Surely these things happened to Judah according to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s command, in order to remove them from his presence because of the sins of Manasseh and all he had done, <verse eid="2KI 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 24:4"/>including the shedding of innocent blood. For he had filled Jerusalem with innocent blood, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was not willing to forgive.<verse eid="2KI 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 24:5"/>As for the other events of Jehoiakim’s reign, and all he did, are they not written in the book of the annals of the kings of Judah? <verse eid="2KI 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 24:6"/>Jehoiakim rested with his ancestors. And Jehoiachin his son succeeded him as king.<verse eid="2KI 24:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 24:7"/>The king of Egypt did not march out from his own country again, because the king of Babylon had taken all his territory, from the Wadi of Egypt to the River Euphrates.<verse eid="2KI 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoiachin king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 24:8"/>Jehoiachin was eighteen years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for three months. His mother’s name was Nehushta daughter of Elnathan; she was from Jerusalem. <verse eid="2KI 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 24:9"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, just as his father had done.<verse eid="2KI 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 24:10"/>At that time the officers of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon advanced on Jerusalem and laid siege to it, <verse eid="2KI 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 24:11"/>and Nebuchadnezzar himself came up to the city while his officers were besieging it. <verse eid="2KI 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 24:12"/>Jehoiachin king of Judah, his mother, his attendants, his nobles and his officials all surrendered to him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 24:12">In the eighth year of the reign of the king of Babylon, he took Jehoiachin prisoner. <verse eid="2KI 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 24:13"/>As the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had declared, Nebuchadnezzar removed the treasures from the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and from the royal palace, and cut up the gold articles that Solomon king of Israel had made for the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="2KI 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 24:14"/>He carried all Jerusalem into exile: all the officers and fighting men, and all the skilled workers and artisans – a total of ten thousand. Only the poorest people of the land were left.<verse eid="2KI 24:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 24:15"/>Nebuchadnezzar took Jehoiachin captive to Babylon. He also took from Jerusalem to Babylon the king’s mother, his wives, his officials and the prominent people of the land. <verse eid="2KI 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 24:16"/>The king of Babylon also deported to Babylon the entire force of seven thousand fighting men, strong and fit for war, and a thousand skilled workers and artisans. <verse eid="2KI 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 24:17"/>He made Mattaniah, Jehoiachin’s uncle, king in his place and changed his name to Zedekiah.<verse eid="2KI 24:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Zedekiah king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 24:18"/>Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he became king, and he reigned in Jerusalem for eleven years. His mother’s name was Hamutal daughter of Jeremiah; she was from Libnah. <verse eid="2KI 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 24:19"/>He did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, just as Jehoiakim had done. <verse eid="2KI 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 24:20"/>It was because of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger that all this happened to Jerusalem and Judah, and in the end he thrust them from his presence.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="2KI 24:20">The fall of Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 24:20">Now Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon.<verse eid="2KI 24:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="2KI 25"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2KI 25:1"/>So in the ninth year of Zedekiah’s reign, on the tenth day of the tenth month, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon marched against Jerusalem with his whole army. He camped outside the city and built siege works all around it. <verse eid="2KI 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2KI 25:2"/>The city was kept under siege until the eleventh year of King Zedekiah.<verse eid="2KI 25:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2KI 25:3"/>By the ninth day of the fourth<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Probable reading of the original Hebrew text (see <char style="xt"><ref loc="JER 52:6">Jer. 52:6</ref></char>); Masoretic Text does not have </char><char style="fq" closed="false">fourth</char><char style="ft" closed="false">.</char></note> month the famine in the city had become so severe that there was no food for the people to eat. <verse eid="2KI 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2KI 25:4"/>Then the city wall was broken through, and the whole army fled at night through the gate between the two walls near the king’s garden, though the Babylonians<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Chaldeans</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 13, 25 and 26</char></note> were surrounding the city. They fled towards the Arabah,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the Jordan Valley</char></note> <verse eid="2KI 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2KI 25:5"/>but the Babylonian<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Chaldean</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 10 and 24</char></note> army pursued the king and overtook him in the plains of Jericho. All his soldiers were separated from him and scattered, <verse eid="2KI 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2KI 25:6"/>and he was captured.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 25:6">He was taken to the king of Babylon at Riblah, where sentence was pronounced on him. <verse eid="2KI 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2KI 25:7"/>They killed the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes. Then they put out his eyes, bound him with bronze shackles and took him to Babylon.<verse eid="2KI 25:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2KI 25:8"/>On the seventh day of the fifth month, in the nineteenth year of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, Nebuzaradan commander of the imperial guard, an official of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2KI 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2KI 25:9"/>He set fire to the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the royal palace and all the houses of Jerusalem. Every important building he burned down. <verse eid="2KI 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2KI 25:10"/>The whole Babylonian army under the commander of the imperial guard broke down the walls around Jerusalem. <verse eid="2KI 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2KI 25:11"/>Nebuzaradan the commander of the guard carried into exile the people who remained in the city, along with the rest of the populace and those who had deserted to the king of Babylon. <verse eid="2KI 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2KI 25:12"/>But the commander left behind some of the poorest people of the land to work the vineyards and fields.<verse eid="2KI 25:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2KI 25:13"/>The Babylonians broke up the bronze pillars, the movable stands and the bronze Sea that were at the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and they carried the bronze to Babylon. <verse eid="2KI 25:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2KI 25:14"/>They also took away the pots, shovels, wick trimmers, dishes and all the bronze articles used in the temple service. <verse eid="2KI 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2KI 25:15"/>The commander of the imperial guard took away the censers and sprinkling bowls – all that were made of pure gold or silver.<verse eid="2KI 25:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2KI 25:16"/>The bronze from the two pillars, the Sea and the movable stands, which Solomon had made for the temple of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, was more than could be weighed. <verse eid="2KI 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2KI 25:17"/>Each pillar was eighteen cubits<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 8.1 metres</char></note> high. The bronze capital on top of one pillar was three cubits<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">25:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 1.4 metres</char></note> high and was decorated with a network and pomegranates of bronze all around. The other pillar, with its network, was similar.<verse eid="2KI 25:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2KI 25:18"/>The commander of the guard took as prisoners Seraiah the chief priest, Zephaniah the priest next in rank and the three doorkeepers. <verse eid="2KI 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2KI 25:19"/>Of those still in the city, he took the officer in charge of the fighting men, and five royal advisors. He also took the secretary who was chief officer in charge of conscripting the people of the land and sixty of the conscripts who were found in the city. <verse eid="2KI 25:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2KI 25:20"/>Nebuzaradan the commander took them all and brought them to the king of Babylon at Riblah. <verse eid="2KI 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2KI 25:21"/>There at Riblah, in the land of Hamath, the king had them executed.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2KI 25:21">So Judah went into captivity, away from her land.<verse eid="2KI 25:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2KI 25:22"/>Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon appointed Gedaliah son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, to be over the people he had left behind in Judah. <verse eid="2KI 25:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2KI 25:23"/>When all the army officers and their men heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Gedaliah as governor, they came to Gedaliah at Mizpah – Ishmael son of Nethaniah, Johanan son of Kareah, Seraiah son of Tanhumeth the Netophathite, Jaazaniah the son of the Maakathite, and their men. <verse eid="2KI 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2KI 25:24"/>Gedaliah took an oath to reassure them and their men. ‘Do not be afraid of the Babylonian officials,’ he said. ‘Settle down in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will go well with you.’<verse eid="2KI 25:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2KI 25:25"/>In the seventh month, however, Ishmael son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama, who was of royal blood, came with ten men and assassinated Gedaliah and also the men of Judah and the Babylonians who were with him at Mizpah. <verse eid="2KI 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2KI 25:26"/>At this, all the people from the least to the greatest, together with the army officers, fled to Egypt for fear of the Babylonians.<verse eid="2KI 25:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoiachin released</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2KI 25:27"/>In the thirty-seventh year of the exile of Jehoiachin king of Judah, in the year Awel-Marduk became king of Babylon, he released Jehoiachin king of Judah from prison. He did this on the twenty-seventh day of the twelfth month. <verse eid="2KI 25:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2KI 25:28"/>He spoke kindly to him and gave him a seat of honour higher than those of the other kings who were with him in Babylon. <verse eid="2KI 25:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2KI 25:29"/>So Jehoiachin put aside his prison clothes and for the rest of his life ate regularly at the king’s table. <verse eid="2KI 25:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2KI 25:30"/>Day by day the king gave Jehoiachin a regular allowance as long as he lived.<verse eid="2KI 25:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2KI 25"/>
</usx>
