<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JDG" style="id">- English-UK: New International Version® (Anglicised) NIV® 2011 (Revised format)</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1973, 1978, 1984, 2011 by Biblica, Inc.®</para>
  <para style="h">Judges</para>
  <para style="toc1">Judges</para>
  <para style="toc2">Judges</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jdg</para>
  <para style="mt1">Judges</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">See the Invitation to Joshua and Judges.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JDG 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Israel fights the remaining Canaanites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 1:1"/>After the death of Joshua, the Israelites asked the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘Who of us is to go up first to fight against the Canaanites?’<verse eid="JDG 1:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 1:2"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> answered, ‘Judah shall go up; I have given the land into their hands.’<verse eid="JDG 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 1:3"/>The men of Judah then said to the Simeonites their fellow Israelites, ‘Come up with us into the territory allotted to us, to fight against the Canaanites. We in turn will go with you into yours.’ So the Simeonites went with them.<verse eid="JDG 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 1:4"/>When Judah attacked, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave the Canaanites and Perizzites into their hands, and they struck down ten thousand men at Bezek. <verse eid="JDG 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 1:5"/>It was there that they found Adoni-Bezek and fought against him, putting to rout the Canaanites and Perizzites. <verse eid="JDG 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 1:6"/>Adoni-Bezek fled, but they chased him and caught him, and cut off his thumbs and big toes.<verse eid="JDG 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 1:7"/>Then Adoni-Bezek said, ‘Seventy kings with their thumbs and big toes cut off have picked up scraps under my table. Now God has paid me back for what I did to them.’ They brought him to Jerusalem, and he died there.<verse eid="JDG 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 1:8"/>The men of Judah attacked Jerusalem also and took it. They put the city to the sword and set it on fire.<verse eid="JDG 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 1:9"/>After that, Judah went down to fight against the Canaanites living in the hill country, the Negev and the western foothills. <verse eid="JDG 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 1:10"/>They advanced against the Canaanites living in Hebron (formerly called Kiriath Arba) and defeated Sheshai, Ahiman and Talmai. <verse eid="JDG 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 1:11"/>From there they advanced against the people living in Debir (formerly called Kiriath Sepher).<verse eid="JDG 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 1:12"/>And Caleb said, ‘I will give my daughter Aksah in marriage to the man who attacks and captures Kiriath Sepher.’ <verse eid="JDG 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 1:13"/>Othniel son of Kenaz, Caleb’s younger brother, took it; so Caleb gave his daughter Aksah to him in marriage.<verse eid="JDG 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 1:14"/>One day when she came to Othniel, she urged him<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; Septuagint and Vulgate </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Othniel, he urged her</char></note> to ask her father for a field. When she got off her donkey, Caleb asked her, ‘What can I do for you?’<verse eid="JDG 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 1:15"/>She replied, ‘Do me a special favour. Since you have given me land in the Negev, give me also springs of water.’ So Caleb gave her the upper and lower springs.<verse eid="JDG 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 1:16"/>The descendants of Moses’ father-in-law, the Kenite, went up from the City of Palms<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, Jericho</char></note> with the people of Judah to live among the inhabitants of the Desert of Judah in the Negev near Arad.<verse eid="JDG 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 1:17"/>Then the men of Judah went with the Simeonites their fellow Israelites and attacked the Canaanites living in Zephath, and they totally destroyed<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them.</char></note> the city. Therefore it was called Hormah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:17 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Hormah </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">destruction.</char></note> <verse eid="JDG 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 1:18"/>Judah also took<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; Septuagint </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Judah did not take</char></note> Gaza, Ashkelon and Ekron – each city with its territory.<verse eid="JDG 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 1:19"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with the men of Judah. They took possession of the hill country, but they were unable to drive the people from the plains, because they had chariots fitted with iron. <verse eid="JDG 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 1:20"/>As Moses had promised, Hebron was given to Caleb, who drove from it the three sons of Anak. <verse eid="JDG 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 1:21"/>The Benjaminites, however, did not drive out the Jebusites, who were living in Jerusalem; to this day the Jebusites live there with the Benjaminites.<verse eid="JDG 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 1:22"/>Now the tribes of Joseph attacked Bethel, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with them. <verse eid="JDG 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 1:23"/>When they sent men to spy out Bethel (formerly called Luz), <verse eid="JDG 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 1:24"/>the spies saw a man coming out of the city and they said to him, ‘Show us how to get into the city and we will see that you are treated well.’ <verse eid="JDG 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 1:25"/>So he showed them, and they put the city to the sword but spared the man and his whole family. <verse eid="JDG 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 1:26"/>He then went to the land of the Hittites, where he built a city and called it Luz, which is its name to this day.<verse eid="JDG 1:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 1:27"/>But Manasseh did not drive out the people of Beth Shan or Taanach or Dor or Ibleam or Megiddo and their surrounding settlements, for the Canaanites were determined to live in that land. <verse eid="JDG 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 1:28"/>When Israel became strong, they pressed the Canaanites into forced labour but never drove them out completely. <verse eid="JDG 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 1:29"/>Nor did Ephraim drive out the Canaanites living in Gezer, but the Canaanites continued to live there among them. <verse eid="JDG 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 1:30"/>Neither did Zebulun drive out the Canaanites living in Kitron or Nahalol, so these Canaanites lived among them, but Zebulun did subject them to forced labour. <verse eid="JDG 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 1:31"/>Nor did Asher drive out those living in Akko or Sidon or Ahlab or Akzib or Helbah or Aphek or Rehob. <verse eid="JDG 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 1:32"/>The Asherites lived among the Canaanite inhabitants of the land because they did not drive them out. <verse eid="JDG 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 1:33"/>Neither did Naphtali drive out those living in Beth Shemesh or Beth Anath; but the Naphtalites too lived among the Canaanite inhabitants of the land, and those living in Beth Shemesh and Beth Anath became forced labourers for them. <verse eid="JDG 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 1:34"/>The Amorites confined the Danites to the hill country, not allowing them to come down into the plain. <verse eid="JDG 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 1:35"/>And the Amorites were determined also to hold out in Mount Heres, Aijalon and Shaalbim, but when the power of the tribes of Joseph increased, they too were pressed into forced labour. <verse eid="JDG 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 1:36"/>The boundary of the Amorites was from Scorpion Pass to Sela and beyond.<verse eid="JDG 1:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JDG 2"/>
  <para style="s1">The angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at Bokim</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 2:1"/>The angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> went up from Gilgal to Bokim and said, ‘I brought you up out of Egypt and led you into the land that I swore to give to your ancestors. I said, “I will never break my covenant with you, <verse eid="JDG 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 2:2"/>and you shall not make a covenant with the people of this land, but you shall break down their altars.” Yet you have disobeyed me. Why have you done this? <verse eid="JDG 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 2:3"/>And I have also said, “I will not drive them out before you; they will become traps for you, and their gods will become snares to you.” ’<verse eid="JDG 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 2:4"/>When the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had spoken these things to all the Israelites, the people wept aloud, <verse eid="JDG 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 2:5"/>and they called that place Bokim.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:5 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Bokim </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">weepers.</char></note> There they offered sacrifices to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JDG 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Disobedience and defeat</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 2:6"/>After Joshua had dismissed the Israelites, they went to take possession of the land, each to their own inheritance. <verse eid="JDG 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 2:7"/>The people served the <char style="sc">Lord</char> throughout the lifetime of Joshua and of the elders who outlived him and who had seen all the great things the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had done for Israel.<verse eid="JDG 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 2:8"/>Joshua son of Nun, the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, died at the age of a hundred and ten. <verse eid="JDG 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 2:9"/>And they buried him in the land of his inheritance, at Timnath Heres<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Also known as </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Timnath Serah </char><char style="ft" closed="false">(see <char style="xt"><ref loc="JOS 19:50">Joshua 19:50</ref></char> and 24:30)</char></note> in the hill country of Ephraim, north of Mount Gaash.<verse eid="JDG 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 2:10"/>After that whole generation had been gathered to their ancestors, another generation grew up who knew neither the <char style="sc">Lord</char> nor what he had done for Israel. <verse eid="JDG 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 2:11"/>Then the Israelites did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and served the Baals. <verse eid="JDG 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 2:12"/>They forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of their ancestors, who had brought them out of Egypt. They followed and worshipped various gods of the peoples around them. They aroused the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger <verse eid="JDG 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 2:13"/>because they forsook him and served Baal and the Ashtoreths. <verse eid="JDG 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 2:14"/>In his anger against Israel the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave them into the hands of raiders who plundered them. He sold them into the hands of their enemies all around, whom they were no longer able to resist. <verse eid="JDG 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 2:15"/>Whenever Israel went out to fight, the hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was against them to defeat them, just as he had sworn to them. They were in great distress.<verse eid="JDG 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 2:16"/>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> raised up judges,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">leaders</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; similarly in verses 17-19</char></note> who saved them out of the hands of these raiders. <verse eid="JDG 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 2:17"/>Yet they would not listen to their judges but prostituted themselves to other gods and worshipped them. They quickly turned from the ways of their ancestors, who had been obedient to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s commands. <verse eid="JDG 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 2:18"/>Whenever the <char style="sc">Lord</char> raised up a judge for them, he was with the judge and saved them out of the hands of their enemies as long as the judge lived; for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> relented because of their groaning under those who oppressed and afflicted them. <verse eid="JDG 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 2:19"/>But when the judge died, the people returned to ways even more corrupt than those of their ancestors, following other gods and serving and worshipping them. They refused to give up their evil practices and stubborn ways.<verse eid="JDG 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 2:20"/>Therefore the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was very angry with Israel and said, ‘Because this nation has violated the covenant I ordained for their ancestors and has not listened to me, <verse eid="JDG 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 2:21"/>I will no longer drive out before them any of the nations Joshua left when he died. <verse eid="JDG 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 2:22"/>I will use them to test Israel and see whether they will keep the way of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and walk in it as their ancestors did.’ <verse eid="JDG 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 2:23"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> had allowed those nations to remain; he did not drive them out at once by giving them into the hands of Joshua.<verse eid="JDG 2:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JDG 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 3:1"/>These are the nations the <char style="sc">Lord</char> left to test all those Israelites who had not experienced any of the wars in Canaan <verse eid="JDG 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 3:2"/>(he did this only to teach warfare to the descendants of the Israelites who had not had previous battle experience): <verse eid="JDG 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 3:3"/>the five rulers of the Philistines, all the Canaanites, the Sidonians, and the Hivites living in the Lebanon mountains from Mount Baal Hermon to Lebo Hamath. <verse eid="JDG 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 3:4"/>They were left to test the Israelites to see whether they would obey the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s commands, which he had given their ancestors through Moses.<verse eid="JDG 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 3:5"/>The Israelites lived among the Canaanites, Hittites, Amorites, Perizzites, Hivites and Jebusites. <verse eid="JDG 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 3:6"/>They took their daughters in marriage and gave their own daughters to their sons, and served their gods.<verse eid="JDG 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Othniel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 3:7"/>The Israelites did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>; they forgot the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God and served the Baals and the Asherahs. <verse eid="JDG 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 3:8"/>The anger of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> burned against Israel so that he sold them into the hands of Cushan-Rishathaim king of Aram Naharaim,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, North-west Mesopotamia</char></note> to whom the Israelites were subject for eight years. <verse eid="JDG 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 3:9"/>But when they cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, he raised up for them a deliverer, Othniel son of Kenaz, Caleb’s younger brother, who saved them. <verse eid="JDG 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 3:10"/>The Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came on him, so that he became Israel’s judge<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">leader</char></note> and went to war. The <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave Cushan-Rishathaim king of Aram into the hands of Othniel, who overpowered him. <verse eid="JDG 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 3:11"/>So the land had peace for forty years, until Othniel son of Kenaz died.<verse eid="JDG 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ehud</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 3:12"/>Again the Israelites did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and because they did this evil the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave Eglon king of Moab power over Israel. <verse eid="JDG 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 3:13"/>Getting the Ammonites and Amalekites to join him, Eglon came and attacked Israel, and they took possession of the City of Palms.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, Jericho</char></note> <verse eid="JDG 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 3:14"/>The Israelites were subject to Eglon king of Moab for eighteen years.<verse eid="JDG 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 3:15"/>Again the Israelites cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and he gave them a deliverer – Ehud, a left-handed man, the son of Gera the Benjaminite. The Israelites sent him with tribute to Eglon king of Moab. <verse eid="JDG 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 3:16"/>Now Ehud had made a double-edged sword about a cubit<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 45 centimetres</char></note> long, which he strapped to his right thigh under his clothing. <verse eid="JDG 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 3:17"/>He presented the tribute to Eglon king of Moab, who was a very fat man. <verse eid="JDG 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 3:18"/>After Ehud had presented the tribute, he sent on their way those who had carried it. <verse eid="JDG 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 3:19"/>But on reaching the stone images near Gilgal he himself went back to Eglon and said, ‘Your majesty, I have a secret message for you.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 3:19">The king said to his attendants, ‘Leave us!’ And they all left.<verse eid="JDG 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 3:20"/>Ehud then approached him while he was sitting alone in the upper room of his palace<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain; also in verse 24.</char></note> and said, ‘I have a message from God for you.’ As the king rose from his seat, <verse eid="JDG 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 3:21"/>Ehud reached with his left hand, drew the sword from his right thigh and plunged it into the king’s belly. <verse eid="JDG 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 3:22"/>Even the handle sank in after the blade, and his bowels discharged. Ehud did not pull the sword out, and the fat closed in over it. <verse eid="JDG 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 3:23"/>Then Ehud went out to the porch<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</char></note>; he shut the doors of the upper room behind him and locked them.<verse eid="JDG 3:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 3:24"/>After he had gone, the servants came and found the doors of the upper room locked. They said, ‘He must be relieving himself in the inner room of the palace.’ <verse eid="JDG 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 3:25"/>They waited to the point of embarrassment, but when he did not open the doors of the room, they took a key and unlocked them. There they saw their lord fallen to the floor, dead.<verse eid="JDG 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 3:26"/>While they waited, Ehud got away. He passed by the stone images and escaped to Seirah. <verse eid="JDG 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 3:27"/>When he arrived there, he blew a trumpet in the hill country of Ephraim, and the Israelites went down with him from the hills, with him leading them.<verse eid="JDG 3:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 3:28"/>‘Follow me,’ he ordered, ‘for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given Moab, your enemy, into your hands.’ So they followed him down and took possession of the fords of the Jordan that led to Moab; they allowed no-one to cross over. <verse eid="JDG 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 3:29"/>At that time they struck down about ten thousand Moabites, all vigorous and strong; not one escaped. <verse eid="JDG 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 3:30"/>That day Moab was made subject to Israel, and the land had peace for eighty years.<verse eid="JDG 3:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Shamgar</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 3:31"/>After Ehud came Shamgar son of Anath, who struck down six hundred Philistines with an ox-goad. He too saved Israel.<verse eid="JDG 3:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JDG 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Deborah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 4:1"/>Again the Israelites did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, now that Ehud was dead. <verse eid="JDG 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 4:2"/>So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sold them into the hands of Jabin king of Canaan, who reigned in Hazor. Sisera, the commander of his army, was based in Harosheth Haggoyim. <verse eid="JDG 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 4:3"/>Because he had nine hundred chariots fitted with iron and had cruelly oppressed the Israelites for twenty years, they cried to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for help.<verse eid="JDG 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 4:4"/>Now Deborah, a prophet, the wife of Lappidoth, was leading<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Traditionally </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">judging</char></note> Israel at that time. <verse eid="JDG 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 4:5"/>She held court under the Palm of Deborah between Ramah and Bethel in the hill country of Ephraim, and the Israelites went up to her to have their disputes decided. <verse eid="JDG 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 4:6"/>She sent for Barak son of Abinoam from Kedesh in Naphtali and said to him, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, commands you: “Go, take with you ten thousand men of Naphtali and Zebulun and lead them up to Mount Tabor. <verse eid="JDG 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 4:7"/>I will lead Sisera, the commander of Jabin’s army, with his chariots and his troops to the River Kishon and give him into your hands.” ’<verse eid="JDG 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 4:8"/>Barak said to her, ‘If you go with me, I will go; but if you don’t go with me, I won’t go.’<verse eid="JDG 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 4:9"/>‘Certainly I will go with you,’ said Deborah. ‘But because of the course you are taking, the honour will not be yours, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will deliver Sisera into the hands of a woman.’ So Deborah went with Barak to Kedesh. <verse eid="JDG 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 4:10"/>There Barak summoned Zebulun and Naphtali, and ten thousand men went up under his command. Deborah also went up with him.<verse eid="JDG 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 4:11"/>Now Heber the Kenite had left the other Kenites, the descendants of Hobab, Moses’ brother-in-law,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">father-in-law</char></note> and pitched his tent by the great tree in Zaanannim near Kedesh.<verse eid="JDG 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 4:12"/>When they told Sisera that Barak son of Abinoam had gone up to Mount Tabor, <verse eid="JDG 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 4:13"/>Sisera summoned from Harosheth Haggoyim to the River Kishon all his men and his nine hundred chariots fitted with iron.<verse eid="JDG 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 4:14"/>Then Deborah said to Barak, ‘Go! This is the day the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given Sisera into your hands. Has not the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gone ahead of you?’ So Barak went down Mount Tabor, with ten thousand men following him. <verse eid="JDG 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 4:15"/>At Barak’s advance, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> routed Sisera and all his chariots and army by the sword, and Sisera got down from his chariot and fled on foot.<verse eid="JDG 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 4:16"/>Barak pursued the chariots and army as far as Harosheth Haggoyim, and all Sisera’s troops fell by the sword; not a man was left. <verse eid="JDG 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 4:17"/>Sisera, meanwhile, fled on foot to the tent of Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite, because there was an alliance between Jabin king of Hazor and the family of Heber the Kenite.<verse eid="JDG 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 4:18"/>Jael went out to meet Sisera and said to him, ‘Come, my lord, come right in. Don’t be afraid.’ So he entered her tent, and she covered him with a blanket.<verse eid="JDG 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 4:19"/>‘I’m thirsty,’ he said. ‘Please give me some water.’ She opened a skin of milk, gave him a drink, and covered him up.<verse eid="JDG 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 4:20"/>‘Stand in the doorway of the tent,’ he told her. ‘If someone comes and asks you, “Is anyone in there?” say “No.” ’<verse eid="JDG 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 4:21"/>But Jael, Heber’s wife, picked up a tent peg and a hammer and went quietly to him while he lay fast asleep, exhausted. She drove the peg through his temple into the ground, and he died.<verse eid="JDG 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 4:22"/>Just then Barak came by in pursuit of Sisera, and Jael went out to meet him. ‘Come,’ she said, ‘I will show you the man you’re looking for.’ So he went in with her, and there lay Sisera with the tent peg through his temple – dead.<verse eid="JDG 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 4:23"/>On that day God subdued Jabin king of Canaan before the Israelites. <verse eid="JDG 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 4:24"/>And the hand of the Israelites pressed harder and harder against Jabin king of Canaan until they destroyed him.<verse eid="JDG 4:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JDG 5"/>
  <para style="s1">The song of Deborah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 5:1"/>On that day Deborah and Barak son of Abinoam sang this song:<verse eid="JDG 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 5:2"/>‘When the princes in Israel take the lead,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:2">when the people willingly offer themselves –</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:2">praise the <char style="sc">Lord</char>!<verse eid="JDG 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 5:3"/>‘Hear this, you kings! Listen, you rulers!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:3">I, even I, will sing to<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">of</char></note> the <char style="sc">Lord</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:3">I will praise the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, in song.<verse eid="JDG 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 5:4"/>‘When you, <char style="sc">Lord</char>, went out from Seir,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:4">when you marched from the land of Edom,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:4">the earth shook, the heavens poured,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:4">the clouds poured down water.<verse eid="JDG 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 5:5"/>The mountains quaked before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the One of Sinai,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:5">before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel.<verse eid="JDG 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 5:6"/>‘In the days of Shamgar son of Anath,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:6">in the days of Jael, the highways were abandoned;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:6">travellers took to winding paths.<verse eid="JDG 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 5:7"/>Villagers in Israel would not fight;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:7">they held back until I, Deborah, arose,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:7">until I arose, a mother in Israel.<verse eid="JDG 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 5:8"/>God chose new leaders</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:8">when war came to the city gates,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:8">but not a shield or spear was seen</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:8">among forty thousand in Israel.<verse eid="JDG 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 5:9"/>My heart is with Israel’s princes,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:9">with the willing volunteers among the people.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:9">Praise the <char style="sc">Lord</char>!<verse eid="JDG 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 5:10"/>‘You who ride on white donkeys,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:10">sitting on your saddle blankets,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:10">and you who walk along the road,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:10">consider <verse eid="JDG 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 5:11"/>the voice of the singers<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</char></note> at the watering places.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:11">They recite the victories of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:11">the victories of his villagers in Israel.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JDG 5:11"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:11">‘Then the people of the <char style="sc">Lord</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:11">went down to the city gates.<verse eid="JDG 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 5:12"/>“Wake up, wake up, Deborah!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:12">Wake up, wake up, break out in song!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:12">Arise, Barak!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:12">Take captive your captives, son of Abinoam.”<verse eid="JDG 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 5:13"/>‘The remnant of the nobles came down;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:13">the people of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came down to me against the mighty.<verse eid="JDG 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 5:14"/>Some came from Ephraim, whose roots were in Amalek;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:14">Benjamin was with the people who followed you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:14">From Makir captains came down,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:14">from Zebulun those who bear a commander’s<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</char></note> staff.<verse eid="JDG 5:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 5:15"/>The princes of Issachar were with Deborah;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:15">yes, Issachar was with Barak,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:15">sent under his command into the valley.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:15">In the districts of Reuben</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:15">there was much searching of heart.<verse eid="JDG 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 5:16"/>Why did you stay among the sheepfolds<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the campfires</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the saddlebags</char></note></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:16">to hear the whistling for the flocks?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:16">In the districts of Reuben</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:16">there was much searching of heart.<verse eid="JDG 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 5:17"/>Gilead stayed beyond the Jordan.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:17">And Dan, why did he linger by the ships?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:17">Asher remained on the coast</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:17">and stayed in his coves.<verse eid="JDG 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 5:18"/>The people of Zebulun risked their very lives;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:18">so did Naphtali on the terraced fields.<verse eid="JDG 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 5:19"/>‘Kings came, they fought,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:19">the kings of Canaan fought.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:19">At Taanach, by the waters of Megiddo,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:19">they took no plunder of silver.<verse eid="JDG 5:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 5:20"/>From the heavens the stars fought,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:20">from their courses they fought against Sisera.<verse eid="JDG 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 5:21"/>The River Kishon swept them away,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:21">the age-old river, the River Kishon.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:21">March on, my soul; be strong!<verse eid="JDG 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 5:22"/>Then thundered the horses’ hooves –</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:22">galloping, galloping go his mighty steeds.<verse eid="JDG 5:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 5:23"/>“Curse Meroz,” said the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:23">“Curse its people bitterly,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:23">because they did not come to help the <char style="sc">Lord</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:23">to help the <char style="sc">Lord</char> against the mighty.”<verse eid="JDG 5:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 5:24"/>‘Most blessed of women be Jael,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:24">the wife of Heber the Kenite,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:24">most blessed of tent-dwelling women.<verse eid="JDG 5:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 5:25"/>He asked for water, and she gave him milk;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:25">in a bowl fit for nobles she brought him curdled milk.<verse eid="JDG 5:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 5:26"/>Her hand reached for the tent peg,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:26">her right hand for the workman’s hammer.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:26">She struck Sisera, she crushed his head,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:26">she shattered and pierced his temple.<verse eid="JDG 5:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 5:27"/>At her feet he sank,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:27">he fell; there he lay.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:27">At her feet he sank, he fell;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:27">where he sank, there he fell – dead.<verse eid="JDG 5:27"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 5:28"/>‘Through the window peered Sisera’s mother;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:28">behind the lattice she cried out,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:28">“Why is his chariot so long in coming?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:28">Why is the clatter of his chariots delayed?”<verse eid="JDG 5:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 5:29"/>The wisest of her ladies answer her;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:29">indeed, she keeps saying to herself,<verse eid="JDG 5:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 5:30"/>“Are they not finding and dividing the spoils:</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:30">a woman or two for each man,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:30">colourful garments as plunder for Sisera,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:30">colourful garments embroidered,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:30">highly embroidered garments for my neck –</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:30">all this as plunder?”<verse eid="JDG 5:30"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 5:31"/>‘So may all your enemies perish, O <char style="sc">Lord</char>!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:31">But may all who love you be like the sun</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:31">when it rises in its strength.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 5:31">Then the land had peace for forty years.<verse eid="JDG 5:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JDG 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Gideon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 6:1"/>The Israelites did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and for seven years he gave them into the hands of the Midianites. <verse eid="JDG 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 6:2"/>Because the power of Midian was so oppressive, the Israelites prepared shelters for themselves in mountain clefts, caves and strongholds. <verse eid="JDG 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 6:3"/>Whenever the Israelites planted their crops, the Midianites, Amalekites and other eastern peoples invaded the country. <verse eid="JDG 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 6:4"/>They camped on the land and ruined the crops all the way to Gaza and did not spare a living thing for Israel, neither sheep nor cattle nor donkeys. <verse eid="JDG 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 6:5"/>They came up with their livestock and their tents like swarms of locusts. It was impossible to count them or their camels; they invaded the land to ravage it. <verse eid="JDG 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 6:6"/>Midian so impoverished the Israelites that they cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for help.<verse eid="JDG 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 6:7"/>When the Israelites cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> because of Midian, <verse eid="JDG 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 6:8"/>he sent them a prophet, who said, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says: I brought you up out of Egypt, out of the land of slavery. <verse eid="JDG 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 6:9"/>I rescued you from the hand of the Egyptians. And I delivered you from the hand of all your oppressors; I drove them out before you and gave you their land. <verse eid="JDG 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 6:10"/>I said to you, “I am the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God; do not worship the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you live.” But you have not listened to me.’<verse eid="JDG 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 6:11"/>The angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came and sat down under the oak in Ophrah that belonged to Joash the Abiezrite, where his son Gideon was threshing wheat in a winepress to keep it from the Midianites. <verse eid="JDG 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 6:12"/>When the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared to Gideon, he said, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> is with you, mighty warrior.’<verse eid="JDG 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 6:13"/>‘Pardon me, my lord,’ Gideon replied, ‘but if the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is with us, why has all this happened to us? Where are all his wonders that our ancestors told us about when they said, “Did not the <char style="sc">Lord</char> bring us up out of Egypt?” But now the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has abandoned us and given us into the hand of Midian.’<verse eid="JDG 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 6:14"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> turned to him and said, ‘Go in the strength you have and save Israel out of Midian’s hand. Am I not sending you?’<verse eid="JDG 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 6:15"/>‘Pardon me, my lord,’ Gideon replied, ‘but how can I save Israel? My clan is the weakest in Manasseh, and I am the least in my family.’<verse eid="JDG 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 6:16"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> answered, ‘I will be with you, and you will strike down all the Midianites, leaving none alive.’<verse eid="JDG 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 6:17"/>Gideon replied, ‘If now I have found favour in your eyes, give me a sign that it is really you talking to me. <verse eid="JDG 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 6:18"/>Please do not go away until I come back and bring my offering and set it before you.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 6:18">And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said, ‘I will wait until you return.’<verse eid="JDG 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 6:19"/>Gideon went inside, prepared a young goat, and from an ephah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, probably about 16 kilograms</char></note> of flour he made bread without yeast. Putting the meat in a basket and its broth in a pot, he brought them out and offered them to him under the oak.<verse eid="JDG 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 6:20"/>The angel of God said to him, ‘Take the meat and the unleavened bread, place them on this rock, and pour out the broth.’ And Gideon did so. <verse eid="JDG 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 6:21"/>Then the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> touched the meat and the unleavened bread with the tip of the staff that was in his hand. Fire flared from the rock, consuming the meat and the bread. And the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> disappeared. <verse eid="JDG 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 6:22"/>When Gideon realised that it was the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, he exclaimed, ‘Alas, Sovereign <char style="sc">Lord</char>! I have seen the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> face to face!’<verse eid="JDG 6:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 6:23"/>But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, ‘Peace! Do not be afraid. You are not going to die.’<verse eid="JDG 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 6:24"/>So Gideon built an altar to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> there and called it The <char style="sc">Lord</char> Is Peace. To this day it stands in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.<verse eid="JDG 6:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 6:25"/>That same night the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, ‘Take the second bull from your father’s herd, the one seven years old.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Take a full-grown, mature bull from your father’s herd</char></note> Tear down your father’s altar to Baal and cut down the Asherah pole<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, a wooden symbol of the goddess Asherah; also in verses 26, 28 and 30</char></note> beside it. <verse eid="JDG 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 6:26"/>Then build a proper kind of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">build with layers of stone an</char></note> altar to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God on the top of this height. Using the wood of the Asherah pole that you cut down, offer the second<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">full-grown</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verse 28</char></note> bull as a burnt offering.’<verse eid="JDG 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 6:27"/>So Gideon took ten of his servants and did as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> told him. But because he was afraid of his family and the townspeople, he did it at night rather than in the daytime.<verse eid="JDG 6:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 6:28"/>In the morning when the people of the town got up, there was Baal’s altar, demolished, with the Asherah pole beside it cut down and the second bull sacrificed on the newly-built altar!<verse eid="JDG 6:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 6:29"/>They asked each other, ‘Who did this?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 6:29">When they carefully investigated, they were told, ‘Gideon son of Joash did it.’<verse eid="JDG 6:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 6:30"/>The people of the town demanded of Joash, ‘Bring out your son. He must die, because he has broken down Baal’s altar and cut down the Asherah pole beside it.’<verse eid="JDG 6:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 6:31"/>But Joash replied to the hostile crowd around him, ‘Are you going to plead Baal’s cause? Are you trying to save him? Whoever fights for him shall be put to death by morning! If Baal really is a god, he can defend himself when someone breaks down his altar.’ <verse eid="JDG 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 6:32"/>So because Gideon broke down Baal’s altar, they gave him the name Jerub-Baal<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:32 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Jerub-Baal </char><char style="ft" closed="false">probably means </char><char style="fq" closed="false">let Baal contend</char><char style="fqa" closed="false">.</char></note> that day, saying, ‘Let Baal contend with him.’<verse eid="JDG 6:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 6:33"/>Now all the Midianites, Amalekites and other eastern peoples joined forces and crossed over the Jordan and camped in the Valley of Jezreel. <verse eid="JDG 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 6:34"/>Then the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came on Gideon, and he blew a trumpet, summoning the Abiezrites to follow him. <verse eid="JDG 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 6:35"/>He sent messengers throughout Manasseh, calling them to arms, and also into Asher, Zebulun and Naphtali, so that they too went up to meet them.<verse eid="JDG 6:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 6:36"/>Gideon said to God, ‘If you will save Israel by my hand as you have promised – <verse eid="JDG 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JDG 6:37"/>look, I will place a wool fleece on the threshing-floor. If there is dew only on the fleece and all the ground is dry, then I will know that you will save Israel by my hand, as you said.’ <verse eid="JDG 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JDG 6:38"/>And that is what happened. Gideon rose early the next day; he squeezed the fleece and wrung out the dew – a bowlful of water.<verse eid="JDG 6:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 6:39"/>Then Gideon said to God, ‘Do not be angry with me. Let me make just one more request. Allow me one more test with the fleece, but this time make the fleece dry and let the ground be covered with dew.’ <verse eid="JDG 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 6:40"/>That night God did so. Only the fleece was dry; all the ground was covered with dew.<verse eid="JDG 6:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JDG 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Gideon defeats the Midianites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 7:1"/>Early in the morning, Jerub-Baal (that is, Gideon) and all his men camped at the spring of Harod. The camp of Midian was north of them in the valley near the hill of Moreh. <verse eid="JDG 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 7:2"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, ‘You have too many men. I cannot deliver Midian into their hands, or Israel would boast against me, “My own strength has saved me.” <verse eid="JDG 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 7:3"/>Now announce to the army, “Anyone who trembles with fear may turn back and leave Mount Gilead.” ’ So twenty-two thousand men left, while ten thousand remained.<verse eid="JDG 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 7:4"/>But the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, ‘There are still too many men. Take them down to the water, and I will thin them out for you there. If I say, “This one shall go with you,” he shall go; but if I say, “This one shall not go with you,” he shall not go.’<verse eid="JDG 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 7:5"/>So Gideon took the men down to the water. There the <char style="sc">Lord</char> told him, ‘Separate those who lap the water with their tongues as a dog laps from those who kneel down to drink.’ <verse eid="JDG 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 7:6"/>Three hundred of them drank from cupped hands, lapping like dogs. All the rest got down on their knees to drink.<verse eid="JDG 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 7:7"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, ‘With the three hundred men that lapped I will save you and give the Midianites into your hands. Let all the others go home.’ <verse eid="JDG 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 7:8"/>So Gideon sent the rest of the Israelites home but kept the three hundred, who took over the provisions and trumpets of the others.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 7:8">Now the camp of Midian lay below him in the valley. <verse eid="JDG 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 7:9"/>During that night the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Gideon, ‘Get up, go down against the camp, because I am going to give it into your hands. <verse eid="JDG 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 7:10"/>If you are afraid to attack, go down to the camp with your servant Purah <verse eid="JDG 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 7:11"/>and listen to what they are saying. Afterwards, you will be encouraged to attack the camp.’ So he and Purah his servant went down to the outposts of the camp. <verse eid="JDG 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 7:12"/>The Midianites, the Amalekites and all the other eastern peoples had settled in the valley, thick as locusts. Their camels could no more be counted than the sand on the seashore.<verse eid="JDG 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 7:13"/>Gideon arrived just as a man was telling a friend his dream. ‘I had a dream,’ he was saying. ‘A round loaf of barley bread came tumbling into the Midianite camp. It struck the tent with such force that the tent overturned and collapsed.’<verse eid="JDG 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 7:14"/>His friend responded, ‘This can be nothing other than the sword of Gideon son of Joash, the Israelite. God has given the Midianites and the whole camp into his hands.’<verse eid="JDG 7:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 7:15"/>When Gideon heard the dream and its interpretation, he bowed down and worshipped. He returned to the camp of Israel and called out, ‘Get up! The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given the Midianite camp into your hands.’ <verse eid="JDG 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 7:16"/>Dividing the three hundred men into three companies, he placed trumpets and empty jars in the hands of all of them, with torches inside.<verse eid="JDG 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 7:17"/>‘Watch me,’ he told them. ‘Follow my lead. When I get to the edge of the camp, do exactly as I do. <verse eid="JDG 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 7:18"/>When I and all who are with me blow our trumpets, then from all round the camp blow yours and shout, “For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and for Gideon.” ’<verse eid="JDG 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 7:19"/>Gideon and the hundred men with him reached the edge of the camp at the beginning of the middle watch, just after they had changed the guard. They blew their trumpets and broke the jars that were in their hands. <verse eid="JDG 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 7:20"/>The three companies blew the trumpets and smashed the jars. Grasping the torches in their left hands and holding in their right hands the trumpets they were to blow, they shouted, ‘A sword for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and for Gideon!’ <verse eid="JDG 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 7:21"/>While each man held his position round the camp, all the Midianites ran, crying out as they fled.<verse eid="JDG 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 7:22"/>When the three hundred trumpets sounded, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> caused the men throughout the camp to turn on each other with their swords. The army fled to Beth Shittah towards Zererah as far as the border of Abel Meholah near Tabbath. <verse eid="JDG 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 7:23"/>Israelites from Naphtali, Asher and all Manasseh were called out, and they pursued the Midianites. <verse eid="JDG 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 7:24"/>Gideon sent messengers throughout the hill country of Ephraim, saying, ‘Come down against the Midianites and seize the waters of the Jordan ahead of them as far as Beth Barah.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 7:24">So all the men of Ephraim were called out and they seized the waters of the Jordan as far as Beth Barah. <verse eid="JDG 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 7:25"/>They also captured two of the Midianite leaders, Oreb and Zeeb. They killed Oreb at the rock of Oreb, and Zeeb at the winepress of Zeeb. They pursued the Midianites and brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon, who was by the Jordan.<verse eid="JDG 7:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JDG 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Zebah and Zalmunna</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 8:1"/>Now the Ephraimites asked Gideon, ‘Why have you treated us like this? Why didn’t you call us when you went to fight Midian?’ And they challenged him vigorously.<verse eid="JDG 8:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 8:2"/>But he answered them, ‘What have I accomplished compared to you? Aren’t the gleanings of Ephraim’s grapes better than the full grape harvest of Abiezer? <verse eid="JDG 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 8:3"/>God gave Oreb and Zeeb, the Midianite leaders, into your hands. What was I able to do compared to you?’ At this, their resentment against him subsided.<verse eid="JDG 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 8:4"/>Gideon and his three hundred men, exhausted yet keeping up the pursuit, came to the Jordan and crossed it. <verse eid="JDG 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 8:5"/>He said to the men of Sukkoth, ‘Give my troops some bread; they are worn out, and I am still pursuing Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian.’<verse eid="JDG 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 8:6"/>But the officials of Sukkoth said, ‘Do you already have the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna in your possession? Why should we give bread to your troops?’<verse eid="JDG 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 8:7"/>Then Gideon replied, ‘Just for that, when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given Zebah and Zalmunna into my hand, I will tear your flesh with desert thorns and briers.’<verse eid="JDG 8:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 8:8"/>From there he went up to Peniel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Penuel, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Peniel</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 9 and 17</char></note> and made the same request of them, but they answered as the men of Sukkoth had. <verse eid="JDG 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 8:9"/>So he said to the men of Peniel, ‘When I return in triumph, I will tear down this tower.’<verse eid="JDG 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 8:10"/>Now Zebah and Zalmunna were in Karkor with a force of about fifteen thousand men, all that were left of the armies of the eastern peoples; a hundred and twenty thousand swordsmen had fallen. <verse eid="JDG 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 8:11"/>Gideon went up by the route of the nomads east of Nobah and Jogbehah and attacked the unsuspecting army. <verse eid="JDG 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 8:12"/>Zebah and Zalmunna, the two kings of Midian, fled, but he pursued them and captured them, routing their entire army.<verse eid="JDG 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 8:13"/>Gideon son of Joash then returned from the battle by the Pass of Heres. <verse eid="JDG 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 8:14"/>He caught a young man of Sukkoth and questioned him, and the young man wrote down for him the names of the seventy-seven officials of Sukkoth, the elders of the town. <verse eid="JDG 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 8:15"/>Then Gideon came and said to the men of Sukkoth, ‘Here are Zebah and Zalmunna, about whom you taunted me by saying, “Do you already have the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna in your possession? Why should we give bread to your exhausted men?” ’ <verse eid="JDG 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 8:16"/>He took the elders of the town and taught the men of Sukkoth a lesson by punishing them with desert thorns and briers. <verse eid="JDG 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 8:17"/>He also pulled down the tower of Peniel and killed the men of the town.<verse eid="JDG 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 8:18"/>Then he asked Zebah and Zalmunna, ‘What kind of men did you kill at Tabor?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 8:18">‘Men like you,’ they answered, ‘each one with the bearing of a prince.’<verse eid="JDG 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 8:19"/>Gideon replied, ‘Those were my brothers, the sons of my own mother. As surely as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> lives, if you had spared their lives, I would not kill you.’ <verse eid="JDG 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 8:20"/>Turning to Jether, his eldest son, he said, ‘Kill them!’ But Jether did not draw his sword, because he was only a boy and was afraid.<verse eid="JDG 8:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 8:21"/>Zebah and Zalmunna said, ‘Come, do it yourself. “As is the man, so is his strength.” ’ So Gideon stepped forward and killed them, and took the ornaments off their camels’ necks.<verse eid="JDG 8:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Gideon’s ephod</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 8:22"/>The Israelites said to Gideon, ‘Rule over us – you, your son and your grandson – because you have saved us from the hand of Midian.’<verse eid="JDG 8:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 8:23"/>But Gideon told them, ‘I will not rule over you, nor will my son rule over you. The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will rule over you.’ <verse eid="JDG 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 8:24"/>And he said, ‘I do have one request, that each of you give me an earring from your share of the plunder.’ (It was the custom of the Ishmaelites to wear gold earrings.)<verse eid="JDG 8:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 8:25"/>They answered, ‘We’ll be glad to give them.’ So they spread out a garment, and each of them threw a ring from his plunder onto it. <verse eid="JDG 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 8:26"/>The weight of the gold rings he asked for came to seventeen hundred shekels,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 20 kilograms</char></note> not counting the ornaments, the pendants and the purple garments worn by the kings of Midian or the chains that were on their camels’ necks. <verse eid="JDG 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 8:27"/>Gideon made the gold into an ephod, which he placed in Ophrah, his town. All Israel prostituted themselves by worshipping it there, and it became a snare to Gideon and his family.<verse eid="JDG 8:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Gideon’s death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 8:28"/>Thus Midian was subdued before the Israelites and did not raise its head again. During Gideon’s lifetime, the land had peace for forty years.<verse eid="JDG 8:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 8:29"/>Jerub-Baal son of Joash went back home to live. <verse eid="JDG 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 8:30"/>He had seventy sons of his own, for he had many wives. <verse eid="JDG 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 8:31"/>His concubine, who lived in Shechem, also bore him a son, whom he named Abimelek. <verse eid="JDG 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 8:32"/>Gideon son of Joash died at a good old age and was buried in the tomb of his father Joash in Ophrah of the Abiezrites.<verse eid="JDG 8:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 8:33"/>No sooner had Gideon died than the Israelites again prostituted themselves to the Baals. They set up Baal-Berith as their god <verse eid="JDG 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 8:34"/>and did not remember the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God, who had rescued them from the hands of all their enemies on every side. <verse eid="JDG 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 8:35"/>They also failed to show any loyalty to the family of Jerub-Baal (that is, Gideon) in spite of all the good things he had done for them.<verse eid="JDG 8:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JDG 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Abimelek</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 9:1"/>Abimelek son of Jerub-Baal went to his mother’s brothers in Shechem and said to them and to all his mother’s clan, <verse eid="JDG 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 9:2"/>‘Ask all the citizens of Shechem, “Which is better for you: to have all seventy of Jerub-Baal’s sons rule over you, or just one man?” Remember, I am your flesh and blood.’<verse eid="JDG 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 9:3"/>When the brothers repeated all this to the citizens of Shechem, they were inclined to follow Abimelek, for they said, ‘He is related to us.’ <verse eid="JDG 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 9:4"/>They gave him seventy shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 800 grams</char></note> of silver from the temple of Baal-Berith, and Abimelek used it to hire reckless scoundrels, who became his followers. <verse eid="JDG 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 9:5"/>He went to his father’s home in Ophrah and on one stone murdered his seventy brothers, the sons of Jerub-Baal. But Jotham, the youngest son of Jerub-Baal, escaped by hiding. <verse eid="JDG 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 9:6"/>Then all the citizens of Shechem and Beth Millo gathered beside the great tree at the pillar in Shechem to crown Abimelek king.<verse eid="JDG 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 9:7"/>When Jotham was told about this, he climbed up on the top of Mount Gerizim and shouted to them, ‘Listen to me, citizens of Shechem, so that God may listen to you. <verse eid="JDG 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 9:8"/>One day the trees went out to anoint a king for themselves. They said to the olive tree, “Be our king.”<verse eid="JDG 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 9:9"/>‘But the olive tree answered, “Should I give up my oil, by which both gods and humans are honoured, to hold sway over the trees?”<verse eid="JDG 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 9:10"/>‘Next, the trees said to the fig-tree, “Come and be our king.”<verse eid="JDG 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 9:11"/>‘But the fig-tree replied, “Should I give up my fruit, so good and sweet, to hold sway over the trees?”<verse eid="JDG 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 9:12"/>‘Then the trees said to the vine, “Come and be our king.”<verse eid="JDG 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 9:13"/>‘But the vine answered, “Should I give up my wine, which cheers both gods and humans, to hold sway over the trees?”<verse eid="JDG 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 9:14"/>‘Finally all the trees said to the thorn-bush, “Come and be our king.”<verse eid="JDG 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 9:15"/>‘The thorn-bush said to the trees, “If you really want to anoint me king over you, come and take refuge in my shade; but if not, then let fire come out of the thorn-bush and consume the cedars of Lebanon!”<verse eid="JDG 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 9:16"/>‘Have you acted honourably and in good faith by making Abimelek king? Have you been fair to Jerub-Baal and his family? Have you treated him as he deserves? <verse eid="JDG 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 9:17"/>Remember that my father fought for you and risked his life to rescue you from the hand of Midian. <verse eid="JDG 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 9:18"/>But today you have revolted against my father’s family. You have murdered his seventy sons on a single stone and have made Abimelek, the son of his female slave, king over the citizens of Shechem because he is related to you. <verse eid="JDG 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 9:19"/>So have you acted honourably and in good faith towards Jerub-Baal and his family today? If you have, may Abimelek be your joy, and may you be his, too! <verse eid="JDG 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 9:20"/>But if you have not, let fire come out from Abimelek and consume you, the citizens of Shechem and Beth Millo, and let fire come out from you, the citizens of Shechem and Beth Millo, and consume Abimelek!’<verse eid="JDG 9:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 9:21"/>Then Jotham fled, escaping to Beer, and he lived there because he was afraid of his brother Abimelek.<verse eid="JDG 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 9:22"/>After Abimelek had governed Israel for three years, <verse eid="JDG 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 9:23"/>God stirred up animosity between Abimelek and the citizens of Shechem so that they acted treacherously against Abimelek. <verse eid="JDG 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 9:24"/>God did this in order that the crime against Jerub-Baal’s seventy sons, the shedding of their blood, might be avenged on their brother Abimelek and on the citizens of Shechem, who had helped him murder his brothers. <verse eid="JDG 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 9:25"/>In opposition to him these citizens of Shechem set men on the hilltops to ambush and rob everyone who passed by, and this was reported to Abimelek.<verse eid="JDG 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 9:26"/>Now Gaal son of Ebed moved with his clan into Shechem, and its citizens put their confidence in him. <verse eid="JDG 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 9:27"/>After they had gone out into the fields and gathered the grapes and trodden them, they held a festival in the temple of their god. While they were eating and drinking, they cursed Abimelek. <verse eid="JDG 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 9:28"/>Then Gaal son of Ebed said, ‘Who is Abimelek, and why should we Shechemites be subject to him? Isn’t he Jerub-Baal’s son, and isn’t Zebul his deputy? Serve the family of Hamor, Shechem’s father! Why should we serve Abimelek? <verse eid="JDG 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 9:29"/>If only this people were under my command! Then I would get rid of him. I would say to Abimelek, “Call out your whole army!” ’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Septuagint; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">him.’ Then he said to Abimelek, ‘Call out your whole army!’</char></note><verse eid="JDG 9:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 9:30"/>When Zebul the governor of the city heard what Gaal son of Ebed said, he was very angry. <verse eid="JDG 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 9:31"/>Under cover he sent messengers to Abimelek, saying, ‘Gaal son of Ebed and his clan have come to Shechem and are stirring up the city against you. <verse eid="JDG 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 9:32"/>Now then, during the night you and your men should come and lie in wait in the fields. <verse eid="JDG 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 9:33"/>In the morning at sunrise, advance against the city. When Gaal and his men come out against you, seize the opportunity to attack them.’<verse eid="JDG 9:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 9:34"/>So Abimelek and all his troops set out by night and took up concealed positions near Shechem in four companies. <verse eid="JDG 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 9:35"/>Now Gaal son of Ebed had gone out and was standing at the entrance of the city gate just as Abimelek and his troops came out from their hiding-place.<verse eid="JDG 9:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 9:36"/>When Gaal saw them, he said to Zebul, ‘Look, people are coming down from the tops of the mountains!’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 9:36">Zebul replied, ‘You mistake the shadows of the mountains for men.’<verse eid="JDG 9:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JDG 9:37"/>But Gaal spoke up again: ‘Look, people are coming down from the central hill,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:37 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew for this phrase means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the navel of the earth.</char></note> and a company is coming from the direction of the diviners’ tree.’<verse eid="JDG 9:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JDG 9:38"/>Then Zebul said to him, ‘Where is your big talk now, you who said, “Who is Abimelek that we should be subject to him?” Aren’t these the men you ridiculed? Go out and fight them!’<verse eid="JDG 9:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 9:39"/>So Gaal led out<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:39 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gaal went out in the sight of</char></note> the citizens of Shechem and fought Abimelek. <verse eid="JDG 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 9:40"/>Abimelek chased him all the way to the entrance of the gate, and many were killed as they fled. <verse eid="JDG 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JDG 9:41"/>Then Abimelek stayed in Arumah, and Zebul drove Gaal and his clan out of Shechem.<verse eid="JDG 9:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JDG 9:42"/>The next day the people of Shechem went out to the fields, and this was reported to Abimelek. <verse eid="JDG 9:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JDG 9:43"/>So he took his men, divided them into three companies and set an ambush in the fields. When he saw the people coming out of the city, he rose to attack them. <verse eid="JDG 9:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JDG 9:44"/>Abimelek and the companies with him rushed forward to a position at the entrance of the city gate. Then two companies attacked those in the fields and struck them down. <verse eid="JDG 9:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JDG 9:45"/>All that day Abimelek pressed his attack against the city until he had captured it and killed its people. Then he destroyed the city and scattered salt over it.<verse eid="JDG 9:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="JDG 9:46"/>On hearing this, the citizens in the tower of Shechem went into the stronghold of the temple of El-Berith. <verse eid="JDG 9:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JDG 9:47"/>When Abimelek heard that they had assembled there, <verse eid="JDG 9:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JDG 9:48"/>he and all his men went up Mount Zalmon. He took an axe and cut off some branches, which he lifted to his shoulders. He ordered the men with him, ‘Quick! Do what you have seen me do!’ <verse eid="JDG 9:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JDG 9:49"/>So all the men cut branches and followed Abimelek. They piled them against the stronghold and set it on fire with the people still inside. So all the people in the tower of Shechem, about a thousand men and women, also died.<verse eid="JDG 9:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="JDG 9:50"/>Next Abimelek went to Thebez and besieged it and captured it. <verse eid="JDG 9:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JDG 9:51"/>Inside the city, however, was a strong tower, to which all the men and women – all the people of the city – had fled. They had locked themselves in and climbed up on the tower roof. <verse eid="JDG 9:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JDG 9:52"/>Abimelek went to the tower and attacked it. But as he approached the entrance to the tower to set it on fire, <verse eid="JDG 9:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JDG 9:53"/>a woman dropped an upper millstone on his head and cracked his skull.<verse eid="JDG 9:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="JDG 9:54"/>Hurriedly he called to his armour-bearer, ‘Draw your sword and kill me, so that they can’t say, “A woman killed him.” ’ So his servant ran him through, and he died. <verse eid="JDG 9:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JDG 9:55"/>When the Israelites saw that Abimelek was dead, they went home.<verse eid="JDG 9:55"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" sid="JDG 9:56"/>Thus God repaid the wickedness that Abimelek had done to his father by murdering his seventy brothers. <verse eid="JDG 9:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JDG 9:57"/>God also made the people of Shechem pay for all their wickedness. The curse of Jotham son of Jerub-Baal came on them.<verse eid="JDG 9:57"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JDG 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Tola</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 10:1"/>After the time of Abimelek, a man of Issachar named Tola son of Puah, the son of Dodo, rose to save Israel. He lived in Shamir, in the hill country of Ephraim. <verse eid="JDG 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 10:2"/>He led<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Traditionally </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">judged</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verse 3</char></note> Israel for twenty-three years; then he died, and was buried in Shamir.<verse eid="JDG 10:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jair</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 10:3"/>He was followed by Jair of Gilead, who led Israel for twenty-two years. <verse eid="JDG 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 10:4"/>He had thirty sons, who rode thirty donkeys. They controlled thirty towns in Gilead, which to this day are called Havvoth Jair.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">called the settlements of Jair</char></note> <verse eid="JDG 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 10:5"/>When Jair died, he was buried in Kamon.<verse eid="JDG 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jephthah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 10:6"/>Again the Israelites did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. They served the Baals and the Ashtoreths, and the gods of Aram, the gods of Sidon, the gods of Moab, the gods of the Ammonites and the gods of the Philistines. And because the Israelites forsook the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and no longer served him, <verse eid="JDG 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 10:7"/>he became angry with them. He sold them into the hands of the Philistines and the Ammonites, <verse eid="JDG 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 10:8"/>who that year shattered and crushed them. For eighteen years they oppressed all the Israelites on the east side of the Jordan in Gilead, the land of the Amorites. <verse eid="JDG 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 10:9"/>The Ammonites also crossed the Jordan to fight against Judah, Benjamin and Ephraim; Israel was in great distress. <verse eid="JDG 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 10:10"/>Then the Israelites cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘We have sinned against you, forsaking our God and serving the Baals.’<verse eid="JDG 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 10:11"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> replied, ‘When the Egyptians, the Amorites, the Ammonites, the Philistines, <verse eid="JDG 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 10:12"/>the Sidonians, the Amalekites and the Maonites<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; some Septuagint manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Midianites</char></note> oppressed you and you cried to me for help, did I not save you from their hands? <verse eid="JDG 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 10:13"/>But you have forsaken me and served other gods, so I will no longer save you. <verse eid="JDG 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 10:14"/>Go and cry out to the gods you have chosen. Let them save you when you are in trouble!’<verse eid="JDG 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 10:15"/>But the Israelites said to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘We have sinned. Do with us whatever you think best, but please rescue us now.’ <verse eid="JDG 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 10:16"/>Then they got rid of the foreign gods among them and served the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And he could bear Israel’s misery no longer.<verse eid="JDG 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 10:17"/>When the Ammonites were called to arms and camped in Gilead, the Israelites assembled and camped at Mizpah. <verse eid="JDG 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 10:18"/>The leaders of the people of Gilead said to each other, ‘Whoever will take the lead in attacking the Ammonites will be head over all who live in Gilead.’<verse eid="JDG 10:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JDG 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 11:1"/>Jephthah the Gileadite was a mighty warrior. His father was Gilead; his mother was a prostitute. <verse eid="JDG 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 11:2"/>Gilead’s wife also bore him sons, and when they were grown up, they drove Jephthah away. ‘You are not going to get any inheritance in our family,’ they said, ‘because you are the son of another woman.’ <verse eid="JDG 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 11:3"/>So Jephthah fled from his brothers and settled in the land of Tob, where a gang of scoundrels gathered around him and followed him.<verse eid="JDG 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 11:4"/>Some time later, when the Ammonites were fighting against Israel, <verse eid="JDG 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 11:5"/>the elders of Gilead went to get Jephthah from the land of Tob. <verse eid="JDG 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 11:6"/>‘Come,’ they said, ‘be our commander, so we can fight the Ammonites.’<verse eid="JDG 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 11:7"/>Jephthah said to them, ‘Didn’t you hate me and drive me from my father’s house? Why do you come to me now, when you’re in trouble?’<verse eid="JDG 11:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 11:8"/>The elders of Gilead said to him, ‘Nevertheless, we are turning to you now; come with us to fight the Ammonites, and you will be head over all of us who live in Gilead.’<verse eid="JDG 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 11:9"/>Jephthah answered, ‘Suppose you take me back to fight the Ammonites and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gives them to me – will I really be your head?’<verse eid="JDG 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 11:10"/>The elders of Gilead replied, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> is our witness; we will certainly do as you say.’ <verse eid="JDG 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 11:11"/>So Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people made him head and commander over them. And he repeated all his words before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Mizpah.<verse eid="JDG 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 11:12"/>Then Jephthah sent messengers to the Ammonite king with the question: ‘What do you have against me that you have attacked my country?’<verse eid="JDG 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 11:13"/>The king of the Ammonites answered Jephthah’s messengers, ‘When Israel came up out of Egypt, they took away my land from the Arnon to the Jabbok, all the way to the Jordan. Now give it back peaceably.’<verse eid="JDG 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 11:14"/>Jephthah sent back messengers to the Ammonite king, <verse eid="JDG 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 11:15"/>saying:</para>
  <para style="pm" vid="JDG 11:15">‘This is what Jephthah says: Israel did not take the land of Moab or the land of the Ammonites. <verse eid="JDG 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 11:16"/>But when they came up out of Egypt, Israel went through the wilderness to the Red Sea<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the Sea of Reeds</char></note> and on to Kadesh. <verse eid="JDG 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 11:17"/>Then Israel sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, “Give us permission to go through your country,” but the king of Edom would not listen. They sent also to the king of Moab, and he refused. So Israel stayed at Kadesh.<verse eid="JDG 11:17"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 11:18"/>‘Next they travelled through the wilderness, skirted the lands of Edom and Moab, passed along the eastern side of the country of Moab, and camped on the other side of the Arnon. They did not enter the territory of Moab, for the Arnon was its border.<verse eid="JDG 11:18"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 11:19"/>‘Then Israel sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites, who ruled in Heshbon, and said to him, “Let us pass through your country to our own place.” <verse eid="JDG 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 11:20"/>Sihon, however, did not trust Israel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">however, would not make an agreement for Israel</char></note> to pass through his territory. He mustered all his troops and encamped at Jahaz and fought with Israel.<verse eid="JDG 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 11:21"/>‘Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, gave Sihon and his whole army into Israel’s hands, and they defeated them. Israel took over all the land of the Amorites who lived in that country, <verse eid="JDG 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 11:22"/>capturing all of it from the Arnon to the Jabbok and from the desert to the Jordan.<verse eid="JDG 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 11:23"/>‘Now since the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, has driven the Amorites out before his people Israel, what right have you to take it over? <verse eid="JDG 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 11:24"/>Will you not take what your god Chemosh gives you? Likewise, whatever the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God has given us, we will possess. <verse eid="JDG 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 11:25"/>Are you any better than Balak son of Zippor, king of Moab? Did he ever quarrel with Israel or fight with them? <verse eid="JDG 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 11:26"/>For three hundred years Israel occupied Heshbon, Aroer, the surrounding settlements and all the towns along the Arnon. Why didn’t you retake them during that time? <verse eid="JDG 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 11:27"/>I have not wronged you, but you are doing me wrong by waging war against me. Let the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the Judge, decide the dispute this day between the Israelites and the Ammonites.’<verse eid="JDG 11:27"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 11:28"/>The king of Ammon, however, paid no attention to the message Jephthah sent him.<verse eid="JDG 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 11:29"/>Then the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came on Jephthah. He crossed Gilead and Manasseh, passed through Mizpah of Gilead, and from there he advanced against the Ammonites. <verse eid="JDG 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 11:30"/>And Jephthah made a vow to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘If you give the Ammonites into my hands, <verse eid="JDG 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 11:31"/>whatever comes out of the door of my house to meet me when I return in triumph from the Ammonites will be the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s, and I will sacrifice it as a burnt offering.’<verse eid="JDG 11:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 11:32"/>Then Jephthah went over to fight the Ammonites, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave them into his hands. <verse eid="JDG 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 11:33"/>He devastated twenty towns from Aroer to the vicinity of Minnith, as far as Abel Keramim. Thus Israel subdued Ammon.<verse eid="JDG 11:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 11:34"/>When Jephthah returned to his home in Mizpah, who should come out to meet him but his daughter, dancing to the sound of tambourines! She was an only child. Except for her he had neither son nor daughter. <verse eid="JDG 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 11:35"/>When he saw her, he tore his clothes and cried, ‘Oh no, my daughter! You have brought me down and I am devastated. I have made a vow to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that I cannot break.’<verse eid="JDG 11:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 11:36"/>‘My father,’ she replied, ‘you have given your word to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Do to me just as you promised, now that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has avenged you of your enemies, the Ammonites. <verse eid="JDG 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JDG 11:37"/>But grant me this one request,’ she said. ‘Give me two months to roam the hills and weep with my friends, because I will never marry.’<verse eid="JDG 11:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JDG 11:38"/>‘You may go,’ he said. And he let her go for two months. She and her friends went into the hills and wept because she would never marry. <verse eid="JDG 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 11:39"/>After the two months, she returned to her father, and he did to her as he had vowed. And she was a virgin.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 11:39">From this comes the Israelite tradition <verse eid="JDG 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 11:40"/>that each year the young women of Israel go out for four days to commemorate the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite.<verse eid="JDG 11:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JDG 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Jephthah and Ephraim</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 12:1"/>The Ephraimite forces were called out, and they crossed over to Zaphon. They said to Jephthah, ‘Why did you go to fight the Ammonites without calling us to go with you? We’re going to burn down your house over your head.’<verse eid="JDG 12:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 12:2"/>Jephthah answered, ‘I and my people were engaged in a great struggle with the Ammonites, and although I called, you didn’t save me out of their hands. <verse eid="JDG 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 12:3"/>When I saw that you wouldn’t help, I took my life in my hands and crossed over to fight the Ammonites, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave me the victory over them. Now why have you come up today to fight me?’<verse eid="JDG 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 12:4"/>Jephthah then called together the men of Gilead and fought against Ephraim. The Gileadites struck them down because the Ephraimites had said, ‘You Gileadites are renegades from Ephraim and Manasseh.’ <verse eid="JDG 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 12:5"/>The Gileadites captured the fords of the Jordan leading to Ephraim, and whenever a survivor of Ephraim said, ‘Let me cross over,’ the men of Gilead asked him, ‘Are you an Ephraimite?’ If he replied, ‘No,’ <verse eid="JDG 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 12:6"/>they said, ‘All right, say “Shibboleth”.’ If he said, ‘Sibboleth’, because he could not pronounce the word correctly, they seized him and killed him at the fords of the Jordan. Forty-two thousand Ephraimites were killed at that time.<verse eid="JDG 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 12:7"/>Jephthah led<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Traditionally </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">judged</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 8-14</char></note> Israel for six years. Then Jephthah the Gileadite died and was buried in a town in Gilead.<verse eid="JDG 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ibzan, Elon and Abdon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 12:8"/>After him, Ibzan of Bethlehem led Israel. <verse eid="JDG 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 12:9"/>He had thirty sons and thirty daughters. He gave his daughters away in marriage to those outside his clan, and for his sons he brought in thirty young women as wives from outside his clan. Ibzan led Israel for seven years. <verse eid="JDG 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 12:10"/>Then Ibzan died and was buried in Bethlehem.<verse eid="JDG 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 12:11"/>After him, Elon the Zebulunite led Israel for ten years. <verse eid="JDG 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 12:12"/>Then Elon died and was buried in Aijalon in the land of Zebulun.<verse eid="JDG 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 12:13"/>After him, Abdon son of Hillel, from Pirathon, led Israel. <verse eid="JDG 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 12:14"/>He had forty sons and thirty grandsons, who rode on seventy donkeys. He led Israel for eight years. <verse eid="JDG 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 12:15"/>Then Abdon son of Hillel died and was buried at Pirathon in Ephraim, in the hill country of the Amalekites.<verse eid="JDG 12:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JDG 13"/>
  <para style="s1">The birth of Samson</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 13:1"/>Again the Israelites did evil in the eyes of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, so the <char style="sc">Lord</char> delivered them into the hands of the Philistines for forty years.<verse eid="JDG 13:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 13:2"/>A certain man of Zorah, named Manoah, from the clan of the Danites, had a wife who was childless, unable to give birth. <verse eid="JDG 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 13:3"/>The angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> appeared to her and said, ‘You are barren and childless, but you are going to become pregnant and give birth to a son. <verse eid="JDG 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 13:4"/>Now see to it that you drink no wine or other fermented drink and that you do not eat anything unclean. <verse eid="JDG 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 13:5"/>You will become pregnant and have a son whose head is never to be touched by a razor because the boy is to be a Nazirite, dedicated to God from the womb. He will take the lead in delivering Israel from the hands of the Philistines.’<verse eid="JDG 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 13:6"/>Then the woman went to her husband and told him, ‘A man of God came to me. He looked like an angel of God, very awesome. I didn’t ask him where he came from, and he didn’t tell me his name. <verse eid="JDG 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 13:7"/>But he said to me, “You will become pregnant and have a son. Now then, drink no wine or other fermented drink and do not eat anything unclean, because the boy will be a Nazirite of God from the womb until the day of his death.” ’<verse eid="JDG 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 13:8"/>Then Manoah prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>: ‘Pardon your servant, Lord. I beg you to let the man of God you sent to us come again to teach us how to bring up the boy who is to be born.’<verse eid="JDG 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 13:9"/>God heard Manoah, and the angel of God came again to the woman while she was out in the field; but her husband Manoah was not with her. <verse eid="JDG 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 13:10"/>The woman hurried to tell her husband, ‘He’s here! The man who appeared to me the other day!’<verse eid="JDG 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 13:11"/>Manoah got up and followed his wife. When he came to the man, he said, ‘Are you the man who talked to my wife?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 13:11">‘I am,’ he said.<verse eid="JDG 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 13:12"/>So Manoah asked him, ‘When your words are fulfilled, what is to be the rule that governs the boy’s life and work?’<verse eid="JDG 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 13:13"/>The angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> answered, ‘Your wife must do all that I have told her. <verse eid="JDG 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 13:14"/>She must not eat anything that comes from the grapevine, nor drink any wine or other fermented drink nor eat anything unclean. She must do everything I have commanded her.’<verse eid="JDG 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 13:15"/>Manoah said to the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘We would like you to stay until we prepare a young goat for you.’<verse eid="JDG 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 13:16"/>The angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> replied, ‘Even though you detain me, I will not eat any of your food. But if you prepare a burnt offering, offer it to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ (Manoah did not realise that it was the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.)<verse eid="JDG 13:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 13:17"/>Then Manoah enquired of the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘What is your name, so that we may honour you when your word comes true?’<verse eid="JDG 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 13:18"/>He replied, ‘Why do you ask my name? It is beyond understanding.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">is wonderful</char></note>’ <verse eid="JDG 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 13:19"/>Then Manoah took a young goat, together with the grain offering, and sacrificed it on a rock to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> did an amazing thing while Manoah and his wife watched: <verse eid="JDG 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 13:20"/>as the flame blazed up from the altar towards heaven, the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> ascended in the flame. Seeing this, Manoah and his wife fell with their faces to the ground. <verse eid="JDG 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 13:21"/>When the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> did not show himself again to Manoah and his wife, Manoah realised that it was the angel of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JDG 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 13:22"/>‘We are doomed to die!’ he said to his wife. ‘We have seen God!’<verse eid="JDG 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 13:23"/>But his wife answered, ‘If the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had meant to kill us, he would not have accepted a burnt offering and grain offering from our hands, nor shown us all these things or now told us this.’<verse eid="JDG 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 13:24"/>The woman gave birth to a boy and named him Samson. He grew and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> blessed him, <verse eid="JDG 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 13:25"/>and the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> began to stir him while he was in Mahaneh Dan, between Zorah and Eshtaol.<verse eid="JDG 13:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JDG 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Samson’s marriage</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 14:1"/>Samson went down to Timnah and saw there a young Philistine woman. <verse eid="JDG 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 14:2"/>When he returned, he said to his father and mother, ‘I have seen a Philistine woman in Timnah; now get her for me as my wife.’<verse eid="JDG 14:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 14:3"/>His father and mother replied, ‘Isn’t there an acceptable woman among your relatives or among all our people? Must you go to the uncircumcised Philistines to get a wife?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 14:3">But Samson said to his father, ‘Get her for me. She’s the right one for me.’ <verse eid="JDG 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 14:4"/>(His parents did not know that this was from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, who was seeking an occasion to confront the Philistines; for at that time they were ruling over Israel.)<verse eid="JDG 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 14:5"/>Samson went down to Timnah together with his father and mother. As they approached the vineyards of Timnah, suddenly a young lion came roaring towards him. <verse eid="JDG 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 14:6"/>The Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came powerfully upon him so that he tore the lion apart with his bare hands as he might have torn a young goat. But he told neither his father nor his mother what he had done. <verse eid="JDG 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 14:7"/>Then he went down and talked with the woman, and he liked her.<verse eid="JDG 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 14:8"/>Some time later, when he went back to marry her, he turned aside to look at the lion’s carcass, and in it he saw a swarm of bees and some honey. <verse eid="JDG 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 14:9"/>He scooped out the honey with his hands and ate as he went along. When he rejoined his parents, he gave them some, and they too ate it. But he did not tell them that he had taken the honey from the lion’s carcass.<verse eid="JDG 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 14:10"/>Now his father went down to see the woman. And there Samson held a feast, as was customary for young men. <verse eid="JDG 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 14:11"/>When the people saw him, they chose thirty men to be his companions.<verse eid="JDG 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 14:12"/>‘Let me tell you a riddle,’ Samson said to them. ‘If you can give me the answer within the seven days of the feast, I will give you thirty linen garments and thirty sets of clothes. <verse eid="JDG 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 14:13"/>If you can’t tell me the answer, you must give me thirty linen garments and thirty sets of clothes.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 14:13">‘Tell us your riddle,’ they said. ‘Let’s hear it.’<verse eid="JDG 14:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 14:14"/>He replied,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 14:14">‘Out of the eater, something to eat;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 14:14">out of the strong, something sweet.’</para>
  <para style="m" vid="JDG 14:14">For three days they could not give the answer.<verse eid="JDG 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 14:15"/>On the fourth<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Septuagint manuscripts and Syriac; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">seventh</char></note> day, they said to Samson’s wife, ‘Coax your husband into explaining the riddle for us, or we will burn you and your father’s household to death. Did you invite us here to steal our property?’<verse eid="JDG 14:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 14:16"/>Then Samson’s wife threw herself on him, sobbing, ‘You hate me! You don’t really love me. You’ve given my people a riddle, but you haven’t told me the answer.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 14:16">‘I haven’t even explained it to my father or mother,’ he replied, ‘so why should I explain it to you?’ <verse eid="JDG 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 14:17"/>She cried the whole seven days of the feast. So on the seventh day he finally told her, because she continued to press him. She in turn explained the riddle to her people.<verse eid="JDG 14:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 14:18"/>Before sunset on the seventh day the men of the town said to him,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 14:18">‘What is sweeter than honey?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 14:18">What is stronger than a lion?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 14:18">Samson said to them,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 14:18">‘If you had not ploughed with my heifer,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 14:18">you would not have solved my riddle.’<verse eid="JDG 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 14:19"/>Then the Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came powerfully upon him. He went down to Ashkelon, struck down thirty of their men, stripped them of everything and gave their clothes to those who had explained the riddle. Burning with anger, he returned to his father’s home. <verse eid="JDG 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 14:20"/>And Samson’s wife was given to one of his companions who had attended him at the feast.<verse eid="JDG 14:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JDG 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Samson’s vengeance on the Philistines</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 15:1"/>Later on, at the time of wheat harvest, Samson took a young goat and went to visit his wife. He said, ‘I’m going to my wife’s room.’ But her father would not let him go in.<verse eid="JDG 15:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 15:2"/>‘I was so sure you hated her,’ he said, ‘that I gave her to your companion. Isn’t her younger sister more attractive? Take her instead.’<verse eid="JDG 15:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 15:3"/>Samson said to them, ‘This time I have a right to get even with the Philistines; I will really harm them.’ <verse eid="JDG 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 15:4"/>So he went out and caught three hundred foxes and tied them tail to tail in pairs. He then fastened a torch to every pair of tails, <verse eid="JDG 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 15:5"/>lit the torches and let the foxes loose in the standing corn of the Philistines. He burned up the shocks and standing corn, together with the vineyards and olive groves.<verse eid="JDG 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 15:6"/>When the Philistines asked, ‘Who did this?’ they were told, ‘Samson, the Timnite’s son-in-law, because his wife was given to his companion.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 15:6">So the Philistines went up and burned her and her father to death. <verse eid="JDG 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 15:7"/>Samson said to them, ‘Since you’ve acted like this, I swear that I won’t stop until I get my revenge on you.’ <verse eid="JDG 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 15:8"/>He attacked them viciously and slaughtered many of them. Then he went down and stayed in a cave in the rock of Etam.<verse eid="JDG 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 15:9"/>The Philistines went up and camped in Judah, spreading out near Lehi. <verse eid="JDG 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 15:10"/>The people of Judah asked, ‘Why have you come to fight us?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 15:10">‘We have come to take Samson prisoner,’ they answered, ‘to do to him as he did to us.’<verse eid="JDG 15:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 15:11"/>Then three thousand men from Judah went down to the cave in the rock of Etam and said to Samson, ‘Don’t you realise that the Philistines are rulers over us? What have you done to us?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 15:11">He answered, ‘I merely did to them what they did to me.’<verse eid="JDG 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 15:12"/>They said to him, ‘We’ve come to tie you up and hand you over to the Philistines.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 15:12">Samson said, ‘Swear to me that you won’t kill me yourselves.’<verse eid="JDG 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 15:13"/>‘Agreed,’ they answered. ‘We will only tie you up and hand you over to them. We will not kill you.’ So they bound him with two new ropes and led him up from the rock. <verse eid="JDG 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 15:14"/>As he approached Lehi, the Philistines came towards him shouting. The Spirit of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> came powerfully upon him. The ropes on his arms became like charred flax, and the bindings dropped from his hands. <verse eid="JDG 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 15:15"/>Finding a fresh jawbone of a donkey, he grabbed it and struck down a thousand men.<verse eid="JDG 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 15:16"/>Then Samson said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 15:16">‘With a donkey’s jawbone</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 15:16">I have made donkeys of them.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">made a heap or two</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; the Hebrew for </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">donkey </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sounds like the Hebrew for </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">heap.</char></note></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 15:16">With a donkey’s jawbone</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 15:16">I have killed a thousand men.’<verse eid="JDG 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 15:17"/>When he finished speaking, he threw away the jawbone; and the place was called Ramath Lehi.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:17 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Ramath Lehi </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fq" closed="false">jawbone </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">hill.</char></note><verse eid="JDG 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 15:18"/>Because he was very thirsty, he cried out to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘You have given your servant this great victory. Must I now die of thirst and fall into the hands of the uncircumcised?’ <verse eid="JDG 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 15:19"/>Then God opened up the hollow place in Lehi, and water came out of it. When Samson drank, his strength returned and he revived. So the spring was called En Hakkore,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:19 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">En Hakkore </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">caller’s </char><char style="fq" closed="false">spring</char><char style="fqa" closed="false">.</char></note> and it is still there in Lehi.<verse eid="JDG 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 15:20"/>Samson led<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Traditionally </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">judged</char></note> Israel for twenty years in the days of the Philistines.<verse eid="JDG 15:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JDG 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Samson and Delilah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 16:1"/>One day Samson went to Gaza, where he saw a prostitute. He went in to spend the night with her. <verse eid="JDG 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 16:2"/>The people of Gaza were told, ‘Samson is here!’ So they surrounded the place and lay in wait for him all night at the city gate. They made no move during the night, saying, ‘At dawn we’ll kill him.’<verse eid="JDG 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 16:3"/>But Samson lay there only until the middle of the night. Then he got up and took hold of the doors of the city gate, together with the two posts, and tore them loose, bar and all. He lifted them to his shoulders and carried them to the top of the hill that faces Hebron.<verse eid="JDG 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 16:4"/>Some time later, he fell in love with a woman in the Valley of Sorek whose name was Delilah. <verse eid="JDG 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 16:5"/>The rulers of the Philistines went to her and said, ‘See if you can lure him into showing you the secret of his great strength and how we can overpower him so that we may tie him up and subdue him. Each one of us will give you eleven hundred shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 13 kilograms</char></note> of silver.’<verse eid="JDG 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 16:6"/>So Delilah said to Samson, ‘Tell me the secret of your great strength and how you can be tied up and subdued.’<verse eid="JDG 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 16:7"/>Samson answered her, ‘If anyone ties me with seven fresh bow-strings that have not been dried, I’ll become as weak as any other man.’<verse eid="JDG 16:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 16:8"/>Then the rulers of the Philistines brought her seven fresh bow-strings that had not been dried, and she tied him with them. <verse eid="JDG 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 16:9"/>With men hidden in the room, she called to him, ‘Samson, the Philistines are upon you!’ But he snapped the bow-strings as easily as a piece of string snaps when it comes close to a flame. So the secret of his strength was not discovered.<verse eid="JDG 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 16:10"/>Then Delilah said to Samson, ‘You have made a fool of me; you lied to me. Come now, tell me how you can be tied.’<verse eid="JDG 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 16:11"/>He said, ‘If anyone ties me securely with new ropes that have never been used, I’ll become as weak as any other man.’<verse eid="JDG 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 16:12"/>So Delilah took new ropes and tied him with them. Then, with men hidden in the room, she called to him, ‘Samson, the Philistines are upon you!’ But he snapped the ropes off his arms as if they were threads.<verse eid="JDG 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 16:13"/>Delilah then said to Samson, ‘All this time you have been making a fool of me and lying to me. Tell me how you can be tied.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 16:13">He replied, ‘If you weave the seven braids of my head into the fabric on the loom and tighten it with the pin, I’ll become as weak as any other man.’ So while he was sleeping, Delilah took the seven braids of his head, wove them into the fabric <verse eid="JDG 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 16:14"/>and<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:13,14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Septuagint manuscripts; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">replied, ‘I can if you weave the seven braids of my head into the fabric on the loom.’ </char><char style="fv" closed="false">14 </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">So she</char></note> tightened it with the pin.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 16:14">Again she called to him, ‘Samson, the Philistines are upon you!’ He awoke from his sleep and pulled up the pin and the loom, with the fabric.<verse eid="JDG 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 16:15"/>Then she said to him, ‘How can you say, “I love you,” when you won’t confide in me? This is the third time you have made a fool of me and haven’t told me the secret of your great strength.’ <verse eid="JDG 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 16:16"/>With such nagging she prodded him day after day until he was sick to death of it.<verse eid="JDG 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 16:17"/>So he told her everything. ‘No razor has ever been used on my head,’ he said, ‘because I have been a Nazirite dedicated to God from my mother’s womb. If my head were shaved, my strength would leave me, and I would become as weak as any other man.’<verse eid="JDG 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 16:18"/>When Delilah saw that he had told her everything, she sent word to the rulers of the Philistines, ‘Come back once more; he has told me everything.’ So the rulers of the Philistines returned with the silver in their hands. <verse eid="JDG 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 16:19"/>After putting him to sleep on her lap, she called for someone to shave off the seven braids of his hair, and so began to subdue him.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:19 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; some Septuagint manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">and he began to weaken</char></note> And his strength left him.<verse eid="JDG 16:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 16:20"/>Then she called, ‘Samson, the Philistines are upon you!’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 16:20">He awoke from his sleep and thought, ‘I’ll go out as before and shake myself free.’ But he did not know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had left him.<verse eid="JDG 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 16:21"/>Then the Philistines seized him, gouged out his eyes and took him down to Gaza. Binding him with bronze shackles, they set him to grinding corn in the prison. <verse eid="JDG 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 16:22"/>But the hair on his head began to grow again after it had been shaved.<verse eid="JDG 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The death of Samson</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 16:23"/>Now the rulers of the Philistines assembled to offer a great sacrifice to Dagon their god and to celebrate, saying, ‘Our god has delivered Samson, our enemy, into our hands.’<verse eid="JDG 16:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 16:24"/>When the people saw him, they praised their god, saying,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 16:24">‘Our god has delivered our enemy</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 16:24">into our hands,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 16:24">the one who laid waste our land</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 16:24">and multiplied our slain.’<verse eid="JDG 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 16:25"/>While they were in high spirits, they shouted, ‘Bring out Samson to entertain us.’ So they called Samson out of the prison, and he performed for them.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 16:25">When they stood him among the pillars, <verse eid="JDG 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 16:26"/>Samson said to the servant who held his hand, ‘Put me where I can feel the pillars that support the temple, so that I may lean against them.’ <verse eid="JDG 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 16:27"/>Now the temple was crowded with men and women; all the rulers of the Philistines were there, and on the roof were about three thousand men and women watching Samson perform. <verse eid="JDG 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 16:28"/>Then Samson prayed to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, ‘Sovereign <char style="sc">Lord</char>, remember me. Please, God, strengthen me just once more, and let me with one blow get revenge on the Philistines for my two eyes.’ <verse eid="JDG 16:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 16:29"/>Then Samson reached towards the two central pillars on which the temple stood. Bracing himself against them, his right hand on the one and his left hand on the other, <verse eid="JDG 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 16:30"/>Samson said, ‘Let me die with the Philistines!’ Then he pushed with all his might, and down came the temple on the rulers and all the people in it. Thus he killed many more when he died than while he lived.<verse eid="JDG 16:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 16:31"/>Then his brothers and his father’s whole family went down to get him. They brought him back and buried him between Zorah and Eshtaol in the tomb of Manoah his father. He had led<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Traditionally </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">judged</char></note> Israel for twenty years.<verse eid="JDG 16:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JDG 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Micah’s idols</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 17:1"/>Now a man named Micah from the hill country of Ephraim <verse eid="JDG 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 17:2"/>said to his mother, ‘The eleven hundred shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 13 kilograms</char></note> of silver that were taken from you and about which I heard you utter a curse – I have that silver with me; I took it.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 17:2">Then his mother said, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> bless you, my son!’<verse eid="JDG 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 17:3"/>When he returned the eleven hundred shekels of silver to his mother, she said, ‘I solemnly consecrate my silver to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for my son to make an image overlaid with silver. I will give it back to you.’<verse eid="JDG 17:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 17:4"/>So after he returned the silver to his mother, she took two hundred shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 2.3 kilograms</char></note> of silver and gave them to a silversmith, who used them to make the idol. And it was put in Micah’s house.<verse eid="JDG 17:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 17:5"/>Now this man Micah had a shrine, and he made an ephod and some household gods and installed one of his sons as his priest. <verse eid="JDG 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 17:6"/>In those days Israel had no king; everyone did as they saw fit.<verse eid="JDG 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 17:7"/>A young Levite from Bethlehem in Judah, who had been living within the clan of Judah, <verse eid="JDG 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 17:8"/>left that town in search of some other place to stay. On his way<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">To carry on his profession</char></note> he came to Micah’s house in the hill country of Ephraim.<verse eid="JDG 17:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 17:9"/>Micah asked him, ‘Where are you from?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 17:9">‘I’m a Levite from Bethlehem in Judah,’ he said, ‘and I’m looking for a place to stay.’<verse eid="JDG 17:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 17:10"/>Then Micah said to him, ‘Live with me and be my father and priest, and I’ll give you ten shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 115 grams</char></note> of silver a year, your clothes and your food.’ <verse eid="JDG 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 17:11"/>So the Levite agreed to live with him, and the young man became like one of his sons to him. <verse eid="JDG 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 17:12"/>Then Micah installed the Levite, and the young man became his priest and lived in his house. <verse eid="JDG 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 17:13"/>And Micah said, ‘Now I know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will be good to me, since this Levite has become my priest.’<verse eid="JDG 17:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JDG 18"/>
  <para style="s1">The Danites settle in Laish</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 18:1"/>In those days Israel had no king.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 18:1">And in those days the tribe of the Danites was seeking a place of their own where they might settle, because they had not yet come into an inheritance among the tribes of Israel. <verse eid="JDG 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 18:2"/>So the Danites sent five of their leading men from Zorah and Eshtaol to spy out the land and explore it. These men represented all the Danites. They told them, ‘Go, explore the land.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 18:2">So they entered the hill country of Ephraim and came to the house of Micah, where they spent the night. <verse eid="JDG 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 18:3"/>When they were near Micah’s house, they recognised the voice of the young Levite; so they turned in there and asked him, ‘Who brought you here? What are you doing in this place? Why are you here?’<verse eid="JDG 18:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 18:4"/>He told them what Micah had done for him, and said, ‘He has hired me and I am his priest.’<verse eid="JDG 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 18:5"/>Then they said to him, ‘Please enquire of God to learn whether our journey will be successful.’<verse eid="JDG 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 18:6"/>The priest answered them, ‘Go in peace. Your journey has the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s approval.’<verse eid="JDG 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 18:7"/>So the five men left and came to Laish, where they saw that the people were living in safety, like the Sidonians, at peace and secure. And since their land lacked nothing, they were prosperous.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this clause is uncertain.</char></note> Also, they lived a long way from the Sidonians and had no relationship with anyone else.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:7 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; some Septuagint manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">with the Arameans</char></note><verse eid="JDG 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 18:8"/>When they returned to Zorah and Eshtaol, their fellow Danites asked them, ‘How did you find things?’<verse eid="JDG 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 18:9"/>They answered, ‘Come on, let’s attack them! We have seen the land, and it is very good. Aren’t you going to do something? Don’t hesitate to go there and take it over. <verse eid="JDG 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 18:10"/>When you get there, you will find an unsuspecting people and a spacious land that God has put into your hands, a land that lacks nothing whatever.’<verse eid="JDG 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 18:11"/>Then six hundred men of the Danites, armed for battle, set out from Zorah and Eshtaol. <verse eid="JDG 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 18:12"/>On their way they set up camp near Kiriath Jearim in Judah. This is why the place west of Kiriath Jearim is called Mahaneh Dan<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:12 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Mahaneh Dan </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Dan’s camp.</char></note> to this day. <verse eid="JDG 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 18:13"/>From there they went on to the hill country of Ephraim and came to Micah’s house.<verse eid="JDG 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 18:14"/>Then the five men who had spied out the land of Laish said to their fellow Danites, ‘Do you know that one of these houses has an ephod, some household gods and an image overlaid with silver? Now you know what to do.’ <verse eid="JDG 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 18:15"/>So they turned in there and went to the house of the young Levite at Micah’s place and greeted him. <verse eid="JDG 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 18:16"/>The six hundred Danites, armed for battle, stood at the entrance of the gate. <verse eid="JDG 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 18:17"/>The five men who had spied out the land went inside and took the idol, the ephod and the household gods while the priest and the six hundred armed men stood at the entrance of the gate.<verse eid="JDG 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 18:18"/>When the five men went into Micah’s house and took the idol, the ephod and the household gods, the priest said to them, ‘What are you doing?’<verse eid="JDG 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 18:19"/>They answered him, ‘Be quiet! Don’t say a word. Come with us, and be our father and priest. Isn’t it better that you serve a tribe and clan in Israel as priest rather than just one man’s household?’ <verse eid="JDG 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 18:20"/>The priest was very pleased. He took the ephod, the household gods and the idol and went along with the people. <verse eid="JDG 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 18:21"/>Putting their little children, their livestock and their possessions in front of them, they turned away and left.<verse eid="JDG 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 18:22"/>When they had gone some distance from Micah’s house, the men who lived near Micah were called together and overtook the Danites. <verse eid="JDG 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 18:23"/>As they shouted after them, the Danites turned and said to Micah, ‘What’s the matter with you that you called out your men to fight?’<verse eid="JDG 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 18:24"/>He replied, ‘You took the gods I made, and my priest, and went away. What else do I have? How can you ask, “What’s the matter with you?” ’<verse eid="JDG 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 18:25"/>The Danites answered, ‘Don’t argue with us, or some of the men may get angry and attack you, and you and your family will lose your lives.’ <verse eid="JDG 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 18:26"/>So the Danites went their way, and Micah, seeing that they were too strong for him, turned round and went back home.<verse eid="JDG 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 18:27"/>Then they took what Micah had made, and his priest, and went on to Laish, against a people at peace and secure. They attacked them with the sword and burned down their city. <verse eid="JDG 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 18:28"/>There was no-one to rescue them because they lived a long way from Sidon and had no relationship with anyone else. The city was in a valley near Beth Rehob.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 18:28">The Danites rebuilt the city and settled there. <verse eid="JDG 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 18:29"/>They named it Dan after their ancestor Dan, who was born to Israel – though the city used to be called Laish. <verse eid="JDG 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 18:30"/>There the Danites set up for themselves the idol, and Jonathan son of Gershom, the son of Moses,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">An ancient Hebrew scribal tradition, some Septuagint manuscripts and Vulgate; Masoretic Text </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Manasseh</char></note> and his sons were priests for the tribe of Dan until the time of the captivity of the land. <verse eid="JDG 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 18:31"/>They continued to use the idol Micah had made, all the time the house of God was in Shiloh.<verse eid="JDG 18:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JDG 19"/>
  <para style="s1">A Levite and his concubine</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 19:1"/>In those days Israel had no king.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 19:1">Now a Levite who lived in a remote area in the hill country of Ephraim took a concubine from Bethlehem in Judah. <verse eid="JDG 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 19:2"/>But she was unfaithful to him. She left him and went back to her parents’ home in Bethlehem, Judah. After she had been there for four months, <verse eid="JDG 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 19:3"/>her husband went to her to persuade her to return. He had with him his servant and two donkeys. She took him into her parents’ home, and when her father saw him, he gladly welcomed him. <verse eid="JDG 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 19:4"/>His father-in-law, the woman’s father, prevailed on him to stay; so he remained with him three days, eating and drinking, and sleeping there.<verse eid="JDG 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 19:5"/>On the fourth day they got up early and he prepared to leave, but the woman’s father said to his son-in-law, ‘Refresh yourself with something to eat; then you can go.’ <verse eid="JDG 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 19:6"/>So the two of them sat down to eat and drink together. Afterwards the woman’s father said, ‘Please stay tonight and enjoy yourself.’ <verse eid="JDG 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 19:7"/>And when the man got up to go, his father-in-law persuaded him, so he stayed there that night. <verse eid="JDG 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 19:8"/>On the morning of the fifth day, when he rose to go, the woman’s father said, ‘Refresh yourself. Wait till afternoon!’ So the two of them ate together.<verse eid="JDG 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 19:9"/>Then when the man, with his concubine and his servant, got up to leave, his father-in-law, the woman’s father, said, ‘Now look, it’s almost evening. Spend the night here; the day is nearly over. Stay and enjoy yourself. Early tomorrow morning you can get up and be on your way home.’ <verse eid="JDG 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 19:10"/>But, unwilling to stay another night, the man left and went towards Jebus (that is, Jerusalem), with his two saddled donkeys and his concubine.<verse eid="JDG 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 19:11"/>When they were near Jebus and the day was almost gone, the servant said to his master, ‘Come, let’s stop at this city of the Jebusites and spend the night.’<verse eid="JDG 19:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 19:12"/>His master replied, ‘No. We won’t go into any city whose people are not Israelites. We will go on to Gibeah.’ <verse eid="JDG 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 19:13"/>He added, ‘Come, let’s try to reach Gibeah or Ramah and spend the night in one of those places.’ <verse eid="JDG 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 19:14"/>So they went on, and the sun set as they neared Gibeah in Benjamin. <verse eid="JDG 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 19:15"/>There they stopped to spend the night. They went and sat in the city square, but no-one took them in for the night.<verse eid="JDG 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 19:16"/>That evening an old man from the hill country of Ephraim, who was living in Gibeah (the inhabitants of the place were Benjaminites), came in from his work in the fields. <verse eid="JDG 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 19:17"/>When he looked and saw the traveller in the city square, the old man asked, ‘Where are you going? Where did you come from?’<verse eid="JDG 19:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 19:18"/>He answered, ‘We are on our way from Bethlehem in Judah to a remote area in the hill country of Ephraim where I live. I have been to Bethlehem in Judah and now I am going to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew, Vulgate, Syriac and Targum; Septuagint </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">going home</char></note> No-one has taken me in for the night. <verse eid="JDG 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 19:19"/>We have both straw and fodder for our donkeys and bread and wine for ourselves your servants – me, the woman and the young man with us. We don’t need anything.’<verse eid="JDG 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 19:20"/>‘You are welcome at my house,’ the old man said. ‘Let me supply whatever you need. Only don’t spend the night in the square.’ <verse eid="JDG 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 19:21"/>So he took him into his house and fed his donkeys. After they had washed their feet, they had something to eat and drink.<verse eid="JDG 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 19:22"/>While they were enjoying themselves, some of the wicked men of the city surrounded the house. Pounding on the door, they shouted to the old man who owned the house, ‘Bring out the man who came to your house so we can have sex with him.’<verse eid="JDG 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 19:23"/>The owner of the house went outside and said to them, ‘No, my friends, don’t be so vile. Since this man is my guest, don’t do this outrageous thing. <verse eid="JDG 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 19:24"/>Look, here is my virgin daughter, and his concubine. I will bring them out to you now, and you can use them and do to them whatever you wish. But as for this man, don’t do such an outrageous thing.’<verse eid="JDG 19:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 19:25"/>But the men would not listen to him. So the man took his concubine and sent her outside to them, and they raped her and abused her throughout the night, and at dawn they let her go. <verse eid="JDG 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 19:26"/>At daybreak the woman went back to the house where her master was staying, fell down at the door and lay there until daylight.<verse eid="JDG 19:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 19:27"/>When her master got up in the morning and opened the door of the house and stepped out to continue on his way, there lay his concubine, fallen in the doorway of the house, with her hands on the threshold. <verse eid="JDG 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 19:28"/>He said to her, ‘Get up; let’s go.’ But there was no answer. Then the man put her on his donkey and set out for home.<verse eid="JDG 19:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 19:29"/>When he reached home, he took a knife and cut up his concubine, limb by limb, into twelve parts and sent them into all the areas of Israel. <verse eid="JDG 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 19:30"/>Everyone who saw it was saying to one another, ‘Such a thing has never been seen or done, not since the day the Israelites came up out of Egypt. Just imagine! We must do something! So speak up!’<verse eid="JDG 19:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JDG 20"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelites punish the Benjaminites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 20:1"/>Then all Israel from Dan to Beersheba and from the land of Gilead came together as one and assembled before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Mizpah. <verse eid="JDG 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 20:2"/>The leaders of all the people of the tribes of Israel took their places in the assembly of God’s people, four hundred thousand men armed with swords. <verse eid="JDG 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 20:3"/>(The Benjaminites heard that the Israelites had gone up to Mizpah.) Then the Israelites said, ‘Tell us how this awful thing happened.’<verse eid="JDG 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 20:4"/>So the Levite, the husband of the murdered woman, said, ‘I and my concubine came to Gibeah in Benjamin to spend the night. <verse eid="JDG 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 20:5"/>During the night the men of Gibeah came after me and surrounded the house, intending to kill me. They raped my concubine, and she died. <verse eid="JDG 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 20:6"/>I took my concubine, cut her into pieces and sent one piece to each region of Israel’s inheritance, because they committed this lewd and outrageous act in Israel. <verse eid="JDG 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 20:7"/>Now, all you Israelites, speak up and tell me what you have decided to do.’<verse eid="JDG 20:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 20:8"/>All the men rose up together as one, saying, ‘None of us will go home. No, not one of us will return to his house. <verse eid="JDG 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 20:9"/>But now this is what we’ll do to Gibeah: we’ll go up against it in the order decided by casting lots. <verse eid="JDG 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 20:10"/>We’ll take ten men out of every hundred from all the tribes of Israel, and a hundred from a thousand, and a thousand from ten thousand, to get provisions for the army. Then, when the army arrives at Gibeah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">One Hebrew manuscript; most Hebrew manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Geba, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Gibeah</char></note> in Benjamin, it can give them what they deserve for this outrageous act done in Israel.’ <verse eid="JDG 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 20:11"/>So all the Israelites got together and united as one against the city.<verse eid="JDG 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 20:12"/>The tribes of Israel sent messengers throughout the tribe of Benjamin, saying, ‘What about this awful crime that was committed among you? <verse eid="JDG 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 20:13"/>Now turn those wicked men of Gibeah over to us so that we may put them to death and purge the evil from Israel.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:13">But the Benjaminites would not listen to their fellow Israelites. <verse eid="JDG 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 20:14"/>From their towns they came together at Gibeah to fight against the Israelites. <verse eid="JDG 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 20:15"/>At once the Benjaminites mobilised twenty-six thousand swordsmen from their towns, in addition to seven hundred able young men from those living in Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 20:16"/>Among all these soldiers there were seven hundred select troops who were left-handed, each of whom could sling a stone at a hair and not miss.<verse eid="JDG 20:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 20:17"/>Israel, apart from Benjamin, mustered four hundred thousand swordsmen, all of them fit for battle.<verse eid="JDG 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 20:18"/>The Israelites went up to Bethel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">to the house of God</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verse 26</char></note> and enquired of God. They said, ‘Who of us is to go up first to fight against the Benjaminites?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:18">The <char style="sc">Lord</char> replied, ‘Judah shall go first.’<verse eid="JDG 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 20:19"/>The next morning the Israelites got up and pitched camp near Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 20:20"/>The Israelites went out to fight the Benjaminites and took up battle positions against them at Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 20:21"/>The Benjaminites came out of Gibeah and cut down twenty-two thousand Israelites on the battlefield that day. <verse eid="JDG 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 20:22"/>But the Israelites encouraged one another and again took up their positions where they had stationed themselves the first day. <verse eid="JDG 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 20:23"/>The Israelites went up and wept before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> until evening, and they enquired of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. They said, ‘Shall we go up again to fight against the Benjaminites, our fellow Israelites?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:23">The <char style="sc">Lord</char> answered, ‘Go up against them.’<verse eid="JDG 20:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 20:24"/>Then the Israelites drew near to Benjamin the second day. <verse eid="JDG 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 20:25"/>This time, when the Benjaminites came out from Gibeah to oppose them, they cut down another eighteen thousand Israelites, all of them armed with swords.<verse eid="JDG 20:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 20:26"/>Then all the Israelites, the whole army, went up to Bethel, and there they sat weeping before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. They fasted that day until evening and presented burnt offerings and fellowship offerings to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="JDG 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 20:27"/>And the Israelites enquired of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. (In those days the ark of the covenant of God was there, <verse eid="JDG 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 20:28"/>with Phinehas son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron, ministering before it.) They asked, ‘Shall we go up again to fight against the Benjaminites, our fellow Israelites, or not?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:28">The <char style="sc">Lord</char> responded, ‘Go, for tomorrow I will give them into your hands.’<verse eid="JDG 20:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 20:29"/>Then Israel set an ambush around Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 20:30"/>They went up against the Benjaminites on the third day and took up positions against Gibeah as they had done before. <verse eid="JDG 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 20:31"/>The Benjaminites came out to meet them and were drawn away from the city. They began to inflict casualties on the Israelites as before, so that about thirty men fell in the open field and on the roads – the one leading to Bethel and the other to Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 20:32"/>While the Benjaminites were saying, ‘We are defeating them as before,’ the Israelites were saying, ‘Let’s retreat and draw them away from the city to the roads.’<verse eid="JDG 20:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 20:33"/>All the men of Israel moved from their places and took up positions at Baal Tamar, and the Israelite ambush charged out of its place on the west<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Septuagint manuscripts and Vulgate; the meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</char></note> of Gibeah.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Geba, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Gibeah</char></note> <verse eid="JDG 20:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 20:34"/>Then ten thousand of Israel’s able young men made a frontal attack on Gibeah. The fighting was so heavy that the Benjaminites did not realise how near disaster was. <verse eid="JDG 20:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 20:35"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> defeated Benjamin before Israel, and on that day the Israelites struck down 25,100 Benjaminites, all armed with swords. <verse eid="JDG 20:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 20:36"/>Then the Benjaminites saw that they were beaten.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:36">Now the men of Israel had given way before Benjamin, because they relied on the ambush they had set near Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JDG 20:37"/>Those who had been in ambush made a sudden dash into Gibeah, spread out and put the whole city to the sword. <verse eid="JDG 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JDG 20:38"/>The Israelites had arranged with the ambush that they should send up a great cloud of smoke from the city, <verse eid="JDG 20:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 20:39"/>and then the Israelites would counterattack.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:39">The Benjaminites had begun to inflict casualties on the Israelites (about thirty), and they said, ‘We are defeating them as in the first battle.’ <verse eid="JDG 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 20:40"/>But when the column of smoke began to rise from the city, the Benjaminites turned and saw the whole city going up in smoke. <verse eid="JDG 20:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JDG 20:41"/>Then the Israelites counterattacked, and the Benjaminites were terrified, because they realised that disaster had come on them. <verse eid="JDG 20:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JDG 20:42"/>So they fled before the Israelites in the direction of the wilderness, but they could not escape the battle. And the Israelites who came out of the towns cut them down there. <verse eid="JDG 20:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JDG 20:43"/>They surrounded the Benjaminites, chased them and easily<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</char></note> overran them in the vicinity of Gibeah on the east. <verse eid="JDG 20:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JDG 20:44"/>Eighteen thousand Benjaminites fell, all of them valiant fighters. <verse eid="JDG 20:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JDG 20:45"/>As they turned and fled towards the wilderness to the rock of Rimmon, the Israelites cut down five thousand men along the roads. They kept pressing after the Benjaminites as far as Gidom and struck down two thousand more.<verse eid="JDG 20:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="JDG 20:46"/>On that day twenty-five thousand Benjaminite swordsmen fell, all of them valiant fighters. <verse eid="JDG 20:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JDG 20:47"/>But six hundred of them turned and fled into the wilderness to the rock of Rimmon, where they stayed for four months. <verse eid="JDG 20:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JDG 20:48"/>The men of Israel went back to Benjamin and put all the towns to the sword, including the animals and everything else they found. All the towns they came across they set on fire.<verse eid="JDG 20:48"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JDG 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Wives for the Benjaminites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 21:1"/>The men of Israel had taken an oath at Mizpah: ‘Not one of us will give his daughter in marriage to a Benjaminite.’<verse eid="JDG 21:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 21:2"/>The people went to Bethel,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">21:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">to the house of God</char></note> where they sat before God until evening, raising their voices and weeping bitterly. <verse eid="JDG 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 21:3"/>‘<char style="sc">Lord</char>, God of Israel,’ they cried, ‘why has this happened to Israel? Why should one tribe be missing from Israel today?’<verse eid="JDG 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 21:4"/>Early the next day the people built an altar and presented burnt offerings and fellowship offerings.<verse eid="JDG 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 21:5"/>Then the Israelites asked, ‘Who from all the tribes of Israel has failed to assemble before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?’ For they had taken a solemn oath that anyone who failed to assemble before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at Mizpah was to be put to death.<verse eid="JDG 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 21:6"/>Now the Israelites grieved for the tribe of Benjamin, their fellow Israelites. ‘Today one tribe is cut off from Israel,’ they said. <verse eid="JDG 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 21:7"/>‘How can we provide wives for those who are left, since we have taken an oath by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> not to give them any of our daughters in marriage?’ <verse eid="JDG 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 21:8"/>Then they asked, ‘Which one of the tribes of Israel failed to assemble before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at Mizpah?’ They discovered that no-one from Jabesh Gilead had come to the camp for the assembly. <verse eid="JDG 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 21:9"/>For when they counted the people, they found that none of the people of Jabesh Gilead were there.<verse eid="JDG 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 21:10"/>So the assembly sent twelve thousand fighting men with instructions to go to Jabesh Gilead and put to the sword those living there, including the women and children. <verse eid="JDG 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 21:11"/>‘This is what you are to do,’ they said. ‘Kill every male and every woman who is not a virgin.’ <verse eid="JDG 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 21:12"/>They found among the people living in Jabesh Gilead four hundred young women who had never slept with a man, and they took them to the camp at Shiloh in Canaan.<verse eid="JDG 21:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 21:13"/>Then the whole assembly sent an offer of peace to the Benjaminites at the rock of Rimmon. <verse eid="JDG 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 21:14"/>So the Benjaminites returned at that time and were given the women of Jabesh Gilead who had been spared. But there were not enough for all of them.<verse eid="JDG 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 21:15"/>The people grieved for Benjamin, because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had made a gap in the tribes of Israel. <verse eid="JDG 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 21:16"/>And the elders of the assembly said, ‘With the women of Benjamin destroyed, how shall we provide wives for the men who are left? <verse eid="JDG 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 21:17"/>The Benjaminite survivors must have heirs,’ they said, ‘so that a tribe of Israel will not be wiped out. <verse eid="JDG 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 21:18"/>We can’t give them our daughters as wives, since we Israelites have taken this oath: “Cursed be anyone who gives a wife to a Benjaminite.” <verse eid="JDG 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 21:19"/>But look, there is the annual festival of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in Shiloh, which lies north of Bethel, east of the road that goes from Bethel to Shechem, and south of Lebonah.’<verse eid="JDG 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 21:20"/>So they instructed the Benjaminites, saying, ‘Go and hide in the vineyards <verse eid="JDG 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 21:21"/>and watch. When the young women of Shiloh come out to join in the dancing, rush from the vineyards and each of you seize one of them to be your wife. Then return to the land of Benjamin. <verse eid="JDG 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 21:22"/>When their fathers or brothers complain to us, we will say to them, “Do us the favour of helping them, because we did not get wives for them during the war. You will not be guilty of breaking your oath because you did not give your daughters to them.” ’<verse eid="JDG 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 21:23"/>So that is what the Benjaminites did. While the young women were dancing, each man caught one and carried her off to be his wife. Then they returned to their inheritance and rebuilt the towns and settled in them.<verse eid="JDG 21:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 21:24"/>At that time the Israelites left that place and went home to their tribes and clans, each to his own inheritance.<verse eid="JDG 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 21:25"/>In those days Israel had no king; everyone did as they saw fit.<verse eid="JDG 21:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 21"/>
</usx>
