<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JOS" style="id">- English-UK: New International Version® (Anglicised) NIV® 2011 (Revised format)</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1973, 1978, 1984, 2011 by Biblica, Inc.®</para>
  <para style="h">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc1">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc2">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jos</para>
  <para style="mt1">Joshua</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The books of Joshua and Judges tell the story of the early years of Israel as a nation. They describe how the Israelites conquer and occupy the land of Canaan, and then struggle to live up to their covenant with God. The Bible’s drama here moves to an important new stage – God’s people are in God’s land. Yet it becomes clear that the road to reconciliation between God and humanity will not be easy.</para>
  <para style="ip">The story describes the preparations and battles of Israel’s invasion, as well as how the land was divided among the tribes. Since pockets of resistance remained, Joshua in his final speech urges each tribe to take full possession of its territory. Next he leads the people to renew their commitment to the covenant relationship with God.</para>
  <para style="ip">Judges then relates the troubling cycle of Israel’s repeated covenant breaking, falling under the rule of other nations, and then crying out to God for help. God responds by raising up ‘judges’ to fight for them and save them. But the relief is temporary as Israel falls back into wrongdoing once again. (‘Judges’ are both military leaders and legal authorities.)</para>
  <para style="ip">Just as Israel was made up of twelve tribes, so the book tells of twelve judges. But as the people persist in going their own way, we see that they have rejected their true Judge and Ruler. As the anarchy and atrocities increase, Israel’s need for a king becomes more evident. By the end the questions are urgent: Can Israel fulfil its destiny and calling to be God’s light to the nations? Who can rule Israel to help it find its proper role in the drama?</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JOS 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua installed as leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 1:1"/>After the death of Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua son of Nun, Moses’ assistant: <verse eid="JOS 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 1:2"/>‘Moses my servant is dead. Now then, you and all these people, get ready to cross the River Jordan into the land I am about to give to them – to the Israelites. <verse eid="JOS 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 1:3"/>I will give you every place where you set your foot, as I promised Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 1:4"/>Your territory will extend from the desert to Lebanon, and from the great river, the Euphrates – all the Hittite country – to the Mediterranean Sea in the west. <verse eid="JOS 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 1:5"/>No-one will be able to stand against you all the days of your life. As I was with Moses, so I will be with you; I will never leave you nor forsake you. <verse eid="JOS 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 1:6"/>Be strong and courageous, because you will lead these people to inherit the land I swore to their ancestors to give them.<verse eid="JOS 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 1:7"/>‘Be strong and very courageous. Be careful to obey all the law my servant Moses gave you; do not turn from it to the right or to the left, that you may be successful wherever you go. <verse eid="JOS 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 1:8"/>Keep this Book of the Law always on your lips; meditate on it day and night, so that you may be careful to do everything written in it. Then you will be prosperous and successful. <verse eid="JOS 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 1:9"/>Have I not commanded you? Be strong and courageous. Do not be afraid; do not be discouraged, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will be with you wherever you go.’<verse eid="JOS 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 1:10"/>So Joshua ordered the officers of the people: <verse eid="JOS 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 1:11"/>‘Go through the camp and tell the people, “Get your provisions ready. Three days from now you will cross the Jordan here to go in and take possession of the land the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God is giving you for your own.” ’<verse eid="JOS 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 1:12"/>But to the Reubenites, the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh, Joshua said, <verse eid="JOS 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 1:13"/>‘Remember the command that Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave you after he said, “The <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will give you rest by giving you this land.” <verse eid="JOS 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 1:14"/>Your wives, your children and your livestock may stay in the land that Moses gave you east of the Jordan, but all your fighting men, ready for battle, must cross over ahead of your fellow Israelites. You are to help them <verse eid="JOS 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 1:15"/>until the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gives them rest, as he has done for you, and until they too have taken possession of the land that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God is giving them. After that, you may go back and occupy your own land, which Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave you east of the Jordan towards the sunrise.’<verse eid="JOS 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 1:16"/>Then they answered Joshua, ‘Whatever you have commanded us we will do, and wherever you send us we will go. <verse eid="JOS 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 1:17"/>Just as we fully obeyed Moses, so we will obey you. Only may the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God be with you as he was with Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 1:18"/>Whoever rebels against your word and does not obey it, whatever you may command them, will be put to death. Only be strong and courageous!’<verse eid="JOS 1:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JOS 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Rahab and the spies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 2:1"/>Then Joshua son of Nun secretly sent two spies from Shittim. ‘Go, look over the land,’ he said, ‘especially Jericho.’ So they went and entered the house of a prostitute named Rahab and stayed there.<verse eid="JOS 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 2:2"/>The king of Jericho was told, ‘Look, some of the Israelites have come here tonight to spy out the land.’ <verse eid="JOS 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 2:3"/>So the king of Jericho sent this message to Rahab: ‘Bring out the men who came to you and entered your house, because they have come to spy out the whole land.’<verse eid="JOS 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 2:4"/>But the woman had taken the two men and hidden them. She said, ‘Yes, the men came to me, but I did not know where they had come from. <verse eid="JOS 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 2:5"/>At dusk, when it was time to close the city gate, they left. I don’t know which way they went. Go after them quickly. You may catch up with them.’ <verse eid="JOS 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 2:6"/>(But she had taken them up to the roof and hidden them under the stalks of flax she had laid out on the roof.) <verse eid="JOS 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 2:7"/>So the men set out in pursuit of the spies on the road that leads to the fords of the Jordan, and as soon as the pursuers had gone out, the gate was shut.<verse eid="JOS 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 2:8"/>Before the spies lay down for the night, she went up on the roof <verse eid="JOS 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 2:9"/>and said to them, ‘I know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given this land to you and that a great fear of you has fallen on us, so that all who live in this country are melting in fear because of you. <verse eid="JOS 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 2:10"/>We have heard how the <char style="sc">Lord</char> dried up the water of the Red Sea<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the Sea of Reeds</char></note> for you when you came out of Egypt, and what you did to Sihon and Og, the two kings of the Amorites east of the Jordan, whom you completely destroyed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:10 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them.</char></note> <verse eid="JOS 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 2:11"/>When we heard of it, our hearts sank and everyone’s courage failed because of you, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God is God in heaven above and on the earth below.<verse eid="JOS 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 2:12"/>‘Now then, please swear to me by the <char style="sc">Lord</char> that you will show kindness to my family, because I have shown kindness to you. Give me a sure sign <verse eid="JOS 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 2:13"/>that you will spare the lives of my father and mother, my brothers and sisters, and all who belong to them – and that you will save us from death.’<verse eid="JOS 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 2:14"/>‘Our lives for your lives!’ the men assured her. ‘If you don’t tell what we are doing, we will treat you kindly and faithfully when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gives us the land.’<verse eid="JOS 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 2:15"/>So she let them down by a rope through the window, for the house she lived in was part of the city wall. <verse eid="JOS 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 2:16"/>She said to them, ‘Go to the hills so that the pursuers will not find you. Hide yourselves there for three days until they return, and then go on your way.’<verse eid="JOS 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 2:17"/>Now the men had said to her, ‘This oath you made us swear will not be binding on us <verse eid="JOS 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 2:18"/>unless, when we enter the land, you have tied this scarlet cord in the window through which you let us down, and unless you have brought your father and mother, your brothers and all your family into your house. <verse eid="JOS 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 2:19"/>If any of them go outside your house into the street, their blood will be on their own heads; we will not be responsible. As for those who are in the house with you, their blood will be on our head if a hand is laid on them. <verse eid="JOS 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 2:20"/>But if you tell what we are doing, we will be released from the oath you made us swear.’<verse eid="JOS 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 2:21"/>‘Agreed,’ she replied. ‘Let it be as you say.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 2:21">So she sent them away, and they departed. And she tied the scarlet cord in the window.<verse eid="JOS 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 2:22"/>When they left, they went into the hills and stayed there three days, until the pursuers had searched all along the road and returned without finding them. <verse eid="JOS 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 2:23"/>Then the two men started back. They went down out of the hills, forded the river and came to Joshua son of Nun and told him everything that had happened to them. <verse eid="JOS 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 2:24"/>They said to Joshua, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has surely given the whole land into our hands; all the people are melting in fear because of us.’<verse eid="JOS 2:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JOS 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Crossing the Jordan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 3:1"/>Early in the morning Joshua and all the Israelites set out from Shittim and went to the Jordan, where they camped before crossing over. <verse eid="JOS 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 3:2"/>After three days the officers went throughout the camp, <verse eid="JOS 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 3:3"/>giving orders to the people: ‘When you see the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, and the Levitical priests carrying it, you are to move out from your positions and follow it. <verse eid="JOS 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 3:4"/>Then you will know which way to go, since you have never been this way before. But keep a distance of about two thousand cubits<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 900 metres</char></note> between you and the ark; do not go near it.’<verse eid="JOS 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 3:5"/>Joshua told the people, ‘Consecrate yourselves, for tomorrow the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will do amazing things among you.’<verse eid="JOS 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 3:6"/>Joshua said to the priests, ‘Take up the ark of the covenant and pass on ahead of the people.’ So they took it up and went ahead of them.<verse eid="JOS 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 3:7"/>And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Today I will begin to exalt you in the eyes of all Israel, so that they may know that I am with you as I was with Moses. <verse eid="JOS 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 3:8"/>Tell the priests who carry the ark of the covenant: “When you reach the edge of the Jordan’s waters, go and stand in the river.” ’<verse eid="JOS 3:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 3:9"/>Joshua said to the Israelites, ‘Come here and listen to the words of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. <verse eid="JOS 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 3:10"/>This is how you will know that the living God is among you and that he will certainly drive out before you the Canaanites, Hittites, Hivites, Perizzites, Girgashites, Amorites and Jebusites. <verse eid="JOS 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 3:11"/>See, the ark of the covenant of the Lord of all the earth will go into the Jordan ahead of you. <verse eid="JOS 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 3:12"/>Now then, choose twelve men from the tribes of Israel, one from each tribe. <verse eid="JOS 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 3:13"/>And as soon as the priests who carry the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> – the Lord of all the earth – set foot in the Jordan, its waters flowing downstream will be cut off and stand up in a heap.’<verse eid="JOS 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 3:14"/>So when the people broke camp to cross the Jordan, the priests carrying the ark of the covenant went ahead of them. <verse eid="JOS 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 3:15"/>Now the Jordan is in flood all during harvest. Yet as soon as the priests who carried the ark reached the Jordan and their feet touched the water’s edge, <verse eid="JOS 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 3:16"/>the water from upstream stopped flowing. It piled up in a heap a great distance away, at a town called Adam in the vicinity of Zarethan, while the water flowing down to the Sea of the Arabah (that is, the Dead Sea) was completely cut off. So the people crossed over opposite Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 3:17"/>The priests who carried the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> stopped in the middle of the Jordan and stood on dry ground, while all Israel passed by until the whole nation had completed the crossing on dry ground.<verse eid="JOS 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JOS 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 4:1"/>When the whole nation had finished crossing the Jordan, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, <verse eid="JOS 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 4:2"/>‘Choose twelve men from among the people, one from each tribe, <verse eid="JOS 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 4:3"/>and tell them to take up twelve stones from the middle of the Jordan, from right where the priests are standing, and carry them over with you and put them down at the place where you stay tonight.’<verse eid="JOS 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 4:4"/>So Joshua called together the twelve men he had appointed from the Israelites, one from each tribe, <verse eid="JOS 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 4:5"/>and said to them, ‘Go over before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God into the middle of the Jordan. Each of you is to take up a stone on his shoulder, according to the number of the tribes of the Israelites, <verse eid="JOS 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 4:6"/>to serve as a sign among you. In the future, when your children ask you, “What do these stones mean?” <verse eid="JOS 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 4:7"/>tell them that the flow of the Jordan was cut off before the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. When it crossed the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan were cut off. These stones are to be a memorial to the people of Israel for ever.’<verse eid="JOS 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 4:8"/>So the Israelites did as Joshua commanded them. They took twelve stones from the middle of the Jordan, according to the number of the tribes of the Israelites, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had told Joshua; and they carried them over with them to their camp, where they put them down. <verse eid="JOS 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 4:9"/>Joshua set up the twelve stones that had been<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Joshua also set up twelve stones</char></note> in the middle of the Jordan at the spot where the priests who carried the ark of the covenant had stood. And they are there to this day.<verse eid="JOS 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 4:10"/>Now the priests who carried the ark remained standing in the middle of the Jordan until everything the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Joshua was done by the people, just as Moses had directed Joshua. The people hurried over, <verse eid="JOS 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 4:11"/>and as soon as all of them had crossed, the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and the priests came to the other side while the people watched. <verse eid="JOS 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 4:12"/>The men of Reuben, Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh crossed over, ready for battle, in front of the Israelites, as Moses had directed them. <verse eid="JOS 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 4:13"/>About forty thousand armed for battle crossed over before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to the plains of Jericho for war.<verse eid="JOS 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 4:14"/>That day the <char style="sc">Lord</char> exalted Joshua in the sight of all Israel; and they stood in awe of him all the days of his life, just as they had stood in awe of Moses.<verse eid="JOS 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 4:15"/>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, <verse eid="JOS 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 4:16"/>‘Command the priests carrying the ark of the covenant law to come up out of the Jordan.’<verse eid="JOS 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 4:17"/>So Joshua commanded the priests, ‘Come up out of the Jordan.’<verse eid="JOS 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 4:18"/>And the priests came up out of the river carrying the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. No sooner had they set their feet on the dry ground than the waters of the Jordan returned to their place and ran in flood as before.<verse eid="JOS 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 4:19"/>On the tenth day of the first month the people went up from the Jordan and camped at Gilgal on the eastern border of Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 4:20"/>And Joshua set up at Gilgal the twelve stones they had taken out of the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 4:21"/>He said to the Israelites, ‘In the future when your descendants ask their parents, “What do these stones mean?” <verse eid="JOS 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 4:22"/>tell them, “Israel crossed the Jordan on dry ground.” <verse eid="JOS 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 4:23"/>For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God dried up the Jordan before you until you had crossed over. The <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God did to the Jordan what he had done to the Red Sea<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the Sea of Reeds</char></note> when he dried it up before us until we had crossed over. <verse eid="JOS 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 4:24"/>He did this so that all the peoples of the earth might know that the hand of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is powerful and so that you might always fear the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.’<verse eid="JOS 4:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JOS 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 5:1"/>Now when all the Amorite kings west of the Jordan and all the Canaanite kings along the coast heard how the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had dried up the Jordan before the Israelites until they<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Another textual tradition </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">we</char></note> had crossed over, their hearts melted in fear and they no longer had the courage to face the Israelites.<verse eid="JOS 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Circumcision and Passover at Gilgal</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 5:2"/>At that time the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Make flint knives and circumcise the Israelites again.’ <verse eid="JOS 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 5:3"/>So Joshua made flint knives and circumcised the Israelites at Gibeath Haaraloth.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:3 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Gibeath Haaraloth </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the hill of foreskins.</char></note><verse eid="JOS 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 5:4"/>Now this is why he did so: all those who came out of Egypt – all the men of military age – died in the wilderness on the way after leaving Egypt. <verse eid="JOS 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 5:5"/>All the people that came out had been circumcised, but all the people born in the wilderness during the journey from Egypt had not. <verse eid="JOS 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 5:6"/>The Israelites had moved about in the wilderness for forty years until all the men who were of military age when they left Egypt had died, since they had not obeyed the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had sworn to them that they would not see the land that he had solemnly promised their ancestors to give us, a land flowing with milk and honey. <verse eid="JOS 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 5:7"/>So he raised up their sons in their place, and these were the ones Joshua circumcised. They were still uncircumcised because they had not been circumcised on the way. <verse eid="JOS 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 5:8"/>And after the whole nation had been circumcised, they remained where they were in camp until they were healed.<verse eid="JOS 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 5:9"/>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Today I have rolled away the reproach of Egypt from you.’ So the place has been called Gilgal<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:9 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Gilgal </char><char style="ft" closed="false">sounds like the Hebrew for </char><char style="fq" closed="false">roll</char><char style="fqa" closed="false">.</char></note> to this day.<verse eid="JOS 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 5:10"/>On the evening of the fourteenth day of the month, while camped at Gilgal on the plains of Jericho, the Israelites celebrated the Passover. <verse eid="JOS 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 5:11"/>The day after the Passover, that very day, they ate some of the produce of the land: unleavened bread and roasted grain. <verse eid="JOS 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 5:12"/>The manna stopped the day after<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the day</char></note> they ate this food from the land; there was no longer any manna for the Israelites, but that year they ate the produce of Canaan.<verse eid="JOS 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The fall of Jericho</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 5:13"/>Now when Joshua was near Jericho, he looked up and saw a man standing in front of him with a drawn sword in his hand. Joshua went up to him and asked, ‘Are you for us or for our enemies?’<verse eid="JOS 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 5:14"/>‘Neither,’ he replied, ‘but as commander of the army of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> I have now come.’ Then Joshua fell face down to the ground in reverence, and asked him, ‘What message does my Lord<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">lord</char></note> have for his servant?’<verse eid="JOS 5:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 5:15"/>The commander of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s army replied, ‘Take off your sandals, for the place where you are standing is holy.’ And Joshua did so.<verse eid="JOS 5:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JOS 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 6:1"/>Now the gates of Jericho were securely barred because of the Israelites. No-one went out and no-one came in.<verse eid="JOS 6:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 6:2"/>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘See, I have delivered Jericho into your hands, along with its king and its fighting men. <verse eid="JOS 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 6:3"/>March round the city once with all the armed men. Do this for six days. <verse eid="JOS 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 6:4"/>Make seven priests carry trumpets of rams’ horns in front of the ark. On the seventh day, march round the city seven times, with the priests blowing the trumpets. <verse eid="JOS 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 6:5"/>When you hear them sound a long blast on the trumpets, make the whole army give a loud shout; then the wall of the city will collapse and the army will go up, everyone straight in.’<verse eid="JOS 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 6:6"/>So Joshua son of Nun called the priests and said to them, ‘Take up the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and make seven priests carry trumpets in front of it.’ <verse eid="JOS 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 6:7"/>And he ordered the army, ‘Advance! March round the city, with an armed guard going ahead of the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’<verse eid="JOS 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 6:8"/>When Joshua had spoken to the people, the seven priests carrying the seven trumpets before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> went forwards, blowing their trumpets, and the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s covenant followed them. <verse eid="JOS 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 6:9"/>The armed guard marched ahead of the priests who blew the trumpets, and the rear guard followed the ark. All this time the trumpets were sounding. <verse eid="JOS 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 6:10"/>But Joshua had commanded the army, ‘Do not give a war cry, do not raise your voices, do not say a word until the day I tell you to shout. Then shout!’ <verse eid="JOS 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 6:11"/>So he had the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> carried round the city, circling it once. Then the army returned to camp and spent the night there.<verse eid="JOS 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 6:12"/>Joshua got up early the next morning and the priests took up the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="JOS 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 6:13"/>The seven priests carrying the seven trumpets went forwards, marching before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and blowing the trumpets. The armed men went ahead of them and the rear guard followed the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, while the trumpets kept sounding. <verse eid="JOS 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 6:14"/>So on the second day they marched round the city once and returned to the camp. They did this for six days.<verse eid="JOS 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 6:15"/>On the seventh day, they got up at daybreak and marched round the city seven times in the same manner, except that on that day they circled the city seven times. <verse eid="JOS 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 6:16"/>The seventh time round, when the priests sounded the trumpet blast, Joshua commanded the army, ‘Shout! For the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has given you the city! <verse eid="JOS 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 6:17"/>The city and all that is in it are to be devoted<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them; also in verses 18 and 21.</char></note> to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. Only Rahab the prostitute and all who are with her in her house shall be spared, because she hid the spies we sent. <verse eid="JOS 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 6:18"/>But keep away from the devoted things, so that you will not bring about your own destruction by taking any of them. Otherwise you will make the camp of Israel liable to destruction and bring trouble on it. <verse eid="JOS 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 6:19"/>All the silver and gold and the articles of bronze and iron are sacred to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and must go into his treasury.’<verse eid="JOS 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 6:20"/>When the trumpets sounded, the army shouted, and at the sound of the trumpet, when the men gave a loud shout, the wall collapsed; so everyone charged straight in, and they took the city. <verse eid="JOS 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 6:21"/>They devoted the city to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and destroyed with the sword every living thing in it – men and women, young and old, cattle, sheep and donkeys.<verse eid="JOS 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 6:22"/>Joshua said to the two men who had spied out the land, ‘Go into the prostitute’s house and bring her out and all who belong to her, in accordance with your oath to her.’ <verse eid="JOS 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 6:23"/>So the young men who had done the spying went in and brought out Rahab, her father and mother, her brothers and sisters and all who belonged to her. They brought out her entire family and put them in a place outside the camp of Israel.<verse eid="JOS 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 6:24"/>Then they burned the whole city and everything in it, but they put the silver and gold and the articles of bronze and iron into the treasury of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s house. <verse eid="JOS 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 6:25"/>But Joshua spared Rahab the prostitute, with her family and all who belonged to her, because she hid the men Joshua had sent as spies to Jericho – and she lives among the Israelites to this day.<verse eid="JOS 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 6:26"/>At that time Joshua pronounced this solemn oath: ‘Cursed before the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is the one who undertakes to rebuild this city, Jericho:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JOS 6:26">‘At the cost of his firstborn son</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 6:26">he will lay its foundations;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JOS 6:26">at the cost of his youngest</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 6:26">he will set up its gates.’<verse eid="JOS 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 6:27"/>So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was with Joshua, and his fame spread throughout the land.<verse eid="JOS 6:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JOS 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Achan’s sin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 7:1"/>But the Israelites were unfaithful in regard to the devoted things<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them; also in verses 11, 12, 13 and 15.</char></note>; Achan son of Karmi, the son of Zimri,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See Septuagint and <char style="xt"><ref loc="1CH 2:6">1 Chron. 2:6</ref></char>; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Zabdi</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verses 17 and 18.</char></note> the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, took some of them. So the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger burned against Israel.<verse eid="JOS 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 7:2"/>Now Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai, which is near Beth Aven to the east of Bethel, and told them, ‘Go up and spy out the region.’ So the men went up and spied out Ai.<verse eid="JOS 7:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 7:3"/>When they returned to Joshua, they said, ‘Not all the army will have to go up against Ai. Send two or three thousand men to take it and do not weary the whole army, for only a few people live there.’ <verse eid="JOS 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 7:4"/>So about three thousand went up; but they were routed by the men of Ai, <verse eid="JOS 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 7:5"/>who killed about thirty-six of them. They chased the Israelites from the city gate as far as the stone quarries and struck them down on the slopes. At this the hearts of the people melted in fear and became like water.<verse eid="JOS 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 7:6"/>Then Joshua tore his clothes and fell face down to the ground before the ark of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, remaining there till evening. The elders of Israel did the same, and sprinkled dust on their heads. <verse eid="JOS 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 7:7"/>And Joshua said, ‘Alas, Sovereign <char style="sc">Lord</char>, why did you ever bring this people across the Jordan to deliver us into the hands of the Amorites to destroy us? If only we had been content to stay on the other side of the Jordan! <verse eid="JOS 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 7:8"/>Pardon your servant, Lord. What can I say, now that Israel has been routed by its enemies? <verse eid="JOS 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 7:9"/>The Canaanites and the other people of the country will hear about this and they will surround us and wipe out our name from the earth. What then will you do for your own great name?’<verse eid="JOS 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 7:10"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Stand up! What are you doing down on your face? <verse eid="JOS 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 7:11"/>Israel has sinned; they have violated my covenant, which I commanded them to keep. They have taken some of the devoted things; they have stolen, they have lied, they have put them with their own possessions. <verse eid="JOS 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 7:12"/>That is why the Israelites cannot stand against their enemies; they turn their backs and run because they have been made liable to destruction. I will not be with you anymore unless you destroy whatever among you is devoted to destruction.<verse eid="JOS 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 7:13"/>‘Go, consecrate the people. Tell them, “Consecrate yourselves in preparation for tomorrow; for this is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says: there are devoted things among you, Israel. You cannot stand against your enemies until you remove them.<verse eid="JOS 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 7:14"/>‘ “In the morning, present yourselves tribe by tribe. The tribe that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> chooses shall come forward clan by clan; the clan that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> chooses shall come forward family by family; and the family that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> chooses shall come forward man by man. <verse eid="JOS 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 7:15"/>Whoever is caught with the devoted things shall be destroyed by fire, along with all that belongs to him. He has violated the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and has done an outrageous thing in Israel!” ’<verse eid="JOS 7:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 7:16"/>Early the next morning Joshua made Israel come forward by tribes, and Judah was chosen. <verse eid="JOS 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 7:17"/>The clans of Judah came forward, and the Zerahites were chosen. He made the clan of the Zerahites come forward by families, and Zimri was chosen. <verse eid="JOS 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 7:18"/>Joshua made his family come forward man by man, and Achan son of Karmi, the son of Zimri, the son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, was chosen.<verse eid="JOS 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 7:19"/>Then Joshua said to Achan, ‘My son, give glory to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, and honour him. Tell me what you have done; do not hide it from me.’<verse eid="JOS 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 7:20"/>Achan replied, ‘It is true! I have sinned against the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel. This is what I have done: <verse eid="JOS 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 7:21"/>when I saw in the plunder a beautiful robe from Babylonia,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shinar</char></note> two hundred shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 2.3 kilograms</char></note> of silver and a bar of gold weighing fifty shekels,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 575 grams</char></note> I coveted them and took them. They are hidden in the ground inside my tent, with the silver underneath.’<verse eid="JOS 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 7:22"/>So Joshua sent messengers, and they ran to the tent, and there it was, hidden in his tent, with the silver underneath. <verse eid="JOS 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 7:23"/>They took the things from the tent, brought them to Joshua and all the Israelites and spread them out before the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JOS 7:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 7:24"/>Then Joshua, together with all Israel, took Achan son of Zerah, the silver, the robe, the gold bar, his sons and daughters, his cattle, donkeys and sheep, his tent and all that he had, to the Valley of Achor. <verse eid="JOS 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 7:25"/>Joshua said, ‘Why have you brought this trouble on us? The <char style="sc">Lord</char> will bring trouble on you today.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 7:25">Then all Israel stoned him, and after they had stoned the rest, they burned them. <verse eid="JOS 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 7:26"/>Over Achan they heaped up a large pile of rocks, which remains to this day. Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> turned from his fierce anger. Therefore that place has been called the Valley of Achor<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:26 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Achor </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">trouble.</char></note> ever since.<verse eid="JOS 7:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JOS 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Ai destroyed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 8:1"/>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Do not be afraid; do not be discouraged. Take the whole army with you, and go up and attack Ai. For I have delivered into your hands the king of Ai, his people, his city and his land. <verse eid="JOS 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 8:2"/>You shall do to Ai and its king as you did to Jericho and its king, except that you may carry off their plunder and livestock for yourselves. Set an ambush behind the city.’<verse eid="JOS 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 8:3"/>So Joshua and the whole army moved out to attack Ai. He chose thirty thousand of his best fighting men and sent them out at night <verse eid="JOS 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 8:4"/>with these orders: ‘Listen carefully. You are to set an ambush behind the city. Don’t go very far from it. All of you be on the alert. <verse eid="JOS 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 8:5"/>I and all those with me will advance on the city, and when the men come out against us, as they did before, we will flee from them. <verse eid="JOS 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 8:6"/>They will pursue us until we have lured them away from the city, for they will say, “They are running away from us as they did before.” So when we flee from them, <verse eid="JOS 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 8:7"/>you are to rise up from ambush and take the city. The <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will give it into your hand. <verse eid="JOS 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 8:8"/>When you have taken the city, set it on fire. Do what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has commanded. See to it; you have my orders.’<verse eid="JOS 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 8:9"/>Then Joshua sent them off, and they went to the place of ambush and lay in wait between Bethel and Ai, to the west of Ai – but Joshua spent that night with the people.<verse eid="JOS 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 8:10"/>Early the next morning Joshua mustered his army, and he and the leaders of Israel marched before them to Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 8:11"/>The entire force that was with him marched up and approached the city and arrived in front of it. They set up camp north of Ai, with the valley between them and the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 8:12"/>Joshua had taken about five thousand men and set them in ambush between Bethel and Ai, to the west of the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 8:13"/>So the soldiers took up their positions – with the main camp to the north of the city and the ambush to the west of it. That night Joshua went into the valley.<verse eid="JOS 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 8:14"/>When the king of Ai saw this, he and all the men of the city hurried out early in the morning to meet Israel in battle at a certain place overlooking the Arabah. But he did not know that an ambush had been set against him behind the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 8:15"/>Joshua and all Israel let themselves be driven back before them, and they fled towards the wilderness. <verse eid="JOS 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 8:16"/>All the men of Ai were called to pursue them, and they pursued Joshua and were lured away from the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 8:17"/>Not a man remained in Ai or Bethel who did not go after Israel. They left the city open and went in pursuit of Israel.<verse eid="JOS 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 8:18"/>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Hold out towards Ai the javelin that is in your hand, for into your hand I will deliver the city.’ So Joshua held out towards the city the javelin that was in his hand. <verse eid="JOS 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 8:19"/>As soon as he did this, the men in the ambush rose quickly from their position and rushed forward. They entered the city and captured it and quickly set it on fire.<verse eid="JOS 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 8:20"/>The men of Ai looked back and saw the smoke of the city rising up into the sky, but they had no chance to escape in any direction; the Israelites who had been fleeing towards the wilderness had turned back against their pursuers. <verse eid="JOS 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 8:21"/>For when Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had taken the city and that smoke was going up from the city, they turned round and attacked the men of Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 8:22"/>Those in the ambush also came out of the city against them, so that they were caught in the middle, with Israelites on both sides. Israel cut them down, leaving them neither survivors nor fugitives. <verse eid="JOS 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 8:23"/>But they took the king of Ai alive and brought him to Joshua.<verse eid="JOS 8:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 8:24"/>When Israel had finished killing all the men of Ai in the fields and in the wilderness where they had chased them, and when every one of them had been put to the sword, all the Israelites returned to Ai and killed those who were in it. <verse eid="JOS 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 8:25"/>Twelve thousand men and women fell that day – all the people of Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 8:26"/>For Joshua did not draw back the hand that held out his javelin until he had destroyed<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them.</char></note> all who lived in Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 8:27"/>But Israel did carry off for themselves the livestock and plunder of this city, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had instructed Joshua.<verse eid="JOS 8:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 8:28"/>So Joshua burned Ai<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:28 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Ai </char><char style="ft" closed="false">means </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the ruin.</char></note> and made it a permanent heap of ruins, a desolate place to this day. <verse eid="JOS 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 8:29"/>He impaled the body of the king of Ai on a pole and left it there until evening. At sunset, Joshua ordered them to take the body from the pole and throw it down at the entrance of the city gate. And they raised a large pile of rocks over it, which remains to this day.<verse eid="JOS 8:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The covenant renewed at Mount Ebal</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 8:30"/>Then Joshua built on Mount Ebal an altar to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, <verse eid="JOS 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 8:31"/>as Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded the Israelites. He built it according to what is written in the Book of the Law of Moses – an altar of uncut stones, on which no iron tool had been used. On it they offered to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> burnt offerings and sacrificed fellowship offerings. <verse eid="JOS 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 8:32"/>There, in the presence of the Israelites, Joshua wrote on stones a copy of the law of Moses. <verse eid="JOS 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 8:33"/>All the Israelites, with their elders, officials and judges, were standing on both sides of the ark of the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, facing the Levitical priests who carried it. Both the foreigners living among them and the native-born were there. Half of the people stood in front of Mount Gerizim and half of them in front of Mount Ebal, as Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had formerly commanded when he gave instructions to bless the people of Israel.<verse eid="JOS 8:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 8:34"/>Afterwards, Joshua read all the words of the law – the blessings and the curses – just as it is written in the Book of the Law. <verse eid="JOS 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 8:35"/>There was not a word of all that Moses had commanded that Joshua did not read to the whole assembly of Israel, including the women and children, and the foreigners who lived among them.<verse eid="JOS 8:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JOS 9"/>
  <para style="s1">The Gibeonite deception</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 9:1"/>Now when all the kings west of the Jordan heard about these things – the kings in the hill country, in the western foothills, and along the entire coast of the Mediterranean Sea as far as Lebanon (the kings of the Hittites, Amorites, Canaanites, Perizzites, Hivites and Jebusites) – <verse eid="JOS 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 9:2"/>they came together to wage war against Joshua and Israel.<verse eid="JOS 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 9:3"/>However, when the people of Gibeon heard what Joshua had done to Jericho and Ai, <verse eid="JOS 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 9:4"/>they resorted to a ruse: they went as a delegation whose donkeys were loaded<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Most Hebrew manuscripts; some Hebrew manuscripts, Vulgate and Syriac (see also Septuagint) </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">They prepared provisions and loaded their donkeys</char></note> with worn-out sacks and old wineskins, cracked and mended. <verse eid="JOS 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 9:5"/>They put worn and patched sandals on their feet and wore old clothes. All the bread of their food supply was dry and mouldy. <verse eid="JOS 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 9:6"/>Then they went to Joshua in the camp at Gilgal and said to him and the Israelites, ‘We have come from a distant country; make a treaty with us.’<verse eid="JOS 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 9:7"/>The Israelites said to the Hivites, ‘But perhaps you live near us, so how can we make a treaty with you?’<verse eid="JOS 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 9:8"/>‘We are your servants,’ they said to Joshua.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 9:8">But Joshua asked, ‘Who are you and where do you come from?’<verse eid="JOS 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 9:9"/>They answered: ‘Your servants have come from a very distant country because of the fame of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. For we have heard reports of him: all that he did in Egypt, <verse eid="JOS 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 9:10"/>and all that he did to the two kings of the Amorites east of the Jordan – Sihon king of Heshbon, and Og king of Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth. <verse eid="JOS 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 9:11"/>And our elders and all those living in our country said to us, “Take provisions for your journey; go and meet them and say to them, ‘We are your servants; make a treaty with us.’ ” <verse eid="JOS 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 9:12"/>This bread of ours was warm when we packed it at home on the day we left to come to you. But now see how dry and mouldy it is. <verse eid="JOS 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 9:13"/>And these wineskins that we filled were new, but see how cracked they are. And our clothes and sandals are worn out by the very long journey.’<verse eid="JOS 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 9:14"/>The Israelites sampled their provisions but did not enquire of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="JOS 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 9:15"/>Then Joshua made a treaty of peace with them to let them live, and the leaders of the assembly ratified it by oath.<verse eid="JOS 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 9:16"/>Three days after they made the treaty with the Gibeonites, the Israelites heard that they were neighbours, living near them. <verse eid="JOS 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 9:17"/>So the Israelites set out and on the third day came to their cities: Gibeon, Kephirah, Beeroth and Kiriath Jearim. <verse eid="JOS 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 9:18"/>But the Israelites did not attack them, because the leaders of the assembly had sworn an oath to them by the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 9:18">The whole assembly grumbled against the leaders, <verse eid="JOS 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 9:19"/>but all the leaders answered, ‘We have given them our oath by the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, and we cannot touch them now. <verse eid="JOS 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 9:20"/>This is what we will do to them: we will let them live, so that God’s wrath will not fall on us for breaking the oath we swore to them.’ <verse eid="JOS 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 9:21"/>They continued, ‘Let them live, but let them be woodcutters and water-carriers in the service of the whole assembly.’ So the leaders’ promise to them was kept.<verse eid="JOS 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 9:22"/>Then Joshua summoned the Gibeonites and said, ‘Why did you deceive us by saying, “We live a long way from you,” while actually you live near us? <verse eid="JOS 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 9:23"/>You are now under a curse: you will never be released from service as woodcutters and water-carriers for the house of my God.’<verse eid="JOS 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 9:24"/>They answered Joshua, ‘Your servants were clearly told how the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God had commanded his servant Moses to give you the whole land and to wipe out all its inhabitants from before you. So we feared for our lives because of you, and that is why we did this. <verse eid="JOS 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 9:25"/>We are now in your hands. Do to us whatever seems good and right to you.’<verse eid="JOS 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 9:26"/>So Joshua saved them from the Israelites, and they did not kill them. <verse eid="JOS 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 9:27"/>That day he made the Gibeonites woodcutters and water-carriers for the assembly, to provide for the needs of the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at the place the <char style="sc">Lord</char> would choose. And that is what they are to this day.<verse eid="JOS 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JOS 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The sun stands still</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 10:1"/>Now Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem heard that Joshua had taken Ai and totally destroyed<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them; also in verses 28, 35, 37, 39 and 40.</char></note> it, doing to Ai and its king as he had done to Jericho and its king, and that the people of Gibeon had made a treaty of peace with Israel and had become their allies. <verse eid="JOS 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 10:2"/>He and his people were very much alarmed at this, because Gibeon was an important city, like one of the royal cities; it was larger than Ai, and all its men were good fighters. <verse eid="JOS 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 10:3"/>So Adoni-Zedek king of Jerusalem appealed to Hoham king of Hebron, Piram king of Jarmuth, Japhia king of Lachish and Debir king of Eglon. <verse eid="JOS 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 10:4"/>‘Come up and help me attack Gibeon,’ he said, ‘because it has made peace with Joshua and the Israelites.’<verse eid="JOS 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 10:5"/>Then the five kings of the Amorites – the kings of Jerusalem, Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish and Eglon – joined forces. They moved up with all their troops and took up positions against Gibeon and attacked it.<verse eid="JOS 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 10:6"/>The Gibeonites then sent word to Joshua in the camp at Gilgal: ‘Do not abandon your servants. Come up to us quickly and save us! Help us, because all the Amorite kings from the hill country have joined forces against us.’<verse eid="JOS 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 10:7"/>So Joshua marched up from Gilgal with his entire army, including all the best fighting men. <verse eid="JOS 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 10:8"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Do not be afraid of them; I have given them into your hand. Not one of them will be able to withstand you.’<verse eid="JOS 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 10:9"/>After an all-night march from Gilgal, Joshua took them by surprise. <verse eid="JOS 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 10:10"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> threw them into confusion before Israel, so Joshua and the Israelites defeated them completely at Gibeon. Israel pursued them along the road going up to Beth Horon and cut them down all the way to Azekah and Makkedah. <verse eid="JOS 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 10:11"/>As they fled before Israel on the road down from Beth Horon to Azekah, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> hurled large hailstones down on them, and more of them died from the hail than were killed by the swords of the Israelites.<verse eid="JOS 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 10:12"/>On the day the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave the Amorites over to Israel, Joshua said to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in the presence of Israel:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JOS 10:12">‘Sun, stand still over Gibeon,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 10:12">and you, moon, over the Valley of Aijalon.’<verse eid="JOS 10:12"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 10:13"/>So the sun stood still,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 10:13">and the moon stopped,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JOS 10:13">till the nation avenged itself on<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">nation triumphed over</char></note> its enemies,</para>
  <para style="m" vid="JOS 10:13">as it is written in the Book of Jashar.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 10:13">The sun stopped in the middle of the sky and delayed going down about a full day. <verse eid="JOS 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 10:14"/>There has never been a day like it before or since, a day when the <char style="sc">Lord</char> listened to a human being. Surely the <char style="sc">Lord</char> was fighting for Israel!<verse eid="JOS 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 10:15"/>Then Joshua returned with all Israel to the camp at Gilgal.<verse eid="JOS 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Five Amorite kings killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 10:16"/>Now the five kings had fled and hidden in the cave at Makkedah. <verse eid="JOS 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 10:17"/>When Joshua was told that the five kings had been found hiding in the cave at Makkedah, <verse eid="JOS 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 10:18"/>he said, ‘Roll large rocks up to the mouth of the cave, and post some men there to guard it. <verse eid="JOS 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 10:19"/>But don’t stop; pursue your enemies! Attack them from the rear and don’t let them reach their cities, for the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has given them into your hand.’<verse eid="JOS 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 10:20"/>So Joshua and the Israelites defeated them completely, but a few survivors managed to reach their fortified cities. <verse eid="JOS 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 10:21"/>The whole army then returned safely to Joshua in the camp at Makkedah, and no-one uttered a word against the Israelites.<verse eid="JOS 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 10:22"/>Joshua said, ‘Open the mouth of the cave and bring those five kings out to me.’ <verse eid="JOS 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 10:23"/>So they brought the five kings out of the cave – the kings of Jerusalem, Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish and Eglon. <verse eid="JOS 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 10:24"/>When they had brought these kings to Joshua, he summoned all the men of Israel and said to the army commanders who had come with him, ‘Come here and put your feet on the necks of these kings.’ So they came forward and placed their feet on their necks.<verse eid="JOS 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 10:25"/>Joshua said to them, ‘Do not be afraid; do not be discouraged. Be strong and courageous. This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> will do to all the enemies you are going to fight.’ <verse eid="JOS 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 10:26"/>Then Joshua put the kings to death and exposed their bodies on five poles, and they were left hanging on the poles until evening.<verse eid="JOS 10:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 10:27"/>At sunset Joshua gave the order and they took them down from the poles and threw them into the cave where they had been hiding. At the mouth of the cave they placed large rocks, which are there to this day.<verse eid="JOS 10:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Southern cities conquered</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 10:28"/>That day Joshua took Makkedah. He put the city and its king to the sword and totally destroyed everyone in it. He left no survivors. And he did to the king of Makkedah as he had done to the king of Jericho.<verse eid="JOS 10:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 10:29"/>Then Joshua and all Israel with him moved on from Makkedah to Libnah and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 10:30"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> also gave that city and its king into Israel’s hand. The city and everyone in it Joshua put to the sword. He left no survivors there. And he did to its king as he had done to the king of Jericho.<verse eid="JOS 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 10:31"/>Then Joshua and all Israel with him moved on from Libnah to Lachish; he took up positions against it and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 10:32"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave Lachish into Israel’s hands, and Joshua took it on the second day. The city and everyone in it he put to the sword, just as he had done to Libnah. <verse eid="JOS 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 10:33"/>Meanwhile, Horam king of Gezer had come up to help Lachish, but Joshua defeated him and his army – until no survivors were left.<verse eid="JOS 10:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 10:34"/>Then Joshua and all Israel with him moved on from Lachish to Eglon; they took up positions against it and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 10:35"/>They captured it that same day and put it to the sword and totally destroyed everyone in it, just as they had done to Lachish.<verse eid="JOS 10:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 10:36"/>Then Joshua and all Israel with him went up from Eglon to Hebron and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 10:37"/>They took the city and put it to the sword, together with its king, its villages and everyone in it. They left no survivors. Just as at Eglon, they totally destroyed it and everyone in it.<verse eid="JOS 10:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 10:38"/>Then Joshua and all Israel with him turned round and attacked Debir. <verse eid="JOS 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 10:39"/>They took the city, its king and its villages, and put them to the sword. Everyone in it they totally destroyed. They left no survivors. They did to Debir and its king as they had done to Libnah and its king and to Hebron.<verse eid="JOS 10:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 10:40"/>So Joshua subdued the whole region, including the hill country, the Negev, the western foothills and the mountain slopes, together with all their kings. He left no survivors. He totally destroyed all who breathed, just as the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, had commanded. <verse eid="JOS 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 10:41"/>Joshua subdued them from Kadesh Barnea to Gaza and from the whole region of Goshen to Gibeon. <verse eid="JOS 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 10:42"/>All these kings and their lands Joshua conquered in one campaign, because the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, fought for Israel.<verse eid="JOS 10:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 10:43"/>Then Joshua returned with all Israel to the camp at Gilgal.<verse eid="JOS 10:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JOS 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Northern kings defeated</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 11:1"/>When Jabin king of Hazor heard of this, he sent word to Jobab king of Madon, to the kings of Shimron and Akshaph, <verse eid="JOS 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 11:2"/>and to the northern kings who were in the mountains, in the Arabah south of Kinnereth, in the western foothills and in Naphoth Dor on the west; <verse eid="JOS 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 11:3"/>to the Canaanites in the east and west; to the Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites and Jebusites in the hill country; and to the Hivites below Hermon in the region of Mizpah. <verse eid="JOS 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 11:4"/>They came out with all their troops and a large number of horses and chariots – a huge army, as numerous as the sand on the seashore. <verse eid="JOS 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 11:5"/>All these kings joined forces and made camp together at the Waters of Merom to fight against Israel.<verse eid="JOS 11:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 11:6"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua, ‘Do not be afraid of them, because by this time tomorrow I will hand all of them, slain, over to Israel. You are to hamstring their horses and burn their chariots.’<verse eid="JOS 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 11:7"/>So Joshua and his whole army came against them suddenly at the Waters of Merom and attacked them, <verse eid="JOS 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 11:8"/>and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave them into the hand of Israel. They defeated them and pursued them all the way to Greater Sidon, to Misrephoth Maim, and to the Valley of Mizpah on the east, until no survivors were left. <verse eid="JOS 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 11:9"/>Joshua did to them as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had directed: he hamstrung their horses and burned their chariots.<verse eid="JOS 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 11:10"/>At that time Joshua turned back and captured Hazor and put its king to the sword. (Hazor had been the head of all these kingdoms.) <verse eid="JOS 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 11:11"/>Everyone in it they put to the sword. They totally destroyed<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them; also in verses 12, 20 and 21.</char></note> them, not sparing anyone that breathed, and he burned Hazor itself.<verse eid="JOS 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 11:12"/>Joshua took all these royal cities and their kings and put them to the sword. He totally destroyed them, as Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded. <verse eid="JOS 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 11:13"/>Yet Israel did not burn any of the cities built on their mounds – except Hazor, which Joshua burned. <verse eid="JOS 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 11:14"/>The Israelites carried off for themselves all the plunder and livestock of these cities, but all the people they put to the sword until they completely destroyed them, not sparing anyone that breathed. <verse eid="JOS 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 11:15"/>As the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded his servant Moses, so Moses commanded Joshua, and Joshua did it; he left nothing undone of all that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded Moses.<verse eid="JOS 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 11:16"/>So Joshua took this entire land: the hill country, all the Negev, the whole region of Goshen, the western foothills, the Arabah and the mountains of Israel with their foothills, <verse eid="JOS 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 11:17"/>from Mount Halak, which rises towards Seir, to Baal Gad in the Valley of Lebanon below Mount Hermon. He captured all their kings and put them to death. <verse eid="JOS 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 11:18"/>Joshua waged war against all these kings for a long time. <verse eid="JOS 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 11:19"/>Except for the Hivites living in Gibeon, not one city made a treaty of peace with the Israelites, who took them all in battle. <verse eid="JOS 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 11:20"/>For it was the <char style="sc">Lord</char> himself who hardened their hearts to wage war against Israel, so that he might destroy them totally, exterminating them without mercy, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="JOS 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 11:21"/>At that time Joshua went and destroyed the Anakites from the hill country: from Hebron, Debir and Anab, from all the hill country of Judah, and from all the hill country of Israel. Joshua totally destroyed them and their towns. <verse eid="JOS 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 11:22"/>No Anakites were left in Israelite territory; only in Gaza, Gath and Ashdod did any survive.<verse eid="JOS 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 11:23"/>So Joshua took the entire land, just as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had directed Moses, and he gave it as an inheritance to Israel according to their tribal divisions. Then the land had rest from war.<verse eid="JOS 11:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JOS 12"/>
  <para style="s1">List of defeated kings</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 12:1"/>These are the kings of the land whom the Israelites had defeated and whose territory they took over east of the Jordan, from the Arnon Gorge to Mount Hermon, including all the eastern side of the Arabah:<verse eid="JOS 12:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 12:2"/>Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 12:2">He ruled from Aroer on the rim of the Arnon Gorge – from the middle of the gorge – to the River Jabbok, which is the border of the Ammonites. This included half of Gilead.<verse eid="JOS 12:2"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 12:3"/>He also ruled over the eastern Arabah from the Sea of Galilee<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:3 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Kinnereth</char></note> to the Sea of the Arabah (that is, the Dead Sea), to Beth Jeshimoth, and then southward below the slopes of Pisgah.<verse eid="JOS 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 12:4"/>And the territory of Og king of Bashan, one of the last of the Rephaites, who reigned in Ashtaroth and Edrei.<verse eid="JOS 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 12:5"/>He ruled over Mount Hermon, Salekah, all of Bashan to the border of the people of Geshur and Maakah, and half of Gilead to the border of Sihon king of Heshbon.<verse eid="JOS 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 12:6"/>Moses, the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and the Israelites conquered them. And Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave their land to the Reubenites, the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh to be their possession.<verse eid="JOS 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 12:7"/>Here is a list of the kings of the land that Joshua and the Israelites conquered on the west side of the Jordan, from Baal Gad in the Valley of Lebanon to Mount Halak, which rises towards Seir. Joshua gave their lands as an inheritance to the tribes of Israel according to their tribal divisions. <verse eid="JOS 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 12:8"/>The lands included the hill country, the western foothills, the Arabah, the mountain slopes, the wilderness and the Negev. These were the lands of the Hittites, Amorites, Canaanites, Perizzites, Hivites and Jebusites.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 12:8"/>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 12:8">These were the kings:<verse eid="JOS 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 12:9"/>the king of Jericho </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Ai (near Bethel) </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:9"/>
        <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 12:10"/>the king of Jerusalem </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Hebron </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:10"/>
        <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 12:11"/>the king of Jarmuth </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Lachish </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:11"/>
        <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 12:12"/>the king of Eglon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Gezer </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:12"/>
        <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 12:13"/>the king of Debir </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Geder </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:13"/>
        <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 12:14"/>the king of Hormah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Arad </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:14"/>
        <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 12:15"/>the king of Libnah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Adullam </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:15"/>
        <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 12:16"/>the king of Makkedah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Bethel </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:16"/>
        <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 12:17"/>the king of Tappuah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Hepher </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:17"/>
        <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 12:18"/>the king of Aphek </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Lasharon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:18"/>
        <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 12:19"/>the king of Madon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Hazor </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:19"/>
        <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 12:20"/>the king of Shimron Meron </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Akshaph </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:20"/>
        <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 12:21"/>the king of Taanach </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Megiddo </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:21"/>
        <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 12:22"/>the king of Kedesh </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Jokneam in Carmel </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:22"/>
        <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 12:23"/>the king of Dor (in Naphoth Dor) </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the king of Goyim in Gilgal </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="JOS 12:23"/>
        <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 12:24"/>the king of Tirzah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">one</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 12:24"/>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start"/>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">thirty-one kings in all.</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <chapter eid="JOS 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JOS 13"/>
  <para style="s1" vid="JOS 12:24">Land still to be taken<verse eid="JOS 12:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 13:1"/>When Joshua had grown old, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to him, ‘You are now very old, and there are still very large areas of land to be taken over.<verse eid="JOS 13:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 13:2"/>‘This is the land that remains:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 13:2"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:2">‘all the regions of the Philistines and Geshurites, <verse eid="JOS 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 13:3"/>from the River Shihor on the east of Egypt to the territory of Ekron on the north, all of it counted as Canaanite though held by the five Philistine rulers in Gaza, Ashdod, Ashkelon, Gath and Ekron;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:3">the territory of the Avvites <verse eid="JOS 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 13:4"/>on the south;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:4">all the land of the Canaanites, from Arah of the Sidonians as far as Aphek and the border of the Amorites;<verse eid="JOS 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 13:5"/>the area of Byblos;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 13:5">and all Lebanon to the east, from Baal Gad below Mount Hermon to Lebo Hamath.<verse eid="JOS 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 13:6"/>‘As for all the inhabitants of the mountain regions from Lebanon to Misrephoth Maim, that is, all the Sidonians, I myself will drive them out before the Israelites. Be sure to allocate this land to Israel for an inheritance, as I have instructed you, <verse eid="JOS 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 13:7"/>and divide it as an inheritance among the nine tribes and half of the tribe of Manasseh.’<verse eid="JOS 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Division of the land east of the Jordan</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 13:8"/>The other half of Manasseh,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">With it </char><char style="ft" closed="false">(that is, with the other half of Manasseh)</char></note> the Reubenites and the Gadites had received the inheritance that Moses had given them east of the Jordan, as he, the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, had assigned it to them.<verse eid="JOS 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 13:9"/>It extended from Aroer on the rim of the Arnon Gorge, and from the town in the middle of the gorge, and included the whole plateau of Medeba as far as Dibon, <verse eid="JOS 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 13:10"/>and all the towns of Sihon king of the Amorites, who ruled in Heshbon, out to the border of the Ammonites.<verse eid="JOS 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 13:11"/>It also included Gilead, the territory of the people of Geshur and Maakah, all of Mount Hermon and all Bashan as far as Salekah – <verse eid="JOS 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 13:12"/>that is, the whole kingdom of Og in Bashan, who had reigned in Ashtaroth and Edrei. (He was the last of the Rephaites.) Moses had defeated them and taken over their land. <verse eid="JOS 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 13:13"/>But the Israelites did not drive out the people of Geshur and Maakah, so they continue to live among the Israelites to this day.<verse eid="JOS 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 13:14"/>But to the tribe of Levi he gave no inheritance, since the food offerings presented to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, are their inheritance, as he promised them.<verse eid="JOS 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 13:15"/>This is what Moses had given to the tribe of Reuben, according to its clans:<verse eid="JOS 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 13:16"/>The territory from Aroer on the rim of the Arnon Gorge, and from the town in the middle of the gorge, and the whole plateau past Medeba <verse eid="JOS 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 13:17"/>to Heshbon and all its towns on the plateau, including Dibon, Bamoth Baal, Beth Baal Meon, <verse eid="JOS 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 13:18"/>Jahaz, Kedemoth, Mephaath, <verse eid="JOS 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 13:19"/>Kiriathaim, Sibmah, Zereth Shahar on the hill in the valley, <verse eid="JOS 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 13:20"/>Beth Peor, the slopes of Pisgah, and Beth Jeshimoth – <verse eid="JOS 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 13:21"/>all the towns on the plateau and the entire realm of Sihon king of the Amorites, who ruled at Heshbon. Moses had defeated him and the Midianite chiefs, Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur and Reba – princes allied with Sihon – who lived in that country. <verse eid="JOS 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 13:22"/>In addition to those slain in battle, the Israelites had put to the sword Balaam son of Beor, who practised divination.<verse eid="JOS 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 13:23"/>The boundary of the Reubenites was the bank of the Jordan. These towns and their villages were the inheritance of the Reubenites, according to their clans.<verse eid="JOS 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 13:24"/>This is what Moses had given to the tribe of Gad, according to its clans:<verse eid="JOS 13:24"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 13:25"/>The territory of Jazer, all the towns of Gilead and half the Ammonite country as far as Aroer, near Rabbah; <verse eid="JOS 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 13:26"/>and from Heshbon to Ramath Mizpah and Betonim, and from Mahanaim to the territory of Debir; <verse eid="JOS 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 13:27"/>and in the valley, Beth Haram, Beth Nimrah, Sukkoth and Zaphon with the rest of the realm of Sihon king of Heshbon (the east side of the Jordan, the territory up to the end of the Sea of Galilee<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Kinnereth</char></note>).<verse eid="JOS 13:27"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 13:28"/>These towns and their villages were the inheritance of the Gadites, according to their clans.<verse eid="JOS 13:28"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 13:29"/>This is what Moses had given to the half-tribe of Manasseh, that is, to half the family of the descendants of Manasseh, according to its clans:<verse eid="JOS 13:29"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 13:30"/>The territory extending from Mahanaim and including all of Bashan, the entire realm of Og king of Bashan – all the settlements of Jair in Bashan, sixty towns, <verse eid="JOS 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 13:31"/>half of Gilead, and Ashtaroth and Edrei (the royal cities of Og in Bashan).</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 13:31">This was for the descendants of Makir son of Manasseh – for half of the sons of Makir, according to their clans.<verse eid="JOS 13:31"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 13:32"/>This is the inheritance Moses had given when he was in the plains of Moab across the Jordan east of Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 13:33"/>But to the tribe of Levi, Moses had given no inheritance; the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, is their inheritance, as he promised them.<verse eid="JOS 13:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JOS 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Division of the land west of the Jordan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 14:1"/>Now these are the areas the Israelites received as an inheritance in the land of Canaan, which Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun and the heads of the tribal clans of Israel allotted to them. <verse eid="JOS 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 14:2"/>Their inheritances were assigned by lot to the nine-and-a-half tribes, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded through Moses. <verse eid="JOS 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 14:3"/>Moses had granted the two-and-a-half tribes their inheritance east of the Jordan but had not granted the Levites an inheritance among the rest, <verse eid="JOS 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 14:4"/>for Joseph’s descendants had become two tribes – Manasseh and Ephraim. The Levites received no share of the land but only towns to live in, with pasture-lands for their flocks and herds. <verse eid="JOS 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 14:5"/>So the Israelites divided the land, just as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded Moses.<verse eid="JOS 14:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Caleb</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 14:6"/>Now the people of Judah approached Joshua at Gilgal, and Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite said to him, ‘You know what the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Moses the man of God at Kadesh Barnea about you and me. <verse eid="JOS 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 14:7"/>I was forty years old when Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> sent me from Kadesh Barnea to explore the land. And I brought him back a report according to my convictions, <verse eid="JOS 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 14:8"/>but my fellow Israelites who went up with me made the hearts of the people sink. I, however, followed the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God wholeheartedly. <verse eid="JOS 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 14:9"/>So on that day Moses swore to me, “The land on which your feet have walked will be your inheritance and that of your children for ever, because you have followed the <char style="sc">Lord</char> my God wholeheartedly.”<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 1:36">Deut. 1:36</ref></char></char></note><verse eid="JOS 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 14:10"/>‘Now then, just as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> promised, he has kept me alive for forty-five years since the time he said this to Moses, while Israel moved about in the wilderness. So here I am today, eighty-five years old! <verse eid="JOS 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 14:11"/>I am still as strong today as the day Moses sent me out; I’m just as vigorous to go out to battle now as I was then. <verse eid="JOS 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 14:12"/>Now give me this hill country that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> promised me that day. You yourself heard then that the Anakites were there and their cities were large and fortified, but, the <char style="sc">Lord</char> helping me, I will drive them out just as he said.’<verse eid="JOS 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 14:13"/>Then Joshua blessed Caleb son of Jephunneh and gave him Hebron as his inheritance. <verse eid="JOS 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 14:14"/>So Hebron has belonged to Caleb son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite ever since, because he followed the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, wholeheartedly. <verse eid="JOS 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 14:15"/>(Hebron used to be called Kiriath Arba after Arba, who was the greatest man among the Anakites.)</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 14:15">Then the land had rest from war.<verse eid="JOS 14:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JOS 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Judah</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 15:1"/>The land allotted to the tribe of Judah, according to its clans, extended down to the territory of Edom, to the Desert of Zin in the extreme south.<verse eid="JOS 15:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 15:2"/>Their southern boundary started from the bay at the southern end of the Dead Sea, <verse eid="JOS 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 15:3"/>crossed south of Scorpion Pass, continued on to Zin and went over to the south of Kadesh Barnea. Then it ran past Hezron up to Addar and curved around to Karka. <verse eid="JOS 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 15:4"/>It then passed along to Azmon and joined the Wadi of Egypt, ending at the Mediterranean Sea. This is their<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Septuagint; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">your</char></note> southern boundary.<verse eid="JOS 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 15:5"/>The eastern boundary is the Dead Sea as far as the mouth of the Jordan.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 15:5">The northern boundary started from the bay of the sea at the mouth of the Jordan, <verse eid="JOS 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 15:6"/>went up to Beth Hoglah and continued north of Beth Arabah to the Stone of Bohan son of Reuben. <verse eid="JOS 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 15:7"/>The boundary then went up to Debir from the Valley of Achor and turned north to Gilgal, which faces the Pass of Adummim south of the gorge. It continued along to the waters of En Shemesh and came out at En Rogel. <verse eid="JOS 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 15:8"/>Then it ran up the Valley of Ben Hinnom along the southern slope of the Jebusite city (that is, Jerusalem). From there it climbed to the top of the hill west of the Hinnom Valley at the northern end of the Valley of Rephaim. <verse eid="JOS 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 15:9"/>From the hilltop the boundary headed towards the spring of the waters of Nephtoah, came out at the towns of Mount Ephron and went down towards Baalah (that is, Kiriath Jearim). <verse eid="JOS 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 15:10"/>Then it curved westward from Baalah to Mount Seir, ran along the northern slope of Mount Jearim (that is, Kesalon), continued down to Beth Shemesh and crossed to Timnah. <verse eid="JOS 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 15:11"/>It went to the northern slope of Ekron, turned towards Shikkeron, passed along to Mount Baalah and reached Jabneel. The boundary ended at the sea.<verse eid="JOS 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 15:12"/>The western boundary is the coastline of the Mediterranean Sea.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 15:12"/>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 15:12">These are the boundaries around the people of Judah by their clans.<verse eid="JOS 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 15:13"/>In accordance with the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s command to him, Joshua gave to Caleb son of Jephunneh a portion in Judah – Kiriath Arba, that is, Hebron. (Arba was the forefather of Anak.) <verse eid="JOS 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 15:14"/>From Hebron Caleb drove out the three Anakites – Sheshai, Ahiman and Talmai, the sons of Anak. <verse eid="JOS 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 15:15"/>From there he marched against the people living in Debir (formerly called Kiriath Sepher). <verse eid="JOS 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 15:16"/>And Caleb said, ‘I will give my daughter Aksah in marriage to the man who attacks and captures Kiriath Sepher.’ <verse eid="JOS 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 15:17"/>Othniel son of Kenaz, Caleb’s brother, took it; so Caleb gave his daughter Aksah to him in marriage.<verse eid="JOS 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 15:18"/>One day when she came to Othniel, she urged him<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew and some Septuagint manuscripts; other Septuagint manuscripts (see also note at <char style="xt"><ref loc="JDG 1:14">Judges 1:14</ref></char>) </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Othniel, he urged her</char></note> to ask her father for a field. When she got off her donkey, Caleb asked her, ‘What can I do for you?’<verse eid="JOS 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 15:19"/>She replied, ‘Do me a special favour. Since you have given me land in the Negev, give me also springs of water.’ So Caleb gave her the upper and lower springs.<verse eid="JOS 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 15:20"/>This is the inheritance of the tribe of Judah, according to its clans:<verse eid="JOS 15:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 15:21"/>The southernmost towns of the tribe of Judah in the Negev towards the boundary of Edom were:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:21">Kabzeel, Eder, Jagur, <verse eid="JOS 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 15:22"/>Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah, <verse eid="JOS 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 15:23"/>Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan, <verse eid="JOS 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 15:24"/>Ziph, Telem, Bealoth, <verse eid="JOS 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 15:25"/>Hazor Hadattah, Kerioth Hezron (that is, Hazor), <verse eid="JOS 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 15:26"/>Amam, Shema, Moladah, <verse eid="JOS 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 15:27"/>Hazar Gaddah, Heshmon, Beth Pelet, <verse eid="JOS 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 15:28"/>Hazar Shual, Beersheba, Biziothiah, <verse eid="JOS 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 15:29"/>Baalah, Iyim, Ezem, <verse eid="JOS 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 15:30"/>Eltolad, Kesil, Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 15:31"/>Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah, <verse eid="JOS 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 15:32"/>Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain and Rimmon – a total of twenty-nine towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:32"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 15:33"/>In the western foothills:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:33">Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah, <verse eid="JOS 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 15:34"/>Zanoah, En Gannim, Tappuah, Enam, <verse eid="JOS 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 15:35"/>Jarmuth, Adullam, Sokoh, Azekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 15:36"/>Shaaraim, Adithaim and Gederah (or Gederothaim)<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gederah and Gederothaim</char></note> – fourteen towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:36"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 15:37"/>Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal Gad, <verse eid="JOS 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 15:38"/>Dilean, Mizpah, Joktheel, <verse eid="JOS 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 15:39"/>Lachish, Bozkath, Eglon, <verse eid="JOS 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 15:40"/>Kabbon, Lahmas, Kitlish, <verse eid="JOS 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 15:41"/>Gederoth, Beth Dagon, Naamah and Makkedah – sixteen towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:41"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 15:42"/>Libnah, Ether, Ashan, <verse eid="JOS 15:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 15:43"/>Iphtah, Ashnah, Nezib, <verse eid="JOS 15:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 15:44"/>Keilah, Akzib and Mareshah – nine towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:44"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 15:45"/>Ekron, with its surrounding settlements and villages; <verse eid="JOS 15:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JOS 15:46"/>west of Ekron, all that were in the vicinity of Ashdod, together with their villages; <verse eid="JOS 15:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JOS 15:47"/>Ashdod, its surrounding settlements and villages; and Gaza, its settlements and villages, as far as the Wadi of Egypt and the coastline of the Mediterranean Sea.<verse eid="JOS 15:47"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 15:48"/>In the hill country:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:48">Shamir, Jattir, Sokoh, <verse eid="JOS 15:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 15:49"/>Dannah, Kiriath Sannah (that is, Debir), <verse eid="JOS 15:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 15:50"/>Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim, <verse eid="JOS 15:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 15:51"/>Goshen, Holon and Giloh – eleven towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:51"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JOS 15:52"/>Arab, Dumah, Eshan, <verse eid="JOS 15:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JOS 15:53"/>Janim, Beth Tappuah, Aphekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JOS 15:54"/>Humtah, Kiriath Arba (that is, Hebron) and Zior – nine towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:54"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="JOS 15:55"/>Maon, Carmel, Ziph, Juttah, <verse eid="JOS 15:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JOS 15:56"/>Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah, <verse eid="JOS 15:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JOS 15:57"/>Kain, Gibeah and Timnah – ten towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:57"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="JOS 15:58"/>Halhul, Beth Zur, Gedor, <verse eid="JOS 15:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JOS 15:59"/>Maarath, Beth Anoth and Eltekon – six towns and their villages.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">15:59 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Septuagint adds another district of eleven towns, including Tekoa and Ephrathah (Bethlehem).</char></note><verse eid="JOS 15:59"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="JOS 15:60"/>Kiriath Baal (that is, Kiriath Jearim) and Rabbah – two towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:60"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="61" style="v" sid="JOS 15:61"/>In the wilderness:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 15:61">Beth Arabah, Middin, Sekakah, <verse eid="JOS 15:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="JOS 15:62"/>Nibshan, the City of Salt and En Gedi – six towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:62"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" sid="JOS 15:63"/>Judah could not dislodge the Jebusites, who were living in Jerusalem; to this day the Jebusites live there with the people of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 15:63"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JOS 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Ephraim and Manasseh</para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 16:1"/>The land allotted to Joseph began at the Jordan, east of the springs of Jericho, and went up from there through the desert into the hill country of Bethel. <verse eid="JOS 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 16:2"/>It went on from Bethel (that is, Luz),<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Septuagint; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bethel to Luz</char></note> crossed over to the territory of the Arkites in Ataroth, <verse eid="JOS 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 16:3"/>descended westward to the territory of the Japhletites as far as the region of Lower Beth Horon and on to Gezer, ending at the Mediterranean Sea.<verse eid="JOS 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 16:4"/>So Manasseh and Ephraim, the descendants of Joseph, received their inheritance.<verse eid="JOS 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 16:5"/>This was the territory of Ephraim, according to its clans:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JOS 16:5"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 16:5">The boundary of their inheritance went from Ataroth Addar in the east to Upper Beth Horon <verse eid="JOS 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 16:6"/>and continued to the Mediterranean Sea. From Mikmethath on the north it curved eastward to Taanath Shiloh, passing by it to Janoah on the east. <verse eid="JOS 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 16:7"/>Then it went down from Janoah to Ataroth and Naarah, touched Jericho and came out at the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 16:8"/>From Tappuah the border went west to the Kanah Ravine and ended at the Mediterranean Sea. This was the inheritance of the tribe of the Ephraimites, according to its clans.<verse eid="JOS 16:8"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 16:9"/>It also included all the towns and their villages that were set aside for the Ephraimites within the inheritance of the Manassites.<verse eid="JOS 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 16:10"/>They did not dislodge the Canaanites living in Gezer; to this day the Canaanites live among the people of Ephraim but are required to do forced labour.<verse eid="JOS 16:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JOS 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 17:1"/>This was the land allotted to the tribe of Manasseh as Joseph’s firstborn. Makir, Manasseh’s firstborn, the ancestor of the Gileadites, had received Gilead and Bashan because the Makirites were great soldiers. <verse eid="JOS 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 17:2"/>So this land was allotted to the rest of the people of Manasseh – the clans of Abiezer, Helek, Asriel, Shechem, Hepher and Shemida. These are the other male descendants of Manasseh son of Joseph by their clans.<verse eid="JOS 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 17:3"/>Now Zelophehad son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Makir, the son of Manasseh, had no sons but only daughters, whose names were Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milkah and Tirzah. <verse eid="JOS 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 17:4"/>They went to Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the leaders and said, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded Moses to give us an inheritance among our relatives.’ So Joshua gave them an inheritance along with the brothers of their father, according to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s command. <verse eid="JOS 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 17:5"/>Manasseh’s share consisted of ten tracts of land besides Gilead and Bashan east of the Jordan, <verse eid="JOS 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 17:6"/>because the daughters of the tribe of Manasseh received an inheritance among the sons. The land of Gilead belonged to the rest of the descendants of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 17:7"/>The territory of Manasseh extended from Asher to Mikmethath east of Shechem. The boundary ran southward from there to include the people living at En Tappuah. <verse eid="JOS 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 17:8"/>(Manasseh had the land of Tappuah, but Tappuah itself, on the boundary of Manasseh, belonged to the Ephraimites.) <verse eid="JOS 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 17:9"/>Then the boundary continued south to the Kanah Ravine. There were towns belonging to Ephraim lying among the towns of Manasseh, but the boundary of Manasseh was the northern side of the ravine and ended at the Mediterranean Sea. <verse eid="JOS 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 17:10"/>On the south the land belonged to Ephraim, on the north to Manasseh. The territory of Manasseh reached the Mediterranean Sea and bordered Asher on the north and Issachar on the east.<verse eid="JOS 17:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 17:11"/>Within Issachar and Asher, Manasseh also had Beth Shan, Ibleam and the people of Dor, Endor, Taanach and Megiddo, together with their surrounding settlements (the third in the list is Naphoth<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, Naphoth Dor</char></note>).<verse eid="JOS 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 17:12"/>Yet the Manassites were not able to occupy these towns, for the Canaanites were determined to live in that region. <verse eid="JOS 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 17:13"/>However, when the Israelites grew stronger, they subjected the Canaanites to forced labour but did not drive them out completely.<verse eid="JOS 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 17:14"/>The people of Joseph said to Joshua, ‘Why have you allotted us only one portion of land and one share for an inheritance? We are a numerous people, and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has blessed us abundantly.’<verse eid="JOS 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 17:15"/>‘If you are so numerous,’ Joshua answered, ‘and if the hill country of Ephraim is too small for you, go up into the forest and clear land for yourselves there in the land of the Perizzites and Rephaites.’<verse eid="JOS 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 17:16"/>The people of Joseph replied, ‘The hill country is not enough for us, and all the Canaanites who live in the plain have chariots fitted with iron, both those in Beth Shan and its settlements and those in the Valley of Jezreel.’<verse eid="JOS 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 17:17"/>But Joshua said to the tribes of Joseph – to Ephraim and Manasseh – ‘You are numerous and very powerful. You will have not only one portion of land allotted to you <verse eid="JOS 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 17:18"/>but the forested hill country as well. Clear it, and its farthest limits will be yours; though the Canaanites have chariots fitted with iron and though they are strong, you can drive them out.’<verse eid="JOS 17:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JOS 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Division of the rest of the land</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 18:1"/>The whole assembly of the Israelites gathered at Shiloh and set up the tent of meeting there. The country was brought under their control, <verse eid="JOS 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 18:2"/>but there were still seven Israelite tribes who had not yet received their inheritance.<verse eid="JOS 18:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 18:3"/>So Joshua said to the Israelites: ‘How long will you wait before you begin to take possession of the land that the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of your ancestors, has given you? <verse eid="JOS 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 18:4"/>Appoint three men from each tribe. I will send them out to make a survey of the land and to write a description of it, according to the inheritance of each. Then they will return to me. <verse eid="JOS 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 18:5"/>You are to divide the land into seven parts. Judah is to remain in its territory on the south and the tribes of Joseph in their territory on the north. <verse eid="JOS 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 18:6"/>After you have written descriptions of the seven parts of the land, bring them here to me and I will cast lots for you in the presence of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God. <verse eid="JOS 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 18:7"/>The Levites, however, do not get a portion among you, because the priestly service of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is their inheritance. And Gad, Reuben and the half-tribe of Manasseh have already received their inheritance on the east side of the Jordan. Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave it to them.’<verse eid="JOS 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 18:8"/>As the men started on their way to map out the land, Joshua instructed them, ‘Go and make a survey of the land and write a description of it. Then return to me, and I will cast lots for you here at Shiloh in the presence of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’ <verse eid="JOS 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 18:9"/>So the men left and went through the land. They wrote its description on a scroll, town by town, in seven parts, and returned to Joshua in the camp at Shiloh.<verse eid="JOS 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 18:10"/>Joshua then cast lots for them in Shiloh in the presence of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, and there he distributed the land to the Israelites according to their tribal divisions.<verse eid="JOS 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Benjamin</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 18:11"/>The first lot came up for the tribe of Benjamin according to its clans. Their allotted territory lay between the tribes of Judah and Joseph:<verse eid="JOS 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 18:12"/>On the north side their boundary began at the Jordan, passed the northern slope of Jericho and headed west into the hill country, coming out at the wilderness of Beth Aven. <verse eid="JOS 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 18:13"/>From there it crossed to the south slope of Luz (that is, Bethel) and went down to Ataroth Addar on the hill south of Lower Beth Horon.<verse eid="JOS 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 18:14"/>From the hill facing Beth Horon on the south the boundary turned south along the western side and came out at Kiriath Baal (that is, Kiriath Jearim), a town of the people of Judah. This was the western side.<verse eid="JOS 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 18:15"/>The southern side began at the outskirts of Kiriath Jearim on the west, and the boundary came out at the spring of the waters of Nephtoah. <verse eid="JOS 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 18:16"/>The boundary went down to the foot of the hill facing the Valley of Ben Hinnom, north of the Valley of Rephaim. It continued down the Hinnom Valley along the southern slope of the Jebusite city and so to En Rogel. <verse eid="JOS 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 18:17"/>It then curved north, went to En Shemesh, continued to Geliloth, which faces the Pass of Adummim, and ran down to the Stone of Bohan son of Reuben. <verse eid="JOS 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 18:18"/>It continued to the northern slope of Beth Arabah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Septuagint; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">slope facing the Arabah</char></note> and on down into the Arabah. <verse eid="JOS 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 18:19"/>It then went to the northern slope of Beth Hoglah and came out at the northern bay of the Dead Sea, at the mouth of the Jordan in the south. This was the southern boundary.<verse eid="JOS 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 18:20"/>The Jordan formed the boundary on the eastern side.</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 18:20">These were the boundaries that marked out the inheritance of the clans of Benjamin on all sides.<verse eid="JOS 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 18:21"/>The tribe of Benjamin, according to its clans, had the following cities:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 18:21">Jericho, Beth Hoglah, Emek Keziz, <verse eid="JOS 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 18:22"/>Beth Arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel, <verse eid="JOS 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 18:23"/>Avvim, Parah, Ophrah, <verse eid="JOS 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 18:24"/>Kephar Ammoni, Ophni and Geba – twelve towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 18:25"/>Gibeon, Ramah, Beeroth, <verse eid="JOS 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 18:26"/>Mizpah, Kephirah, Mozah, <verse eid="JOS 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 18:27"/>Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah, <verse eid="JOS 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 18:28"/>Zelah, Haeleph, the Jebusite city (that is, Jerusalem), Gibeah and Kiriath – fourteen towns and their villages.</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 18:28">This was the inheritance of Benjamin for its clans.<verse eid="JOS 18:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JOS 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Simeon</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 19:1"/>The second lot came out for the tribe of Simeon according to its clans. Their inheritance lay within the territory of Judah. <verse eid="JOS 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 19:2"/>It included:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:2">Beersheba (or Sheba),<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Beersheba, Sheba</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; <char style="xt"><ref loc="1CH 4:28">1 Chron. 4:28</ref></char> does not have </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Sheba</char><char style="fqa" closed="false">.</char></note> Moladah, <verse eid="JOS 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 19:3"/>Hazar Shual, Balah, Ezem, <verse eid="JOS 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 19:4"/>Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 19:5"/>Ziklag, Beth Markaboth, Hazar Susah, <verse eid="JOS 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 19:6"/>Beth Lebaoth and Sharuhen – thirteen towns and their villages;<verse eid="JOS 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 19:7"/>Ain, Rimmon, Ether and Ashan – four towns and their villages – <verse eid="JOS 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 19:8"/>and all the villages around these towns as far as Baalath Beer (Ramah in the Negev).</para>
  <para style="li4" vid="JOS 19:8">This was the inheritance of the tribe of the Simeonites, according to its clans. <verse eid="JOS 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 19:9"/>The inheritance of the Simeonites was taken from the share of Judah, because Judah’s portion was more than they needed. So the Simeonites received their inheritance within the territory of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 19:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Zebulun</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 19:10"/>The third lot came up for Zebulun according to its clans:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:10">The boundary of their inheritance went as far as Sarid. <verse eid="JOS 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 19:11"/>Going west it ran to Maralah, touched Dabbesheth, and extended to the ravine near Jokneam. <verse eid="JOS 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 19:12"/>It turned east from Sarid towards the sunrise to the territory of Kisloth Tabor and went on to Daberath and up to Japhia. <verse eid="JOS 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 19:13"/>Then it continued eastward to Gath Hepher and Eth Kazin; it came out at Rimmon and turned towards Neah. <verse eid="JOS 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 19:14"/>There the boundary went round on the north to Hannathon and ended at the Valley of Iphtah El.<verse eid="JOS 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 19:15"/>Included were Kattath, Nahalal, Shimron, Idalah and Bethlehem. There were twelve towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 19:16"/>These towns and their villages were the inheritance of Zebulun, according to its clans.<verse eid="JOS 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Issachar</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 19:17"/>The fourth lot came out for Issachar according to its clans. <verse eid="JOS 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 19:18"/>Their territory included:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:18">Jezreel, Kesulloth, Shunem, <verse eid="JOS 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 19:19"/>Hapharaim, Shion, Anaharath, <verse eid="JOS 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 19:20"/>Rabbith, Kishion, Ebez, <verse eid="JOS 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 19:21"/>Remeth, En Gannim, En Haddah and Beth Pazzez.<verse eid="JOS 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 19:22"/>The boundary touched Tabor, Shahazumah and Beth Shemesh, and ended at the Jordan.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:22">There were sixteen towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 19:23"/>These towns and their villages were the inheritance of the tribe of Issachar, according to its clans.<verse eid="JOS 19:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Asher</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 19:24"/>The fifth lot came out for the tribe of Asher according to its clans. <verse eid="JOS 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 19:25"/>Their territory included:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:25">Helkath, Hali, Beten, Akshaph, <verse eid="JOS 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 19:26"/>Allammelek, Amad and Mishal. On the west the boundary touched Carmel and Shihor Libnath. <verse eid="JOS 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 19:27"/>It then turned east towards Beth Dagon, touched Zebulun and the Valley of Iphtah El, and went north to Beth Emek and Neiel, passing Kabul on the left. <verse eid="JOS 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 19:28"/>It went to Abdon,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:28 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Hebrew manuscripts (see also 21:30); most Hebrew manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ebron</char></note> Rehob, Hammon and Kanah, as far as Greater Sidon. <verse eid="JOS 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 19:29"/>The boundary then turned back towards Ramah and went to the fortified city of Tyre, turned towards Hosah and came out at the Mediterranean Sea in the region of Akzib, <verse eid="JOS 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 19:30"/>Ummah, Aphek and Rehob.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:30">There were twenty-two towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 19:31"/>These towns and their villages were the inheritance of the tribe of Asher, according to its clans.<verse eid="JOS 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Naphtali</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 19:32"/>The sixth lot came out for Naphtali according to its clans:<verse eid="JOS 19:32"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 19:33"/>Their boundary went from Heleph and the large tree in Zaanannim, passing Adami Nekeb and Jabneel to Lakkum and ending at the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 19:34"/>The boundary ran west through Aznoth Tabor and came out at Hukkok. It touched Zebulun on the south, Asher on the west and the Jordan<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Septuagint; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">west, and Judah, the Jordan,</char></note> on the east.<verse eid="JOS 19:34"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 19:35"/>The fortified cities were Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, Kinnereth, <verse eid="JOS 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 19:36"/>Adamah, Ramah, Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 19:37"/>Kedesh, Edrei, En Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 19:38"/>Iron, Migdal El, Horem, Beth Anath and Beth Shemesh.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:38">There were nineteen towns and their villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:38"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 19:39"/>These towns and their villages were the inheritance of the tribe of Naphtali, according to its clans.<verse eid="JOS 19:39"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Dan</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 19:40"/>The seventh lot came out for the tribe of Dan according to its clans. <verse eid="JOS 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 19:41"/>The territory of their inheritance included:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 19:41">Zorah, Eshtaol, Ir Shemesh, <verse eid="JOS 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 19:42"/>Shaalabbin, Aijalon, Ithlah, <verse eid="JOS 19:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 19:43"/>Elon, Timnah, Ekron, <verse eid="JOS 19:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 19:44"/>Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath, <verse eid="JOS 19:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 19:45"/>Jehud, Bene Berak, Gath Rimmon, <verse eid="JOS 19:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JOS 19:46"/>Me Jarkon and Rakkon, with the area facing Joppa.<verse eid="JOS 19:46"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="JOS 19:47"/>(When the territory of the Danites was lost to them, they went up and attacked Leshem, took it, put it to the sword and occupied it. They settled in Leshem and named it Dan after their ancestor.)<verse eid="JOS 19:47"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 19:48"/>These towns and their villages were the inheritance of the tribe of Dan, according to its clans.<verse eid="JOS 19:48"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land allotted to Joshua</para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 19:49"/>When they had finished dividing the land into its allotted portions, the Israelites gave Joshua son of Nun an inheritance among them, <verse eid="JOS 19:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 19:50"/>as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded. They gave him the town he asked for – Timnath Serah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:50 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Also known as </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Timnath Heres </char><char style="ft" closed="false">(see <char style="xt"><ref loc="JDG 2:9">Judges 2:9</ref></char>)</char></note> in the hill country of Ephraim. And he built up the town and settled there.<verse eid="JOS 19:50"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 19:51"/>These are the territories that Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun and the heads of the tribal clans of Israel assigned by lot at Shiloh in the presence of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at the entrance to the tent of meeting. And so they finished dividing the land.<verse eid="JOS 19:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JOS 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Cities of refuge</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 20:1"/>Then the <char style="sc">Lord</char> said to Joshua: <verse eid="JOS 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 20:2"/>‘Tell the Israelites to designate the cities of refuge, as I instructed you through Moses, <verse eid="JOS 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 20:3"/>so that anyone who kills a person accidentally and unintentionally may flee there and find protection from the avenger of blood. <verse eid="JOS 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 20:4"/>When they flee to one of these cities, they are to stand in the entrance of the city gate and state their case before the elders of that city. Then the elders are to admit the fugitive into their city and provide a place to live among them. <verse eid="JOS 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 20:5"/>If the avenger of blood comes in pursuit, the elders must not surrender the fugitive, because the fugitive killed their neighbour unintentionally and without malice aforethought. <verse eid="JOS 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 20:6"/>They are to stay in that city until they have stood trial before the assembly and until the death of the high priest who is serving at that time. Then they may go back to their own home in the town from which they fled.’<verse eid="JOS 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 20:7"/>So they set apart Kedesh in Galilee in the hill country of Naphtali, Shechem in the hill country of Ephraim, and Kiriath Arba (that is, Hebron) in the hill country of Judah. <verse eid="JOS 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 20:8"/>East of the Jordan (on the other side from Jericho) they designated Bezer in the wilderness on the plateau in the tribe of Reuben, Ramoth in Gilead in the tribe of Gad, and Golan in Bashan in the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 20:9"/>Any of the Israelites or any foreigner residing among them who killed someone accidentally could flee to these designated cities and not be killed by the avenger of blood prior to standing trial before the assembly.<verse eid="JOS 20:9"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JOS 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Towns for the Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 21:1"/>Now the family heads of the Levites approached Eleazar the priest, Joshua son of Nun, and the heads of the other tribal families of Israel <verse eid="JOS 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 21:2"/>at Shiloh in Canaan and said to them, ‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded through Moses that you give us towns to live in, with pasture-lands for our livestock.’<verse eid="JOS 21:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 21:3"/>So, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded, the Israelites gave the Levites the following towns and pasture-lands out of their own inheritance:<verse eid="JOS 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 21:4"/>The first lot came out for the Kohathites, according to their clans. The Levites who were descendants of Aaron the priest were allotted thirteen towns from the tribes of Judah, Simeon and Benjamin.<verse eid="JOS 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 21:5"/>The rest of Kohath’s descendants were allotted ten towns from the clans of the tribes of Ephraim, Dan and half of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 21:6"/>The descendants of Gershon were allotted thirteen towns from the clans of the tribes of Issachar, Asher, Naphtali and the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan.<verse eid="JOS 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 21:7"/>The descendants of Merari, according to their clans, received twelve towns from the tribes of Reuben, Gad and Zebulun.<verse eid="JOS 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 21:8"/>So the Israelites allotted to the Levites these towns and their pasture-lands, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded through Moses.<verse eid="JOS 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 21:9"/>They allotted towns by name from the tribes of Judah and Simeon. <verse eid="JOS 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 21:10"/>The following towns were assigned to the descendants of Aaron who were from the Kohathite clans of the Levites, because the first lot fell to them:<verse eid="JOS 21:10"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 21:11"/>They gave them Kiriath Arba (that is, Hebron), with its surrounding pasture-land, in the hill country of Judah. (Arba was the forefather of Anak.) <verse eid="JOS 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 21:12"/>But the fields and villages around the city they had given to Caleb son of Jephunneh as his possession. <verse eid="JOS 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 21:13"/>So to the descendants of Aaron the priest they gave Hebron (a city of refuge for one accused of murder), Libnah, <verse eid="JOS 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 21:14"/>Jattir, Eshtemoa, <verse eid="JOS 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 21:15"/>Holon, Debir, <verse eid="JOS 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 21:16"/>Ain, Juttah and Beth Shemesh, together with their pasture-lands – nine towns from these two tribes.<verse eid="JOS 21:16"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 21:17"/>And from the tribe of Benjamin they gave them:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:17">Gibeon, Geba, <verse eid="JOS 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 21:18"/>Anathoth and Almon, together with their pasture-lands – four towns.<verse eid="JOS 21:18"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 21:19"/>The total number of towns for the priests, the descendants of Aaron, came to thirteen, together with their pasture-lands.<verse eid="JOS 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 21:20"/>The rest of the Kohathite clans of the Levites were allotted towns from the tribe of Ephraim:<verse eid="JOS 21:20"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 21:21"/>In the hill country of Ephraim they were given:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:21">Shechem (a city of refuge for one accused of murder) and Gezer, <verse eid="JOS 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 21:22"/>Kibzaim and Beth Horon, together with their pasture-lands – four towns.<verse eid="JOS 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 21:23"/>Also from the tribe of Dan they received:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:23">Eltekeh, Gibbethon, <verse eid="JOS 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 21:24"/>Aijalon and Gath Rimmon, together with their pasture-lands – four towns.<verse eid="JOS 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 21:25"/>From half the tribe of Manasseh they received:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:25">Taanach and Gath Rimmon, together with their pasture-lands – two towns.<verse eid="JOS 21:25"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 21:26"/>All these ten towns and their pasture-lands were given to the rest of the Kohathite clans.<verse eid="JOS 21:26"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 21:27"/>The Levite clans of the Gershonites were given:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 21:27">from the half-tribe of Manasseh:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:27">Golan in Bashan (a city of refuge for one accused of murder) and Be Eshterah, together with their pasture-lands – two towns;<verse eid="JOS 21:27"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 21:28"/>from the tribe of Issachar:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:28">Kishion, Daberath, <verse eid="JOS 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 21:29"/>Jarmuth and En Gannim, together with their pasture-lands – four towns;<verse eid="JOS 21:29"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 21:30"/>from the tribe of Asher:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:30">Mishal, Abdon, <verse eid="JOS 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 21:31"/>Helkath and Rehob, together with their pasture-lands – four towns;<verse eid="JOS 21:31"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 21:32"/>from the tribe of Naphtali:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:32">Kedesh in Galilee (a city of refuge for one accused of murder), Hammoth Dor and Kartan, together with their pasture-lands – three towns.<verse eid="JOS 21:32"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 21:33"/>The total number of towns of the Gershonite clans came to thirteen, together with their pasture-lands.<verse eid="JOS 21:33"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 21:34"/>The Merarite clans (the rest of the Levites) were given:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="JOS 21:34">from the tribe of Zebulun:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:34">Jokneam, Kartah, <verse eid="JOS 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 21:35"/>Dimnah and Nahalal, together with their pasture-lands – four towns;<verse eid="JOS 21:35"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 21:36"/>from the tribe of Reuben:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:36">Bezer, Jahaz, <verse eid="JOS 21:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 21:37"/>Kedemoth and Mephaath, together with their pasture-lands – four towns;<verse eid="JOS 21:37"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 21:38"/>from the tribe of Gad:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="JOS 21:38">Ramoth in Gilead (a city of refuge for one accused of murder), Mahanaim, <verse eid="JOS 21:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 21:39"/>Heshbon and Jazer, together with their pasture-lands – four towns in all.<verse eid="JOS 21:39"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 21:40"/>The total number of towns allotted to the Merarite clans, who were the rest of the Levites, came to twelve.<verse eid="JOS 21:40"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 21:41"/>The towns of the Levites in the territory held by the Israelites were forty-eight in all, together with their pasture-lands. <verse eid="JOS 21:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 21:42"/>Each of these towns had pasture-lands surrounding it; this was true for all these towns.<verse eid="JOS 21:42"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 21:43"/>So the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave Israel all the land he had sworn to give their ancestors, and they took possession of it and settled there. <verse eid="JOS 21:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 21:44"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave them rest on every side, just as he had sworn to their ancestors. Not one of their enemies withstood them; the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave all their enemies into their hands. <verse eid="JOS 21:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 21:45"/>Not one of all the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s good promises to Israel failed; every one was fulfilled.<verse eid="JOS 21:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="JOS 22"/>
  <para style="s1">Eastern tribes return home</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 22:1"/>Then Joshua summoned the Reubenites, the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh <verse eid="JOS 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 22:2"/>and said to them, ‘You have done all that Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> commanded, and you have obeyed me in everything I commanded. <verse eid="JOS 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 22:3"/>For a long time now – to this very day – you have not deserted your fellow Israelites but have carried out the mission the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God gave you. <verse eid="JOS 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 22:4"/>Now that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has given them rest as he promised, return to your homes in the land that Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave you on the other side of the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 22:5"/>But be very careful to keep the commandment and the law that Moses the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> gave you: to love the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, to walk in obedience to him, to keep his commands, to hold fast to him and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul.’<verse eid="JOS 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 22:6"/>Then Joshua blessed them and sent them away, and they went to their homes. <verse eid="JOS 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 22:7"/>(To the half-tribe of Manasseh Moses had given land in Bashan, and to the other half of the tribe Joshua gave land on the west side of the Jordan along with their fellow Israelites.) When Joshua sent them home, he blessed them, <verse eid="JOS 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 22:8"/>saying, ‘Return to your homes with your great wealth – with large herds of livestock, with silver, gold, bronze and iron, and a great quantity of clothing – and divide the plunder from your enemies with your fellow Israelites.’<verse eid="JOS 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 22:9"/>So the Reubenites, the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh left the Israelites at Shiloh in Canaan to return to Gilead, their own land, which they had acquired in accordance with the command of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> through Moses.<verse eid="JOS 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 22:10"/>When they came to Geliloth near the Jordan in the land of Canaan, the Reubenites, the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh built an imposing altar there by the Jordan. <verse eid="JOS 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 22:11"/>And when the Israelites heard that they had built the altar on the border of Canaan at Geliloth near the Jordan on the Israelite side, <verse eid="JOS 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 22:12"/>the whole assembly of Israel gathered at Shiloh to go to war against them.<verse eid="JOS 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 22:13"/>So the Israelites sent Phinehas son of Eleazar, the priest, to the land of Gilead – to Reuben, Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 22:14"/>With him they sent ten of the chief men, one from each of the tribes of Israel, each the head of a family division among the Israelite clans.<verse eid="JOS 22:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 22:15"/>When they went to Gilead – to Reuben, Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh – they said to them: <verse eid="JOS 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 22:16"/>‘The whole assembly of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> says: “How could you break faith with the God of Israel like this? How could you turn away from the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and build yourselves an altar in rebellion against him now? <verse eid="JOS 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 22:17"/>Was not the sin of Peor enough for us? Up to this very day we have not cleansed ourselves from that sin, even though a plague fell on the community of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>! <verse eid="JOS 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 22:18"/>And are you now turning away from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>?</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 22:18">‘ “If you rebel against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> today, tomorrow he will be angry with the whole community of Israel. <verse eid="JOS 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 22:19"/>If the land you possess is defiled, come over to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s land, where the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s tabernacle stands, and share the land with us. But do not rebel against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> or against us by building an altar for yourselves, other than the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God. <verse eid="JOS 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 22:20"/>When Achan son of Zerah was unfaithful in regard to the devoted things,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Hebrew term refers to the irrevocable giving over of things or persons to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, often by totally destroying them.</char></note> did not wrath come on the whole community of Israel? He was not the only one who died for his sin.” ’<verse eid="JOS 22:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 22:21"/>Then Reuben, Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh replied to the heads of the clans of Israel: <verse eid="JOS 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 22:22"/>‘The Mighty One, God, the <char style="sc">Lord</char>! The Mighty One, God, the <char style="sc">Lord</char>! He knows! And let Israel know! If this has been in rebellion or disobedience to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, do not spare us this day. <verse eid="JOS 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 22:23"/>If we have built our own altar to turn away from the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and to offer burnt offerings and grain offerings, or to sacrifice fellowship offerings on it, may the <char style="sc">Lord</char> himself call us to account.<verse eid="JOS 22:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 22:24"/>‘No! We did it for fear that some day your descendants might say to ours, “What do you have to do with the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel? <verse eid="JOS 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 22:25"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has made the Jordan a boundary between us and you – you Reubenites and Gadites! You have no share in the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.” So your descendants might cause ours to stop fearing the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JOS 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 22:26"/>‘That is why we said, “Let us get ready and build an altar – but not for burnt offerings or sacrifices.” <verse eid="JOS 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 22:27"/>On the contrary, it is to be a witness between us and you and the generations that follow, that we will worship the <char style="sc">Lord</char> at his sanctuary with our burnt offerings, sacrifices and fellowship offerings. Then in the future your descendants will not be able to say to ours, “You have no share in the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 22:28"/>‘And we said, “If they ever say this to us, or to our descendants, we will answer: look at the replica of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s altar, which our ancestors built, not for burnt offerings and sacrifices, but as a witness between us and you.”<verse eid="JOS 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 22:29"/>‘Far be it from us to rebel against the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and turn away from him today by building an altar for burnt offerings, grain offerings and sacrifices, other than the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God that stands before his tabernacle.’<verse eid="JOS 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 22:30"/>When Phinehas the priest and the leaders of the community – the heads of the clans of the Israelites – heard what Reuben, Gad and Manasseh had to say, they were pleased. <verse eid="JOS 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 22:31"/>And Phinehas son of Eleazar, the priest, said to Reuben, Gad and Manasseh, ‘Today we know that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is with us, because you have not been unfaithful to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> in this matter. Now you have rescued the Israelites from the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s hand.’<verse eid="JOS 22:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 22:32"/>Then Phinehas son of Eleazar, the priest, and the leaders returned to Canaan from their meeting with the Reubenites and Gadites in Gilead and reported to the Israelites. <verse eid="JOS 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 22:33"/>They were glad to hear the report and praised God. And they talked no more about going to war against them to devastate the country where the Reubenites and the Gadites lived.<verse eid="JOS 22:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 22:34"/>And the Reubenites and the Gadites gave the altar this name: A Witness Between Us – that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is God.<verse eid="JOS 22:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="JOS 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua’s farewell to the leaders</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 23:1"/>After a long time had passed and the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had given Israel rest from all their enemies around them, Joshua, by then a very old man, <verse eid="JOS 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 23:2"/>summoned all Israel – their elders, leaders, judges and officials – and said to them: ‘I am very old. <verse eid="JOS 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 23:3"/>You yourselves have seen everything the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has done to all these nations for your sake; it was the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God who fought for you. <verse eid="JOS 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 23:4"/>Remember how I have allotted as an inheritance for your tribes all the land of the nations that remain – the nations I conquered – between the Jordan and the Mediterranean Sea in the west. <verse eid="JOS 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 23:5"/>The <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God himself will push them out for your sake. He will drive them out before you, and you will take possession of their land, as the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God promised you.<verse eid="JOS 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 23:6"/>‘Be very strong; be careful to obey all that is written in the Book of the Law of Moses, without turning aside to the right or to the left. <verse eid="JOS 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 23:7"/>Do not associate with these nations that remain among you; do not invoke the names of their gods or swear by them. You must not serve them or bow down to them. <verse eid="JOS 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 23:8"/>But you are to hold fast to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, as you have until now.<verse eid="JOS 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 23:9"/>‘The <char style="sc">Lord</char> has driven out before you great and powerful nations; to this day no-one has been able to withstand you. <verse eid="JOS 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 23:10"/>One of you routs a thousand, because the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God fights for you, just as he promised. <verse eid="JOS 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 23:11"/>So be very careful to love the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God.<verse eid="JOS 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 23:12"/>‘But if you turn away and ally yourselves with the survivors of these nations that remain among you and if you intermarry with them and associate with them, <verse eid="JOS 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 23:13"/>then you may be sure that the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God will no longer drive out these nations before you. Instead, they will become snares and traps for you, whips on your backs and thorns in your eyes, until you perish from this good land, which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has given you.<verse eid="JOS 23:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 23:14"/>‘Now I am about to go the way of all the earth. You know with all your heart and soul that not one of all the good promises the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God gave you has failed. Every promise has been fulfilled; not one has failed. <verse eid="JOS 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 23:15"/>But just as all the good things the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has promised you have come to you, so he will bring on you all the evil things he has threatened, until the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God has destroyed you from this good land he has given you. <verse eid="JOS 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 23:16"/>If you violate the covenant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, which he commanded you, and go and serve other gods and bow down to them, the <char style="sc">Lord</char>’s anger will burn against you, and you will quickly perish from the good land he has given you.’<verse eid="JOS 23:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="JOS 24"/>
  <para style="s1">The covenant renewed at Shechem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 24:1"/>Then Joshua assembled all the tribes of Israel at Shechem. He summoned the elders, leaders, judges and officials of Israel, and they presented themselves before God.<verse eid="JOS 24:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 24:2"/>Joshua said to all the people, ‘This is what the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel, says: “Long ago your ancestors, including Terah the father of Abraham and Nahor, lived beyond the River Euphrates and worshipped other gods. <verse eid="JOS 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 24:3"/>But I took your father Abraham from the land beyond the Euphrates and led him throughout Canaan and gave him many descendants. I gave him Isaac, <verse eid="JOS 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 24:4"/>and to Isaac I gave Jacob and Esau. I assigned the hill country of Seir to Esau, but Jacob and his family went down to Egypt.<verse eid="JOS 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 24:5"/>‘ “Then I sent Moses and Aaron, and I afflicted the Egyptians by what I did there, and I brought you out. <verse eid="JOS 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 24:6"/>When I brought your people out of Egypt, you came to the sea, and the Egyptians pursued them with chariots and horsemen<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">charioteers</char></note> as far as the Red Sea.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the Sea of Reeds</char></note> <verse eid="JOS 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 24:7"/>But they cried to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> for help, and he put darkness between you and the Egyptians; he brought the sea over them and covered them. You saw with your own eyes what I did to the Egyptians. Then you lived in the wilderness for a long time.<verse eid="JOS 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 24:8"/>‘ “I brought you to the land of the Amorites who lived east of the Jordan. They fought against you, but I gave them into your hands. I destroyed them from before you, and you took possession of their land. <verse eid="JOS 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 24:9"/>When Balak son of Zippor, the king of Moab, prepared to fight against Israel, he sent for Balaam son of Beor to put a curse on you. <verse eid="JOS 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 24:10"/>But I would not listen to Balaam, so he blessed you again and again, and I delivered you out of his hand.<verse eid="JOS 24:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 24:11"/>‘ “Then you crossed the Jordan and came to Jericho. The citizens of Jericho fought against you, as did also the Amorites, Perizzites, Canaanites, Hittites, Girgashites, Hivites and Jebusites, but I gave them into your hands. <verse eid="JOS 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 24:12"/>I sent the hornet ahead of you, which drove them out before you – also the two Amorite kings. You did not do it with your own sword and bow. <verse eid="JOS 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 24:13"/>So I gave you a land on which you did not toil and cities you did not build; and you live in them and eat from vineyards and olive groves that you did not plant.”<verse eid="JOS 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 24:14"/>‘Now fear the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and serve him with all faithfulness. Throw away the gods your ancestors worshipped beyond the River Euphrates and in Egypt, and serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. <verse eid="JOS 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 24:15"/>But if serving the <char style="sc">Lord</char> seems undesirable to you, then choose for yourselves this day whom you will serve, whether the gods your ancestors served beyond the Euphrates, or the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you are living. But as for me and my household, we will serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’<verse eid="JOS 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 24:16"/>Then the people answered, ‘Far be it from us to forsake the <char style="sc">Lord</char> to serve other gods! <verse eid="JOS 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 24:17"/>It was the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God himself who brought us and our parents up out of Egypt, from that land of slavery, and performed those great signs before our eyes. He protected us on our entire journey and among all the nations through which we travelled. <verse eid="JOS 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 24:18"/>And the <char style="sc">Lord</char> drove out before us all the nations, including the Amorites, who lived in the land. We too will serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, because he is our God.’<verse eid="JOS 24:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 24:19"/>Joshua said to the people, ‘You are not able to serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. He is a holy God; he is a jealous God. He will not forgive your rebellion and your sins. <verse eid="JOS 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 24:20"/>If you forsake the <char style="sc">Lord</char> and serve foreign gods, he will turn and bring disaster on you and make an end of you, after he has been good to you.’<verse eid="JOS 24:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 24:21"/>But the people said to Joshua, ‘No! We will serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’<verse eid="JOS 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 24:22"/>Then Joshua said, ‘You are witnesses against yourselves that you have chosen to serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 24:22">‘Yes, we are witnesses,’ they replied.<verse eid="JOS 24:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 24:23"/>‘Now then,’ said Joshua, ‘throw away the foreign gods that are among you and yield your hearts to the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of Israel.’<verse eid="JOS 24:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 24:24"/>And the people said to Joshua, ‘We will serve the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God and obey him.’<verse eid="JOS 24:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 24:25"/>On that day Joshua made a covenant for the people, and there at Shechem he reaffirmed for them decrees and laws. <verse eid="JOS 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 24:26"/>And Joshua recorded these things in the Book of the Law of God. Then he took a large stone and set it up there under the oak near the holy place of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>.<verse eid="JOS 24:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 24:27"/>‘See!’ he said to all the people. ‘This stone will be a witness against us. It has heard all the words the <char style="sc">Lord</char> has said to us. It will be a witness against you if you are untrue to your God.’<verse eid="JOS 24:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 24:28"/>Then Joshua dismissed the people, each to their own inheritance.<verse eid="JOS 24:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Buried in the promised land</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 24:29"/>After these things, Joshua son of Nun, the servant of the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, died at the age of a hundred and ten. <verse eid="JOS 24:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 24:30"/>And they buried him in the land of his inheritance, at Timnath Serah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:30 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Also known as </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Timnath Heres </char><char style="ft" closed="false">(see <char style="xt"><ref loc="JDG 2:9">Judges 2:9</ref></char>)</char></note> in the hill country of Ephraim, north of Mount Gaash.<verse eid="JOS 24:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 24:31"/>Israel served the <char style="sc">Lord</char> throughout the lifetime of Joshua and of the elders who outlived him and who had experienced everything the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had done for Israel.<verse eid="JOS 24:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 24:32"/>And Joseph’s bones, which the Israelites had brought up from Egypt, were buried at Shechem in the tract of land that Jacob bought for a hundred pieces of silver<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">hundred kesitahs</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; a kesitah was a unit of money of unknown weight and value.</char></note> from the sons of Hamor, the father of Shechem. This became the inheritance of Joseph’s descendants.<verse eid="JOS 24:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 24:33"/>And Eleazar son of Aaron died and was buried at Gibeah, which had been allotted to his son Phinehas in the hill country of Ephraim.<verse eid="JOS 24:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 24"/>
</usx>
