<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="LUK" style="id">- English-UK: New International Version® (Anglicised) NIV® 2011 (Revised format)</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1973, 1978, 1984, 2011 by Biblica, Inc.®</para>
  <para style="h">Luke</para>
  <para style="toc1">Luke</para>
  <para style="toc2">Luke</para>
  <para style="toc3">Lk</para>
  <para style="mt1">Luke</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">The books of Luke and Acts are two volumes of a single work (see <char style="xt">the Invitation to <ref loc="ACT 1">Acts</ref></char> for a more detailed introduction to Acts). Together they tell the story of how God first invited the people of Israel, and then all nations, to follow Jesus. In the first volume, the movement is towards Jerusalem, the centre of Jewish national life. In the second, the movement is from Jerusalem to other nations, closing with Paul proclaiming the kingdom of God in Rome, the capital of the empire.</para>
  <para style="ip">Luke addresses his history to <char style="qt">most excellent Theophilus,</char> most likely a Roman official. His volumes are stocked with details from sources Luke had available: letters, speeches, songs, travel accounts, trial transcripts and biographical anecdotes. Luke’s purpose is to show the fulfilment of God’s plan to bring his light to the world through Israel. The earliest Jesus-followers take up this calling by announcing Jesus’ victory over sin and death to all the nations.</para>
  <para style="ip">The first volume, Luke’s telling of the story of Jesus, has three main sections:</para>
  <para style="ili1">: First, Jesus ministers in Galilee, the northern area of the land of Israel.</para>
  <para style="ili1">: Next, he takes a long journey to Jerusalem, during which he welcomes people into the way of God’s reign and challenges Israel’s current understanding of the kingdom.</para>
  <para style="ili1">: Third, Luke tells how Jesus gives his life in Jerusalem and then rises from the dead to be revealed as Israel’s King and the world’s true Lord.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="LUK 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Introduction</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 1:1"/>Many have undertaken to draw up an account of the things that have been fulfilled<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">been surely believed</char></note> among us, <verse eid="LUK 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 1:2"/>just as they were handed down to us by those who from the first were eyewitnesses and servants of the word. <verse eid="LUK 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 1:3"/>With this in mind, since I myself have carefully investigated everything from the beginning, I too decided to write an orderly account for you, most excellent Theophilus, <verse eid="LUK 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 1:4"/>so that you may know the certainty of the things you have been taught.<verse eid="LUK 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The birth of John the Baptist foretold</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 1:5"/>In the time of Herod king of Judea there was a priest named Zechariah, who belonged to the priestly division of Abijah; his wife Elizabeth was also a descendant of Aaron. <verse eid="LUK 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 1:6"/>Both of them were righteous in the sight of God, observing all the Lord’s commands and decrees blamelessly. <verse eid="LUK 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 1:7"/>But they were childless because Elizabeth was not able to conceive, and they were both very old.<verse eid="LUK 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 1:8"/>Once when Zechariah’s division was on duty and he was serving as priest before God, <verse eid="LUK 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 1:9"/>he was chosen by lot, according to the custom of the priesthood, to go into the temple of the Lord and burn incense. <verse eid="LUK 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 1:10"/>And when the time for the burning of incense came, all the assembled worshippers were praying outside.<verse eid="LUK 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 1:11"/>Then an angel of the Lord appeared to him, standing at the right side of the altar of incense. <verse eid="LUK 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 1:12"/>When Zechariah saw him, he was startled and was gripped with fear. <verse eid="LUK 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 1:13"/>But the angel said to him: ‘Do not be afraid, Zechariah; your prayer has been heard. Your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son, and you are to call him John. <verse eid="LUK 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 1:14"/>He will be a joy and delight to you, and many will rejoice because of his birth, <verse eid="LUK 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 1:15"/>for he will be great in the sight of the Lord. He is never to take wine or other fermented drink, and he will be filled with the Holy Spirit even before he is born. <verse eid="LUK 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 1:16"/>He will bring back many of the people of Israel to the Lord their God. <verse eid="LUK 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 1:17"/>And he will go on before the Lord, in the spirit and power of Elijah, to turn the hearts of the parents to their children and the disobedient to the wisdom of the righteous – to make ready a people prepared for the Lord.’<verse eid="LUK 1:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 1:18"/>Zechariah asked the angel, ‘How can I be sure of this? I am an old man and my wife is well on in years.’<verse eid="LUK 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 1:19"/>The angel said to him, ‘I am Gabriel. I stand in the presence of God, and I have been sent to speak to you and to tell you this good news. <verse eid="LUK 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 1:20"/>And now you will be silent and not able to speak until the day this happens, because you did not believe my words, which will come true at their appointed time.’<verse eid="LUK 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 1:21"/>Meanwhile, the people were waiting for Zechariah and wondering why he stayed so long in the temple. <verse eid="LUK 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 1:22"/>When he came out, he could not speak to them. They realised he had seen a vision in the temple, for he kept making signs to them but remained unable to speak.<verse eid="LUK 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 1:23"/>When his time of service was completed, he returned home. <verse eid="LUK 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 1:24"/>After this his wife Elizabeth became pregnant and for five months remained in seclusion. <verse eid="LUK 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 1:25"/>‘The Lord has done this for me,’ she said. ‘In these days he has shown his favour and taken away my disgrace among the people.’<verse eid="LUK 1:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The birth of Jesus foretold</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 1:26"/>In the sixth month of Elizabeth’s pregnancy, God sent the angel Gabriel to Nazareth, a town in Galilee, <verse eid="LUK 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 1:27"/>to a virgin pledged to be married to a man named Joseph, a descendant of David. The virgin’s name was Mary. <verse eid="LUK 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 1:28"/>The angel went to her and said, ‘Greetings, you who are highly favoured! The Lord is with you.’<verse eid="LUK 1:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 1:29"/>Mary was greatly troubled at his words and wondered what kind of greeting this might be. <verse eid="LUK 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 1:30"/>But the angel said to her, ‘Do not be afraid, Mary, you have found favour with God. <verse eid="LUK 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 1:31"/>You will conceive and give birth to a son, and you are to call him Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 1:32"/>He will be great and will be called the Son of the Most High. The Lord God will give him the throne of his father David, <verse eid="LUK 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 1:33"/>and he will reign over Jacob’s descendants for ever; his kingdom will never end.’<verse eid="LUK 1:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 1:34"/>‘How will this be,’ Mary asked the angel, ‘since I am a virgin?’<verse eid="LUK 1:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 1:35"/>The angel answered, ‘The Holy Spirit will come on you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow you. So the holy one to be born will be called<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">So the child to be born will be called holy,</char></note> the Son of God. <verse eid="LUK 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 1:36"/>Even Elizabeth your relative is going to have a child in her old age, and she who was said to be unable to conceive is in her sixth month. <verse eid="LUK 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 1:37"/>For no word from God will ever fail.’<verse eid="LUK 1:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 1:38"/>‘I am the Lord’s servant,’ Mary answered. ‘May your word to me be fulfilled.’ Then the angel left her.<verse eid="LUK 1:38"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Mary visits Elizabeth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 1:39"/>At that time Mary got ready and hurried to a town in the hill country of Judea, <verse eid="LUK 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 1:40"/>where she entered Zechariah’s home and greeted Elizabeth. <verse eid="LUK 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 1:41"/>When Elizabeth heard Mary’s greeting, the baby leaped in her womb, and Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="LUK 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 1:42"/>In a loud voice she exclaimed: ‘Blessed are you among women, and blessed is the child you will bear! <verse eid="LUK 1:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 1:43"/>But why am I so favoured, that the mother of my Lord should come to me? <verse eid="LUK 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 1:44"/>As soon as the sound of your greeting reached my ears, the baby in my womb leaped for joy. <verse eid="LUK 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 1:45"/>Blessed is she who has believed that the Lord would fulfil his promises to her!’<verse eid="LUK 1:45"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Mary’s song</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 1:46"/>And Mary said:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 1:46">‘My soul glorifies the Lord<verse eid="LUK 1:46"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 1:47"/>and my spirit rejoices in God my Saviour,<verse eid="LUK 1:47"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 1:48"/>for he has been mindful</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:48">of the humble state of his servant.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 1:48">From now on all generations will call me blessed,<verse eid="LUK 1:48"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 1:49"/>for the Mighty One has done great things for me –</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:49">holy is his name.<verse eid="LUK 1:49"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 1:50"/>His mercy extends to those who fear him,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:50">from generation to generation.<verse eid="LUK 1:50"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 1:51"/>He has performed mighty deeds with his arm;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:51">he has scattered those who are proud in their inmost thoughts.<verse eid="LUK 1:51"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 1:52"/>He has brought down rulers from their thrones</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:52">but has lifted up the humble.<verse eid="LUK 1:52"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 1:53"/>He has filled the hungry with good things</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:53">but has sent the rich away empty.<verse eid="LUK 1:53"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 1:54"/>He has helped his servant Israel,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:54">remembering to be merciful<verse eid="LUK 1:54"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 1:55"/>to Abraham and his descendants for ever,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:55">just as he promised our ancestors.’<verse eid="LUK 1:55"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 1:56"/>Mary stayed with Elizabeth for about three months and then returned home.<verse eid="LUK 1:56"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The birth of John the Baptist</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 1:57"/>When it was time for Elizabeth to have her baby, she gave birth to a son. <verse eid="LUK 1:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 1:58"/>Her neighbours and relatives heard that the Lord had shown her great mercy, and they shared her joy.<verse eid="LUK 1:58"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 1:59"/>On the eighth day they came to circumcise the child, and they were going to name him after his father Zechariah, <verse eid="LUK 1:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="LUK 1:60"/>but his mother spoke up and said, ‘No! He is to be called John.’<verse eid="LUK 1:60"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="61" style="v" sid="LUK 1:61"/>They said to her, ‘There is no-one among your relatives who has that name.’<verse eid="LUK 1:61"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="62" style="v" sid="LUK 1:62"/>Then they made signs to his father, to find out what he would like to name the child. <verse eid="LUK 1:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="LUK 1:63"/>He asked for a writing tablet, and to everyone’s astonishment he wrote, ‘His name is John.’ <verse eid="LUK 1:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="LUK 1:64"/>Immediately his mouth was opened and his tongue set free, and he began to speak, praising God. <verse eid="LUK 1:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="LUK 1:65"/>All the neighbours were filled with awe, and throughout the hill country of Judea people were talking about all these things. <verse eid="LUK 1:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="LUK 1:66"/>Everyone who heard this wondered about it, asking, ‘What then is this child going to be?’ For the Lord’s hand was with him.<verse eid="LUK 1:66"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Zechariah’s song</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="67" style="v" sid="LUK 1:67"/>His father Zechariah was filled with the Holy Spirit and prophesied:<verse eid="LUK 1:67"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="68" style="v" sid="LUK 1:68"/>‘Praise be to the Lord, the God of Israel,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:68">because he has come to his people and redeemed them.<verse eid="LUK 1:68"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="69" style="v" sid="LUK 1:69"/>He has raised up a horn<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:69 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Horn </char><char style="ft" closed="false">here symbolises a strong king.</char></note> of salvation for us</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:69">in the house of his servant David<verse eid="LUK 1:69"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="70" style="v" sid="LUK 1:70"/>(as he said through his holy prophets of long ago),<verse eid="LUK 1:70"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="71" style="v" sid="LUK 1:71"/>salvation from our enemies</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:71">and from the hand of all who hate us –<verse eid="LUK 1:71"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="72" style="v" sid="LUK 1:72"/>to show mercy to our ancestors</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:72">and to remember his holy covenant,<verse eid="LUK 1:72"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="73" style="v" sid="LUK 1:73"/>the oath he swore to our father Abraham:<verse eid="LUK 1:73"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="74" style="v" sid="LUK 1:74"/>to rescue us from the hand of our enemies,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:74">and to enable us to serve him without fear<verse eid="LUK 1:74"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="75" style="v" sid="LUK 1:75"/>in holiness and righteousness before him all our days.<verse eid="LUK 1:75"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="76" style="v" sid="LUK 1:76"/>And you, my child, will be called a prophet of the Most High;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:76">for you will go on before the Lord to prepare the way for him,<verse eid="LUK 1:76"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="77" style="v" sid="LUK 1:77"/>to give his people the knowledge of salvation</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:77">through the forgiveness of their sins,<verse eid="LUK 1:77"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="78" style="v" sid="LUK 1:78"/>because of the tender mercy of our God,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:78">by which the rising sun will come to us from heaven<verse eid="LUK 1:78"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="79" style="v" sid="LUK 1:79"/>to shine on those living in darkness</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 1:79">and in the shadow of death,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 1:79">to guide our feet into the path of peace.’<verse eid="LUK 1:79"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="80" style="v" sid="LUK 1:80"/>And the child grew and became strong in spirit<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">1:80 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">in the Spirit</char></note>; and he lived in the wilderness until he appeared publicly to Israel.<verse eid="LUK 1:80"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="LUK 2"/>
  <para style="s1">The birth of Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 2:1"/>In those days Caesar Augustus issued a decree that a census should be taken of the entire Roman world. <verse eid="LUK 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 2:2"/>(This was the first census that took place while<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">This census took place before</char></note> Quirinius was governor of Syria.) <verse eid="LUK 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 2:3"/>And everyone went to their own town to register.<verse eid="LUK 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 2:4"/>So Joseph also went up from the town of Nazareth in Galilee to Judea, to Bethlehem the town of David, because he belonged to the house and line of David. <verse eid="LUK 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 2:5"/>He went there to register with Mary, who was pledged to be married to him and was expecting a child. <verse eid="LUK 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 2:6"/>While they were there, the time came for the baby to be born, <verse eid="LUK 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 2:7"/>and she gave birth to her firstborn, a son. She wrapped him in cloths and placed him in a manger, because there was no guest room available for them.<verse eid="LUK 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 2:8"/>And there were shepherds living out in the fields near by, keeping watch over their flocks at night. <verse eid="LUK 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 2:9"/>An angel of the Lord appeared to them, and the glory of the Lord shone around them, and they were terrified. <verse eid="LUK 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 2:10"/>But the angel said to them, ‘Do not be afraid. I bring you good news that will cause great joy for all the people. <verse eid="LUK 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 2:11"/>Today in the town of David a Saviour has been born to you; he is the Messiah, the Lord. <verse eid="LUK 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 2:12"/>This will be a sign to you: you will find a baby wrapped in cloths and lying in a manger.’<verse eid="LUK 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 2:13"/>Suddenly a great company of the heavenly host appeared with the angel, praising God and saying,<verse eid="LUK 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 2:14"/>‘Glory to God in the highest heaven,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 2:14">and on earth peace to those on whom his favour rests.’<verse eid="LUK 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 2:15"/>When the angels had left them and gone into heaven, the shepherds said to one another, ‘Let’s go to Bethlehem and see this thing that has happened, which the Lord has told us about.’<verse eid="LUK 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 2:16"/>So they hurried off and found Mary and Joseph, and the baby, who was lying in the manger. <verse eid="LUK 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 2:17"/>When they had seen him, they spread the word concerning what had been told them about this child, <verse eid="LUK 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 2:18"/>and all who heard it were amazed at what the shepherds said to them. <verse eid="LUK 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 2:19"/>But Mary treasured up all these things and pondered them in her heart. <verse eid="LUK 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 2:20"/>The shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all the things they had heard and seen, which were just as they had been told.<verse eid="LUK 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 2:21"/>On the eighth day, when it was time to circumcise the child, he was named Jesus, the name the angel had given him before he was conceived.<verse eid="LUK 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus presented in the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 2:22"/>When the time came for the purification rites required by the Law of Moses, Joseph and Mary took him to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord <verse eid="LUK 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 2:23"/>(as it is written in the Law of the Lord, ‘Every firstborn male is to be consecrated to the Lord’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="EXO 13:2">Exodus 13:2</ref>,<ref loc="EXO 13:12">12</ref></char></char></note>), <verse eid="LUK 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 2:24"/>and to offer a sacrifice in keeping with what is said in the Law of the Lord: ‘a pair of doves or two young pigeons’.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="LEV 12:8">Lev. 12:8</ref></char></char></note><verse eid="LUK 2:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 2:25"/>Now there was a man in Jerusalem called Simeon, who was righteous and devout. He was waiting for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was on him. <verse eid="LUK 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 2:26"/>It had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not die before he had seen the Lord’s Messiah. <verse eid="LUK 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 2:27"/>Moved by the Spirit, he went into the temple courts. When the parents brought in the child Jesus to do for him what the custom of the Law required, <verse eid="LUK 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 2:28"/>Simeon took him in his arms and praised God, saying:<verse eid="LUK 2:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 2:29"/>‘Sovereign Lord, as you have promised,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 2:29">you may now dismiss<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:29 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">promised, / now dismiss</char></note> your servant in peace.<verse eid="LUK 2:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 2:30"/>For my eyes have seen your salvation,<verse eid="LUK 2:30"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 2:31"/>which you have prepared in the sight of all nations:<verse eid="LUK 2:31"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 2:32"/>a light for revelation to the Gentiles,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 2:32">and the glory of your people Israel.’<verse eid="LUK 2:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 2:33"/>The child’s father and mother marvelled at what was said about him. <verse eid="LUK 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 2:34"/>Then Simeon blessed them and said to Mary, his mother: ‘This child is destined to cause the falling and rising of many in Israel, and to be a sign that will be spoken against, <verse eid="LUK 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 2:35"/>so that the thoughts of many hearts will be revealed. And a sword will pierce your own soul too.’<verse eid="LUK 2:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 2:36"/>There was also a prophet, Anna, the daughter of Penuel, of the tribe of Asher. She was very old; she had lived with her husband seven years after her marriage, <verse eid="LUK 2:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 2:37"/>and then was a widow until she was eighty-four.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:37 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">then had been a widow for eighty-four years.</char></note> She never left the temple but worshipped night and day, fasting and praying. <verse eid="LUK 2:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 2:38"/>Coming up to them at that very moment, she gave thanks to God and spoke about the child to all who were looking forward to the redemption of Jerusalem.<verse eid="LUK 2:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 2:39"/>When Joseph and Mary had done everything required by the Law of the Lord, they returned to Galilee to their own town of Nazareth. <verse eid="LUK 2:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 2:40"/>And the child grew and became strong; he was filled with wisdom, and the grace of God was on him.<verse eid="LUK 2:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The boy Jesus at the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 2:41"/>Every year Jesus’ parents went to Jerusalem for the Festival of the Passover. <verse eid="LUK 2:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 2:42"/>When he was twelve years old, they went up to the festival, according to the custom. <verse eid="LUK 2:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 2:43"/>After the festival was over, while his parents were returning home, the boy Jesus stayed behind in Jerusalem, but they were unaware of it. <verse eid="LUK 2:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 2:44"/>Thinking he was in their company, they travelled on for a day. Then they began looking for him among their relatives and friends. <verse eid="LUK 2:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 2:45"/>When they did not find him, they went back to Jerusalem to look for him. <verse eid="LUK 2:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 2:46"/>After three days they found him in the temple courts, sitting among the teachers, listening to them and asking them questions. <verse eid="LUK 2:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 2:47"/>Everyone who heard him was amazed at his understanding and his answers. <verse eid="LUK 2:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 2:48"/>When his parents saw him, they were astonished. His mother said to him, ‘Son, why have you treated us like this? Your father and I have been anxiously searching for you.’<verse eid="LUK 2:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 2:49"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Why were you searching for me?’</char> he asked. <char style="wj">‘Didn’t you know I had to be in my Father’s house?’</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:49 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">be about my Father’s business</char></note> <verse eid="LUK 2:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 2:50"/>But they did not understand what he was saying to them.<verse eid="LUK 2:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 2:51"/>Then he went down to Nazareth with them and was obedient to them. But his mother treasured all these things in her heart. <verse eid="LUK 2:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 2:52"/>And Jesus grew in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man.<verse eid="LUK 2:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="LUK 3"/>
  <para style="s1">John the Baptist prepares the way</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 3:1"/>In the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar – when Pontius Pilate was governor of Judea, Herod tetrarch of Galilee, his brother Philip tetrarch of Iturea and Traconitis, and Lysanias tetrarch of Abilene – <verse eid="LUK 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 3:2"/>during the high-priesthood of Annas and Caiaphas, the word of God came to John son of Zechariah in the wilderness. <verse eid="LUK 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 3:3"/>He went into all the country around the Jordan, preaching a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins. <verse eid="LUK 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 3:4"/>As it is written in the book of the words of Isaiah the prophet:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 3:4">‘A voice of one calling in the wilderness,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 3:4">“Prepare the way for the Lord,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 3:4">make straight paths for him.<verse eid="LUK 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 3:5"/>Every valley shall be filled in,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 3:5">every mountain and hill made low.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 3:5">The crooked roads shall become straight,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 3:5">the rough ways smooth.<verse eid="LUK 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 3:6"/>And all people will see God’s salvation.” ’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="ISA 40:3-5">Isaiah 40:3-5</ref></char></char></note><verse eid="LUK 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 3:7"/>John said to the crowds coming out to be baptised by him, ‘You brood of vipers! Who warned you to flee from the coming wrath? <verse eid="LUK 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 3:8"/>Produce fruit in keeping with repentance. And do not begin to say to yourselves, “We have Abraham as our father.” For I tell you that out of these stones God can raise up children for Abraham. <verse eid="LUK 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 3:9"/>The axe has been laid to the root of the trees, and every tree that does not produce good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire.’<verse eid="LUK 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 3:10"/>‘What should we do then?’ the crowd asked.<verse eid="LUK 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 3:11"/>John answered, ‘Anyone who has two shirts should share with the one who has none, and anyone who has food should do the same.’<verse eid="LUK 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 3:12"/>Even tax collectors came to be baptised. ‘Teacher,’ they asked, ‘what should we do?’<verse eid="LUK 3:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 3:13"/>‘Don’t collect any more than you are required to,’ he told them.<verse eid="LUK 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 3:14"/>Then some soldiers asked him, ‘And what should we do?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 3:14">He replied, ‘Don’t extort money and don’t accuse people falsely – be content with your pay.’<verse eid="LUK 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 3:15"/>The people were waiting expectantly and were all wondering in their hearts if John might possibly be the Messiah. <verse eid="LUK 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 3:16"/>John answered them all, ‘I baptise you with<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">in</char></note> water. But one who is more powerful than I will come, the straps of whose sandals I am not worthy to untie. He will baptise you with<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">in</char></note> the Holy Spirit and fire. <verse eid="LUK 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 3:17"/>His winnowing fork is in his hand to clear his threshing-floor and to gather the wheat into his barn, but he will burn up the chaff with unquenchable fire.’ <verse eid="LUK 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 3:18"/>And with many other words John exhorted the people and proclaimed the good news to them.<verse eid="LUK 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 3:19"/>But when John rebuked Herod the tetrarch because of his marriage to Herodias, his brother’s wife, and all the other evil things he had done, <verse eid="LUK 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 3:20"/>Herod added this to them all: he locked John up in prison.<verse eid="LUK 3:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The baptism and genealogy of Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 3:21"/>When all the people were being baptised, Jesus was baptised too. And as he was praying, heaven was opened <verse eid="LUK 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 3:22"/>and the Holy Spirit descended on him in bodily form like a dove. And a voice came from heaven: ‘You are my Son, whom I love; with you I am well pleased.’<verse eid="LUK 3:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 3:23"/>Now Jesus himself was about thirty years old when he began his ministry. He was the son, so it was thought, of Joseph,</para>
  <para style="b" vid="LUK 3:23"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:23">the son of Heli, <verse eid="LUK 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 3:24"/>the son of Matthat,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:24">the son of Levi, the son of Melki,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:24">the son of Jannai, the son of Joseph,<verse eid="LUK 3:24"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 3:25"/>the son of Mattathias, the son of Amos,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:25">the son of Nahum, the son of Esli,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:25">the son of Naggai, <verse eid="LUK 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 3:26"/>the son of Maath,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:26">the son of Mattathias, the son of Semein,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:26">the son of Josek, the son of Joda,<verse eid="LUK 3:26"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 3:27"/>the son of Joanan, the son of Rhesa,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:27">the son of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:27">the son of Neri, <verse eid="LUK 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 3:28"/>the son of Melki,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:28">the son of Addi, the son of Cosam,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:28">the son of Elmadam, the son of Er,<verse eid="LUK 3:28"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 3:29"/>the son of Joshua, the son of Eliezer,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:29">the son of Jorim, the son of Matthat,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:29">the son of Levi, <verse eid="LUK 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 3:30"/>the son of Simeon,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:30">the son of Judah, the son of Joseph,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:30">the son of Jonam, the son of Eliakim,<verse eid="LUK 3:30"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 3:31"/>the son of Melea, the son of Menna,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:31">the son of Mattatha, the son of Nathan,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:31">the son of David, <verse eid="LUK 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 3:32"/>the son of Jesse,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:32">the son of Obed, the son of Boaz,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:32">the son of Salmon,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some early manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Sala</char></note> the son of Nahshon,<verse eid="LUK 3:32"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 3:33"/>the son of Amminadab, the son of Ram,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Amminadab, the son of Admin, the son of Arni</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; other manuscripts vary widely.</char></note></para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:33">the son of Hezron, the son of Perez,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:33">the son of Judah, <verse eid="LUK 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 3:34"/>the son of Jacob,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:34">the son of Isaac, the son of Abraham,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:34">the son of Terah, the son of Nahor,<verse eid="LUK 3:34"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 3:35"/>the son of Serug, the son of Reu,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:35">the son of Peleg, the son of Eber,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:35">the son of Shelah, <verse eid="LUK 3:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 3:36"/>the son of Cainan,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:36">the son of Arphaxad, the son of Shem,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:36">the son of Noah, the son of Lamech,<verse eid="LUK 3:36"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 3:37"/>the son of Methuselah, the son of Enoch,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:37">the son of Jared, the son of Mahalalel,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:37">the son of Kenan, <verse eid="LUK 3:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 3:38"/>the son of Enosh,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:38">the son of Seth, the son of Adam,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 3:38">the son of God.<verse eid="LUK 3:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="LUK 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus is tested in the wilderness</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 4:1"/>Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, left the Jordan and was led by the Spirit into the wilderness, <verse eid="LUK 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 4:2"/>where for forty days he was tempted<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek for </char><char style="fq" closed="false">tempted </char><char style="ft" closed="false">can also mean </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">tested.</char></note> by the devil. He ate nothing during those days, and at the end of them he was hungry.<verse eid="LUK 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 4:3"/>The devil said to him, ‘If you are the Son of God, tell this stone to become bread.’<verse eid="LUK 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 4:4"/>Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘It is written: “Man shall not live on bread alone.”</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 8:3">Deut. 8:3</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">’</char><verse eid="LUK 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 4:5"/>The devil led him up to a high place and showed him in an instant all the kingdoms of the world. <verse eid="LUK 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 4:6"/>And he said to him, ‘I will give you all their authority and splendour; it has been given to me, and I can give it to anyone I want to. <verse eid="LUK 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 4:7"/>If you worship me, it will all be yours.’<verse eid="LUK 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 4:8"/>Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘It is written: “Worship the Lord your God and serve him only.”</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 6:13">Deut. 6:13</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">’</char><verse eid="LUK 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 4:9"/>The devil led him to Jerusalem and had him stand on the highest point of the temple. ‘If you are the Son of God,’ he said, ‘throw yourself down from here. <verse eid="LUK 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 4:10"/>For it is written:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 4:10">‘ “He will command his angels concerning you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 4:10">to guard you carefully;<verse eid="LUK 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 4:11"/>they will lift you up in their hands,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 4:11">so that you will not strike your foot against a stone.”<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:11 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="PSA 91:11">Psalm 91:11</ref>,<ref loc="PSA 91:12">12</ref></char></char></note>’<verse eid="LUK 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 4:12"/>Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘It is said: “Do not put the Lord your God to the test.”</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 6:16">Deut. 6:16</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">’</char><verse eid="LUK 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 4:13"/>When the devil had finished all this tempting, he left him until an opportune time.<verse eid="LUK 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus rejected at Nazareth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 4:14"/>Jesus returned to Galilee in the power of the Spirit, and news about him spread through the whole countryside. <verse eid="LUK 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 4:15"/>He was teaching in their synagogues, and everyone praised him.<verse eid="LUK 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 4:16"/>He went to Nazareth, where he had been brought up, and on the Sabbath day he went into the synagogue, as was his custom. He stood up to read, <verse eid="LUK 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 4:17"/>and the scroll of the prophet Isaiah was handed to him. Unrolling it, he found the place where it is written:<verse eid="LUK 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 4:18"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The Spirit of the Lord is on me,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 4:18">
    <char style="wj">because he has anointed me</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 4:18">
    <char style="wj">to proclaim good news to the poor.</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 4:18">
    <char style="wj">He has sent me to proclaim freedom for the prisoners</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 4:18">
    <char style="wj">and recovery of sight for the blind,</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 4:18">
    <char style="wj">to set the oppressed free,</char><verse eid="LUK 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 4:19"/>
    <char style="wj">to proclaim the year of the Lord’s favour.’</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">4:19 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">
        <char style="xt">
          <ref loc="ISA 61:1">Isaiah 61:1</ref>,<ref loc="ISA 61:2">2</ref></char> (see Septuagint); <char style="xt"><ref loc="ISA 58:6">Isaiah 58:6</ref></char></char>
    </note><verse eid="LUK 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 4:20"/>Then he rolled up the scroll, gave it back to the attendant and sat down. The eyes of everyone in the synagogue were fastened on him. <verse eid="LUK 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 4:21"/>He began by saying to them, <char style="wj">‘Today this scripture is fulfilled in your hearing.’</char><verse eid="LUK 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 4:22"/>All spoke well of him and were amazed at the gracious words that came from his lips. ‘Isn’t this Joseph’s son?’ they asked.<verse eid="LUK 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 4:23"/>Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">‘Surely you will quote this proverb to me: “Physician, heal yourself!” And you will tell me, “Do here in your home town what we have heard that you did in Capernaum.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 4:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 4:24"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Truly I tell you,’</char> he continued, <char style="wj">‘no prophet is accepted in his home town.</char> <verse eid="LUK 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 4:25"/><char style="wj">I assure you that there were many widows in Israel in Elijah’s time, when the sky was shut for three and a half years and there was a severe famine throughout the land.</char> <verse eid="LUK 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 4:26"/><char style="wj">Yet Elijah was not sent to any of them, but to a widow in Zarephath in the region of Sidon.</char> <verse eid="LUK 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 4:27"/><char style="wj">And there were many in Israel with leprosy</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek word traditionally translated </char><char style="fq" closed="false">leprosy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was used for various diseases affecting the skin.</char></note> <char style="wj">in the time of Elisha the prophet, yet not one of them was cleansed – only Naaman the Syrian.’</char><verse eid="LUK 4:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 4:28"/>All the people in the synagogue were furious when they heard this. <verse eid="LUK 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 4:29"/>They got up, drove him out of the town, and took him to the brow of the hill on which the town was built, in order to throw him off the cliff. <verse eid="LUK 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 4:30"/>But he walked right through the crowd and went on his way.<verse eid="LUK 4:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus drives out an impure spirit</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 4:31"/>Then he went down to Capernaum, a town in Galilee, and on the Sabbath he taught the people. <verse eid="LUK 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 4:32"/>They were amazed at his teaching, because his words had authority.<verse eid="LUK 4:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 4:33"/>In the synagogue there was a man possessed by a demon, an impure spirit. He cried out at the top of his voice, <verse eid="LUK 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 4:34"/>‘Go away! What do you want with us, Jesus of Nazareth? Have you come to destroy us? I know who you are – the Holy One of God!’<verse eid="LUK 4:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 4:35"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Be quiet!’</char> Jesus said sternly. <char style="wj">‘Come out of him!’</char> Then the demon threw the man down before them all and came out without injuring him.<verse eid="LUK 4:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 4:36"/>All the people were amazed and said to each other, ‘What words these are! With authority and power he gives orders to impure spirits and they come out!’ <verse eid="LUK 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 4:37"/>And the news about him spread throughout the surrounding area.<verse eid="LUK 4:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus heals many</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 4:38"/>Jesus left the synagogue and went to the home of Simon. Now Simon’s mother-in-law was suffering from a high fever, and they asked Jesus to help her. <verse eid="LUK 4:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 4:39"/>So he bent over her and rebuked the fever, and it left her. She got up at once and began to wait on them.<verse eid="LUK 4:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 4:40"/>At sunset, the people brought to Jesus all who had various kinds of illness, and laying his hands on each one, he healed them. <verse eid="LUK 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 4:41"/>Moreover, demons came out of many people, shouting, ‘You are the Son of God!’ But he rebuked them and would not allow them to speak, because they knew he was the Messiah.<verse eid="LUK 4:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 4:42"/>At daybreak, Jesus went out to a solitary place. The people were looking for him and when they came to where he was, they tried to keep him from leaving them. <verse eid="LUK 4:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 4:43"/>But he said, <char style="wj">‘I must proclaim the good news of the kingdom of God to the other towns also, because that is why I was sent.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 4:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 4:44"/>And he kept on preaching in the synagogues of Judea.<verse eid="LUK 4:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="LUK 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus calls his first disciples</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 5:1"/>One day as Jesus was standing by the Lake of Gennesaret,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, Sea of Galilee</char></note> the people were crowding round him and listening to the word of God. <verse eid="LUK 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 5:2"/>He saw at the water’s edge two boats, left there by the fishermen, who were washing their nets. <verse eid="LUK 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 5:3"/>He got into one of the boats, the one belonging to Simon, and asked him to put out a little from the shore. Then he sat down and taught the people from the boat.<verse eid="LUK 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 5:4"/>When he had finished speaking, he said to Simon, <char style="wj">‘Put out into deep water, and let down the nets for a catch.’</char><verse eid="LUK 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 5:5"/>Simon answered, ‘Master, we’ve worked hard all night and haven’t caught anything. But because you say so, I will let down the nets.’<verse eid="LUK 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 5:6"/>When they had done so, they caught such a large number of fish that their nets began to break. <verse eid="LUK 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 5:7"/>So they signalled to their partners in the other boat to come and help them, and they came and filled both boats so full that they began to sink.<verse eid="LUK 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 5:8"/>When Simon Peter saw this, he fell at Jesus’ knees and said, ‘Go away from me, Lord; I am a sinful man!’ <verse eid="LUK 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 5:9"/>For he and all his companions were astonished at the catch of fish they had taken, <verse eid="LUK 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 5:10"/>and so were James and John, the sons of Zebedee, Simon’s partners.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 5:10">Then Jesus said to Simon, <char style="wj">‘Don’t be afraid; from now on you will fish for people.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 5:11"/>So they pulled their boats up on shore, left everything and followed him.<verse eid="LUK 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus heals a man with leprosy</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 5:12"/>While Jesus was in one of the towns, a man came along who was covered with leprosy.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek word traditionally translated </char><char style="fq" closed="false">leprosy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was used for various diseases affecting the skin.</char></note> When he saw Jesus, he fell with his face to the ground and begged him, ‘Lord, if you are willing, you can make me clean.’<verse eid="LUK 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 5:13"/>Jesus reached out his hand and touched the man. <char style="wj">‘I am willing,’</char> he said. <char style="wj">‘Be clean!’</char> And immediately the leprosy left him.<verse eid="LUK 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 5:14"/>Then Jesus ordered him, <char style="wj">‘Don’t tell anyone, but go, show yourself to the priest and offer the sacrifices that Moses commanded for your cleansing, as a testimony to them.’</char><verse eid="LUK 5:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 5:15"/>Yet the news about him spread all the more, so that crowds of people came to hear him and to be healed of their illnesses. <verse eid="LUK 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 5:16"/>But Jesus often withdrew to lonely places and prayed.<verse eid="LUK 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus forgives and heals a paralysed man</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 5:17"/>One day Jesus was teaching, and Pharisees and teachers of the law were sitting there. They had come from every village of Galilee and from Judea and Jerusalem. And the power of the Lord was with Jesus to heal those who were ill. <verse eid="LUK 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 5:18"/>Some men came carrying a paralysed man on a mat and tried to take him into the house to lay him before Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 5:19"/>When they could not find a way to do this because of the crowd, they went up on the roof and lowered him on his mat through the tiles into the middle of the crowd, right in front of Jesus.<verse eid="LUK 5:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 5:20"/>When Jesus saw their faith, he said, <char style="wj">‘Friend, your sins are forgiven.’</char><verse eid="LUK 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 5:21"/>The Pharisees and the teachers of the law began thinking to themselves, ‘Who is this fellow who speaks blasphemy? Who can forgive sins but God alone?’<verse eid="LUK 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 5:22"/>Jesus knew what they were thinking and asked, <char style="wj">‘Why are you thinking these things in your hearts?</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 5:23"/><char style="wj">Which is easier: to say, “Your sins are forgiven,” or to say, “Get up and walk”?</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 5:24"/><char style="wj">But I want you to know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins.’</char> So he said to the paralysed man, <char style="wj">‘I tell you, get up, take your mat and go home.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 5:25"/>Immediately he stood up in front of them, took what he had been lying on and went home praising God. <verse eid="LUK 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 5:26"/>Everyone was amazed and gave praise to God. They were filled with awe and said, ‘We have seen remarkable things today.’<verse eid="LUK 5:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus calls Levi and eats with sinners</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 5:27"/>After this, Jesus went out and saw a tax collector by the name of Levi sitting at his tax booth. <char style="wj">‘Follow me,’</char> Jesus said to him, <verse eid="LUK 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 5:28"/>and Levi got up, left everything and followed him.<verse eid="LUK 5:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 5:29"/>Then Levi held a great banquet for Jesus at his house, and a large crowd of tax collectors and others were eating with them. <verse eid="LUK 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 5:30"/>But the Pharisees and the teachers of the law who belonged to their sect complained to his disciples, ‘Why do you eat and drink with tax collectors and sinners?’<verse eid="LUK 5:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 5:31"/>Jesus answered them, <char style="wj">‘It is not the healthy who need a doctor, but those who are ill.</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 5:32"/><char style="wj">I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.’</char><verse eid="LUK 5:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus questioned about fasting</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 5:33"/>They said to him, ‘John’s disciples often fast and pray, and so do the disciples of the Pharisees, but yours go on eating and drinking.’<verse eid="LUK 5:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 5:34"/>Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘Can you make the friends of the bridegroom fast while he is with them?</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 5:35"/><char style="wj">But the time will come when the bridegroom will be taken from them; in those days they will fast.’</char><verse eid="LUK 5:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 5:36"/>He told them this parable: <char style="wj">‘No-one tears a piece out of a new garment to patch an old one. Otherwise, they will have torn the new garment, and the patch from the new will not match the old.</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 5:37"/><char style="wj">And no-one pours new wine into old wineskins. Otherwise, the new wine will burst the skins; the wine will run out and the wineskins will be ruined.</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 5:38"/><char style="wj">No, new wine must be poured into new wineskins.</char> <verse eid="LUK 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 5:39"/><char style="wj">And no-one after drinking old wine wants the new, for they say, “The old is better.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 5:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="LUK 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus is Lord of the Sabbath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 6:1"/>One Sabbath Jesus was going through the cornfields, and his disciples began to pick some ears of corn, rub them in their hands and eat the grain. <verse eid="LUK 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 6:2"/>Some of the Pharisees asked, ‘Why are you doing what is unlawful on the Sabbath?’<verse eid="LUK 6:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 6:3"/>Jesus answered them, <char style="wj">‘Have you never read what David did when he and his companions were hungry?</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 6:4"/><char style="wj">He entered the house of God, and taking the consecrated bread, he ate what is lawful only for priests to eat. And he also gave some to his companions.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 6:5"/>Then Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">‘The Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath.’</char><verse eid="LUK 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 6:6"/>On another Sabbath he went into the synagogue and was teaching, and a man was there whose right hand was shrivelled. <verse eid="LUK 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 6:7"/>The Pharisees and the teachers of the law were looking for a reason to accuse Jesus, so they watched him closely to see if he would heal on the Sabbath. <verse eid="LUK 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 6:8"/>But Jesus knew what they were thinking and said to the man with the shrivelled hand, <char style="wj">‘Get up and stand in front of everyone.’</char> So he got up and stood there.<verse eid="LUK 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 6:9"/>Then Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">‘I ask you, which is lawful on the Sabbath: to do good or to do evil, to save life or to destroy it?’</char><verse eid="LUK 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 6:10"/>He looked round at them all, and then said to the man, <char style="wj">‘Stretch out your hand.’</char> He did so, and his hand was completely restored. <verse eid="LUK 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 6:11"/>But the Pharisees and the teachers of the law were furious and began to discuss with one another what they might do to Jesus.<verse eid="LUK 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The twelve apostles</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 6:12"/>One of those days Jesus went out to a mountainside to pray, and spent the night praying to God. <verse eid="LUK 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 6:13"/>When morning came, he called his disciples to him and chose twelve of them, whom he also designated apostles:<verse eid="LUK 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 6:14"/>Simon (whom he named Peter) and his brother Andrew,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:14">James,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:14">John,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:14">Philip,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:14">Bartholomew,<verse eid="LUK 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 6:15"/>Matthew,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:15">Thomas,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:15">James son of Alphaeus,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:15">Simon who was called the Zealot,<verse eid="LUK 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 6:16"/>Judas son of James,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="LUK 6:16">and Judas Iscariot, who became a traitor.<verse eid="LUK 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Blessings and woes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 6:17"/>He went down with them and stood on a level place. A large crowd of his disciples was there and a great number of people from all over Judea, from Jerusalem, and from the coastal region around Tyre and Sidon, <verse eid="LUK 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 6:18"/>who had come to hear him and to be healed of their diseases. Those troubled by impure spirits were cured, <verse eid="LUK 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 6:19"/>and the people all tried to touch him, because power was coming from him and healing them all.<verse eid="LUK 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 6:20"/>Looking at his disciples, he said:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 6:20">
    <char style="wj">‘Blessed are you who are poor,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:20">
    <char style="wj">for yours is the kingdom of God.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 6:21"/>
    <char style="wj">Blessed are you who hunger now,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:21">
    <char style="wj">for you will be satisfied.</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 6:21">
    <char style="wj">Blessed are you who weep now,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:21">
    <char style="wj">for you will laugh.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 6:22"/>
    <char style="wj">Blessed are you when people hate you,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:22">
    <char style="wj">when they exclude you and insult you</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:22">
    <char style="wj">and reject your name as evil,</char></para>
  <para style="q3" vid="LUK 6:22">
    <char style="wj">because of the Son of Man.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 6:23"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Rejoice in that day and leap for joy, because great is your reward in heaven. For that is how their ancestors treated the prophets.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 6:24"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But woe to you who are rich,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:24">
    <char style="wj">for you have already received your comfort.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 6:25"/>
    <char style="wj">Woe to you who are well fed now,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:25">
    <char style="wj">for you will go hungry.</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 6:25">
    <char style="wj">Woe to you who laugh now,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:25">
    <char style="wj">for you will mourn and weep.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 6:26"/>
    <char style="wj">Woe to you when everyone speaks well of you,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 6:26">
    <char style="wj">for that is how their ancestors treated the false prophets.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Love for enemies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 6:27"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But to you who are listening I say: love your enemies, do good to those who hate you,</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 6:28"/><char style="wj">bless those who curse you, pray for those who ill-treat you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 6:29"/><char style="wj">If someone slaps you on one cheek, turn to them the other also. If someone takes your coat, do not withhold your shirt from them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 6:30"/><char style="wj">Give to everyone who asks you, and if anyone takes what belongs to you, do not demand it back.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 6:31"/><char style="wj">Do to others as you would have them do to you.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 6:32"/>
    <char style="wj">‘If you love those who love you, what credit is that to you? Even sinners love those who love them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 6:33"/><char style="wj">And if you do good to those who are good to you, what credit is that to you? Even sinners do that.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 6:34"/><char style="wj">And if you lend to those from whom you expect repayment, what credit is that to you? Even sinners lend to sinners, expecting to be repaid in full.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 6:35"/><char style="wj">But love your enemies, do good to them, and lend to them without expecting to get anything back. Then your reward will be great, and you will be children of the Most High, because he is kind to the ungrateful and wicked.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 6:36"/><char style="wj">Be merciful, just as your Father is merciful.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:36"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Judging others</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 6:37"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Do not judge, and you will not be judged. Do not condemn, and you will not be condemned. Forgive, and you will be forgiven.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 6:38"/><char style="wj">Give, and it will be given to you. A good measure, pressed down, shaken together and running over, will be poured into your lap. For with the measure you use, it will be measured to you.’</char><verse eid="LUK 6:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 6:39"/>He also told them this parable: <char style="wj">‘Can the blind lead the blind? Will they not both fall into a pit?</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 6:40"/><char style="wj">The student is not above the teacher, but everyone who is fully trained will be like their teacher.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 6:41"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Why do you look at the speck of sawdust in your brother’s eye and pay no attention to the plank in your own eye?</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 6:42"/><char style="wj">How can you say to your brother, “Brother, let me take the speck out of your eye,” when you yourself fail to see the plank in your own eye? You hypocrite, first take the plank out of your eye, and then you will see clearly to remove the speck from your brother’s eye.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:42"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A tree and its fruit</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 6:43"/>
    <char style="wj">‘No good tree bears bad fruit, nor does a bad tree bear good fruit.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 6:44"/><char style="wj">Each tree is recognised by its own fruit. People do not pick figs from thorn-bushes, or grapes from briers.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 6:45"/><char style="wj">A good man brings good things out of the good stored up in his heart, and an evil man brings evil things out of the evil stored up in his heart. For the mouth speaks what the heart is full of.</char><verse eid="LUK 6:45"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The wise and foolish builders</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 6:46"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Why do you call me, “Lord, Lord,” and do not do what I say?</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 6:47"/><char style="wj">As for everyone who comes to me and hears my words and puts them into practice, I will show you what they are like.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 6:48"/><char style="wj">They are like a man building a house, who dug down deep and laid the foundation on rock. When the flood came, the torrent struck that house but could not shake it, because it was well built.</char> <verse eid="LUK 6:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 6:49"/><char style="wj">But the one who hears my words and does not put them into practice is like a man who built a house on the ground without a foundation. The moment the torrent struck that house, it collapsed and its destruction was complete.’</char><verse eid="LUK 6:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="LUK 7"/>
  <para style="s1">The faith of the centurion</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 7:1"/>When Jesus had finished saying all this to the people who were listening, he entered Capernaum. <verse eid="LUK 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 7:2"/>There a centurion’s servant, whom his master valued highly, was ill and about to die. <verse eid="LUK 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 7:3"/>The centurion heard of Jesus and sent some elders of the Jews to him, asking him to come and heal his servant. <verse eid="LUK 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 7:4"/>When they came to Jesus, they pleaded earnestly with him, ‘This man deserves to have you do this, <verse eid="LUK 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 7:5"/>because he loves our nation and has built our synagogue.’ <verse eid="LUK 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 7:6"/>So Jesus went with them.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 7:6">He was not far from the house when the centurion sent friends to say to him: ‘Lord, don’t trouble yourself, for I do not deserve to have you come under my roof. <verse eid="LUK 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 7:7"/>That is why I did not even consider myself worthy to come to you. But say the word, and my servant will be healed. <verse eid="LUK 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 7:8"/>For I myself am a man under authority, with soldiers under me. I tell this one, “Go”, and he goes; and that one, “Come”, and he comes. I say to my servant, “Do this”, and he does it.’<verse eid="LUK 7:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 7:9"/>When Jesus heard this, he was amazed at him, and turning to the crowd following him, he said, <char style="wj">‘I tell you, I have not found such great faith even in Israel.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 7:10"/>Then the men who had been sent returned to the house and found the servant well.<verse eid="LUK 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus raises a widow’s son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 7:11"/>Soon afterwards, Jesus went to a town called Nain, and his disciples and a large crowd went along with him. <verse eid="LUK 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 7:12"/>As he approached the town gate, a dead person was being carried out – the only son of his mother, and she was a widow. And a large crowd from the town was with her. <verse eid="LUK 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 7:13"/>When the Lord saw her, his heart went out to her and he said, <char style="wj">‘Don’t cry.’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 7:14"/>Then he went up and touched the bier they were carrying him on, and the bearers stood still. He said, <char style="wj">‘Young man, I say to you, get up!’</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 7:15"/>The dead man sat up and began to talk, and Jesus gave him back to his mother.<verse eid="LUK 7:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 7:16"/>They were all filled with awe and praised God. ‘A great prophet has appeared among us,’ they said. ‘God has come to help his people.’ <verse eid="LUK 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 7:17"/>This news about Jesus spread throughout Judea and the surrounding country.<verse eid="LUK 7:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus and John the Baptist</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 7:18"/>John’s disciples told him about all these things. Calling two of them, <verse eid="LUK 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 7:19"/>he sent them to the Lord to ask, ‘Are you the one who is to come, or should we expect someone else?’<verse eid="LUK 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 7:20"/>When the men came to Jesus, they said, ‘John the Baptist sent us to you to ask, “Are you the one who is to come, or should we expect someone else?” ’<verse eid="LUK 7:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 7:21"/>At that very time Jesus cured many who had diseases, illnesses and evil spirits, and gave sight to many who were blind. <verse eid="LUK 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 7:22"/>So he replied to the messengers, <char style="wj">‘Go back and report to John what you have seen and heard: the blind receive sight, the lame walk, those who have leprosy</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek word traditionally translated </char><char style="fq" closed="false">leprosy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was used for various diseases affecting the skin.</char></note> <char style="wj">are cleansed, the deaf hear, the dead are raised, and the good news is proclaimed to the poor.</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 7:23"/><char style="wj">Blessed is anyone who does not stumble on account of me.’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 7:24"/>After John’s messengers left, Jesus began to speak to the crowd about John: <char style="wj">‘What did you go out into the wilderness to see? A reed swayed by the wind?</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 7:25"/><char style="wj">If not, what did you go out to see? A man dressed in fine clothes? No, those who wear expensive clothes and indulge in luxury are in palaces.</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 7:26"/><char style="wj">But what did you go out to see? A prophet? Yes, I tell you, and more than a prophet.</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 7:27"/><char style="wj">This is the one about whom it is written:</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 7:27">
    <char style="wj">‘ “I will send my messenger ahead of you,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 7:27">
    <char style="wj">who will prepare your way before you.”</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">7:27 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">
        <char style="xt">
          <ref loc="MAL 3:1">Mal. 3:1</ref>
        </char>
      </char>
    </note><verse eid="LUK 7:27"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 7:28"/>
    <char style="wj">I tell you, among those born of women there is no-one greater than John; yet the one who is least in the kingdom of God is greater than he.’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 7:29"/>(All the people, even the tax collectors, when they heard Jesus’ words, acknowledged that God’s way was right, because they had been baptised by John. <verse eid="LUK 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 7:30"/>But the Pharisees and the experts in the law rejected God’s purpose for themselves, because they had not been baptised by John.)<verse eid="LUK 7:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 7:31"/>Jesus went on to say, <char style="wj">‘To what, then, can I compare the people of this generation? What are they like?</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 7:32"/><char style="wj">They are like children sitting in the market-place and calling out to each other:</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 7:32">
    <char style="wj">‘ “We played the pipe for you,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 7:32">
    <char style="wj">and you did not dance;</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 7:32">
    <char style="wj">we sang a dirge,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 7:32">
    <char style="wj">and you did not cry.”</char><verse eid="LUK 7:32"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 7:33"/>
    <char style="wj">For John the Baptist came neither eating bread nor drinking wine, and you say, “He has a demon.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 7:34"/><char style="wj">The Son of Man came eating and drinking, and you say, “Here is a glutton and a drunkard, a friend of tax collectors and sinners.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 7:35"/><char style="wj">But wisdom is proved right by all her children.’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus anointed by a sinful woman</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 7:36"/>When one of the Pharisees invited Jesus to have dinner with him, he went to the Pharisee’s house and reclined at the table. <verse eid="LUK 7:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 7:37"/>A woman in that town who lived a sinful life learned that Jesus was eating at the Pharisee’s house, so she came there with an alabaster jar of perfume. <verse eid="LUK 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 7:38"/>As she stood behind him at his feet weeping, she began to wet his feet with her tears. Then she wiped them with her hair, kissed them and poured perfume on them.<verse eid="LUK 7:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 7:39"/>When the Pharisee who had invited him saw this, he said to himself, ‘If this man were a prophet, he would know who is touching him and what kind of woman she is – that she is a sinner.’<verse eid="LUK 7:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 7:40"/>Jesus answered him, <char style="wj">‘Simon, I have something to tell you.’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 7:40">‘Tell me, teacher,’ he said.<verse eid="LUK 7:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 7:41"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Two people owed money to a certain money-lender. One owed him five hundred denarii,</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">7:41 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">A denarius was the usual daily wage of a day labourer (see <char style="xt"><ref loc="MAT 20:2">Matt. 20:2</ref></char>).</char>
    </note> <char style="wj">and the other fifty.</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 7:42"/><char style="wj">Neither of them had the money to pay him back, so he forgave the debts of both. Now which of them will love him more?’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 7:43"/>Simon replied, ‘I suppose the one who had the bigger debt forgiven.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 7:43">
    <char style="wj">‘You have judged correctly,’</char> Jesus said.<verse eid="LUK 7:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 7:44"/>Then he turned towards the woman and said to Simon, <char style="wj">‘Do you see this woman? I came into your house. You did not give me any water for my feet, but she wet my feet with her tears and wiped them with her hair.</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 7:45"/><char style="wj">You did not give me a kiss, but this woman, from the time I entered, has not stopped kissing my feet.</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 7:46"/><char style="wj">You did not put oil on my head, but she has poured perfume on my feet.</char> <verse eid="LUK 7:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 7:47"/><char style="wj">Therefore, I tell you, her many sins have been forgiven – as her great love has shown. But whoever has been forgiven little loves little.’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 7:48"/>Then Jesus said to her, <char style="wj">‘Your sins are forgiven.’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 7:49"/>The other guests began to say among themselves, ‘Who is this who even forgives sins?’<verse eid="LUK 7:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 7:50"/>Jesus said to the woman, <char style="wj">‘Your faith has saved you; go in peace.’</char><verse eid="LUK 7:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="LUK 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the sower</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 8:1"/>After this, Jesus travelled about from one town and village to another, proclaiming the good news of the kingdom of God. The Twelve were with him, <verse eid="LUK 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 8:2"/>and also some women who had been cured of evil spirits and diseases: Mary (called Magdalene) from whom seven demons had come out; <verse eid="LUK 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 8:3"/>Joanna the wife of Chuza, the manager of Herod’s household; Susanna; and many others. These women were helping to support them out of their own means.<verse eid="LUK 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 8:4"/>While a large crowd was gathering and people were coming to Jesus from town after town, he told this parable: <verse eid="LUK 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 8:5"/><char style="wj">‘A farmer went out to sow his seed. As he was scattering the seed, some fell along the path; it was trampled on, and the birds ate it up.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 8:6"/><char style="wj">Some fell on rocky ground, and when it came up, the plants withered because they had no moisture.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 8:7"/><char style="wj">Other seed fell among thorns, which grew up with it and choked the plants.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 8:8"/><char style="wj">Still other seed fell on good soil. It came up and yielded a crop, a hundred times more than was sown.’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 8:8">When he said this, he called out, <char style="wj">‘Whoever has ears to hear, let them hear.’</char><verse eid="LUK 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 8:9"/>His disciples asked him what this parable meant. <verse eid="LUK 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 8:10"/>He said, <char style="wj">‘The knowledge of the secrets of the kingdom of God has been given to you, but to others I speak in parables, so that,</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 8:10">
    <char style="wj">‘ “though seeing, they may not see;</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 8:10">
    <char style="wj">though hearing, they may not understand.”</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">8:10 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">
        <char style="xt">
          <ref loc="ISA 6:9">Isaiah 6:9</ref>
        </char>
      </char>
    </note><verse eid="LUK 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 8:11"/>
    <char style="wj">‘This is the meaning of the parable: the seed is the word of God.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 8:12"/><char style="wj">Those along the path are the ones who hear, and then the devil comes and takes away the word from their hearts, so that they may not believe and be saved.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 8:13"/><char style="wj">Those on the rocky ground are the ones who receive the word with joy when they hear it, but they have no root. They believe for a while, but in the time of testing they fall away.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 8:14"/><char style="wj">The seed that fell among thorns stands for those who hear, but as they go on their way they are choked by life’s worries, riches and pleasures, and they do not mature.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 8:15"/><char style="wj">But the seed on good soil stands for those with a noble and good heart, who hear the word, retain it, and by persevering produce a crop.</char><verse eid="LUK 8:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A lamp on a stand</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 8:16"/>
    <char style="wj">‘No-one lights a lamp and hides it in a clay jar or puts it under a bed. Instead, they put it on a stand, so that those who come in can see the light.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 8:17"/><char style="wj">For there is nothing hidden that will not be disclosed, and nothing concealed that will not be known or brought out into the open.</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 8:18"/><char style="wj">Therefore consider carefully how you listen. Whoever has will be given more; whoever does not have, even what they think they have will be taken from them.’</char><verse eid="LUK 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus’ mother and brothers</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 8:19"/>Now Jesus’ mother and brothers came to see him, but they were not able to get near him because of the crowd. <verse eid="LUK 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 8:20"/>Someone told him, ‘Your mother and brothers are standing outside, wanting to see you.’<verse eid="LUK 8:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 8:21"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘My mother and brothers are those who hear God’s word and put it into practice.’</char><verse eid="LUK 8:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus calms the storm</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 8:22"/>One day Jesus said to his disciples, <char style="wj">‘Let us go over to the other side of the lake.’</char> So they got into a boat and set out. <verse eid="LUK 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 8:23"/>As they sailed, he fell asleep. A squall came down on the lake, so that the boat was being swamped, and they were in great danger.<verse eid="LUK 8:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 8:24"/>The disciples went and woke him, saying, ‘Master, Master, we’re going to drown!’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 8:24">He got up and rebuked the wind and the raging waters; the storm subsided, and all was calm. <verse eid="LUK 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 8:25"/><char style="wj">‘Where is your faith?’</char> he asked his disciples.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 8:25">In fear and amazement they asked one another, ‘Who is this? He commands even the winds and the water, and they obey him.’<verse eid="LUK 8:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus restores a demon-possessed man</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 8:26"/>They sailed to the region of the Gerasenes,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:26 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gadarenes</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; other manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gergesenes</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verse 37</char></note> which is across the lake from Galilee. <verse eid="LUK 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 8:27"/>When Jesus stepped ashore, he was met by a demon-possessed man from the town. For a long time this man had not worn clothes or lived in a house, but had lived in the tombs. <verse eid="LUK 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 8:28"/>When he saw Jesus, he cried out and fell at his feet, shouting at the top of his voice, ‘What do you want with me, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I beg you, don’t torture me!’ <verse eid="LUK 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 8:29"/>For Jesus had commanded the impure spirit to come out of the man. Many times it had seized him, and though he was chained hand and foot and kept under guard, he had broken his chains and had been driven by the demon into solitary places.<verse eid="LUK 8:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 8:30"/>Jesus asked him, <char style="wj">‘What is your name?’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 8:30">‘Legion,’ he replied, because many demons had gone into him. <verse eid="LUK 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 8:31"/>And they begged Jesus repeatedly not to order them to go into the Abyss.<verse eid="LUK 8:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 8:32"/>A large herd of pigs was feeding there on the hillside. The demons begged Jesus to let them go into the pigs, and he gave them permission. <verse eid="LUK 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 8:33"/>When the demons came out of the man, they went into the pigs, and the herd rushed down the steep bank into the lake and was drowned.<verse eid="LUK 8:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 8:34"/>When those tending the pigs saw what had happened, they ran off and reported this in the town and countryside, <verse eid="LUK 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 8:35"/>and the people went out to see what had happened. When they came to Jesus, they found the man from whom the demons had gone out, sitting at Jesus’ feet, dressed and in his right mind; and they were afraid. <verse eid="LUK 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 8:36"/>Those who had seen it told the people how the demon-possessed man had been cured. <verse eid="LUK 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 8:37"/>Then all the people of the region of the Gerasenes asked Jesus to leave them, because they were overcome with fear. So he got into the boat and left.<verse eid="LUK 8:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 8:38"/>The man from whom the demons had gone out begged to go with him, but Jesus sent him away, saying, <verse eid="LUK 8:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 8:39"/><char style="wj">‘Return home and tell how much God has done for you.’</char> So the man went away and told all over the town how much Jesus had done for him.<verse eid="LUK 8:39"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus raises a dead girl and heals a sick woman</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 8:40"/>Now when Jesus returned, a crowd welcomed him, for they were all expecting him. <verse eid="LUK 8:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 8:41"/>Then a man named Jairus, a synagogue leader, came and fell at Jesus’ feet, pleading with him to come to his house <verse eid="LUK 8:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 8:42"/>because his only daughter, a girl of about twelve, was dying.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 8:42">As Jesus was on his way, the crowds almost crushed him. <verse eid="LUK 8:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 8:43"/>And a woman was there who had been subject to bleeding for twelve years,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:43 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Many manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">years, and she had spent all she had on doctors</char></note> but no-one could heal her. <verse eid="LUK 8:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 8:44"/>She came up behind him and touched the edge of his cloak, and immediately her bleeding stopped.<verse eid="LUK 8:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 8:45"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Who touched me?’</char> Jesus asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 8:45">When they all denied it, Peter said, ‘Master, the people are crowding and pressing against you.’<verse eid="LUK 8:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 8:46"/>But Jesus said, <char style="wj">‘Someone touched me; I know that power has gone out from me.’</char><verse eid="LUK 8:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 8:47"/>Then the woman, seeing that she could not go unnoticed, came trembling and fell at his feet. In the presence of all the people, she told why she had touched him and how she had been instantly healed. <verse eid="LUK 8:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 8:48"/>Then he said to her, <char style="wj">‘Daughter, your faith has healed you. Go in peace.’</char><verse eid="LUK 8:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 8:49"/>While Jesus was still speaking, someone came from the house of Jairus, the synagogue leader. ‘Your daughter is dead,’ he said. ‘Don’t bother the teacher anymore.’<verse eid="LUK 8:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 8:50"/>Hearing this, Jesus said to Jairus, <char style="wj">‘Don’t be afraid; just believe, and she will be healed.’</char><verse eid="LUK 8:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 8:51"/>When he arrived at the house of Jairus, he did not let anyone go in with him except Peter, John and James, and the child’s father and mother. <verse eid="LUK 8:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 8:52"/>Meanwhile, all the people were wailing and mourning for her. <char style="wj">‘Stop wailing,’</char> Jesus said. <char style="wj">‘She is not dead but asleep.’</char><verse eid="LUK 8:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 8:53"/>They laughed at him, knowing that she was dead. <verse eid="LUK 8:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 8:54"/>But he took her by the hand and said, <char style="wj">‘My child, get up!’</char> <verse eid="LUK 8:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 8:55"/>Her spirit returned, and at once she stood up. Then Jesus told them to give her something to eat. <verse eid="LUK 8:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 8:56"/>Her parents were astonished, but he ordered them not to tell anyone what had happened.<verse eid="LUK 8:56"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="LUK 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus sends out the Twelve</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 9:1"/>When Jesus had called the Twelve together, he gave them power and authority to drive out all demons and to cure diseases, <verse eid="LUK 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 9:2"/>and he sent them out to proclaim the kingdom of God and to heal those who were ill. <verse eid="LUK 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 9:3"/>He told them: <char style="wj">‘Take nothing for the journey – no staff, no bag, no bread, no money, no extra shirt.</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 9:4"/><char style="wj">Whatever house you enter, stay there until you leave that town.</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 9:5"/><char style="wj">If people do not welcome you, leave their town and shake the dust off your feet as a testimony against them.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 9:6"/>So they set out and went from village to village, proclaiming the good news and healing people everywhere.<verse eid="LUK 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 9:7"/>Now Herod the tetrarch heard about all that was going on. And he was perplexed because some were saying that John had been raised from the dead, <verse eid="LUK 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 9:8"/>others that Elijah had appeared, and still others that one of the prophets of long ago had come back to life. <verse eid="LUK 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 9:9"/>But Herod said, ‘I beheaded John. Who, then, is this I hear such things about?’ And he tried to see him.<verse eid="LUK 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus feeds the five thousand</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 9:10"/>When the apostles returned, they reported to Jesus what they had done. Then he took them with him and they withdrew by themselves to a town called Bethsaida, <verse eid="LUK 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 9:11"/>but the crowds learned about it and followed him. He welcomed them and spoke to them about the kingdom of God, and healed those who needed healing.<verse eid="LUK 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 9:12"/>Late in the afternoon the Twelve came to him and said, ‘Send the crowd away so they can go to the surrounding villages and countryside and find food and lodging, because we are in a remote place here.’<verse eid="LUK 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 9:13"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘You give them something to eat.’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 9:13">They answered, ‘We have only five loaves of bread and two fish – unless we go and buy food for all this crowd.’ <verse eid="LUK 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 9:14"/>(About five thousand men were there.)</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 9:14">But he said to his disciples, <char style="wj">‘Make them sit down in groups of about fifty each.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 9:15"/>The disciples did so, and everyone sat down. <verse eid="LUK 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 9:16"/>Taking the five loaves and the two fish and looking up to heaven, he gave thanks and broke them. Then he gave them to the disciples to distribute to the people. <verse eid="LUK 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 9:17"/>They all ate and were satisfied, and the disciples picked up twelve basketfuls of broken pieces that were left over.<verse eid="LUK 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter declares that Jesus is the Messiah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 9:18"/>Once when Jesus was praying in private and his disciples were with him, he asked them, <char style="wj">‘Who do the crowds say I am?’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 9:19"/>They replied, ‘Some say John the Baptist; others say Elijah; and still others, that one of the prophets of long ago has come back to life.’<verse eid="LUK 9:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 9:20"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But what about you?’</char> he asked. <char style="wj">‘Who do you say I am?’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 9:20">Peter answered, ‘God’s Messiah.’<verse eid="LUK 9:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus predicts his death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 9:21"/>Jesus strictly warned them not to tell this to anyone. <verse eid="LUK 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 9:22"/>And he said, <char style="wj">‘The Son of Man must suffer many things and be rejected by the elders, the chief priests and the teachers of the law, and he must be killed and on the third day be raised to life.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 9:23"/>Then he said to them all: <char style="wj">‘Whoever wants to be my disciple must deny themselves and take up their cross daily and follow me.</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 9:24"/><char style="wj">For whoever wants to save their life will lose it, but whoever loses their life for me will save it.</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 9:25"/><char style="wj">What good is it for someone to gain the whole world, and yet lose or forfeit their very self?</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 9:26"/><char style="wj">Whoever is ashamed of me and my words, the Son of Man will be ashamed of them when he comes in his glory and in the glory of the Father and of the holy angels.</char><verse eid="LUK 9:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 9:27"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Truly I tell you, some who are standing here will not taste death before they see the kingdom of God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The transfiguration</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 9:28"/>About eight days after Jesus said this, he took Peter, John and James with him and went up onto a mountain to pray. <verse eid="LUK 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 9:29"/>As he was praying, the appearance of his face changed, and his clothes became as bright as a flash of lightning. <verse eid="LUK 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 9:30"/>Two men, Moses and Elijah, appeared in glorious splendour, talking with Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 9:31"/>They spoke about his departure,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Greek </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">exodos</char></note> which he was about to bring to fulfilment at Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 9:32"/>Peter and his companions were very sleepy, but when they became fully awake, they saw his glory and the two men standing with him. <verse eid="LUK 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 9:33"/>As the men were leaving Jesus, Peter said to him, ‘Master, it is good for us to be here. Let us put up three shelters – one for you, one for Moses and one for Elijah.’ (He did not know what he was saying.)<verse eid="LUK 9:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 9:34"/>While he was speaking, a cloud appeared and covered them, and they were afraid as they entered the cloud. <verse eid="LUK 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 9:35"/>A voice came from the cloud, saying, ‘This is my Son, whom I have chosen; listen to him.’ <verse eid="LUK 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 9:36"/>When the voice had spoken, they found that Jesus was alone. The disciples kept this to themselves and did not tell anyone at that time what they had seen.<verse eid="LUK 9:36"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus heals a demon-possessed boy</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 9:37"/>The next day, when they came down from the mountain, a large crowd met him. <verse eid="LUK 9:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 9:38"/>A man in the crowd called out, ‘Teacher, I beg you to look at my son, for he is my only child. <verse eid="LUK 9:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 9:39"/>A spirit seizes him and he suddenly screams; it throws him into convulsions so that he foams at the mouth. It scarcely ever leaves him and is destroying him. <verse eid="LUK 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 9:40"/>I begged your disciples to drive it out, but they could not.’<verse eid="LUK 9:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 9:41"/>
    <char style="wj">‘You unbelieving and perverse generation,’</char> Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘how long shall I stay with you and put up with you? Bring your son here.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 9:42"/>Even while the boy was coming, the demon threw him to the ground in a convulsion. But Jesus rebuked the impure spirit, healed the boy and gave him back to his father. <verse eid="LUK 9:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 9:43"/>And they were all amazed at the greatness of God.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="LUK 9:43">Jesus predicts his death a second time</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 9:43">While everyone was marvelling at all that Jesus did, he said to his disciples, <verse eid="LUK 9:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 9:44"/><char style="wj">‘Listen carefully to what I am about to tell you: the Son of Man is going to be delivered into the hands of men.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 9:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 9:45"/>But they did not understand what this meant. It was hidden from them, so that they did not grasp it, and they were afraid to ask him about it.<verse eid="LUK 9:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 9:46"/>An argument started among the disciples as to which of them would be the greatest. <verse eid="LUK 9:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 9:47"/>Jesus, knowing their thoughts, took a little child and made him stand beside him. <verse eid="LUK 9:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 9:48"/>Then he said to them, <char style="wj">‘Whoever welcomes this little child in my name welcomes me; and whoever welcomes me welcomes the one who sent me. For it is the one who is least among you all who is the greatest.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 9:49"/>‘Master,’ said John, ‘we saw someone driving out demons in your name and we tried to stop him, because he is not one of us.’<verse eid="LUK 9:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 9:50"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Do not stop him,’</char> Jesus said, <char style="wj">‘for whoever is not against you is for you.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:50"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Samaritan opposition</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 9:51"/>As the time approached for him to be taken up to heaven, Jesus resolutely set out for Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 9:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 9:52"/>And he sent messengers on ahead, who went into a Samaritan village to get things ready for him; <verse eid="LUK 9:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 9:53"/>but the people there did not welcome him, because he was heading for Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 9:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 9:54"/>When the disciples James and John saw this, they asked, ‘Lord, do you want us to call fire down from heaven to destroy them<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:54 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">them, just as Elijah did</char></note>?’ <verse eid="LUK 9:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 9:55"/>But Jesus turned and rebuked them. <verse eid="LUK 9:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 9:56"/>Then he and his disciples went to another village.<verse eid="LUK 9:56"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The cost of following Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 9:57"/>As they were walking along the road, a man said to him, ‘I will follow you wherever you go.’<verse eid="LUK 9:57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 9:58"/>Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘Foxes have dens and birds have nests, but the Son of Man has nowhere to lay his head.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:58"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 9:59"/>He said to another man, <char style="wj">‘Follow me.’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 9:59">But he replied, ‘Lord, first let me go and bury my father.’<verse eid="LUK 9:59"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="LUK 9:60"/>Jesus said to him, <char style="wj">‘Let the dead bury their own dead, but you go and proclaim the kingdom of God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:60"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="61" style="v" sid="LUK 9:61"/>Still another said, ‘I will follow you, Lord; but first let me go back and say goodbye to my family.’<verse eid="LUK 9:61"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="62" style="v" sid="LUK 9:62"/>Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘No-one who puts a hand to the plough and looks back is fit for service in the kingdom of God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 9:62"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="LUK 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus sends out the seventy-two</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 10:1"/>After this the Lord appointed seventy-two<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">seventy</char><char style="ft" closed="false">; also in verse 17</char></note> others and sent them two by two ahead of him to every town and place where he was about to go. <verse eid="LUK 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 10:2"/>He told them, <char style="wj">‘The harvest is plentiful, but the workers are few. Ask the Lord of the harvest, therefore, to send out workers into his harvest field.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 10:3"/><char style="wj">Go! I am sending you out like lambs among wolves.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 10:4"/><char style="wj">Do not take a purse or bag or sandals; and do not greet anyone on the road.</char><verse eid="LUK 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 10:5"/>
    <char style="wj">‘When you enter a house, first say, “Peace to this house.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 10:6"/><char style="wj">If someone who promotes peace is there, your peace will rest on them; if not, it will return to you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 10:7"/><char style="wj">Stay there, eating and drinking whatever they give you, for the worker deserves his wages. Do not move around from house to house.</char><verse eid="LUK 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 10:8"/>
    <char style="wj">‘When you enter a town and are welcomed, eat what is offered to you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 10:9"/><char style="wj">Heal those there who are ill and tell them, “The kingdom of God has come near to you.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 10:10"/><char style="wj">But when you enter a town and are not welcomed, go into its streets and say,</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 10:11"/><char style="wj">“Even the dust of your town we wipe from our feet as a warning to you. Yet be sure of this: the kingdom of God has come near.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 10:12"/><char style="wj">I tell you, it will be more bearable on that day for Sodom than for that town.</char><verse eid="LUK 10:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 10:13"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! For if the miracles that were performed in you had been performed in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago, sitting in sackcloth and ashes.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 10:14"/><char style="wj">But it will be more bearable for Tyre and Sidon at the judgment than for you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 10:15"/><char style="wj">And you, Capernaum, will you be lifted to the heavens? No, you will go down to Hades.</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, the realm of the dead</char></note><verse eid="LUK 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 10:16"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Whoever listens to you listens to me; whoever rejects you rejects me; but whoever rejects me rejects him who sent me.’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 10:17"/>The seventy-two returned with joy and said, ‘Lord, even the demons submit to us in your name.’<verse eid="LUK 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 10:18"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘I saw Satan fall like lightning from heaven.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 10:19"/><char style="wj">I have given you authority to trample on snakes and scorpions and to overcome all the power of the enemy; nothing will harm you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 10:20"/><char style="wj">However, do not rejoice that the spirits submit to you, but rejoice that your names are written in heaven.’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 10:21"/>At that time Jesus, full of joy through the Holy Spirit, said, <char style="wj">‘I praise you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have hidden these things from the wise and learned, and revealed them to little children. Yes, Father, for this is what you were pleased to do.</char><verse eid="LUK 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 10:22"/>
    <char style="wj">‘All things have been committed to me by my Father. No-one knows who the Son is except the Father, and no-one knows who the Father is except the Son and those to whom the Son chooses to reveal him.’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 10:23"/>Then he turned to his disciples and said privately, <char style="wj">‘Blessed are the eyes that see what you see.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 10:24"/><char style="wj">For I tell you that many prophets and kings wanted to see what you see but did not see it, and to hear what you hear but did not hear it.’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the good Samaritan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 10:25"/>On one occasion an expert in the law stood up to test Jesus. ‘Teacher,’ he asked, ‘what must I do to inherit eternal life?’<verse eid="LUK 10:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 10:26"/>
    <char style="wj">‘What is written in the Law?’</char> he replied. <char style="wj">‘How do you read it?’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 10:27"/>He answered, ‘ “Love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your strength and with all your mind”<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 6:5">Deut. 6:5</ref></char></char></note>; and, “Love your neighbour as yourself.”<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:27 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="LEV 19:18">Lev. 19:18</ref></char></char></note>’<verse eid="LUK 10:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 10:28"/>
    <char style="wj">‘You have answered correctly,’</char> Jesus replied. <char style="wj">‘Do this and you will live.’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 10:29"/>But he wanted to justify himself, so he asked Jesus, ‘And who is my neighbour?’<verse eid="LUK 10:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 10:30"/>In reply Jesus said: <char style="wj">‘A man was going down from Jerusalem to Jericho, when he was attacked by robbers. They stripped him of his clothes, beat him and went away, leaving him half-dead.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 10:31"/><char style="wj">A priest happened to be going down the same road, and when he saw the man, he passed by on the other side.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 10:32"/><char style="wj">So too, a Levite, when he came to the place and saw him, passed by on the other side.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 10:33"/><char style="wj">But a Samaritan, as he travelled, came where the man was; and when he saw him, he took pity on him.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 10:34"/><char style="wj">He went to him and bandaged his wounds, pouring on oil and wine. Then he put the man on his own donkey, brought him to an inn and took care of him.</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 10:35"/><char style="wj">The next day he took out two denarii</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A denarius was the usual daily wage of a day labourer (see <char style="xt"><ref loc="MAT 20:2">Matt. 20:2</ref></char>).</char></note> <char style="wj">and gave them to the innkeeper. “Look after him,” he said, “and when I return, I will reimburse you for any extra expense you may have.”</char><verse eid="LUK 10:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 10:36"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Which of these three do you think was a neighbour to the man who fell into the hands of robbers?’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 10:37"/>The expert in the law replied, ‘The one who had mercy on him.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 10:37">Jesus told him, <char style="wj">‘Go and do likewise.’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">At the home of Martha and Mary</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 10:38"/>As Jesus and his disciples were on their way, he came to a village where a woman named Martha opened her home to him. <verse eid="LUK 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 10:39"/>She had a sister called Mary, who sat at the Lord’s feet listening to what he said. <verse eid="LUK 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 10:40"/>But Martha was distracted by all the preparations that had to be made. She came to him and asked, ‘Lord, don’t you care that my sister has left me to do the work by myself? Tell her to help me!’<verse eid="LUK 10:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 10:41"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Martha, Martha,’</char> the Lord answered, <char style="wj">‘you are worried and upset about many things,</char> <verse eid="LUK 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 10:42"/><char style="wj">but few things are needed – or indeed only one.</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:42 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">but only one thing is needed</char></note> <char style="wj">Mary has chosen what is better, and it will not be taken away from her.’</char><verse eid="LUK 10:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="LUK 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus’ teaching on prayer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 11:1"/>One day Jesus was praying in a certain place. When he finished, one of his disciples said to him, ‘Lord, teach us to pray, just as John taught his disciples.’<verse eid="LUK 11:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 11:2"/>He said to them, <char style="wj">‘When you pray, say:</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 11:2">
    <char style="wj">‘ “Father,</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">11:2 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char>
      <char style="fqa" closed="false">Our Father in heaven</char>
    </note></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 11:2">
    <char style="wj">hallowed be your name,</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 11:2">
    <char style="wj">your kingdom come.</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">11:2 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char>
      <char style="fqa" closed="false">come. May your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.</char>
    </note><verse eid="LUK 11:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 11:3"/>
    <char style="wj">Give us each day our daily bread.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 11:4"/>
    <char style="wj">Forgive us our sins,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 11:4">
    <char style="wj">for we also forgive everyone who sins against us.</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">11:4 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Greek </char>
      <char style="fqa" closed="false">everyone who is indebted to us</char>
    </note></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 11:4">
    <char style="wj">And lead us not into temptation.</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">11:4 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char>
      <char style="fqa" closed="false">temptation, but deliver us from the evil one</char>
    </note>
    <char style="wj">” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 11:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 11:5"/>Then Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">‘Suppose you have a friend, and you go to him at midnight and say, “Friend, lend me three loaves of bread;</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 11:6"/><char style="wj">a friend of mine on a journey has come to me, and I have no food to offer him.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 11:7"/><char style="wj">And suppose the one inside answers, “Don’t bother me. The door is already locked, and my children and I are in bed. I can’t get up and give you anything.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 11:8"/><char style="wj">I tell you, even though he will not get up and give you the bread because of friendship, yet because of your shameless audacity</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">yet to preserve his good name</char></note> <char style="wj">he will surely get up and give you as much as you need.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 11:9"/>
    <char style="wj">‘So I say to you: ask and it will be given to you; seek and you will find; knock and the door will be opened to you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 11:10"/><char style="wj">For everyone who asks receives; the one who seeks finds; and to the one who knocks, the door will be opened.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 11:11"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Which of you fathers, if your son asks for</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">11:11 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char>
      <char style="fqa" closed="false">for bread, will give him a stone? Or if he asks for</char>
    </note> <char style="wj">a fish, will give him a snake instead?</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 11:12"/><char style="wj">Or if he asks for an egg, will give him a scorpion?</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 11:13"/><char style="wj">If you then, though you are evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father in heaven give the Holy Spirit to those who ask him!’</char><verse eid="LUK 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus and Beelzebul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 11:14"/>Jesus was driving out a demon that was mute. When the demon left, the man who had been mute spoke, and the crowd was amazed. <verse eid="LUK 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 11:15"/>But some of them said, ‘By Beelzebul, the prince of demons, he is driving out demons.’ <verse eid="LUK 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 11:16"/>Others tested him by asking for a sign from heaven.<verse eid="LUK 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 11:17"/>Jesus knew their thoughts and said to them: <char style="wj">‘Any kingdom divided against itself will be ruined, and a house divided against itself will fall.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 11:18"/><char style="wj">If Satan is divided against himself, how can his kingdom stand? I say this because you claim that I drive out demons by Beelzebul.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 11:19"/><char style="wj">Now if I drive out demons by Beelzebul, by whom do your followers drive them out? So then, they will be your judges.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 11:20"/><char style="wj">But if I drive out demons by the finger of God, then the kingdom of God has come upon you.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 11:21"/>
    <char style="wj">‘When a strong man, fully armed, guards his own house, his possessions are safe.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 11:22"/><char style="wj">But when someone stronger attacks and overpowers him, he takes away the armour in which the man trusted and divides up his plunder.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 11:23"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Whoever is not with me is against me, and whoever does not gather with me scatters.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 11:24"/>
    <char style="wj">‘When an impure spirit comes out of a person, it goes through arid places seeking rest and does not find it. Then it says, “I will return to the house I left.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 11:25"/><char style="wj">When it arrives, it finds the house swept clean and put in order.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 11:26"/><char style="wj">Then it goes and takes seven other spirits more wicked than itself, and they go in and live there. And the final condition of that person is worse than the first.’</char><verse eid="LUK 11:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 11:27"/>As Jesus was saying these things, a woman in the crowd called out, ‘Blessed is the mother who gave you birth and nursed you.’<verse eid="LUK 11:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 11:28"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘Blessed rather are those who hear the word of God and obey it.’</char><verse eid="LUK 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The sign of Jonah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 11:29"/>As the crowds increased, Jesus said, <char style="wj">‘This is a wicked generation. It asks for a sign, but none will be given it except the sign of Jonah.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 11:30"/><char style="wj">For as Jonah was a sign to the Ninevites, so also will the Son of Man be to this generation.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 11:31"/><char style="wj">The Queen of the South will rise at the judgment with the people of this generation and condemn them, for she came from the ends of the earth to listen to Solomon’s wisdom; and now something greater than Solomon is here.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 11:32"/><char style="wj">The men of Nineveh will stand up at the judgment with this generation and condemn it, for they repented at the preaching of Jonah; and now something greater than Jonah is here.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The lamp of the body</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 11:33"/>
    <char style="wj">‘No-one lights a lamp and puts it in a place where it will be hidden, or under a bowl. Instead they put it on its stand, so that those who come in may see the light.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 11:34"/><char style="wj">Your eye is the lamp of your body. When your eyes are healthy,</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek for </char><char style="fq" closed="false">healthy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">here implies generous.</char></note> <char style="wj">your whole body also is full of light. But when they are unhealthy,</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek for </char><char style="fq" closed="false">unhealthy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">here implies stingy.</char></note> <char style="wj">your body also is full of darkness.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 11:35"/><char style="wj">See to it, then, that the light within you is not darkness.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 11:36"/><char style="wj">Therefore, if your whole body is full of light, and no part of it dark, it will be just as full of light as when a lamp shines its light on you.’</char><verse eid="LUK 11:36"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Woes on the Pharisees and the experts in the law</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 11:37"/>When Jesus had finished speaking, a Pharisee invited him to eat with him; so he went in and reclined at the table. <verse eid="LUK 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 11:38"/>But the Pharisee was surprised when he noticed that Jesus did not first wash before the meal.<verse eid="LUK 11:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 11:39"/>Then the Lord said to him, <char style="wj">‘Now then, you Pharisees clean the outside of the cup and dish, but inside you are full of greed and wickedness.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 11:40"/><char style="wj">You foolish people! Did not the one who made the outside make the inside also?</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 11:41"/><char style="wj">But now as for what is inside you – be generous to the poor, and everything will be clean for you.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 11:42"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Woe to you Pharisees, because you give God a tenth of your mint, rue and all other kinds of garden herbs, but you neglect justice and the love of God. You should have practised the latter without leaving the former undone.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 11:43"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Woe to you Pharisees, because you love the most important seats in the synagogues and respectful greetings in the market-places.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 11:44"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Woe to you, because you are like unmarked graves, which people walk over without knowing it.’</char><verse eid="LUK 11:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 11:45"/>One of the experts in the law answered him, ‘Teacher, when you say these things, you insult us also.’<verse eid="LUK 11:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 11:46"/>Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘And you experts in the law, woe to you, because you load people down with burdens they can hardly carry, and you yourselves will not lift one finger to help them.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 11:47"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Woe to you, because you build tombs for the prophets, and it was your ancestors who killed them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 11:48"/><char style="wj">So you testify that you approve of what your ancestors did; they killed the prophets, and you build their tombs.</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 11:49"/><char style="wj">Because of this, God in his wisdom said, “I will send them prophets and apostles, some of whom they will kill and others they will persecute.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 11:50"/><char style="wj">Therefore this generation will be held responsible for the blood of all the prophets that has been shed since the beginning of the world,</char> <verse eid="LUK 11:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 11:51"/><char style="wj">from the blood of Abel to the blood of Zechariah, who was killed between the altar and the sanctuary. Yes, I tell you, this generation will be held responsible for it all.</char><verse eid="LUK 11:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 11:52"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Woe to you experts in the law, because you have taken away the key to knowledge. You yourselves have not entered, and you have hindered those who were entering.’</char><verse eid="LUK 11:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 11:53"/>When Jesus went outside, the Pharisees and the teachers of the law began to oppose him fiercely and to besiege him with questions, <verse eid="LUK 11:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 11:54"/>waiting to catch him in something he might say.<verse eid="LUK 11:54"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="LUK 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Warnings and encouragements</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 12:1"/>Meanwhile, when a crowd of many thousands had gathered, so that they were trampling on one another, Jesus began to speak first to his disciples, saying: <char style="wj">‘Be</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:1 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">speak to his disciples, saying: ‘First of all, be</char></note> <char style="wj">on your guard against the yeast of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 12:2"/><char style="wj">There is nothing concealed that will not be disclosed, or hidden that will not be made known.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 12:3"/><char style="wj">What you have said in the dark will be heard in the daylight, and what you have whispered in the ear in the inner rooms will be proclaimed from the roofs.</char><verse eid="LUK 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 12:4"/>
    <char style="wj">‘I tell you, my friends, do not be afraid of those who kill the body and after that can do no more.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 12:5"/><char style="wj">But I will show you whom you should fear: fear him who, after your body has been killed, has authority to throw you into hell. Yes, I tell you, fear him.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 12:6"/><char style="wj">Are not five sparrows sold for two pennies? Yet not one of them is forgotten by God.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 12:7"/><char style="wj">Indeed, the very hairs of your head are all numbered. Don’t be afraid; you are worth more than many sparrows.</char><verse eid="LUK 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 12:8"/>
    <char style="wj">‘I tell you, whoever publicly acknowledges me before others, the Son of Man will also acknowledge before the angels of God.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 12:9"/><char style="wj">But whoever disowns me before others will be disowned before the angels of God.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 12:10"/><char style="wj">And everyone who speaks a word against the Son of Man will be forgiven, but anyone who blasphemes against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven.</char><verse eid="LUK 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 12:11"/>
    <char style="wj">‘When you are brought before synagogues, rulers and authorities, do not worry about how you will defend yourselves or what you will say,</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 12:12"/><char style="wj">for the Holy Spirit will teach you at that time what you should say.’</char><verse eid="LUK 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the rich fool</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 12:13"/>Someone in the crowd said to him, ‘Teacher, tell my brother to divide the inheritance with me.’<verse eid="LUK 12:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 12:14"/>Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘Man, who appointed me a judge or an arbiter between you?’</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 12:15"/>Then he said to them, <char style="wj">‘Watch out! Be on your guard against all kinds of greed; life does not consist in an abundance of possessions.’</char><verse eid="LUK 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 12:16"/>And he told them this parable: <char style="wj">‘The ground of a certain rich man yielded an abundant harvest.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 12:17"/><char style="wj">He thought to himself, “What shall I do? I have no place to store my crops.”</char><verse eid="LUK 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 12:18"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Then he said, “This is what I’ll do. I will tear down my barns and build bigger ones, and there I will store my surplus grain.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 12:19"/><char style="wj">And I’ll say to myself, ‘You have plenty of grain laid up for many years. Take life easy; eat, drink and be merry.’ ”</char><verse eid="LUK 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 12:20"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But God said to him, “You fool! This very night your life will be demanded from you. Then who will get what you have prepared for yourself?”</char><verse eid="LUK 12:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 12:21"/>
    <char style="wj">‘This is how it will be with whoever stores up things for themselves but is not rich towards God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 12:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not worry</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 12:22"/>Then Jesus said to his disciples: <char style="wj">‘Therefore I tell you, do not worry about your life, what you will eat; or about your body, what you will wear.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 12:23"/><char style="wj">For life is more than food, and the body more than clothes.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 12:24"/><char style="wj">Consider the ravens: they do not sow or reap, they have no storeroom or barn; yet God feeds them. And how much more valuable you are than birds!</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 12:25"/><char style="wj">Who of you by worrying can add a single hour to your life</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:25 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">single cubit to your height</char></note><char style="wj">?</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 12:26"/><char style="wj">Since you cannot do this very little thing, why do you worry about the rest?</char><verse eid="LUK 12:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 12:27"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Consider how the wild flowers grow. They do not labour or spin. Yet I tell you, not even Solomon in all his splendour was dressed like one of these.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 12:28"/><char style="wj">If that is how God clothes the grass of the field, which is here today, and tomorrow is thrown into the fire, how much more will he clothe you – you of little faith!</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 12:29"/><char style="wj">And do not set your heart on what you will eat or drink; do not worry about it.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 12:30"/><char style="wj">For the pagan world runs after all such things, and your Father knows that you need them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 12:31"/><char style="wj">But seek his kingdom, and these things will be given to you as well.</char><verse eid="LUK 12:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 12:32"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Do not be afraid, little flock, for your Father has been pleased to give you the kingdom.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 12:33"/><char style="wj">Sell your possessions and give to the poor. Provide purses for yourselves that will not wear out, a treasure in heaven that will never fail, where no thief comes near and no moth destroys.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 12:34"/><char style="wj">For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.</char><verse eid="LUK 12:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Watchfulness</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 12:35"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Be dressed ready for service and keep your lamps burning,</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 12:36"/><char style="wj">like servants waiting for their master to return from a wedding banquet, so that when he comes and knocks they can immediately open the door for him.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 12:37"/><char style="wj">It will be good for those servants whose master finds them watching when he comes. Truly I tell you, he will dress himself to serve, will make them recline at the table and will come and wait on them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 12:38"/><char style="wj">It will be good for those servants whose master finds them ready, even if he comes in the middle of the night or towards daybreak.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 12:39"/><char style="wj">But understand this: if the owner of the house had known at what hour the thief was coming, he would not have let his house be broken into.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 12:40"/><char style="wj">You also must be ready, because the Son of Man will come at an hour when you do not expect him.’</char><verse eid="LUK 12:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 12:41"/>Peter asked, ‘Lord, are you telling this parable to us, or to everyone?’<verse eid="LUK 12:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 12:42"/>The Lord answered, <char style="wj">‘Who then is the faithful and wise manager, whom the master puts in charge of his servants to give them their food allowance at the proper time?</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 12:43"/><char style="wj">It will be good for that servant whom the master finds doing so when he returns.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 12:44"/><char style="wj">Truly I tell you, he will put him in charge of all his possessions.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 12:45"/><char style="wj">But suppose the servant says to himself, “My master is taking a long time in coming,” and he then begins to beat the other servants, both men and women, and to eat and drink and get drunk.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 12:46"/><char style="wj">The master of that servant will come on a day when he does not expect him and at an hour he is not aware of. He will cut him to pieces and assign him a place with the unbelievers.</char><verse eid="LUK 12:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 12:47"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The servant who knows the master’s will and does not get ready or does not do what the master wants will be beaten with many blows.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 12:48"/><char style="wj">But the one who does not know and does things deserving punishment will be beaten with few blows. From everyone who has been given much, much will be demanded; and from the one who has been entrusted with much, much more will be asked.</char><verse eid="LUK 12:48"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Not peace but division</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 12:49"/>
    <char style="wj">‘I have come to bring fire on the earth, and how I wish it were already kindled!</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 12:50"/><char style="wj">But I have a baptism to undergo, and what constraint I am under until it is completed!</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 12:51"/><char style="wj">Do you think I came to bring peace on earth? No, I tell you, but division.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 12:52"/><char style="wj">From now on there will be five in one family divided against each other, three against two and two against three.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 12:53"/><char style="wj">They will be divided, father against son and son against father, mother against daughter and daughter against mother, mother-in-law against daughter-in-law and daughter-in-law against mother-in-law.’</char><verse eid="LUK 12:53"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Interpreting the times</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 12:54"/>He said to the crowd: <char style="wj">‘When you see a cloud rising in the west, immediately you say, “It’s going to rain,” and it does.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 12:55"/><char style="wj">And when the south wind blows, you say, “It’s going to be hot,” and it is.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 12:56"/><char style="wj">Hypocrites! You know how to interpret the appearance of the earth and the sky. How is it that you don’t know how to interpret this present time?</char><verse eid="LUK 12:56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 12:57"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Why don’t you judge for yourselves what is right?</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 12:58"/><char style="wj">As you are going with your adversary to the magistrate, try hard to be reconciled on the way, or your adversary may drag you off to the judge, and the judge turn you over to the officer, and the officer throw you into prison.</char> <verse eid="LUK 12:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 12:59"/><char style="wj">I tell you, you will not get out until you have paid the last penny.’</char><verse eid="LUK 12:59"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="LUK 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Repent or perish</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 13:1"/>Now there were some present at that time who told Jesus about the Galileans whose blood Pilate had mixed with their sacrifices. <verse eid="LUK 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 13:2"/>Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘Do you think that these Galileans were worse sinners than all the other Galileans because they suffered this way?</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 13:3"/><char style="wj">I tell you, no! But unless you repent, you too will all perish.</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 13:4"/><char style="wj">Or those eighteen who died when the tower in Siloam fell on them – do you think they were more guilty than all the others living in Jerusalem?</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 13:5"/><char style="wj">I tell you, no! But unless you repent, you too will all perish.’</char><verse eid="LUK 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 13:6"/>Then he told this parable: <char style="wj">‘A man had a fig-tree growing in his vineyard, and he went to look for fruit on it but did not find any.</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 13:7"/><char style="wj">So he said to the man who took care of the vineyard, “For three years now I’ve been coming to look for fruit on this fig-tree and haven’t found any. Cut it down! Why should it use up the soil?”</char><verse eid="LUK 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 13:8"/>
    <char style="wj">‘ “Sir,” the man replied, “leave it alone for one more year, and I’ll dig round it and fertilise it.</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 13:9"/><char style="wj">If it bears fruit next year, fine! If not, then cut it down.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus heals a crippled woman on the Sabbath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 13:10"/>On a Sabbath Jesus was teaching in one of the synagogues, <verse eid="LUK 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 13:11"/>and a woman was there who had been crippled by a spirit for eighteen years. She was bent over and could not straighten up at all. <verse eid="LUK 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 13:12"/>When Jesus saw her, he called her forward and said to her, <char style="wj">‘Woman, you are set free from your infirmity.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 13:13"/>Then he put his hands on her, and immediately she straightened up and praised God.<verse eid="LUK 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 13:14"/>Indignant because Jesus had healed on the Sabbath, the synagogue leader said to the people, ‘There are six days for work. So come and be healed on those days, not on the Sabbath.’<verse eid="LUK 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 13:15"/>The Lord answered him, <char style="wj">‘You hypocrites! Doesn’t each of you on the Sabbath untie your ox or donkey from the stall and lead it out to give it water?</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 13:16"/><char style="wj">Then should not this woman, a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan has kept bound for eighteen long years, be set free on the Sabbath day from what bound her?’</char><verse eid="LUK 13:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 13:17"/>When he said this, all his opponents were humiliated, but the people were delighted with all the wonderful things he was doing.<verse eid="LUK 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parables of the mustard seed and the yeast</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 13:18"/>Then Jesus asked, <char style="wj">‘What is the kingdom of God like? What shall I compare it to?</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 13:19"/><char style="wj">It is like a mustard seed, which a man took and planted in his garden. It grew and became a tree, and the birds perched in its branches.’</char><verse eid="LUK 13:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 13:20"/>Again he asked, <char style="wj">‘What shall I compare the kingdom of God to?</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 13:21"/><char style="wj">It is like yeast that a woman took and mixed into about thirty kilograms of flour until it worked all through the dough.’</char><verse eid="LUK 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The narrow door</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 13:22"/>Then Jesus went through the towns and villages, teaching as he made his way to Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 13:23"/>Someone asked him, ‘Lord, are only a few people going to be saved?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 13:23">He said to them, <verse eid="LUK 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 13:24"/><char style="wj">‘Make every effort to enter through the narrow door, because many, I tell you, will try to enter and will not be able to.</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 13:25"/><char style="wj">Once the owner of the house gets up and closes the door, you will stand outside knocking and pleading, “Sir, open the door for us.”</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 13:25">
    <char style="wj">‘But he will answer, “I don’t know you or where you come from.”</char><verse eid="LUK 13:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 13:26"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Then you will say, “We ate and drank with you, and you taught in our streets.”</char><verse eid="LUK 13:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 13:27"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But he will reply, “I don’t know you or where you come from. Away from me, all you evildoers!”</char><verse eid="LUK 13:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 13:28"/>
    <char style="wj">‘There will be weeping there, and gnashing of teeth, when you see Abraham, Isaac and Jacob and all the prophets in the kingdom of God, but you yourselves thrown out.</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 13:29"/><char style="wj">People will come from east and west and north and south, and will take their places at the feast in the kingdom of God.</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 13:30"/><char style="wj">Indeed there are those who are last who will be first, and first who will be last.’</char><verse eid="LUK 13:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus’ sorrow for Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 13:31"/>At that time some Pharisees came to Jesus and said to him, ‘Leave this place and go somewhere else. Herod wants to kill you.’<verse eid="LUK 13:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 13:32"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘Go and tell that fox, “I will keep on driving out demons and healing people today and tomorrow, and on the third day I will reach my goal.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 13:33"/><char style="wj">In any case, I must press on today and tomorrow and the next day – for surely no prophet can die outside Jerusalem!</char><verse eid="LUK 13:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 13:34"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you, how often I have longed to gather your children together, as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, and you were not willing.</char> <verse eid="LUK 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 13:35"/><char style="wj">Look, your house is left to you desolate. I tell you, you will not see me again until you say, “Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord.”</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">13:35 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="PSA 118:26">Psalm 118:26</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">’</char><verse eid="LUK 13:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="LUK 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus at a Pharisee’s house</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 14:1"/>One Sabbath, when Jesus went to eat in the house of a prominent Pharisee, he was being carefully watched. <verse eid="LUK 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 14:2"/>There in front of him was a man suffering from abnormal swelling of his body. <verse eid="LUK 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 14:3"/>Jesus asked the Pharisees and experts in the law, <char style="wj">‘Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath or not?’</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 14:4"/>But they remained silent. So taking hold of the man, he healed him and sent him on his way.<verse eid="LUK 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 14:5"/>Then he asked them, <char style="wj">‘If one of you has a child</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">14:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">donkey</char></note> <char style="wj">or an ox that falls into a well on the Sabbath day, will you not immediately pull it out?’</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 14:6"/>And they had nothing to say.<verse eid="LUK 14:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 14:7"/>When he noticed how the guests picked the places of honour at the table, he told them this parable: <verse eid="LUK 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 14:8"/><char style="wj">‘When someone invites you to a wedding feast, do not take the place of honour, for a person more distinguished than you may have been invited.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 14:9"/><char style="wj">If so, the host who invited both of you will come and say to you, “Give this person your seat.” Then, humiliated, you will have to take the least important place.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 14:10"/><char style="wj">But when you are invited, take the lowest place, so that when your host comes, he will say to you, “Friend, move up to a better place.” Then you will be honoured in the presence of all the other guests.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 14:11"/><char style="wj">For all those who exalt themselves will be humbled, and those who humble themselves will be exalted.’</char><verse eid="LUK 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 14:12"/>Then Jesus said to his host, <char style="wj">‘When you give a luncheon or dinner, do not invite your friends, your brothers or sisters, your relatives, or your rich neighbours; if you do, they may invite you back and so you will be repaid.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 14:13"/><char style="wj">But when you give a banquet, invite the poor, the crippled, the lame, the blind,</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 14:14"/><char style="wj">and you will be blessed. Although they cannot repay you, you will be repaid at the resurrection of the righteous.’</char><verse eid="LUK 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the great banquet</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 14:15"/>When one of those at the table with him heard this, he said to Jesus, ‘Blessed is the one who will eat at the feast in the kingdom of God.’<verse eid="LUK 14:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 14:16"/>Jesus replied: <char style="wj">‘A certain man was preparing a great banquet and invited many guests.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 14:17"/><char style="wj">At the time of the banquet he sent his servant to tell those who had been invited, “Come, for everything is now ready.”</char><verse eid="LUK 14:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 14:18"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But they all alike began to make excuses. The first said, “I have just bought a field, and I must go and see it. Please excuse me.”</char><verse eid="LUK 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 14:19"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Another said, “I have just bought five yoke of oxen, and I’m on my way to try them out. Please excuse me.”</char><verse eid="LUK 14:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 14:20"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Still another said, “I have just got married, so I can’t come.”</char><verse eid="LUK 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 14:21"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The servant came back and reported this to his master. Then the owner of the house became angry and ordered his servant, “Go out quickly into the streets and alleys of the town and bring in the poor, the crippled, the blind and the lame.”</char><verse eid="LUK 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 14:22"/>
    <char style="wj">‘ “Sir,” the servant said, “what you ordered has been done, but there is still room.”</char><verse eid="LUK 14:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 14:23"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Then the master told his servant, “Go out to the roads and country lanes and compel them to come in, so that my house will be full.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 14:24"/><char style="wj">I tell you, not one of those who were invited will get a taste of my banquet.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 14:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The cost of being a disciple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 14:25"/>Large crowds were travelling with Jesus, and turning to them he said: <verse eid="LUK 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 14:26"/><char style="wj">‘If anyone comes to me and does not hate father and mother, wife and children, brothers and sisters – yes, even their own life – such a person cannot be my disciple.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 14:27"/><char style="wj">And whoever does not carry their cross and follow me cannot be my disciple.</char><verse eid="LUK 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 14:28"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Suppose one of you wants to build a tower. Won’t you first sit down and estimate the cost to see if you have enough money to complete it?</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 14:29"/><char style="wj">For if you lay the foundation and are not able to finish it, everyone who sees it will ridicule you,</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 14:30"/><char style="wj">saying, “This person began to build and wasn’t able to finish.”</char><verse eid="LUK 14:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 14:31"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Or suppose a king is about to go to war against another king. Won’t he first sit down and consider whether he is able with ten thousand men to oppose the one coming against him with twenty thousand?</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 14:32"/><char style="wj">If he is not able, he will send a delegation while the other is still a long way off and will ask for terms of peace.</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 14:33"/><char style="wj">In the same way, those of you who do not give up everything you have cannot be my disciples.</char><verse eid="LUK 14:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 14:34"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Salt is good, but if it loses its saltiness, how can it be made salty again?</char> <verse eid="LUK 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 14:35"/><char style="wj">It is fit neither for the soil nor for the manure heap; it is thrown out.</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 14:35">
    <char style="wj">‘Whoever has ears to hear, let them hear.’</char><verse eid="LUK 14:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="LUK 15"/>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the lost sheep</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 15:1"/>Now the tax collectors and sinners were all gathering round to hear Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 15:2"/>But the Pharisees and the teachers of the law muttered, ‘This man welcomes sinners, and eats with them.’<verse eid="LUK 15:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 15:3"/>Then Jesus told them this parable: <verse eid="LUK 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 15:4"/><char style="wj">‘Suppose one of you has a hundred sheep and loses one of them. Doesn’t he leave the ninety-nine in the open country and go after the lost sheep until he finds it?</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 15:5"/><char style="wj">And when he finds it, he joyfully puts it on his shoulders</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 15:6"/><char style="wj">and goes home. Then he calls his friends and neighbours together and says, “Rejoice with me; I have found my lost sheep.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 15:7"/><char style="wj">I tell you that in the same way there will be more rejoicing in heaven over one sinner who repents than over ninety-nine righteous people who do not need to repent.</char><verse eid="LUK 15:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the lost coin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 15:8"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Or suppose a woman has ten silver coins</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">15:8 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">Greek </char>
      <char style="fqa" closed="false">ten drachmas, </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">each worth about a day’s wages</char>
    </note> <char style="wj">and loses one. Doesn’t she light a lamp, sweep the house and search carefully until she finds it?</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 15:9"/><char style="wj">And when she finds it, she calls her friends and neighbours together and says, “Rejoice with me; I have found my lost coin.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 15:10"/><char style="wj">In the same way, I tell you, there is rejoicing in the presence of the angels of God over one sinner who repents.’</char><verse eid="LUK 15:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the lost son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 15:11"/>Jesus continued: <char style="wj">‘There was a man who had two sons.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 15:12"/><char style="wj">The younger one said to his father, “Father, give me my share of the estate.” So he divided his property between them.</char><verse eid="LUK 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 15:13"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Not long after that, the younger son got together all he had, set off for a distant country and there squandered his wealth in wild living.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 15:14"/><char style="wj">After he had spent everything, there was a severe famine in that whole country, and he began to be in need.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 15:15"/><char style="wj">So he went and hired himself out to a citizen of that country, who sent him to his fields to feed pigs.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 15:16"/><char style="wj">He longed to fill his stomach with the pods that the pigs were eating, but no-one gave him anything.</char><verse eid="LUK 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 15:17"/>
    <char style="wj">‘When he came to his senses, he said, “How many of my father’s hired servants have food to spare, and here I am starving to death!</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 15:18"/><char style="wj">I will set out and go back to my father and say to him: Father, I have sinned against heaven and against you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 15:19"/><char style="wj">I am no longer worthy to be called your son; make me like one of your hired servants.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 15:20"/><char style="wj">So he got up and went to his father.</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 15:20">
    <char style="wj">‘But while he was still a long way off, his father saw him and was filled with compassion for him; he ran to his son, threw his arms round him and kissed him.</char><verse eid="LUK 15:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 15:21"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The son said to him, “Father, I have sinned against heaven and against you. I am no longer worthy to be called your son.”</char><verse eid="LUK 15:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 15:22"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But the father said to his servants, “Quick! Bring the best robe and put it on him. Put a ring on his finger and sandals on his feet.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 15:23"/><char style="wj">Bring the fattened calf and kill it. Let’s have a feast and celebrate.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 15:24"/><char style="wj">For this son of mine was dead and is alive again; he was lost and is found.” So they began to celebrate.</char><verse eid="LUK 15:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 15:25"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Meanwhile, the elder son was in the field. When he came near the house, he heard music and dancing.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 15:26"/><char style="wj">So he called one of the servants and asked him what was going on.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 15:27"/><char style="wj">“Your brother has come,” he replied, “and your father has killed the fattened calf because he has him back safe and sound.”</char><verse eid="LUK 15:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 15:28"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The elder brother became angry and refused to go in. So his father went out and pleaded with him.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 15:29"/><char style="wj">But he answered his father, “Look! All these years I’ve been slaving for you and never disobeyed your orders. Yet you never gave me even a young goat so I could celebrate with my friends.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 15:30"/><char style="wj">But when this son of yours who has squandered your property with prostitutes comes home, you kill the fattened calf for him!”</char><verse eid="LUK 15:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 15:31"/>
    <char style="wj">‘ “My son,” the father said, “you are always with me, and everything I have is yours.</char> <verse eid="LUK 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 15:32"/><char style="wj">But we had to celebrate and be glad, because this brother of yours was dead and is alive again; he was lost and is found.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 15:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="LUK 16"/>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the shrewd manager</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 16:1"/>Jesus told his disciples: <char style="wj">‘There was a rich man whose manager was accused of wasting his possessions.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 16:2"/><char style="wj">So he called him in and asked him, “What is this I hear about you? Give an account of your management, because you cannot be manager any longer.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 16:3"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The manager said to himself, “What shall I do now? My master is taking away my job. I’m not strong enough to dig, and I’m ashamed to beg –</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 16:4"/><char style="wj">I know what I’ll do so that, when I lose my job here, people will welcome me into their houses.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 16:5"/>
    <char style="wj">‘So he called in each one of his master’s debtors. He asked the first, “How much do you owe my master?”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 16:6"/>
    <char style="wj">‘ “Three thousand litres of olive oil,” he replied.</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 16:6">
    <char style="wj">‘The manager told him, “Take your bill, sit down quickly, and make it fifteen hundred.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 16:7"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Then he asked the second, “And how much do you owe?”</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 16:7">
    <char style="wj">‘ “Thirty tons of wheat,” he replied.</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 16:7">
    <char style="wj">‘He told him, “Take your bill and make it twenty-four.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 16:8"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The master commended the dishonest manager because he had acted shrewdly. For the people of this world are more shrewd in dealing with their own kind than are the people of the light.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 16:9"/><char style="wj">I tell you, use worldly wealth to gain friends for yourselves, so that when it is gone, you will be welcomed into eternal dwellings.</char><verse eid="LUK 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 16:10"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Whoever can be trusted with very little can also be trusted with much, and whoever is dishonest with very little will also be dishonest with much.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 16:11"/><char style="wj">So if you have not been trustworthy in handling worldly wealth, who will trust you with true riches?</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 16:12"/><char style="wj">And if you have not been trustworthy with someone else’s property, who will give you property of your own?</char><verse eid="LUK 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 16:13"/>
    <char style="wj">‘No-one can serve two masters. Either you will hate the one and love the other, or you will be devoted to the one and despise the other. You cannot serve both God and Money.’</char><verse eid="LUK 16:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 16:14"/>The Pharisees, who loved money, heard all this and were sneering at Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 16:15"/>He said to them, <char style="wj">‘You are the ones who justify yourselves in the eyes of others, but God knows your hearts. What people value highly is detestable in God’s sight.</char><verse eid="LUK 16:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Additional teachings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 16:16"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The Law and the Prophets were proclaimed until John. Since that time, the good news of the kingdom of God is being preached, and everyone is forcing their way into it.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 16:17"/><char style="wj">It is easier for heaven and earth to disappear than for the least stroke of a pen to drop out of the Law.</char><verse eid="LUK 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 16:18"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Anyone who divorces his wife and marries another woman commits adultery, and the man who marries a divorced woman commits adultery.</char><verse eid="LUK 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The rich man and Lazarus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 16:19"/>
    <char style="wj">‘There was a rich man who was dressed in purple and fine linen and lived in luxury every day.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 16:20"/><char style="wj">At his gate was laid a beggar named Lazarus, covered with sores</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 16:21"/><char style="wj">and longing to eat what fell from the rich man’s table. Even the dogs came and licked his sores.</char><verse eid="LUK 16:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 16:22"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The time came when the beggar died and the angels carried him to Abraham’s side. The rich man also died and was buried.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 16:23"/><char style="wj">In Hades, where he was in torment, he looked up and saw Abraham far away, with Lazarus by his side.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 16:24"/><char style="wj">So he called to him, “Father Abraham, have pity on me and send Lazarus to dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue, because I am in agony in this fire.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 16:25"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But Abraham replied, “Son, remember that in your lifetime you received your good things, while Lazarus received bad things, but now he is comforted here and you are in agony.</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 16:26"/><char style="wj">And besides all this, between us and you a great chasm has been set in place, so that those who want to go from here to you cannot, nor can anyone cross over from there to us.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 16:27"/>
    <char style="wj">‘He answered, “Then I beg you, father, send Lazarus to my family,</char> <verse eid="LUK 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 16:28"/><char style="wj">for I have five brothers. Let him warn them, so that they will not also come to this place of torment.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 16:29"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Abraham replied, “They have Moses and the Prophets; let them listen to them.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 16:30"/>
    <char style="wj">‘ “No, father Abraham,” he said, “but if someone from the dead goes to them, they will repent.”</char><verse eid="LUK 16:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 16:31"/>
    <char style="wj">‘He said to him, “If they do not listen to Moses and the Prophets, they will not be convinced even if someone rises from the dead.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 16:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="LUK 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Sin, faith, duty</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 17:1"/>Jesus said to his disciples: <char style="wj">‘Things that cause people to stumble are bound to come, but woe to anyone through whom they come.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 17:2"/><char style="wj">It would be better for them to be thrown into the sea with a millstone tied round their neck than to cause one of these little ones to stumble.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 17:3"/><char style="wj">So watch yourselves.</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 17:3">
    <char style="wj">‘If your brother or sister</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">17:3 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek word for </char>
      <char style="fq" closed="false">brother or sister </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">(<char style="tl">adelphos</char>) refers here to a fellow disciple, whether man or woman.</char>
    </note> <char style="wj">sins against you, rebuke them; and if they repent, forgive them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 17:4"/><char style="wj">Even if they sin against you seven times in a day and seven times come back to you saying “I repent,” you must forgive them.’</char><verse eid="LUK 17:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 17:5"/>The apostles said to the Lord, ‘Increase our faith!’<verse eid="LUK 17:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 17:6"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘If you have faith as small as a mustard seed, you can say to this mulberry tree, “Be uprooted and planted in the sea,” and it will obey you.</char><verse eid="LUK 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 17:7"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Suppose one of you has a servant ploughing or looking after the sheep. Will he say to the servant when he comes in from the field, “Come along now and sit down to eat”?</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 17:8"/><char style="wj">Won’t he rather say, “Prepare my supper, get yourself ready and wait on me while I eat and drink; after that you may eat and drink”?</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 17:9"/><char style="wj">Will he thank the servant because he did what he was told to do?</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 17:10"/><char style="wj">So you also, when you have done everything you were told to do, should say, “We are unworthy servants; we have only done our duty.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 17:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus heals ten men with leprosy</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 17:11"/>Now on his way to Jerusalem, Jesus travelled along the border between Samaria and Galilee. <verse eid="LUK 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 17:12"/>As he was going into a village, ten men who had leprosy<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The Greek word traditionally translated </char><char style="fq" closed="false">leprosy </char><char style="ft" closed="false">was used for various diseases affecting the skin.</char></note> met him. They stood at a distance <verse eid="LUK 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 17:13"/>and called out in a loud voice, ‘Jesus, Master, have pity on us!’<verse eid="LUK 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 17:14"/>When he saw them, he said, <char style="wj">‘Go, show yourselves to the priests.’</char> And as they went, they were cleansed.<verse eid="LUK 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 17:15"/>One of them, when he saw he was healed, came back, praising God in a loud voice. <verse eid="LUK 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 17:16"/>He threw himself at Jesus’ feet and thanked him – and he was a Samaritan.<verse eid="LUK 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 17:17"/>Jesus asked, <char style="wj">‘Were not all ten cleansed? Where are the other nine?</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 17:18"/><char style="wj">Has no-one returned to give praise to God except this foreigner?’</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 17:19"/>Then he said to him, <char style="wj">‘Rise and go; your faith has made you well.’</char><verse eid="LUK 17:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The coming of the kingdom of God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 17:20"/>Once, on being asked by the Pharisees when the kingdom of God would come, Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘The coming of the kingdom of God is not something that can be observed,</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 17:21"/><char style="wj">nor will people say, “Here it is,” or “There it is,” because the kingdom of God is in your midst.’</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:21 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">is within you</char></note><verse eid="LUK 17:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 17:22"/>Then he said to his disciples, <char style="wj">‘The time is coming when you will long to see one of the days of the Son of Man, but you will not see it.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 17:23"/><char style="wj">People will tell you, “There he is!” or “Here he is!” Do not go running off after them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 17:24"/><char style="wj">For the Son of Man in his day</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts do not have </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">in his day.</char></note> <char style="wj">will be like the lightning, which flashes and lights up the sky from one end to the other.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 17:25"/><char style="wj">But first he must suffer many things and be rejected by this generation.</char><verse eid="LUK 17:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 17:26"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Just as it was in the days of Noah, so also will it be in the days of the Son of Man.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 17:27"/><char style="wj">People were eating, drinking, marrying and being given in marriage up to the day Noah entered the ark. Then the flood came and destroyed them all.</char><verse eid="LUK 17:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 17:28"/>
    <char style="wj">‘It was the same in the days of Lot. People were eating and drinking, buying and selling, planting and building.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 17:29"/><char style="wj">But the day Lot left Sodom, fire and sulphur rained down from heaven and destroyed them all.</char><verse eid="LUK 17:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 17:30"/>
    <char style="wj">‘It will be just like this on the day the Son of Man is revealed.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 17:31"/><char style="wj">On that day no-one who is on the housetop, with possessions inside, should go down to get them. Likewise, no-one in the field should go back for anything.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 17:32"/><char style="wj">Remember Lot’s wife!</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 17:33"/><char style="wj">Whoever tries to keep their life will lose it, and whoever loses their life will preserve it.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 17:34"/><char style="wj">I tell you, on that night two people will be in one bed; one will be taken and the other left.</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 17:35"/><char style="wj">Two women will be grinding corn together; one will be taken and the other left.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 17:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" pubnumber="[36]" sid="LUK 17:36"/><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">17:36 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts include here words similar to <char style="xt"><ref loc="MAT 24:40">Matt. 24:40</ref></char>.</char></note><verse eid="LUK 17:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 17:37"/>‘Where, Lord?’ they asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 17:37">He replied, <char style="wj">‘Where there is a dead body, there the vultures will gather.’</char><verse eid="LUK 17:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="LUK 18"/>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the persistent widow</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 18:1"/>Then Jesus told his disciples a parable to show them that they should always pray and not give up. <verse eid="LUK 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 18:2"/>He said: <char style="wj">‘In a certain town there was a judge who neither feared God nor cared what people thought.</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 18:3"/><char style="wj">And there was a widow in that town who kept coming to him with the plea, “Grant me justice against my adversary.”</char><verse eid="LUK 18:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 18:4"/>
    <char style="wj">‘For some time he refused. But finally he said to himself, “Even though I don’t fear God or care what people think,</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 18:5"/><char style="wj">yet because this widow keeps bothering me, I will see that she gets justice, so that she won’t eventually come and attack me!” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 18:6"/>And the Lord said, <char style="wj">‘Listen to what the unjust judge says.</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 18:7"/><char style="wj">And will not God bring about justice for his chosen ones, who cry out to him day and night? Will he keep putting them off?</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 18:8"/><char style="wj">I tell you, he will see that they get justice, and quickly. However, when the Son of Man comes, will he find faith on the earth?’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the Pharisee and the tax collector</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 18:9"/>To some who were confident of their own righteousness and looked down on everyone else, Jesus told this parable: <verse eid="LUK 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 18:10"/><char style="wj">‘Two men went up to the temple to pray, one a Pharisee and the other a tax collector.</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 18:11"/><char style="wj">The Pharisee stood by himself and prayed: “God, I thank you that I am not like other people – robbers, evildoers, adulterers – or even like this tax collector.</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 18:12"/><char style="wj">I fast twice a week and give a tenth of all I get.”</char><verse eid="LUK 18:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 18:13"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But the tax collector stood at a distance. He would not even look up to heaven, but beat his breast and said, “God, have mercy on me, a sinner.”</char><verse eid="LUK 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 18:14"/>
    <char style="wj">‘I tell you that this man, rather than the other, went home justified before God. For all those who exalt themselves will be humbled, and those who humble themselves will be exalted.’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The little children and Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 18:15"/>People were also bringing babies to Jesus for him to place his hands on them. When the disciples saw this, they rebuked them. <verse eid="LUK 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 18:16"/>But Jesus called the children to him and said, <char style="wj">‘Let the little children come to me, and do not hinder them, for the kingdom of God belongs to such as these.</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 18:17"/><char style="wj">Truly I tell you, anyone who will not receive the kingdom of God like a little child will never enter it.’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The rich and the kingdom of God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 18:18"/>A certain ruler asked him, ‘Good teacher, what must I do to inherit eternal life?’<verse eid="LUK 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 18:19"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Why do you call me good?’</char> Jesus answered. <char style="wj">‘No-one is good – except God alone.</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 18:20"/><char style="wj">You know the commandments: “You shall not commit adultery, you shall not murder, you shall not steal, you shall not give false testimony, honour your father and mother.”</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">18:20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="EXO 20:12-16">Exodus 20:12-16</ref></char>; <char style="xt"><ref loc="DEU 5:16-20">Deut. 5:16-20</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 18:21"/>‘All these I have kept since I was a boy,’ he said.<verse eid="LUK 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 18:22"/>When Jesus heard this, he said to him, <char style="wj">‘You still lack one thing. Sell everything you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven. Then come, follow me.’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 18:23"/>When he heard this, he became very sad, because he was very wealthy. <verse eid="LUK 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 18:24"/>Jesus looked at him and said, <char style="wj">‘How hard it is for the rich to enter the kingdom of God!</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 18:25"/><char style="wj">Indeed, it is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for someone who is rich to enter the kingdom of God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 18:26"/>Those who heard this asked, ‘Who then can be saved?’<verse eid="LUK 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 18:27"/>Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘What is impossible with man is possible with God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 18:28"/>Peter said to him, ‘We have left all we had to follow you!’<verse eid="LUK 18:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 18:29"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Truly I tell you,’</char> Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">‘no-one who has left home or wife or brothers or sisters or parents or children for the sake of the kingdom of God</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 18:30"/><char style="wj">will fail to receive many times as much in this age, and in the age to come eternal life.’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus predicts his death a third time</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 18:31"/>Jesus took the Twelve aside and told them, <char style="wj">‘We are going up to Jerusalem, and everything that is written by the prophets about the Son of Man will be fulfilled.</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 18:32"/><char style="wj">He will be handed over to the Gentiles. They will mock him, insult him and spit on him;</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 18:33"/><char style="wj">they will flog him and kill him. On the third day he will rise again.’</char><verse eid="LUK 18:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 18:34"/>The disciples did not understand any of this. Its meaning was hidden from them, and they did not know what he was talking about.<verse eid="LUK 18:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A blind beggar receives his sight</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 18:35"/>As Jesus approached Jericho, a blind man was sitting by the roadside begging. <verse eid="LUK 18:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 18:36"/>When he heard the crowd going by, he asked what was happening. <verse eid="LUK 18:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 18:37"/>They told him, ‘Jesus of Nazareth is passing by.’<verse eid="LUK 18:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 18:38"/>He called out, ‘Jesus, Son of David, have mercy on me!’<verse eid="LUK 18:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 18:39"/>Those who led the way rebuked him and told him to be quiet, but he shouted all the more, ‘Son of David, have mercy on me!’<verse eid="LUK 18:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 18:40"/>Jesus stopped and ordered the man to be brought to him. When he came near, Jesus asked him, <verse eid="LUK 18:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 18:41"/><char style="wj">‘What do you want me to do for you?’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 18:41">‘Lord, I want to see,’ he replied.<verse eid="LUK 18:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 18:42"/>Jesus said to him, <char style="wj">‘Receive your sight; your faith has healed you.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 18:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 18:43"/>Immediately he received his sight and followed Jesus, praising God. When all the people saw it, they also praised God.<verse eid="LUK 18:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="LUK 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Zacchaeus the tax collector</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 19:1"/>Jesus entered Jericho and was passing through. <verse eid="LUK 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 19:2"/>A man was there by the name of Zacchaeus; he was a chief tax collector and was wealthy. <verse eid="LUK 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 19:3"/>He wanted to see who Jesus was, but because he was short he could not see over the crowd. <verse eid="LUK 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 19:4"/>So he ran ahead and climbed a sycamore-fig tree to see him, since Jesus was coming that way.<verse eid="LUK 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 19:5"/>When Jesus reached the spot, he looked up and said to him, <char style="wj">‘Zacchaeus, come down immediately. I must stay at your house today.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 19:6"/>So he came down at once and welcomed him gladly.<verse eid="LUK 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 19:7"/>All the people saw this and began to mutter, ‘He has gone to be the guest of a sinner.’<verse eid="LUK 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 19:8"/>But Zacchaeus stood up and said to the Lord, ‘Look, Lord! Here and now I give half of my possessions to the poor, and if I have cheated anybody out of anything, I will pay back four times the amount.’<verse eid="LUK 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 19:9"/>Jesus said to him, <char style="wj">‘Today salvation has come to this house, because this man, too, is a son of Abraham.</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 19:10"/><char style="wj">For the Son of Man came to seek and to save the lost.’</char><verse eid="LUK 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the ten minas</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 19:11"/>While they were listening to this, he went on to tell them a parable, because he was near Jerusalem and the people thought that the kingdom of God was going to appear at once. <verse eid="LUK 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 19:12"/>He said: <char style="wj">‘A man of noble birth went to a distant country to have himself appointed king and then to return.</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 19:13"/><char style="wj">So he called ten of his servants and gave them ten minas.</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A mina was about three months’ wages.</char></note> <char style="wj">“Put this money to work,” he said, “until I come back.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 19:14"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But his subjects hated him and sent a delegation after him to say, “We don’t want this man to be our king.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 19:15"/>
    <char style="wj">‘He was made king, however, and returned home. Then he sent for the servants to whom he had given the money, in order to find out what they had gained with it.</char><verse eid="LUK 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 19:16"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The first one came and said, “Sir, your mina has earned ten more.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 19:17"/>
    <char style="wj">‘ “Well done, my good servant!” his master replied. “Because you have been trustworthy in a very small matter, take charge of ten cities.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 19:18"/>
    <char style="wj">‘The second came and said, “Sir, your mina has earned five more.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 19:19"/>
    <char style="wj">‘His master answered, “You take charge of five cities.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 19:20"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Then another servant came and said, “Sir, here is your mina; I have kept it laid away in a piece of cloth.</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 19:21"/><char style="wj">I was afraid of you, because you are a hard man. You take out what you did not put in and reap what you did not sow.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 19:22"/>
    <char style="wj">‘His master replied, “I will judge you by your own words, you wicked servant! You knew, did you, that I am a hard man, taking out what I did not put in, and reaping what I did not sow?</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 19:23"/><char style="wj">Why then didn’t you put my money on deposit, so that when I came back, I could have collected it with interest?”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 19:24"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Then he said to those standing by, “Take his mina away from him and give it to the one who has ten minas.”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 19:25"/>
    <char style="wj">‘ “Sir,” they said, “he already has ten!”</char><verse eid="LUK 19:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 19:26"/>
    <char style="wj">‘He replied, “I tell you that to everyone who has, more will be given, but as for the one who has nothing, even what they have will be taken away.</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 19:27"/><char style="wj">But those enemies of mine who did not want me to be king over them – bring them here and kill them in front of me.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 19:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus comes to Jerusalem as king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 19:28"/>After Jesus had said this, he went on ahead, going up to Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 19:29"/>As he approached Bethphage and Bethany at the hill called the Mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples, saying to them, <verse eid="LUK 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 19:30"/><char style="wj">‘Go to the village ahead of you, and as you enter it, you will find a colt tied there, which no-one has ever ridden. Untie it and bring it here.</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 19:31"/><char style="wj">If anyone asks you, “Why are you untying it?” say, “The Lord needs it.” ’</char><verse eid="LUK 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 19:32"/>Those who were sent ahead went and found it just as he had told them. <verse eid="LUK 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 19:33"/>As they were untying the colt, its owners asked them, ‘Why are you untying the colt?’<verse eid="LUK 19:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 19:34"/>They replied, ‘The Lord needs it.’<verse eid="LUK 19:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 19:35"/>They brought it to Jesus, threw their cloaks on the colt and put Jesus on it. <verse eid="LUK 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 19:36"/>As he went along, people spread their cloaks on the road.<verse eid="LUK 19:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 19:37"/>When he came near the place where the road goes down the Mount of Olives, the whole crowd of disciples began joyfully to praise God in loud voices for all the miracles they had seen:<verse eid="LUK 19:37"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 19:38"/>‘Blessed is the king who comes in the name of the Lord!’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="PSA 118:26">Psalm 118:26</ref></char></char></note></para>
  <para style="b" vid="LUK 19:38"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 19:38">‘Peace in heaven and glory in the highest!’<verse eid="LUK 19:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 19:39"/>Some of the Pharisees in the crowd said to Jesus, ‘Teacher, rebuke your disciples!’<verse eid="LUK 19:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 19:40"/>
    <char style="wj">‘I tell you,’</char> he replied, <char style="wj">‘if they keep quiet, the stones will cry out.’</char><verse eid="LUK 19:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 19:41"/>As he approached Jerusalem and saw the city, he wept over it <verse eid="LUK 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 19:42"/>and said, <char style="wj">‘If you, even you, had only known on this day what would bring you peace – but now it is hidden from your eyes.</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 19:43"/><char style="wj">The days will come upon you when your enemies will build an embankment against you and encircle you and hem you in on every side.</char> <verse eid="LUK 19:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 19:44"/><char style="wj">They will dash you to the ground, you and the children within your walls. They will not leave one stone on another, because you did not recognise the time of God’s coming to you.’</char><verse eid="LUK 19:44"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus at the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 19:45"/>When Jesus entered the temple courts, he began to drive out those who were selling. <verse eid="LUK 19:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 19:46"/><char style="wj">‘It is written,’</char> he said to them, <char style="wj">‘ “My house will be a house of prayer”</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:46 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="ISA 56:7">Isaiah 56:7</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">; but you have made it “a den of robbers”.</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">19:46 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="JER 7:11">Jer. 7:11</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">’</char><verse eid="LUK 19:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 19:47"/>Every day he was teaching at the temple. But the chief priests, the teachers of the law and the leaders among the people were trying to kill him. <verse eid="LUK 19:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 19:48"/>Yet they could not find any way to do it, because all the people hung on his words.<verse eid="LUK 19:48"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="LUK 20"/>
  <para style="s1">The authority of Jesus questioned</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 20:1"/>One day as Jesus was teaching the people in the temple courts and proclaiming the good news, the chief priests and the teachers of the law, together with the elders, came up to him. <verse eid="LUK 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 20:2"/>‘Tell us by what authority you are doing these things,’ they said. ‘Who gave you this authority?’<verse eid="LUK 20:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 20:3"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘I will also ask you a question. Tell me:</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 20:4"/><char style="wj">John’s baptism – was it from heaven, or of human origin?’</char><verse eid="LUK 20:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 20:5"/>They discussed it among themselves and said, ‘If we say, “From heaven,” he will ask, “Why didn’t you believe him?” <verse eid="LUK 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 20:6"/>But if we say, “Of human origin,” all the people will stone us, because they are persuaded that John was a prophet.’<verse eid="LUK 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 20:7"/>So they answered, ‘We don’t know where it was from.’<verse eid="LUK 20:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 20:8"/>Jesus said, <char style="wj">‘Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these things.’</char><verse eid="LUK 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The parable of the tenants</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 20:9"/>He went on to tell the people this parable: <char style="wj">‘A man planted a vineyard, rented it to some farmers and went away for a long time.</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 20:10"/><char style="wj">At harvest time he sent a servant to the tenants so they would give him some of the fruit of the vineyard. But the tenants beat him and sent him away empty-handed.</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 20:11"/><char style="wj">He sent another servant, but that one also they beat and treated shamefully and sent away empty-handed.</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 20:12"/><char style="wj">He sent still a third, and they wounded him and threw him out.</char><verse eid="LUK 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 20:13"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Then the owner of the vineyard said, “What shall I do? I will send my son, whom I love; perhaps they will respect him.”</char><verse eid="LUK 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 20:14"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But when the tenants saw him, they talked the matter over. “This is the heir,” they said. “Let’s kill him, and the inheritance will be ours.”</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 20:15"/><char style="wj">So they threw him out of the vineyard and killed him.</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 20:15">
    <char style="wj">‘What then will the owner of the vineyard do to them?</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 20:16"/><char style="wj">He will come and kill those tenants and give the vineyard to others.’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 20:16">When the people heard this, they said, ‘God forbid!’<verse eid="LUK 20:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 20:17"/>Jesus looked directly at them and asked, <char style="wj">‘Then what is the meaning of that which is written:</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 20:17">
    <char style="wj">‘ “The stone the builders rejected</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 20:17">
    <char style="wj">has become the cornerstone”</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">20:17 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">
        <char style="xt">
          <ref loc="PSA 118:22">Psalm 118:22</ref>
        </char>
      </char>
    </note>
    <char style="wj">?</char><verse eid="LUK 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 20:18"/>
    <char style="wj">Everyone who falls on that stone will be broken to pieces; anyone on whom it falls will be crushed.’</char><verse eid="LUK 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 20:19"/>The teachers of the law and the chief priests looked for a way to arrest him immediately, because they knew he had spoken this parable against them. But they were afraid of the people.<verse eid="LUK 20:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paying taxes to Caesar</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 20:20"/>Keeping a close watch on him, they sent spies, who pretended to be sincere. They hoped to catch Jesus in something he said, so that they might hand him over to the power and authority of the governor. <verse eid="LUK 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 20:21"/>So the spies questioned him: ‘Teacher, we know that you speak and teach what is right, and that you do not show partiality but teach the way of God in accordance with the truth. <verse eid="LUK 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 20:22"/>Is it right for us to pay taxes to Caesar or not?’<verse eid="LUK 20:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 20:23"/>He saw through their duplicity and said to them, <verse eid="LUK 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 20:24"/><char style="wj">‘Show me a denarius. Whose image and inscription are on it?’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 20:24">‘Caesar’s,’ they replied.<verse eid="LUK 20:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 20:25"/>He said to them, <char style="wj">‘Then give back to Caesar what is Caesar’s, and to God what is God’s.’</char><verse eid="LUK 20:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 20:26"/>They were unable to trap him in what he had said there in public. And astonished by his answer, they became silent.<verse eid="LUK 20:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The resurrection and marriage</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 20:27"/>Some of the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, came to Jesus with a question. <verse eid="LUK 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 20:28"/>‘Teacher,’ they said, ‘Moses wrote for us that if a man’s brother dies and leaves a wife but no children, the man must marry the widow and raise up offspring for his brother. <verse eid="LUK 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 20:29"/>Now there were seven brothers. The first one married a woman and died childless. <verse eid="LUK 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 20:30"/>The second <verse eid="LUK 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 20:31"/>and then the third married her, and in the same way the seven died, leaving no children. <verse eid="LUK 20:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 20:32"/>Finally, the woman died too. <verse eid="LUK 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 20:33"/>Now then, at the resurrection whose wife will she be, since the seven were married to her?’<verse eid="LUK 20:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 20:34"/>Jesus replied, <char style="wj">‘The people of this age marry and are given in marriage.</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 20:35"/><char style="wj">But those who are considered worthy of taking part in the age to come and in the resurrection from the dead will neither marry nor be given in marriage,</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 20:36"/><char style="wj">and they can no longer die; for they are like the angels. They are God’s children, since they are children of the resurrection.</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 20:37"/><char style="wj">But in the account of the burning bush, even Moses showed that the dead rise, for he calls the Lord “the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob”.</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">20:37 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="EXO 3:6">Exodus 3:6</ref></char></char></note> <verse eid="LUK 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 20:38"/><char style="wj">He is not the God of the dead, but of the living, for to him all are alive.’</char><verse eid="LUK 20:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 20:39"/>Some of the teachers of the law responded, ‘Well said, teacher!’ <verse eid="LUK 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 20:40"/>And no-one dared to ask him any more questions.<verse eid="LUK 20:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Whose son is the Messiah?</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 20:41"/>Then Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">‘Why is it said that the Messiah is the son of David?</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 20:42"/><char style="wj">David himself declares in the Book of Psalms:</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 20:42">
    <char style="wj">‘ “The Lord said to my Lord:</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 20:42">
    <char style="wj">‘Sit at my right hand</char><verse eid="LUK 20:42"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 20:43"/>
    <char style="wj">until I make your enemies</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 20:43">
    <char style="wj">a footstool for your feet.’ ”</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">20:43 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">
        <char style="xt">
          <ref loc="PSA 110:1">Psalm 110:1</ref>
        </char>
      </char>
    </note><verse eid="LUK 20:43"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 20:44"/>
    <char style="wj">David calls him “Lord.” How then can he be his son?’</char><verse eid="LUK 20:44"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Warning against the teachers of the law</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 20:45"/>While all the people were listening, Jesus said to his disciples, <verse eid="LUK 20:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 20:46"/><char style="wj">‘Beware of the teachers of the law. They like to walk around in flowing robes and love to be greeted with respect in the market-places and have the most important seats in the synagogues and the places of honour at banquets.</char> <verse eid="LUK 20:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 20:47"/><char style="wj">They devour widows’ houses and for a show make lengthy prayers. These men will be punished most severely.’</char><verse eid="LUK 20:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="LUK 21"/>
  <para style="s1">The widow’s offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 21:1"/>As Jesus looked up, he saw the rich putting their gifts into the temple treasury. <verse eid="LUK 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 21:2"/>He also saw a poor widow put in two very small copper coins. <verse eid="LUK 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 21:3"/><char style="wj">‘Truly I tell you,’</char> he said, <char style="wj">‘this poor widow has put in more than all the others.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 21:4"/><char style="wj">All these people gave their gifts out of their wealth; but she out of her poverty put in all she had to live on.’</char><verse eid="LUK 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The destruction of the temple and signs of the end times</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 21:5"/>Some of his disciples were remarking about how the temple was adorned with beautiful stones and with gifts dedicated to God. But Jesus said, <verse eid="LUK 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 21:6"/><char style="wj">‘As for what you see here, the time will come when not one stone will be left on another; every one of them will be thrown down.’</char><verse eid="LUK 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 21:7"/>‘Teacher,’ they asked, ‘when will these things happen? And what will be the sign that they are about to take place?’<verse eid="LUK 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 21:8"/>He replied: <char style="wj">‘Watch out that you are not deceived. For many will come in my name, claiming, “I am he,” and, “The time is near.” Do not follow them.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 21:9"/><char style="wj">When you hear of wars and uprisings, do not be frightened. These things must happen first, but the end will not come right away.’</char><verse eid="LUK 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 21:10"/>Then he said to them: <char style="wj">‘Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 21:11"/><char style="wj">There will be great earthquakes, famines and pestilences in various places, and fearful events and great signs from heaven.</char><verse eid="LUK 21:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 21:12"/>
    <char style="wj">‘But before all this, they will seize you and persecute you. They will hand you over to synagogues and put you in prison, and you will be brought before kings and governors, and all on account of my name.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 21:13"/><char style="wj">And so you will bear testimony to me.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 21:14"/><char style="wj">But make up your mind not to worry beforehand how you will defend yourselves.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 21:15"/><char style="wj">For I will give you words and wisdom that none of your adversaries will be able to resist or contradict.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 21:16"/><char style="wj">You will be betrayed even by parents, brothers and sisters, relatives and friends, and they will put some of you to death.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 21:17"/><char style="wj">Everyone will hate you because of me.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 21:18"/><char style="wj">But not a hair of your head will perish.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 21:19"/><char style="wj">Stand firm, and you will win life.</char><verse eid="LUK 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 21:20"/>
    <char style="wj">‘When you see Jerusalem being surrounded by armies, you will know that its desolation is near.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 21:21"/><char style="wj">Then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains, let those in the city get out, and let those in the country not enter the city.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 21:22"/><char style="wj">For this is the time of punishment in fulfilment of all that has been written.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 21:23"/><char style="wj">How dreadful it will be in those days for pregnant women and nursing mothers! There will be great distress in the land and wrath against this people.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 21:24"/><char style="wj">They will fall by the sword and will be taken as prisoners to all the nations. Jerusalem will be trampled on by the Gentiles until the times of the Gentiles are fulfilled.</char><verse eid="LUK 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 21:25"/>
    <char style="wj">‘There will be signs in the sun, moon and stars. On the earth, nations will be in anguish and perplexity at the roaring and tossing of the sea.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 21:26"/><char style="wj">People will faint from terror, apprehensive of what is coming on the world, for the heavenly bodies will be shaken.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 21:27"/><char style="wj">At that time they will see the Son of Man coming in a cloud with power and great glory.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 21:28"/><char style="wj">When these things begin to take place, stand up and lift up your heads, because your redemption is drawing near.’</char><verse eid="LUK 21:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 21:29"/>He told them this parable: <char style="wj">‘Look at the fig-tree and all the trees.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 21:30"/><char style="wj">When they sprout leaves, you can see for yourselves and know that summer is near.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 21:31"/><char style="wj">Even so, when you see these things happening, you know that the kingdom of God is near.</char><verse eid="LUK 21:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 21:32"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Truly I tell you, this generation will certainly not pass away until all these things have happened.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 21:33"/><char style="wj">Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will never pass away.</char><verse eid="LUK 21:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 21:34"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Be careful, or your hearts will be weighed down with carousing, drunkenness and the anxieties of life, and that day will close on you suddenly like a trap.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 21:35"/><char style="wj">For it will come on all those who live on the face of the whole earth.</char> <verse eid="LUK 21:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 21:36"/><char style="wj">Be always on the watch, and pray that you may be able to escape all that is about to happen, and that you may be able to stand before the Son of Man.’</char><verse eid="LUK 21:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 21:37"/>Each day Jesus was teaching at the temple, and each evening he went out to spend the night on the hill called the Mount of Olives, <verse eid="LUK 21:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 21:38"/>and all the people came early in the morning to hear him at the temple.<verse eid="LUK 21:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="LUK 22"/>
  <para style="s1">Judas agrees to betray Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 22:1"/>Now the Festival of Unleavened Bread, called the Passover, was approaching, <verse eid="LUK 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 22:2"/>and the chief priests and the teachers of the law were looking for some way to get rid of Jesus, for they were afraid of the people. <verse eid="LUK 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 22:3"/>Then Satan entered Judas, called Iscariot, one of the Twelve. <verse eid="LUK 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 22:4"/>And Judas went to the chief priests and the officers of the temple guard and discussed with them how he might betray Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 22:5"/>They were delighted and agreed to give him money. <verse eid="LUK 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 22:6"/>He consented, and watched for an opportunity to hand Jesus over to them when no crowd was present.<verse eid="LUK 22:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Last Supper</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 22:7"/>Then came the day of Unleavened Bread on which the Passover lamb had to be sacrificed. <verse eid="LUK 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 22:8"/>Jesus sent Peter and John, saying, <char style="wj">‘Go and make preparations for us to eat the Passover.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 22:9"/>‘Where do you want us to prepare for it?’ they asked.<verse eid="LUK 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 22:10"/>He replied, <char style="wj">‘As you enter the city, a man carrying a jar of water will meet you. Follow him to the house that he enters,</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 22:11"/><char style="wj">and say to the owner of the house, “The Teacher asks: where is the guest room, where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?”</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 22:12"/><char style="wj">He will show you a large room upstairs, all furnished. Make preparations there.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 22:13"/>They left and found things just as Jesus had told them. So they prepared the Passover.<verse eid="LUK 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 22:14"/>When the hour came, Jesus and his apostles reclined at the table. <verse eid="LUK 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 22:15"/>And he said to them, <char style="wj">‘I have eagerly desired to eat this Passover with you before I suffer.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 22:16"/><char style="wj">For I tell you, I will not eat it again until it finds fulfilment in the kingdom of God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 22:17"/>After taking the cup, he gave thanks and said, <char style="wj">‘Take this and divide it among you.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 22:18"/><char style="wj">For I tell you I will not drink again from the fruit of the vine until the kingdom of God comes.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 22:19"/>And he took bread, gave thanks and broke it, and gave it to them, saying, <char style="wj">‘This is my body given for you; do this in remembrance of me.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 22:20"/>In the same way, after the supper he took the cup, saying, <char style="wj">‘This cup is the new covenant in my blood, which is poured out for you.</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:19,20 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts do not have </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">given for you… poured out for you.</char></note> <verse eid="LUK 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 22:21"/><char style="wj">But the hand of him who is going to betray me is with mine on the table.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 22:22"/><char style="wj">The Son of Man will go as it has been decreed. But woe to that man who betrays him!’</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 22:23"/>They began to question among themselves which of them it might be who would do this.<verse eid="LUK 22:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 22:24"/>A dispute also arose among them as to which of them was considered to be greatest. <verse eid="LUK 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 22:25"/>Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">‘The kings of the Gentiles lord it over them; and those who exercise authority over them call themselves Benefactors.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 22:26"/><char style="wj">But you are not to be like that. Instead, the greatest among you should be like the youngest, and the one who rules like the one who serves.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 22:27"/><char style="wj">For who is greater, the one who is at the table or the one who serves? Is it not the one who is at the table? But I am among you as one who serves.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 22:28"/><char style="wj">You are those who have stood by me in my trials.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 22:29"/><char style="wj">And I confer on you a kingdom, just as my Father conferred one on me,</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 22:30"/><char style="wj">so that you may eat and drink at my table in my kingdom and sit on thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel.</char><verse eid="LUK 22:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 22:31"/>
    <char style="wj">‘Simon, Simon, Satan has asked to sift all of you as wheat.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 22:32"/><char style="wj">But I have prayed for you, Simon, that your faith may not fail. And when you have turned back, strengthen your brothers.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 22:33"/>But he replied, ‘Lord, I am ready to go with you to prison and to death.’<verse eid="LUK 22:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 22:34"/>Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘I tell you, Peter, before the cock crows today, you will deny three times that you know me.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 22:35"/>Then Jesus asked them, <char style="wj">‘When I sent you without purse, bag or sandals, did you lack anything?’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 22:35">‘Nothing,’ they answered.<verse eid="LUK 22:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 22:36"/>He said to them, <char style="wj">‘But now if you have a purse, take it, and also a bag; and if you don’t have a sword, sell your cloak and buy one.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 22:37"/><char style="wj">It is written: “And he was numbered with the transgressors”</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:37 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="ISA 53:12">Isaiah 53:12</ref></char></char></note><char style="wj">; and I tell you that this must be fulfilled in me. Yes, what is written about me is reaching its fulfilment.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 22:38"/>The disciples said, ‘See, Lord, here are two swords.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 22:38">
    <char style="wj">‘That’s enough!’</char> he replied.<verse eid="LUK 22:38"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus prays on the Mount of Olives</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 22:39"/>Jesus went out as usual to the Mount of Olives, and his disciples followed him. <verse eid="LUK 22:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 22:40"/>On reaching the place, he said to them, <char style="wj">‘Pray that you will not fall into temptation.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 22:41"/>He withdrew about a stone’s throw beyond them, knelt down and prayed, <verse eid="LUK 22:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 22:42"/><char style="wj">‘Father, if you are willing, take this cup from me; yet not my will, but yours be done.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 22:43"/>An angel from heaven appeared to him and strengthened him. <verse eid="LUK 22:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 22:44"/>And being in anguish, he prayed more earnestly, and his sweat was like drops of blood falling to the ground.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">22:43,44 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Many early manuscripts do not have verses 43 and 44.</char></note><verse eid="LUK 22:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 22:45"/>When he rose from prayer and went back to the disciples, he found them asleep, exhausted from sorrow. <verse eid="LUK 22:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 22:46"/><char style="wj">‘Why are you sleeping?’</char> he asked them. <char style="wj">‘Get up and pray so that you will not fall into temptation.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:46"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus arrested</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 22:47"/>While he was still speaking a crowd came up, and the man who was called Judas, one of the Twelve, was leading them. He approached Jesus to kiss him, <verse eid="LUK 22:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 22:48"/>but Jesus asked him, <char style="wj">‘Judas, are you betraying the Son of Man with a kiss?’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 22:49"/>When Jesus’ followers saw what was going to happen, they said, ‘Lord, should we strike with our swords?’ <verse eid="LUK 22:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 22:50"/>And one of them struck the servant of the high priest, cutting off his right ear.<verse eid="LUK 22:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 22:51"/>But Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘No more of this!’</char> And he touched the man’s ear and healed him.<verse eid="LUK 22:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 22:52"/>Then Jesus said to the chief priests, the officers of the temple guard, and the elders, who had come for him, <char style="wj">‘Am I leading a rebellion, that you have come with swords and clubs?</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 22:53"/><char style="wj">Every day I was with you in the temple courts, and you did not lay a hand on me. But this is your hour – when darkness reigns.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:53"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter disowns Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 22:54"/>Then seizing him, they led him away and took him into the house of the high priest. Peter followed at a distance. <verse eid="LUK 22:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 22:55"/>And when some there had kindled a fire in the middle of the courtyard and had sat down together, Peter sat down with them. <verse eid="LUK 22:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 22:56"/>A servant-girl saw him seated there in the firelight. She looked closely at him and said, ‘This man was with him.’<verse eid="LUK 22:56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="LUK 22:57"/>But he denied it. ‘Woman, I don’t know him,’ he said.<verse eid="LUK 22:57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="LUK 22:58"/>A little later someone else saw him and said, ‘You also are one of them.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 22:58">‘Man, I am not!’ Peter replied.<verse eid="LUK 22:58"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" sid="LUK 22:59"/>About an hour later another asserted, ‘Certainly this fellow was with him, for he is a Galilean.’<verse eid="LUK 22:59"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="LUK 22:60"/>Peter replied, ‘Man, I don’t know what you’re talking about!’ Just as he was speaking, the cock crowed. <verse eid="LUK 22:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="LUK 22:61"/>The Lord turned and looked straight at Peter. Then Peter remembered the word the Lord had spoken to him: <char style="wj">‘Before the cock crows today, you will disown me three times.’</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="LUK 22:62"/>And he went outside and wept bitterly.<verse eid="LUK 22:62"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The guards mock Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" sid="LUK 22:63"/>The men who were guarding Jesus began mocking and beating him. <verse eid="LUK 22:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="LUK 22:64"/>They blindfolded him and demanded, ‘Prophesy! Who hit you?’ <verse eid="LUK 22:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="LUK 22:65"/>And they said many other insulting things to him.<verse eid="LUK 22:65"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus before Pilate and Herod</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" sid="LUK 22:66"/>At daybreak the council of the elders of the people, both the chief priests and the teachers of the law, met together, and Jesus was led before them. <verse eid="LUK 22:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="LUK 22:67"/>‘If you are the Messiah,’ they said, ‘tell us.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 22:67">Jesus answered, <char style="wj">‘If I tell you, you will not believe me,</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="LUK 22:68"/><char style="wj">and if I asked you, you would not answer.</char> <verse eid="LUK 22:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="LUK 22:69"/><char style="wj">But from now on, the Son of Man will be seated at the right hand of the mighty God.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:69"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="70" style="v" sid="LUK 22:70"/>They all asked, ‘Are you then the Son of God?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 22:70">He replied, <char style="wj">‘You say that I am.’</char><verse eid="LUK 22:70"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="71" style="v" sid="LUK 22:71"/>Then they said, ‘Why do we need any more testimony? We have heard it from his own lips.’<verse eid="LUK 22:71"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="LUK 23"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 23:1"/>Then the whole assembly rose and led him off to Pilate. <verse eid="LUK 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 23:2"/>And they began to accuse him, saying, ‘We have found this man subverting our nation. He opposes payment of taxes to Caesar and claims to be Messiah, a king.’<verse eid="LUK 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 23:3"/>So Pilate asked Jesus, ‘Are you the king of the Jews?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 23:3">
    <char style="wj">‘You have said so,’</char> Jesus replied.<verse eid="LUK 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 23:4"/>Then Pilate announced to the chief priests and the crowd, ‘I find no basis for a charge against this man.’<verse eid="LUK 23:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 23:5"/>But they insisted, ‘He stirs up the people all over Judea by his teaching. He started in Galilee and has come all the way here.’<verse eid="LUK 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 23:6"/>On hearing this, Pilate asked if the man was a Galilean. <verse eid="LUK 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 23:7"/>When he learned that Jesus was under Herod’s jurisdiction, he sent him to Herod, who was also in Jerusalem at that time.<verse eid="LUK 23:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 23:8"/>When Herod saw Jesus, he was greatly pleased, because for a long time he had been wanting to see him. From what he had heard about him, he hoped to see him perform a sign of some sort. <verse eid="LUK 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 23:9"/>He plied him with many questions, but Jesus gave him no answer. <verse eid="LUK 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 23:10"/>The chief priests and the teachers of the law were standing there, vehemently accusing him. <verse eid="LUK 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 23:11"/>Then Herod and his soldiers ridiculed and mocked him. Dressing him in an elegant robe, they sent him back to Pilate. <verse eid="LUK 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 23:12"/>That day Herod and Pilate became friends – before this they had been enemies.<verse eid="LUK 23:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 23:13"/>Pilate called together the chief priests, the rulers and the people, <verse eid="LUK 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 23:14"/>and said to them, ‘You brought me this man as one who was inciting the people to rebellion. I have examined him in your presence and have found no basis for your charges against him. <verse eid="LUK 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 23:15"/>Neither has Herod, for he sent him back to us; as you can see, he has done nothing to deserve death. <verse eid="LUK 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 23:16"/>Therefore, I will punish him and then release him.’ <verse eid="LUK 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" pubnumber="[17]" sid="LUK 23:17"/><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:17 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts include here words similar to <char style="xt"><ref loc="MAT 27:15">Matt. 27:15</ref></char> and <char style="xt"><ref loc="MRK 15:6">Mark 15:6</ref></char>.</char></note><verse eid="LUK 23:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 23:18"/>But the whole crowd shouted, ‘Away with this man! Release Barabbas to us!’ <verse eid="LUK 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 23:19"/>(Barabbas had been thrown into prison for an insurrection in the city, and for murder.)<verse eid="LUK 23:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 23:20"/>Wanting to release Jesus, Pilate appealed to them again. <verse eid="LUK 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 23:21"/>But they kept shouting, ‘Crucify him! Crucify him!’<verse eid="LUK 23:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 23:22"/>For the third time he spoke to them: ‘Why? What crime has this man committed? I have found in him no grounds for the death penalty. Therefore I will have him punished and then release him.’<verse eid="LUK 23:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 23:23"/>But with loud shouts they insistently demanded that he be crucified, and their shouts prevailed. <verse eid="LUK 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 23:24"/>So Pilate decided to grant their demand. <verse eid="LUK 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 23:25"/>He released the man who had been thrown into prison for insurrection and murder, the one they asked for, and surrendered Jesus to their will.<verse eid="LUK 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The crucifixion of Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 23:26"/>As the soldiers led him away, they seized Simon from Cyrene, who was on his way in from the country, and put the cross on him and made him carry it behind Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 23:27"/>A large number of people followed him, including women who mourned and wailed for him. <verse eid="LUK 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 23:28"/>Jesus turned and said to them, <char style="wj">‘Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for me; weep for yourselves and for your children.</char> <verse eid="LUK 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 23:29"/><char style="wj">For the time will come when you will say, “Blessed are the childless women, the wombs that never bore and the breasts that never nursed!”</char> <verse eid="LUK 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 23:30"/><char style="wj">Then</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LUK 23:30">
    <char style="wj">‘ “they will say to the mountains, ‘Fall on us!’</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LUK 23:30">
    <char style="wj">and to the hills, ‘Cover us!’ ”</char>
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="fr" closed="false">23:30 </char>
      <char style="ft" closed="false">
        <char style="xt">
          <ref loc="HOS 10:8">Hosea 10:8</ref>
        </char>
      </char>
    </note><verse eid="LUK 23:30"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 23:31"/>
    <char style="wj">For if people do these things when the tree is green, what will happen when it is dry?’</char><verse eid="LUK 23:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 23:32"/>Two other men, both criminals, were also led out with him to be executed. <verse eid="LUK 23:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 23:33"/>When they came to the place called the Skull, they crucified him there, along with the criminals – one on his right, the other on his left. <verse eid="LUK 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 23:34"/>Jesus said, <char style="wj">‘Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing.’</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:34 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some early manuscripts do not have this sentence.</char></note> And they divided up his clothes by casting lots.<verse eid="LUK 23:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 23:35"/>The people stood watching, and the rulers even sneered at him. They said, ‘He saved others; let him save himself if he is God’s Messiah, the Chosen One.’<verse eid="LUK 23:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 23:36"/>The soldiers also came up and mocked him. They offered him wine vinegar <verse eid="LUK 23:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 23:37"/>and said, ‘If you are the king of the Jews, save yourself.’<verse eid="LUK 23:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 23:38"/>There was a written notice above him, which read:</para>
  <para style="pc" vid="LUK 23:38">This is the king of the Jews.<verse eid="LUK 23:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 23:39"/>One of the criminals who hung there hurled insults at him: ‘Aren’t you the Messiah? Save yourself and us!’<verse eid="LUK 23:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 23:40"/>But the other criminal rebuked him. ‘Don’t you fear God,’ he said, ‘since you are under the same sentence? <verse eid="LUK 23:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 23:41"/>We are punished justly, for we are getting what our deeds deserve. But this man has done nothing wrong.’<verse eid="LUK 23:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 23:42"/>Then he said, ‘Jesus, remember me when you come into your kingdom.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:42 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">come with your kingly power</char></note>’<verse eid="LUK 23:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 23:43"/>Jesus answered him, <char style="wj">‘Truly I tell you, today you will be with me in paradise.’</char><verse eid="LUK 23:43"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The death of Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 23:44"/>It was now about noon, and darkness came over the whole land until three in the afternoon, <verse eid="LUK 23:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 23:45"/>for the sun stopped shining. And the curtain of the temple was torn in two. <verse eid="LUK 23:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 23:46"/>Jesus called out with a loud voice, <char style="wj">‘Father, into your hands I commit my spirit.’</char><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">23:46 </char><char style="ft" closed="false"><char style="xt"><ref loc="PSA 31:5">Psalm 31:5</ref></char></char></note> When he had said this, he breathed his last.<verse eid="LUK 23:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 23:47"/>The centurion, seeing what had happened, praised God and said, ‘Surely this was a righteous man.’ <verse eid="LUK 23:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 23:48"/>When all the people who had gathered to witness this sight saw what took place, they beat their breasts and went away. <verse eid="LUK 23:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 23:49"/>But all those who knew him, including the women who had followed him from Galilee, stood at a distance, watching these things.<verse eid="LUK 23:49"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The burial of Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 23:50"/>Now there was a man named Joseph, a member of the Council, a good and upright man, <verse eid="LUK 23:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 23:51"/>who had not consented to their decision and action. He came from the Judean town of Arimathea, and he himself was waiting for the kingdom of God. <verse eid="LUK 23:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 23:52"/>Going to Pilate, he asked for Jesus’ body. <verse eid="LUK 23:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 23:53"/>Then he took it down, wrapped it in linen cloth and placed it in a tomb cut in the rock, one in which no-one had yet been laid. <verse eid="LUK 23:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LUK 23:54"/>It was Preparation Day, and the Sabbath was about to begin.<verse eid="LUK 23:54"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="LUK 23:55"/>The women who had come with Jesus from Galilee followed Joseph and saw the tomb and how his body was laid in it. <verse eid="LUK 23:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LUK 23:56"/>Then they went home and prepared spices and perfumes. But they rested on the Sabbath in obedience to the commandment.<verse eid="LUK 23:56"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="LUK 24"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus has risen</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LUK 24:1"/>On the first day of the week, very early in the morning, the women took the spices they had prepared and went to the tomb. <verse eid="LUK 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LUK 24:2"/>They found the stone rolled away from the tomb, <verse eid="LUK 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LUK 24:3"/>but when they entered, they did not find the body of the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="LUK 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LUK 24:4"/>While they were wondering about this, suddenly two men in clothes that gleamed like lightning stood beside them. <verse eid="LUK 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LUK 24:5"/>In their fright the women bowed down with their faces to the ground, but the men said to them, ‘Why do you look for the living among the dead? <verse eid="LUK 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LUK 24:6"/>He is not here; he has risen! Remember how he told you, while he was still with you in Galilee: <verse eid="LUK 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LUK 24:7"/><char style="wj">“The Son of Man must be delivered over to the hands of sinners, be crucified and on the third day be raised again.”</char> ’ <verse eid="LUK 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LUK 24:8"/>Then they remembered his words.<verse eid="LUK 24:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LUK 24:9"/>When they came back from the tomb, they told all these things to the Eleven and to all the others. <verse eid="LUK 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LUK 24:10"/>It was Mary Magdalene, Joanna, Mary the mother of James, and the others with them who told this to the apostles. <verse eid="LUK 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LUK 24:11"/>But they did not believe the women, because their words seemed to them like nonsense. <verse eid="LUK 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LUK 24:12"/>Peter, however, got up and ran to the tomb. Bending over, he saw the strips of linen lying by themselves, and he went away, wondering to himself what had happened.<verse eid="LUK 24:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">On the road to Emmaus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LUK 24:13"/>Now that same day two of them were going to a village called Emmaus, about seven miles<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">24:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or about 11 kilometres</char></note> from Jerusalem. <verse eid="LUK 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LUK 24:14"/>They were talking with each other about everything that had happened. <verse eid="LUK 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LUK 24:15"/>As they talked and discussed these things with each other, Jesus himself came up and walked along with them; <verse eid="LUK 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LUK 24:16"/>but they were kept from recognising him.<verse eid="LUK 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LUK 24:17"/>He asked them, <char style="wj">‘What are you discussing together as you walk along?’</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 24:17">They stood still, their faces downcast. <verse eid="LUK 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LUK 24:18"/>One of them, named Cleopas, asked him, ‘Are you the only one visiting Jerusalem who does not know the things that have happened there in these days?’<verse eid="LUK 24:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LUK 24:19"/>
    <char style="wj">‘What things?’</char> he asked.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LUK 24:19">‘About Jesus of Nazareth,’ they replied. ‘He was a prophet, powerful in word and deed before God and all the people. <verse eid="LUK 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LUK 24:20"/>The chief priests and our rulers handed him over to be sentenced to death, and they crucified him; <verse eid="LUK 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LUK 24:21"/>but we had hoped that he was the one who was going to redeem Israel. And what is more, it is the third day since all this took place. <verse eid="LUK 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LUK 24:22"/>In addition, some of our women amazed us. They went to the tomb early this morning <verse eid="LUK 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LUK 24:23"/>but didn’t find his body. They came and told us that they had seen a vision of angels, who said he was alive. <verse eid="LUK 24:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LUK 24:24"/>Then some of our companions went to the tomb and found it just as the women had said, but they did not see Jesus.’<verse eid="LUK 24:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LUK 24:25"/>He said to them, <char style="wj">‘How foolish you are, and how slow to believe all that the prophets have spoken!</char> <verse eid="LUK 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LUK 24:26"/><char style="wj">Did not the Messiah have to suffer these things and then enter his glory?’</char> <verse eid="LUK 24:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LUK 24:27"/>And beginning with Moses and all the Prophets, he explained to them what was said in all the Scriptures concerning himself.<verse eid="LUK 24:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LUK 24:28"/>As they approached the village to which they were going, Jesus continued on as if he were going further. <verse eid="LUK 24:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LUK 24:29"/>But they urged him strongly, ‘Stay with us, for it is nearly evening; the day is almost over.’ So he went in to stay with them.<verse eid="LUK 24:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LUK 24:30"/>When he was at the table with them, he took bread, gave thanks, broke it and began to give it to them. <verse eid="LUK 24:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LUK 24:31"/>Then their eyes were opened and they recognised him, and he disappeared from their sight. <verse eid="LUK 24:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LUK 24:32"/>They asked each other, ‘Were not our hearts burning within us while he talked with us on the road and opened the Scriptures to us?’<verse eid="LUK 24:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LUK 24:33"/>They got up and returned at once to Jerusalem. There they found the Eleven and those with them, assembled together <verse eid="LUK 24:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LUK 24:34"/>and saying, ‘It is true! The Lord has risen and has appeared to Simon.’ <verse eid="LUK 24:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LUK 24:35"/>Then the two told what had happened on the way, and how Jesus was recognised by them when he broke the bread.<verse eid="LUK 24:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus appears to the disciples</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LUK 24:36"/>While they were still talking about this, Jesus himself stood among them and said to them, <char style="wj">‘Peace be with you.’</char><verse eid="LUK 24:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LUK 24:37"/>They were startled and frightened, thinking they saw a ghost. <verse eid="LUK 24:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LUK 24:38"/>He said to them, <char style="wj">‘Why are you troubled, and why do doubts rise in your minds?</char> <verse eid="LUK 24:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LUK 24:39"/><char style="wj">Look at my hands and my feet. It is I myself! Touch me and see; a ghost does not have flesh and bones, as you see I have.’</char><verse eid="LUK 24:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="LUK 24:40"/>When he had said this, he showed them his hands and feet. <verse eid="LUK 24:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LUK 24:41"/>And while they still did not believe it because of joy and amazement, he asked them, <char style="wj">‘Do you have anything here to eat?’</char> <verse eid="LUK 24:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LUK 24:42"/>They gave him a piece of broiled fish, <verse eid="LUK 24:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LUK 24:43"/>and he took it and ate it in their presence.<verse eid="LUK 24:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LUK 24:44"/>He said to them, <char style="wj">‘This is what I told you while I was still with you: everything must be fulfilled that is written about me in the Law of Moses, the Prophets and the Psalms.’</char><verse eid="LUK 24:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LUK 24:45"/>Then he opened their minds so they could understand the Scriptures. <verse eid="LUK 24:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LUK 24:46"/>He told them, <char style="wj">‘This is what is written: the Messiah will suffer and rise from the dead on the third day,</char> <verse eid="LUK 24:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LUK 24:47"/><char style="wj">and repentance for the forgiveness of sins will be preached in his name to all nations, beginning at Jerusalem.</char> <verse eid="LUK 24:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LUK 24:48"/><char style="wj">You are witnesses of these things.</char> <verse eid="LUK 24:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LUK 24:49"/><char style="wj">I am going to send you what my Father has promised; but stay in the city until you have been clothed with power from on high.’</char><verse eid="LUK 24:49"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The ascension of Jesus</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="LUK 24:50"/>When he had led them out to the vicinity of Bethany, he lifted up his hands and blessed them. <verse eid="LUK 24:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LUK 24:51"/>While he was blessing them, he left them and was taken up into heaven. <verse eid="LUK 24:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LUK 24:52"/>Then they worshipped him and returned to Jerusalem with great joy. <verse eid="LUK 24:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LUK 24:53"/>And they stayed continually at the temple, praising God.<verse eid="LUK 24:53"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LUK 24"/>
</usx>
