<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="NEH" style="id">- English-UK: New International Version® (Anglicised) NIV® 2011 (Revised format)</book>
  <para style="rem">Copyright © 1973, 1978, 1984, 2011 by Biblica, Inc.®</para>
  <para style="h">Nehemiah</para>
  <para style="toc1">Nehemiah</para>
  <para style="toc2">Neh.</para>
  <para style="toc3">Ne</para>
  <para style="mt1">Nehemiah</para>
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="im">See the Invitation to Chronicles-Ezra-Nehemiah.</para>
  <para style="ie"/>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="NEH 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Nehemiah’s prayer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 1:1"/>The words of Nehemiah son of Hakaliah:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 1:1"/>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 1:1"/>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 1:1">In the month of Kislev in the twentieth year, while I was in the citadel of Susa, <verse eid="NEH 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 1:2"/>Hanani, one of my brothers, came from Judah with some other men, and I questioned them about the Jewish remnant that had survived the exile, and also about Jerusalem.<verse eid="NEH 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 1:3"/>They said to me, ‘Those who survived the exile and are back in the province are in great trouble and disgrace. The wall of Jerusalem is broken down, and its gates have been burned with fire.’<verse eid="NEH 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 1:4"/>When I heard these things, I sat down and wept. For some days I mourned and fasted and prayed before the God of heaven. <verse eid="NEH 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 1:5"/>Then I said:</para>
  <para style="pm" vid="NEH 1:5">‘<char style="sc">Lord</char>, the God of heaven, the great and awesome God, who keeps his covenant of love with those who love him and keep his commandments, <verse eid="NEH 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 1:6"/>let your ear be attentive and your eyes open to hear the prayer your servant is praying before you day and night for your servants, the people of Israel. I confess the sins we Israelites, including myself and my father’s family, have committed against you. <verse eid="NEH 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 1:7"/>We have acted very wickedly towards you. We have not obeyed the commands, decrees and laws you gave your servant Moses.<verse eid="NEH 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 1:8"/>‘Remember the instruction you gave your servant Moses, saying, “If you are unfaithful, I will scatter you among the nations, <verse eid="NEH 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 1:9"/>but if you return to me and obey my commands, then even if your exiled people are at the farthest horizon, I will gather them from there and bring them to the place I have chosen as a dwelling for my Name.”<verse eid="NEH 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 1:10"/>‘They are your servants and your people, whom you redeemed by your great strength and your mighty hand. <verse eid="NEH 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 1:11"/>Lord, let your ear be attentive to the prayer of this your servant and to the prayer of your servants who delight in revering your name. Give your servant success today by granting him favour in the presence of this man.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 1:11">I was cupbearer to the king.<verse eid="NEH 1:11"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="NEH 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Artaxerxes sends Nehemiah to Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 2:1"/>In the month of Nisan in the twentieth year of King Artaxerxes, when wine was brought for him, I took the wine and gave it to the king. I had not been sad in his presence before, <verse eid="NEH 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 2:2"/>so the king asked me, ‘Why does your face look so sad when you are not ill? This can be nothing but sadness of heart.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 2:2">I was very much afraid, <verse eid="NEH 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 2:3"/>but I said to the king, ‘May the king live for ever! Why should my face not look sad when the city where my ancestors are buried lies in ruins, and its gates have been destroyed by fire?’<verse eid="NEH 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 2:4"/>The king said to me, ‘What is it you want?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 2:4">Then I prayed to the God of heaven, <verse eid="NEH 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 2:5"/>and I answered the king, ‘If it pleases the king and if your servant has found favour in his sight, let him send me to the city in Judah where my ancestors are buried so that I can rebuild it.’<verse eid="NEH 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 2:6"/>Then the king, with the queen sitting beside him, asked me, ‘How long will your journey take, and when will you get back?’ It pleased the king to send me; so I set a time.<verse eid="NEH 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 2:7"/>I also said to him, ‘If it pleases the king, may I have letters to the governors of Trans-Euphrates, so that they will provide me safe-conduct until I arrive in Judah? <verse eid="NEH 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 2:8"/>And may I have a letter to Asaph, keeper of the royal park, so he will give me timber to make beams for the gates of the citadel by the temple and for the city wall and for the residence I will occupy?’ And because the gracious hand of my God was on me, the king granted my requests. <verse eid="NEH 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 2:9"/>So I went to the governors of Trans-Euphrates and gave them the king’s letters. The king had also sent army officers and cavalry with me.<verse eid="NEH 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 2:10"/>When Sanballat the Horonite and Tobiah the Ammonite official heard about this, they were very much disturbed that someone had come to promote the welfare of the Israelites.<verse eid="NEH 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Nehemiah inspects Jerusalem’s walls</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 2:11"/>I went to Jerusalem, and after staying there three days <verse eid="NEH 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 2:12"/>I set out during the night with a few others. I had not told anyone what my God had put in my heart to do for Jerusalem. There were no mounts with me except the one I was riding on.<verse eid="NEH 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 2:13"/>By night I went out through the Valley Gate towards the Jackal<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Serpent </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Fig</char></note> Well and the Dung Gate, examining the walls of Jerusalem, which had been broken down, and its gates, which had been destroyed by fire. <verse eid="NEH 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 2:14"/>Then I moved on towards the Fountain Gate and the King’s Pool, but there was not enough room for my mount to get through; <verse eid="NEH 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 2:15"/>so I went up the valley by night, examining the wall. Finally, I turned back and re-entered through the Valley Gate. <verse eid="NEH 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 2:16"/>The officials did not know where I had gone or what I was doing, because as yet I had said nothing to the Jews or the priests or nobles or officials or any others who would be doing the work.<verse eid="NEH 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 2:17"/>Then I said to them, ‘You see the trouble we are in: Jerusalem lies in ruins, and its gates have been burned with fire. Come, let us rebuild the wall of Jerusalem, and we will no longer be in disgrace.’ <verse eid="NEH 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 2:18"/>I also told them about the gracious hand of my God on me and what the king had said to me.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 2:18">They replied, ‘Let us start rebuilding.’ So they began this good work.<verse eid="NEH 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 2:19"/>But when Sanballat the Horonite, Tobiah the Ammonite official and Geshem the Arab heard about it, they mocked and ridiculed us. ‘What is this you are doing?’ they asked. ‘Are you rebelling against the king?’<verse eid="NEH 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 2:20"/>I answered them by saying, ‘The God of heaven will give us success. We his servants will start rebuilding, but as for you, you have no share in Jerusalem or any claim or historic right to it.’<verse eid="NEH 2:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="NEH 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Builders of the wall</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 3:1"/>Eliashib the high priest and his fellow priests went to work and rebuilt the Sheep Gate. They dedicated it and set its doors in place, building as far as the Tower of the Hundred, which they dedicated, and as far as the Tower of Hananel. <verse eid="NEH 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 3:2"/>The men of Jericho built the adjoining section, and Zakkur son of Imri built next to them.<verse eid="NEH 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 3:3"/>The Fish Gate was rebuilt by the sons of Hassenaah. They laid its beams and put its doors and bolts and bars in place. <verse eid="NEH 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 3:4"/>Meremoth son of Uriah, the son of Hakkoz, repaired the next section. Next to him Meshullam son of Berekiah, the son of Meshezabel, made repairs, and next to him Zadok son of Baana also made repairs. <verse eid="NEH 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 3:5"/>The next section was repaired by the men of Tekoa, but their nobles would not put their shoulders to the work under their supervisors.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">their Lord </char><char style="ft" closed="false">or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the governor</char></note><verse eid="NEH 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 3:6"/>The Jeshanah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Old</char></note> Gate was repaired by Joiada son of Paseah and Meshullam son of Besodeiah. They laid its beams and put its doors with their bolts and bars in place. <verse eid="NEH 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 3:7"/>Next to them, repairs were made by men from Gibeon and Mizpah – Melatiah of Gibeon and Jadon of Meronoth – places under the authority of the governor of Trans-Euphrates. <verse eid="NEH 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 3:8"/>Uzziel son of Harhaiah, one of the goldsmiths, repaired the next section; and Hananiah, one of the perfume-makers, made repairs next to that. They restored Jerusalem as far as the Broad Wall. <verse eid="NEH 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 3:9"/>Rephaiah son of Hur, ruler of a half-district of Jerusalem, repaired the next section. <verse eid="NEH 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 3:10"/>Adjoining this, Jedaiah son of Harumaph made repairs opposite his house, and Hattush son of Hashabneiah made repairs next to him. <verse eid="NEH 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 3:11"/>Malkijah son of Harim and Hasshub son of Pahath-Moab repaired another section and the Tower of the Ovens. <verse eid="NEH 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 3:12"/>Shallum son of Hallohesh, ruler of a half-district of Jerusalem, repaired the next section with the help of his daughters.<verse eid="NEH 3:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 3:13"/>The Valley Gate was repaired by Hanun and the residents of Zanoah. They rebuilt it and put its doors with their bolts and bars in place. They also repaired a thousand cubits<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:13 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 450 metres</char></note> of the wall as far as the Dung Gate.<verse eid="NEH 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 3:14"/>The Dung Gate was repaired by Malkijah son of Rekab, ruler of the district of Beth Hakkerem. He rebuilt it and put its doors with their bolts and bars in place.<verse eid="NEH 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 3:15"/>The Fountain Gate was repaired by Shallun son of Kol-Hozeh, ruler of the district of Mizpah. He rebuilt it, roofing it over and putting its doors and bolts and bars in place. He also repaired the wall of the Pool of Siloam,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shelah, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shiloah, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">that is, Siloam</char></note> by the King’s Garden, as far as the steps going down from the City of David. <verse eid="NEH 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 3:16"/>Beyond him, Nehemiah son of Azbuk, ruler of a half-district of Beth Zur, made repairs up to a point opposite the tombs<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew; Septuagint, some Vulgate manuscripts and Syriac </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">tomb</char></note> of David, as far as the artificial pool and the House of the Heroes.<verse eid="NEH 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 3:17"/>Next to him, the repairs were made by the Levites under Rehum son of Bani. Beside him, Hashabiah, ruler of half the district of Keilah, carried out repairs for his district. <verse eid="NEH 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 3:18"/>Next to him, the repairs were made by their fellow Levites under Binnui<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">3:18 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Two Hebrew manuscripts and Syriac (see also Septuagint and verse 24); most Hebrew manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Bavvai</char></note> son of Henadad, ruler of the other half-district of Keilah. <verse eid="NEH 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 3:19"/>Next to him, Ezer son of Jeshua, ruler of Mizpah, repaired another section, from a point facing the ascent to the armoury as far as the angle of the wall. <verse eid="NEH 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 3:20"/>Next to him, Baruch son of Zabbai zealously repaired another section, from the angle to the entrance of the house of Eliashib the high priest. <verse eid="NEH 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 3:21"/>Next to him, Meremoth son of Uriah, the son of Hakkoz, repaired another section, from the entrance of Eliashib’s house to the end of it.<verse eid="NEH 3:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 3:22"/>The repairs next to him were made by the priests from the surrounding region. <verse eid="NEH 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 3:23"/>Beyond them, Benjamin and Hasshub made repairs in front of their house; and next to them, Azariah son of Maaseiah, the son of Ananiah, made repairs beside his house. <verse eid="NEH 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 3:24"/>Next to him, Binnui son of Henadad repaired another section, from Azariah’s house to the angle and the corner, <verse eid="NEH 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 3:25"/>and Palal son of Uzai worked opposite the angle and the tower projecting from the upper palace near the court of the guard. Next to him, Pedaiah son of Parosh <verse eid="NEH 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 3:26"/>and the temple servants living on the hill of Ophel made repairs up to a point opposite the Water Gate towards the east and the projecting tower. <verse eid="NEH 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 3:27"/>Next to them, the men of Tekoa repaired another section, from the great projecting tower to the wall of Ophel.<verse eid="NEH 3:27"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 3:28"/>Above the Horse Gate, the priests made repairs, each in front of his own house. <verse eid="NEH 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 3:29"/>Next to them, Zadok son of Immer made repairs opposite his house. Next to him, Shemaiah son of Shekaniah, the guard at the East Gate, made repairs. <verse eid="NEH 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 3:30"/>Next to him, Hananiah son of Shelemiah, and Hanun, the sixth son of Zalaph, repaired another section. Next to them, Meshullam son of Berekiah made repairs opposite his living quarters. <verse eid="NEH 3:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 3:31"/>Next to him, Malkijah, one of the goldsmiths, made repairs as far as the house of the temple servants and the merchants, opposite the Inspection Gate, and as far as the room above the corner; <verse eid="NEH 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 3:32"/>and between the room above the corner and the Sheep Gate the goldsmiths and merchants made repairs.<verse eid="NEH 3:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="NEH 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Opposition to the rebuilding</para>
  <para style="p">
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="ft" closed="false">In Hebrew texts 4:1-6 is numbered 3:33-38, and 4:7-23 is numbered 4:1-17.</char>
    </note> <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 4:1"/>When Sanballat heard that we were rebuilding the wall, he became angry and was greatly incensed. He ridiculed the Jews, <verse eid="NEH 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 4:2"/>and in the presence of his associates and the army of Samaria, he said, ‘What are those feeble Jews doing? Will they restore their wall? Will they offer sacrifices? Will they finish in a day? Can they bring the stones back to life from those heaps of rubble – burned as they are?’<verse eid="NEH 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 4:3"/>Tobiah the Ammonite, who was at his side, said, ‘What they are building – even a fox climbing up on it would break down their wall of stones!’<verse eid="NEH 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 4:4"/>Hear us, our God, for we are despised. Turn their insults back on their own heads. Give them over as plunder in a land of captivity. <verse eid="NEH 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 4:5"/>Do not cover up their guilt or blot out their sins from your sight, for they have thrown insults in the face of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">have aroused your anger before</char></note> the builders.<verse eid="NEH 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 4:6"/>So we rebuilt the wall till all of it reached half its height, for the people worked with all their heart.<verse eid="NEH 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 4:7"/>But when Sanballat, Tobiah, the Arabs, the Ammonites and the people of Ashdod heard that the repairs to Jerusalem’s walls had gone ahead and that the gaps were being closed, they were very angry. <verse eid="NEH 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 4:8"/>They all plotted together to come and fight against Jerusalem and stir up trouble against it. <verse eid="NEH 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 4:9"/>But we prayed to our God and posted a guard day and night to meet this threat.<verse eid="NEH 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 4:10"/>Meanwhile, the people in Judah said, ‘The strength of the labourers is giving out, and there is so much rubble that we cannot rebuild the wall.’<verse eid="NEH 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 4:11"/>Also our enemies said, ‘Before they know it or see us, we will be right there among them and will kill them and put an end to the work.’<verse eid="NEH 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 4:12"/>Then the Jews who lived near them came and told us ten times over, ‘Wherever you turn, they will attack us.’<verse eid="NEH 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 4:13"/>Therefore I stationed some of the people behind the lowest points of the wall at the exposed places, posting them by families, with their swords, spears and bows. <verse eid="NEH 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 4:14"/>After I looked things over, I stood up and said to the nobles, the officials and the rest of the people, ‘Don’t be afraid of them. Remember the Lord, who is great and awesome, and fight for your families, your sons and your daughters, your wives and your homes.’<verse eid="NEH 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 4:15"/>When our enemies heard that we were aware of their plot and that God had frustrated it, we all returned to the wall, each to our work.<verse eid="NEH 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 4:16"/>From that day on, half of my men did the work, while the other half were equipped with spears, shields, bows and armour. The officers posted themselves behind all the people of Judah <verse eid="NEH 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 4:17"/>who were building the wall. Those who carried materials did their work with one hand and held a weapon in the other, <verse eid="NEH 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 4:18"/>and each of the builders wore his sword at his side as he worked. But the man who sounded the trumpet stayed with me.<verse eid="NEH 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 4:19"/>Then I said to the nobles, the officials and the rest of the people, ‘The work is extensive and spread out, and we are widely separated from each other along the wall. <verse eid="NEH 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 4:20"/>Wherever you hear the sound of the trumpet, join us there. Our God will fight for us!’<verse eid="NEH 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 4:21"/>So we continued the work with half the men holding spears, from the first light of dawn till the stars came out. <verse eid="NEH 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 4:22"/>At that time I also said to the people, ‘Let every man and his helper stay inside Jerusalem at night, so that they can serve us as guards by night and as workers by day.’ <verse eid="NEH 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 4:23"/>Neither I nor my brothers nor my men nor the guards with me took off our clothes; each had his weapon, even when he went for water.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">4:23 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">The meaning of the Hebrew for this clause is uncertain.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 4:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="NEH 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Nehemiah helps the poor</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 5:1"/>Now the men and their wives raised a great outcry against their fellow Jews. <verse eid="NEH 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 5:2"/>Some were saying, ‘We and our sons and daughters are numerous; in order for us to eat and stay alive, we must get grain.’<verse eid="NEH 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 5:3"/>Others were saying, ‘We are mortgaging our fields, our vineyards and our homes to get grain during the famine.’<verse eid="NEH 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 5:4"/>Still others were saying, ‘We have had to borrow money to pay the king’s tax on our fields and vineyards. <verse eid="NEH 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 5:5"/>Although we are of the same flesh and blood as our fellow Jews and though our children are as good as theirs, yet we have to subject our sons and daughters to slavery. Some of our daughters have already been enslaved, but we are powerless, because our fields and our vineyards belong to others.’<verse eid="NEH 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 5:6"/>When I heard their outcry and these charges, I was very angry. <verse eid="NEH 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 5:7"/>I pondered them in my mind and then accused the nobles and officials. I told them, ‘You are charging your own people interest!’ So I called together a large meeting to deal with them <verse eid="NEH 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 5:8"/>and said: ‘As far as possible, we have bought back our fellow Jews who were sold to the Gentiles. Now you are selling your own people, only for them to be sold back to us!’ They kept quiet, because they could find nothing to say.<verse eid="NEH 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 5:9"/>So I continued, ‘What you are doing is not right. Shouldn’t you walk in the fear of our God to avoid the reproach of our Gentile enemies? <verse eid="NEH 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 5:10"/>I and my brothers and my men are also lending the people money and grain. But let us stop charging interest! <verse eid="NEH 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 5:11"/>Give back to them immediately their fields, vineyards, olive groves and houses, and also the interest you are charging them – one per cent of the money, grain, new wine and olive oil.’<verse eid="NEH 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 5:12"/>‘We will give it back,’ they said. ‘And we will not demand anything more from them. We will do as you say.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 5:12">Then I summoned the priests and made the nobles and officials take an oath to do what they had promised. <verse eid="NEH 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 5:13"/>I also shook out the folds of my robe and said, ‘In this way may God shake out of their house and possessions anyone who does not keep this promise. So may such a person be shaken out and emptied!’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 5:13">At this the whole assembly said, ‘Amen,’ and praised the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. And the people did as they had promised.<verse eid="NEH 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 5:14"/>Moreover, from the twentieth year of King Artaxerxes, when I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, until his thirty-second year – twelve years – neither I nor my brothers ate the food allotted to the governor. <verse eid="NEH 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 5:15"/>But the earlier governors – those preceding me – placed a heavy burden on the people and took forty shekels<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 460 grams</char></note> of silver from them in addition to food and wine. Their assistants also lorded it over the people. But out of reverence for God I did not act like that. <verse eid="NEH 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 5:16"/>Instead, I devoted myself to the work on this wall. All my men were assembled there for the work; we<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:16 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Most Hebrew manuscripts; some Hebrew manuscripts, Septuagint, Vulgate and Syriac </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">I</char></note> did not acquire any land.<verse eid="NEH 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 5:17"/>Furthermore, a hundred and fifty Jews and officials ate at my table, as well as those who came to us from the surrounding nations. <verse eid="NEH 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 5:18"/>Each day one ox, six choice sheep and some poultry were prepared for me, and every ten days an abundant supply of wine of all kinds. In spite of all this, I never demanded the food allotted to the governor, because the demands were heavy on these people.<verse eid="NEH 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 5:19"/>Remember me with favour, my God, for all I have done for these people.<verse eid="NEH 5:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="NEH 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Further opposition to the rebuilding</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 6:1"/>When word came to Sanballat, Tobiah, Geshem the Arab and the rest of our enemies that I had rebuilt the wall and not a gap was left in it – though up to that time I had not set the doors in the gates – <verse eid="NEH 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 6:2"/>Sanballat and Geshem sent me this message: ‘Come, let us meet together in one of the villages<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:2 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">in Kephirim</char></note> on the plain of Ono.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 6:2">But they were scheming to harm me; <verse eid="NEH 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 6:3"/>so I sent messengers to them with this reply: ‘I am carrying on a great project and cannot go down. Why should the work stop while I leave it and go down to you?’ <verse eid="NEH 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 6:4"/>Four times they sent me the same message, and each time I gave them the same answer.<verse eid="NEH 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 6:5"/>Then, the fifth time, Sanballat sent his assistant to me with the same message, and in his hand was an unsealed letter <verse eid="NEH 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 6:6"/>in which was written:</para>
  <para style="pm" vid="NEH 6:6">‘It is reported among the nations – and Geshem<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">6:6 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Gashmu, </char><char style="ft" closed="false">a variant of </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Geshem</char></note> says it is true – that you and the Jews are plotting to revolt, and therefore you are building the wall. Moreover, according to these reports you are about to become their king <verse eid="NEH 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 6:7"/>and have even appointed prophets to make this proclamation about you in Jerusalem: “There is a king in Judah!” Now this report will get back to the king; so come, let us meet together.’<verse eid="NEH 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 6:8"/>I sent him this reply: ‘Nothing like what you are saying is happening; you are just making it up out of your head.’<verse eid="NEH 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 6:9"/>They were all trying to frighten us, thinking, ‘Their hands will get too weak for the work, and it will not be completed.’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 6:9">But I prayed, ‘Now strengthen my hands.’<verse eid="NEH 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 6:10"/>One day I went to the house of Shemaiah son of Delaiah, the son of Mehetabel, who was shut in at his home. He said, ‘Let us meet in the house of God, inside the temple, and let us close the temple doors, because men are coming to kill you – by night they are coming to kill you.’<verse eid="NEH 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 6:11"/>But I said, ‘Should a man like me run away? Or should someone like me go into the temple to save his life? I will not go!’ <verse eid="NEH 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 6:12"/>I realised that God had not sent him, but that he had prophesied against me because Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him. <verse eid="NEH 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 6:13"/>He had been hired to intimidate me so that I would commit a sin by doing this, and then they would give me a bad name to discredit me.<verse eid="NEH 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 6:14"/>Remember Tobiah and Sanballat, my God, because of what they have done; remember also the prophet Noadiah and how she and the rest of the prophets have been trying to intimidate me. <verse eid="NEH 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 6:15"/>So the wall was completed on the twenty-fifth of Elul, in fifty-two days.<verse eid="NEH 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Opposition to the completed wall</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 6:16"/>When all our enemies heard about this, all the surrounding nations were afraid and lost their self-confidence, because they realised that this work had been done with the help of our God.<verse eid="NEH 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 6:17"/>Also, in those days the nobles of Judah were sending many letters to Tobiah, and replies from Tobiah kept coming to them. <verse eid="NEH 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 6:18"/>For many in Judah were under oath to him, since he was son-in-law to Shekaniah son of Arah, and his son Jehohanan had married the daughter of Meshullam son of Berekiah. <verse eid="NEH 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 6:19"/>Moreover, they kept reporting to me his good deeds and then telling him what I said. And Tobiah sent letters to intimidate me.<verse eid="NEH 6:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="NEH 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 7:1"/>After the wall had been rebuilt and I had set the doors in place, the gatekeepers, the musicians and the Levites were appointed. <verse eid="NEH 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 7:2"/>I put in charge of Jerusalem my brother Hanani, along with Hananiah the commander of the citadel, because he was a man of integrity and feared God more than most people do. <verse eid="NEH 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 7:3"/>I said to them, ‘The gates of Jerusalem are not to be opened until the sun is hot. While the gatekeepers are still on duty, make them shut the doors and bar them. Also appoint residents of Jerusalem as guards, some at their posts and some near their own houses.’<verse eid="NEH 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The list of the exiles who returned</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 7:4"/>Now the city was large and spacious, but there were few people in it, and the houses had not yet been rebuilt. <verse eid="NEH 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 7:5"/>So my God put it into my heart to assemble the nobles, the officials and the common people for registration by families. I found the genealogical record of those who had been the first to return. This is what I found written there:<verse eid="NEH 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 7:6"/>These are the people of the province who came up from the captivity of the exiles whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had taken captive (they returned to Jerusalem and Judah, each to his own town, <verse eid="NEH 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 7:7"/>in company with Zerubbabel, Joshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum and Baanah):</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:7"/>
  <para style="li4" vid="NEH 7:7">The list of the men of the people of Israel:<verse eid="NEH 7:7"/></para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 7:8"/>the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Parosh </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">2,172</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:8"/>
        <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 7:9"/>Shephatiah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">372</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:9"/>
        <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 7:10"/>Arah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">652</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:10"/>
        <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 7:11"/>Pahath-Moab (through the line of Jeshua and Joab) </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">2,818</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:11"/>
        <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 7:12"/>Elam </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">1,254</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:12"/>
        <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 7:13"/>Zattu </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">845</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:13"/>
        <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 7:14"/>Zakkai </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">760</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:14"/>
        <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 7:15"/>Binnui </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">648</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:15"/>
        <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 7:16"/>Bebai </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">628</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:16"/>
        <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 7:17"/>Azgad </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">2,322</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:17"/>
        <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 7:18"/>Adonikam </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">667</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:18"/>
        <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 7:19"/>Bigvai </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">2,067</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:19"/>
        <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 7:20"/>Adin </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">655</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:20"/>
        <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 7:21"/>Ater (through Hezekiah) </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">98</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:21"/>
        <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 7:22"/>Hashum </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">328</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:22"/>
        <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 7:23"/>Bezai </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">324</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:23"/>
        <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 7:24"/>Hariph </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">112</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:24"/>
        <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 7:25"/>Gibeon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">95</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:25"/>
        <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 7:26"/>the men of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Bethlehem and Netophah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">188</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:26"/>
        <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 7:27"/>Anathoth </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">128</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:27"/>
        <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 7:28"/>Beth Azmaveth </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">42</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:28"/>
        <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 7:29"/>Kiriath Jearim, Kephirah and Beeroth </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">743</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:29"/>
        <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 7:30"/>of Ramah and Geba </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">621</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:30"/>
        <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 7:31"/>of Mikmash </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">122</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:31"/>
        <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 7:32"/>of Bethel and Ai </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">123</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:32"/>
        <verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 7:33"/>of the other Nebo </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">52</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:33"/>
        <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 7:34"/>of the other Elam </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">1,254</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:34"/>
        <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 7:35"/>of Harim </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">320</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:35"/>
        <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 7:36"/>of Jericho </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">345</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:36"/>
        <verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 7:37"/>of Lod, Hadid and Ono </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">721</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:37"/>
        <verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 7:38"/>of Senaah </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">3,930</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:38">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:38"/>
  </para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NEH 7:39"/>The priests:</para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Jedaiah (through the family of Jeshua) </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">973</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:39"/>
        <verse number="40" style="v" sid="NEH 7:40"/>Immer </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">1,052</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:40"/>
        <verse number="41" style="v" sid="NEH 7:41"/>Pashhur </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">1,247</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:41"/>
        <verse number="42" style="v" sid="NEH 7:42"/>Harim </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">1,017</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:42">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:42"/>
  </para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="NEH 7:43"/>The Levites:</para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Jeshua (through Kadmiel through the line of Hodaviah) </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">74</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:43">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:43"/>
  </para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="NEH 7:44"/>The musicians:</para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Asaph </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">148</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:44">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:44"/>
  </para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="NEH 7:45"/>The gatekeepers of the temple:</para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Shallum, Ater, Talmon,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Akkub, Hatita and Shobai </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">138</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:45">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:45"/>
  </para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="NEH 7:46"/>The temple servants:</para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Ziha, Hasupha, Tabbaoth,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:46"/>
        <verse number="47" style="v" sid="NEH 7:47"/>Keros, Sia, Padon,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:47"/>
        <verse number="48" style="v" sid="NEH 7:48"/>Lebana, Hagaba, Shalmai,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:48"/>
        <verse number="49" style="v" sid="NEH 7:49"/>Hanan, Giddel, Gahar,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:49"/>
        <verse number="50" style="v" sid="NEH 7:50"/>Reaiah, Rezin, Nekoda,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:50"/>
        <verse number="51" style="v" sid="NEH 7:51"/>Gazzam, Uzza, Paseah,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:51"/>
        <verse number="52" style="v" sid="NEH 7:52"/>Besai, Meunim, Nephussim,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:52"/>
        <verse number="53" style="v" sid="NEH 7:53"/>Bakbuk, Hakupha, Harhur,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:53"/>
        <verse number="54" style="v" sid="NEH 7:54"/>Bazluth, Mehida, Harsha,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:54"/>
        <verse number="55" style="v" sid="NEH 7:55"/>Barkos, Sisera, Temah,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:55"/>
        <verse number="56" style="v" sid="NEH 7:56"/>Neziah and Hatipha</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="li4" vid="NEH 7:56">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:56"/>
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="NEH 7:57"/>The descendants of the servants of Solomon:</para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Sotai, Sophereth, Perida,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:57"/>
        <verse number="58" style="v" sid="NEH 7:58"/>Jaala, Darkon, Giddel,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:58"/>
        <verse number="59" style="v" sid="NEH 7:59"/>Shephatiah, Hattil,</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Pokereth-Hazzebaim and Amon</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse eid="NEH 7:59"/>
        <verse number="60" style="v" sid="NEH 7:60"/>The temple servants and the descendants of the servants of Solomon </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">392</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:60">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:60"/>
  </para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="61" style="v" sid="NEH 7:61"/>The following came up from the towns of Tel Melah, Tel Harsha, Kerub, Addon and Immer, but they could not show that their families were descended from Israel:<verse eid="NEH 7:61"/></para>
  <table>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">
        <verse number="62" style="v" sid="NEH 7:62"/>the descendants of</cell>
    </row>
    <row style="tr">
      <cell style="tc1" align="start">Delaiah, Tobiah and Nekoda </cell>
      <cell style="tcr2" align="end">642</cell>
    </row>
  </table>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 7:62">
    <verse eid="NEH 7:62"/>
  </para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="63" style="v" sid="NEH 7:63"/>And from among the priests:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 7:63">the descendants of</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 7:63">Hobaiah, Hakkoz and Barzillai (a man who had married a daughter of Barzillai the Gileadite and was called by that name).<verse eid="NEH 7:63"/></para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="64" style="v" sid="NEH 7:64"/>These searched for their family records, but they could not find them and so were excluded from the priesthood as unclean. <verse eid="NEH 7:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="NEH 7:65"/>The governor, therefore, ordered them not to eat any of the most sacred food until there should be a priest ministering with the Urim and Thummim.<verse eid="NEH 7:65"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="66" style="v" sid="NEH 7:66"/>The whole company numbered 42,360, <verse eid="NEH 7:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="NEH 7:67"/>besides their 7,337 male and female slaves; and they also had 245 male and female singers. <verse eid="NEH 7:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="NEH 7:68"/>There were 736 horses, 245 mules,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:68 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Hebrew manuscripts (see also <char style="xt"><ref loc="EZR 2:66">Ezra 2:66</ref></char>); most Hebrew manuscripts do not have this verse.</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 7:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="NEH 7:69"/>435 camels and 6,720 donkeys.<verse eid="NEH 7:69"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="70" style="v" sid="NEH 7:70"/>Some of the heads of the families contributed to the work. The governor gave to the treasury 1,000 darics<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:70 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 8.4 kilograms</char></note> of gold, 50 bowls and 530 garments for priests. <verse eid="NEH 7:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="NEH 7:71"/>Some of the heads of the families gave to the treasury for the work 20,000 darics<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:71 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 170 kilograms; also in verse 72</char></note> of gold and 2,200 minas<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:71 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 1.2 metric tons</char></note> of silver. <verse eid="NEH 7:71"/><verse number="72" style="v" sid="NEH 7:72"/>The total given by the rest of the people was 20,000 darics of gold, 2,000 minas<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">7:72 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 1.1 metric tons</char></note> of silver and 67 garments for priests.<verse eid="NEH 7:72"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="73" style="v" sid="NEH 7:73"/>The priests, the Levites, the gatekeepers, the musicians and the temple servants, along with certain of the people and the rest of the Israelites, settled in their own towns.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="NEH 7:73">Ezra reads the Law</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 7:73">When the seventh month came and the Israelites had settled in their towns,<verse eid="NEH 7:73"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="NEH 8"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 8:1"/>all the people came together as one in the square before the Water Gate. They told Ezra the teacher of the Law to bring out the Book of the Law of Moses, which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded for Israel.<verse eid="NEH 8:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 8:2"/>So on the first day of the seventh month Ezra the priest brought the Law before the assembly, which was made up of men and women and all who were able to understand. <verse eid="NEH 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 8:3"/>He read it aloud from daybreak till noon as he faced the square before the Water Gate in the presence of the men, women and others who could understand. And all the people listened attentively to the Book of the Law.<verse eid="NEH 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 8:4"/>Ezra the teacher of the Law stood on a high wooden platform built for the occasion. Beside him on his right stood Mattithiah, Shema, Anaiah, Uriah, Hilkiah and Maaseiah; and on his left were Pedaiah, Mishael, Malkijah, Hashum, Hashbaddanah, Zechariah and Meshullam.<verse eid="NEH 8:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 8:5"/>Ezra opened the book. All the people could see him because he was standing above them; and as he opened it, the people all stood up. <verse eid="NEH 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 8:6"/>Ezra praised the <char style="sc">Lord</char>, the great God; and all the people lifted their hands and responded, ‘Amen! Amen!’ Then they bowed down and worshipped the <char style="sc">Lord</char> with their faces to the ground.<verse eid="NEH 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 8:7"/>The Levites – Jeshua, Bani, Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodiah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan and Pelaiah – instructed the people in the Law while the people were standing there. <verse eid="NEH 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 8:8"/>They read from the Book of the Law of God, making it clear<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:8 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">God, translating it</char></note> and giving the meaning so that the people understood what was being read.<verse eid="NEH 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 8:9"/>Then Nehemiah the governor, Ezra the priest and teacher of the Law, and the Levites who were instructing the people said to them all, ‘This day is holy to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God. Do not mourn or weep.’ For all the people had been weeping as they listened to the words of the Law.<verse eid="NEH 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 8:10"/>Nehemiah said, ‘Go and enjoy choice food and sweet drinks, and send some to those who have nothing prepared. This day is holy to our Lord. Do not grieve, for the joy of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> is your strength.’<verse eid="NEH 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 8:11"/>The Levites calmed all the people, saying, ‘Be still, for this is a holy day. Do not grieve.’<verse eid="NEH 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 8:12"/>Then all the people went away to eat and drink, to send portions of food and to celebrate with great joy, because they now understood the words that had been made known to them.<verse eid="NEH 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 8:13"/>On the second day of the month, the heads of all the families, along with the priests and the Levites, gathered round Ezra the teacher of the Law to give attention to the words of the Law. <verse eid="NEH 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 8:14"/>They found written in the Law, which the <char style="sc">Lord</char> had commanded through Moses, that the Israelites were to live in temporary shelters during the festival of the seventh month <verse eid="NEH 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 8:15"/>and that they should proclaim this word and spread it throughout their towns and in Jerusalem: ‘Go out into the hill country and bring back branches from olive and wild olive trees, and from myrtles, palms and other leafy trees, to make temporary shelters’ – as it is written.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">8:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">See <char style="xt"><ref loc="LEV 23:37-40">Lev. 23:37-40</ref></char>.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 8:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 8:16"/>So the people went out and brought back branches and built themselves temporary shelters on their own roofs, in their courtyards, in the courts of the house of God and in the square by the Water Gate and the one by the Gate of Ephraim. <verse eid="NEH 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 8:17"/>The whole company that had returned from exile built temporary shelters and lived in them. From the days of Joshua son of Nun until that day, the Israelites had not celebrated it like this. And their joy was very great.<verse eid="NEH 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 8:18"/>Day after day, from the first day to the last, Ezra read from the Book of the Law of God. They celebrated the festival for seven days, and on the eighth day, in accordance with the regulation, there was an assembly.<verse eid="NEH 8:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="NEH 9"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelites confess their sins</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 9:1"/>On the twenty-fourth day of the same month, the Israelites gathered together, fasting and wearing sackcloth and putting dust on their heads. <verse eid="NEH 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 9:2"/>Those of Israelite descent had separated themselves from all foreigners. They stood in their places and confessed their sins and the sins of their ancestors. <verse eid="NEH 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 9:3"/>They stood where they were and read from the Book of the Law of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God for a quarter of the day, and spent another quarter in confession and in worshipping the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God. <verse eid="NEH 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 9:4"/>Standing on the stairs of the Levites were Jeshua, Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani and Kenani. They cried out with loud voices to the <char style="sc">Lord</char> their God. <verse eid="NEH 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 9:5"/>And the Levites – Jeshua, Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabneiah, Sherebiah, Hodiah, Shebaniah and Pethahiah – said: ‘Stand up and praise the <char style="sc">Lord</char> your God, who is from everlasting to everlasting.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">God for ever and ever</char></note>’</para>
  <para style="pm" vid="NEH 9:5">‘Blessed be your glorious name, and may it be exalted above all blessing and praise. <verse eid="NEH 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 9:6"/>You alone are the <char style="sc">Lord</char>. You made the heavens, even the highest heavens, and all their starry host, the earth and all that is on it, the seas and all that is in them. You give life to everything, and the multitudes of heaven worship you.<verse eid="NEH 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 9:7"/>‘You are the <char style="sc">Lord</char> God, who chose Abram and brought him out of Ur of the Chaldeans and named him Abraham. <verse eid="NEH 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 9:8"/>You found his heart faithful to you, and you made a covenant with him to give to his descendants the land of the Canaanites, Hittites, Amorites, Perizzites, Jebusites and Girgashites. You have kept your promise because you are righteous.<verse eid="NEH 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 9:9"/>‘You saw the suffering of our ancestors in Egypt; you heard their cry at the Red Sea.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:9 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">the Sea of Reeds</char></note> <verse eid="NEH 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 9:10"/>You sent signs and wonders against Pharaoh, against all his officials and all the people of his land, for you knew how arrogantly the Egyptians treated them. You made a name for yourself, which remains to this day. <verse eid="NEH 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 9:11"/>You divided the sea before them, so that they passed through it on dry ground, but you hurled their pursuers into the depths, like a stone into mighty waters. <verse eid="NEH 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 9:12"/>By day you led them with a pillar of cloud, and by night with a pillar of fire to give them light on the way they were to take.<verse eid="NEH 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 9:13"/>‘You came down on Mount Sinai; you spoke to them from heaven. You gave them regulations and laws that are just and right, and decrees and commands that are good. <verse eid="NEH 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 9:14"/>You made known to them your holy Sabbath and gave them commands, decrees and laws through your servant Moses. <verse eid="NEH 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 9:15"/>In their hunger you gave them bread from heaven and in their thirst you brought them water from the rock; you told them to go in and take possession of the land you had sworn with uplifted hand to give them.<verse eid="NEH 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 9:16"/>‘But they, our ancestors, became arrogant and stiff-necked, and they did not obey your commands. <verse eid="NEH 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 9:17"/>They refused to listen and failed to remember the miracles you performed among them. They became stiff-necked and in their rebellion appointed a leader in order to return to their slavery. But you are a forgiving God, gracious and compassionate, slow to anger and abounding in love. Therefore you did not desert them, <verse eid="NEH 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 9:18"/>even when they cast for themselves an image of a calf and said, “This is your god, who brought you up out of Egypt,” or when they committed awful blasphemies.<verse eid="NEH 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 9:19"/>‘Because of your great compassion you did not abandon them in the wilderness. By day the pillar of cloud did not fail to guide them on their path, nor the pillar of fire by night to shine on the way they were to take. <verse eid="NEH 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 9:20"/>You gave your good Spirit to instruct them. You did not withhold your manna from their mouths, and you gave them water for their thirst. <verse eid="NEH 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 9:21"/>For forty years you sustained them in the wilderness; they lacked nothing, their clothes did not wear out nor did their feet become swollen.<verse eid="NEH 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 9:22"/>‘You gave them kingdoms and nations, allotting to them even the remotest frontiers. They took over the country of Sihon<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:22 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">One Hebrew manuscript and Septuagint; most Hebrew manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Sihon, that is, the country of the</char></note> king of Heshbon and the country of Og king of Bashan. <verse eid="NEH 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 9:23"/>You made their children as numerous as the stars in the sky, and you brought them into the land that you told their parents to enter and possess. <verse eid="NEH 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 9:24"/>Their children went in and took possession of the land. You subdued before them the Canaanites, who lived in the land; you gave the Canaanites into their hands, along with their kings and the peoples of the land, to deal with them as they pleased. <verse eid="NEH 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 9:25"/>They captured fortified cities and fertile land; they took possession of houses filled with all kinds of good things, wells already dug, vineyards, olive groves and fruit trees in abundance. They ate to the full and were well-nourished; they revelled in your great goodness.<verse eid="NEH 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 9:26"/>‘But they were disobedient and rebelled against you; they turned their backs on your law. They killed your prophets, who had warned them in order to turn them back to you; they committed awful blasphemies. <verse eid="NEH 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 9:27"/>So you delivered them into the hands of their enemies, who oppressed them. But when they were oppressed they cried out to you. From heaven you heard them, and in your great compassion you gave them deliverers, who rescued them from the hand of their enemies.<verse eid="NEH 9:27"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 9:28"/>‘But as soon as they were at rest, they again did what was evil in your sight. Then you abandoned them to the hand of their enemies so that they ruled over them. And when they cried out to you again, you heard from heaven, and in your compassion you delivered them time after time.<verse eid="NEH 9:28"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 9:29"/>‘You warned them in order to turn them back to your law, but they became arrogant and disobeyed your commands. They sinned against your ordinances, of which you said, “The person who obeys them will live by them.” Stubbornly they turned their backs on you, became stiff-necked and refused to listen. <verse eid="NEH 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 9:30"/>For many years you were patient with them. By your Spirit you warned them through your prophets. Yet they paid no attention, so you gave them into the hands of the neighbouring peoples. <verse eid="NEH 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 9:31"/>But in your great mercy you did not put an end to them or abandon them, for you are a gracious and merciful God.<verse eid="NEH 9:31"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 9:32"/>‘Now therefore, our God, the great God, mighty and awesome, who keeps his covenant of love, do not let all this hardship seem trifling in your eyes – the hardship that has come on us, on our kings and leaders, on our priests and prophets, on our ancestors and all your people, from the days of the kings of Assyria until today. <verse eid="NEH 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 9:33"/>In all that has happened to us, you have remained righteous; you have acted faithfully, while we acted wickedly. <verse eid="NEH 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 9:34"/>Our kings, our leaders, our priests and our ancestors did not follow your law; they did not pay attention to your commands or the statutes you warned them to keep. <verse eid="NEH 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 9:35"/>Even while they were in their kingdom, enjoying your great goodness to them in the spacious and fertile land you gave them, they did not serve you or turn from their evil ways.<verse eid="NEH 9:35"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 9:36"/>‘But see, we are slaves today, slaves in the land you gave our ancestors so that they could eat its fruit and the other good things it produces. <verse eid="NEH 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 9:37"/>Because of our sins, its abundant harvest goes to the kings you have placed over us. They rule over our bodies and our cattle as they please. We are in great distress.<verse eid="NEH 9:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The agreement of the people</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 9:38"/>‘In view of all this, we are making a binding agreement, putting it in writing, and our leaders, our Levites and our priests are affixing their seals to it.’<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">9:38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">In Hebrew texts this verse (9:38) is numbered 10:1.</char></note><verse eid="NEH 9:38"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <chapter eid="NEH 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="NEH 10"/>
  <para style="p">
    <note caller="+" style="f">
      <char style="ft" closed="false">In Hebrew texts 10:1-39 is numbered 10:2-40. </char>
    </note> <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 10:1"/>Those who sealed it were:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 10:1"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 10:1">The governor:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 10:1">Nehemiah son of Hakaliah.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 10:1"/>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 10:1">Zedekiah, <verse eid="NEH 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 10:2"/>Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah,<verse eid="NEH 10:2"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 10:3"/>Pashhur, Amariah, Malkijah,<verse eid="NEH 10:3"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 10:4"/>Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluk,<verse eid="NEH 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 10:5"/>Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah,<verse eid="NEH 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 10:6"/>Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch,<verse eid="NEH 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 10:7"/>Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin,<verse eid="NEH 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 10:8"/>Maaziah, Bilgai and Shemaiah.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 10:8">These were the priests.<verse eid="NEH 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 10:9"/>The Levites:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 10:9">Jeshua son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel,<verse eid="NEH 10:9"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 10:10"/>and their associates: Shebaniah,</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 10:10">Hodiah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan,<verse eid="NEH 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 10:11"/>Mika, Rehob, Hashabiah,<verse eid="NEH 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 10:12"/>Zakkur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah,<verse eid="NEH 10:12"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 10:13"/>Hodiah, Bani and Beninu.<verse eid="NEH 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 10:14"/>The leaders of the people:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 10:14">Parosh, Pahath-Moab, Elam, Zattu, Bani,<verse eid="NEH 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 10:15"/>Bunni, Azgad, Bebai,<verse eid="NEH 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 10:16"/>Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin,<verse eid="NEH 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 10:17"/>Ater, Hezekiah, Azzur,<verse eid="NEH 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 10:18"/>Hodiah, Hashum, Bezai,<verse eid="NEH 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 10:19"/>Hariph, Anathoth, Nebai,<verse eid="NEH 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 10:20"/>Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir,<verse eid="NEH 10:20"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 10:21"/>Meshezabel, Zadok, Jaddua,<verse eid="NEH 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 10:22"/>Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah,<verse eid="NEH 10:22"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 10:23"/>Hoshea, Hananiah, Hasshub,<verse eid="NEH 10:23"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 10:24"/>Hallohesh, Pilha, Shobek,<verse eid="NEH 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 10:25"/>Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah,<verse eid="NEH 10:25"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 10:26"/>Ahiah, Hanan, Anan,<verse eid="NEH 10:26"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 10:27"/>Malluk, Harim and Baanah.<verse eid="NEH 10:27"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 10:28"/>‘The rest of the people – priests, Levites, gatekeepers, musicians, temple servants and all who separated themselves from the neighbouring peoples for the sake of the Law of God, together with their wives and all their sons and daughters who are able to understand – <verse eid="NEH 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 10:29"/>all these now join their fellow Israelites the nobles, and bind themselves with a curse and an oath to follow the Law of God given through Moses the servant of God and to obey carefully all the commands, regulations and decrees of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our Lord.<verse eid="NEH 10:29"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 10:30"/>‘We promise not to give our daughters in marriage to the peoples around us or take their daughters for our sons.<verse eid="NEH 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 10:31"/>‘When the neighbouring peoples bring merchandise or grain to sell on the Sabbath, we will not buy from them on the Sabbath or on any holy day. Every seventh year we will forgo working the land and will cancel all debts.<verse eid="NEH 10:31"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 10:32"/>‘We assume the responsibility for carrying out the commands to give a third of a shekel<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:32 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">That is, about 4 grams</char></note> each year for the service of the house of our God: <verse eid="NEH 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 10:33"/>for the bread set out on the table; for the regular grain offerings and burnt offerings; for the offerings on the Sabbaths, at the New Moon feasts and at the appointed festivals; for the holy offerings; for sin offerings<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">10:33 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">purification offerings</char></note> to make atonement for Israel; and for all the duties of the house of our God.<verse eid="NEH 10:33"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 10:34"/>‘We – the priests, the Levites and the people – have cast lots to determine when each of our families is to bring to the house of our God at set times each year a contribution of wood to burn on the altar of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> our God, as it is written in the Law.<verse eid="NEH 10:34"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 10:35"/>‘We also assume responsibility for bringing to the house of the <char style="sc">Lord</char> each year the firstfruits of our crops and of every fruit tree.<verse eid="NEH 10:35"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 10:36"/>‘As it is also written in the Law, we will bring the firstborn of our sons and of our cattle, of our herds and of our flocks to the house of our God, to the priests ministering there.<verse eid="NEH 10:36"/></para>
  <para style="pm">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 10:37"/>‘Moreover, we will bring to the storerooms of the house of our God, to the priests, the first of our ground meal, of our grain offerings, of the fruit of all our trees and of our new wine and olive oil. And we will bring a tithe of our crops to the Levites, for it is the Levites who collect the tithes in all the towns where we work. <verse eid="NEH 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 10:38"/>A priest descended from Aaron is to accompany the Levites when they receive the tithes, and the Levites are to bring a tenth of the tithes up to the house of our God, to the storerooms of the treasury. <verse eid="NEH 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NEH 10:39"/>The people of Israel, including the Levites, are to bring their contributions of grain, new wine and olive oil to the storerooms, where the articles for the sanctuary and for the ministering priests, the gatekeepers and the musicians are also kept.</para>
  <para style="pm" vid="NEH 10:39">‘We will not neglect the house of our God.’<verse eid="NEH 10:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="NEH 11"/>
  <para style="s1">The new residents of Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 11:1"/>Now the leaders of the people settled in Jerusalem. The rest of the people cast lots to bring one out of every ten of them to live in Jerusalem, the holy city, while the remaining nine were to stay in their own towns. <verse eid="NEH 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 11:2"/>The people commended all who volunteered to live in Jerusalem.<verse eid="NEH 11:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 11:3"/>These are the provincial leaders who settled in Jerusalem (now some Israelites, priests, Levites, temple servants and descendants of Solomon’s servants lived in the towns of Judah, each on their own property in the various towns, <verse eid="NEH 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 11:4"/>while other people from both Judah and Benjamin lived in Jerusalem):</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 11:4"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 11:4">From the descendants of Judah:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:4">Athaiah son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalalel, a descendant of Perez;<verse eid="NEH 11:4"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 11:5"/>and Maaseiah son of Baruch, the son of Kol-Hozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, a descendant of Shelah.<verse eid="NEH 11:5"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 11:6"/>The descendants of Perez who lived in Jerusalem totalled 468 men of standing.<verse eid="NEH 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 11:7"/>From the descendants of Benjamin:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:7">Sallu son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jeshaiah, <verse eid="NEH 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 11:8"/>and his followers, Gabbai and Sallai – 928 men.<verse eid="NEH 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 11:9"/>Joel son of Zikri was their chief officer, and Judah son of Hassenuah was over the New Quarter of the city.<verse eid="NEH 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 11:10"/>From the priests:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:10">Jedaiah; the son of Joiarib; Jakin;<verse eid="NEH 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 11:11"/>Seraiah son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the official in charge of the house of God, <verse eid="NEH 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 11:12"/>and their associates, who carried on work for the temple – 822 men;</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:12">Adaiah son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malkijah, <verse eid="NEH 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 11:13"/>and his associates, who were heads of families – 242 men;</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:13">Amashsai son of Azarel, the son of Ahzai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer, <verse eid="NEH 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 11:14"/>and his<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">11:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Most Septuagint manuscripts; Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">their</char></note> associates, who were men of standing – 128.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:14">Their chief officer was Zabdiel son of Haggedolim.<verse eid="NEH 11:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 11:15"/>From the Levites:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:15">Shemaiah son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni;<verse eid="NEH 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 11:16"/>Shabbethai and Jozabad, two of the heads of the Levites, who had charge of the outside work of the house of God;<verse eid="NEH 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 11:17"/>Mattaniah son of Mika, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, the director who led in thanksgiving and prayer;</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:17">Bakbukiah, second among his associates;</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:17">and Abda son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun.<verse eid="NEH 11:17"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 11:18"/>The Levites in the holy city totalled 284.<verse eid="NEH 11:18"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 11:19"/>The gatekeepers:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="NEH 11:19">Akkub, Talmon and their associates, who kept watch at the gates – 172 men.<verse eid="NEH 11:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 11:20"/>The rest of the Israelites, with the priests and Levites, were in all the towns of Judah, each on their ancestral property.<verse eid="NEH 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 11:21"/>The temple servants lived on the hill of Ophel, and Ziha and Gishpa were in charge of them.<verse eid="NEH 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 11:22"/>The chief officer of the Levites in Jerusalem was Uzzi son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Mika. Uzzi was one of Asaph’s descendants, who were the musicians responsible for the service of the house of God. <verse eid="NEH 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 11:23"/>The musicians were under the king’s orders, which regulated their daily activity.<verse eid="NEH 11:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 11:24"/>Pethahiah son of Meshezabel, one of the descendants of Zerah son of Judah, was the king’s agent in all affairs relating to the people.<verse eid="NEH 11:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 11:25"/>As for the villages with their fields, some of the people of Judah lived in Kiriath Arba and its surrounding settlements, in Dibon and its settlements, in Jekabzeel and its villages, <verse eid="NEH 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 11:26"/>in Jeshua, in Moladah, in Beth Pelet, <verse eid="NEH 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 11:27"/>in Hazar Shual, in Beersheba and its settlements, <verse eid="NEH 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 11:28"/>in Ziklag, in Mekonah and its settlements, <verse eid="NEH 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 11:29"/>in En Rimmon, in Zorah, in Jarmuth, <verse eid="NEH 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 11:30"/>Zanoah, Adullam and their villages, in Lachish and its fields, and in Azekah and its settlements. So they were living all the way from Beersheba to the Valley of Hinnom.<verse eid="NEH 11:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 11:31"/>The descendants of the Benjaminites from Geba lived in Mikmash, Aija, Bethel and its settlements, <verse eid="NEH 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 11:32"/>in Anathoth, Nob and Ananiah, <verse eid="NEH 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 11:33"/>in Hazor, Ramah and Gittaim, <verse eid="NEH 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 11:34"/>in Hadid, Zeboim and Neballat, <verse eid="NEH 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 11:35"/>in Lod and Ono, and in Ge Harashim.<verse eid="NEH 11:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 11:36"/>Some of the divisions of the Levites of Judah settled in Benjamin.<verse eid="NEH 11:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="NEH 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Priests and Levites</para>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 12:1"/>These were the priests and Levites who returned with Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel and with Joshua:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 12:1"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:1">Seraiah, Jeremiah, Ezra,<verse eid="NEH 12:1"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 12:2"/>Amariah, Malluk, Hattush,<verse eid="NEH 12:2"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 12:3"/>Shekaniah, Rehum, Meremoth,<verse eid="NEH 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 12:4"/>Iddo, Ginnethon,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Many Hebrew manuscripts and Vulgate (see also verse 16); most Hebrew manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Ginnethoi</char></note> Abijah,<verse eid="NEH 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 12:5"/>Mijamin,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:5 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">A variant of </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Miniamin</char></note> Moadiah, Bilgah,<verse eid="NEH 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 12:6"/>Shemaiah, Joiarib, Jedaiah,<verse eid="NEH 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 12:7"/>Sallu, Amok, Hilkiah and Jedaiah.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 12:7"/>
  <para style="li4" vid="NEH 12:7">These were the leaders of the priests and their associates in the days of Joshua.<verse eid="NEH 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 12:8"/>The Levites were Jeshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Judah, and also Mattaniah, who, together with his associates, was in charge of the songs of thanksgiving. <verse eid="NEH 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 12:9"/>Bakbukiah and Unni, their associates, stood opposite them in the services.<verse eid="NEH 12:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 12:10"/>Joshua was the father of Joiakim,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:10">Joiakim the father of Eliashib,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:10">Eliashib the father of Joiada,<verse eid="NEH 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 12:11"/>Joiada the father of Jonathan,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:11">and Jonathan the father of Jaddua.<verse eid="NEH 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li4">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 12:12"/>In the days of Joiakim, these were the heads of the priestly families:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 12:12"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:12">of Seraiah’s family, Meraiah;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:12">of Jeremiah’s, Hananiah;<verse eid="NEH 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 12:13"/>of Ezra’s, Meshullam;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:13">of Amariah’s, Jehohanan;<verse eid="NEH 12:13"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 12:14"/>of Malluk’s, Jonathan;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:14">of Shekaniah’s,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:14 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Very many Hebrew manuscripts, some Septuagint manuscripts and Syriac (see also verse 3); most Hebrew manuscripts </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Shebaniah’s</char></note> Joseph;<verse eid="NEH 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 12:15"/>of Harim’s, Adna;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:15">of Meremoth’s,<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:15 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Septuagint manuscripts (see also verse 3); Hebrew </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Meraioth’s</char></note> Helkai;<verse eid="NEH 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 12:16"/>of Iddo’s, Zechariah;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:16">of Ginnethon’s, Meshullam;<verse eid="NEH 12:16"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 12:17"/>of Abijah’s, Zikri;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:17">of Miniamin’s and of Moadiah’s, Piltai;<verse eid="NEH 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 12:18"/>of Bilgah’s, Shammua;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:18">of Shemaiah’s, Jehonathan;<verse eid="NEH 12:18"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 12:19"/>of Joiarib’s, Mattenai;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:19">of Jedaiah’s, Uzzi;<verse eid="NEH 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 12:20"/>of Sallu’s, Kallai;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:20">of Amok’s, Eber;<verse eid="NEH 12:20"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 12:21"/>of Hilkiah’s, Hashabiah;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NEH 12:21">of Jedaiah’s, Nethanel.<verse eid="NEH 12:21"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 12:22"/>The family heads of the Levites in the days of Eliashib, Joiada, Johanan and Jaddua, as well as those of the priests, were recorded in the reign of Darius the Persian. <verse eid="NEH 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 12:23"/>The family heads among the descendants of Levi up to the time of Johanan son of Eliashib were recorded in the book of the annals. <verse eid="NEH 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 12:24"/>And the leaders of the Levites were Hashabiah, Sherebiah, Jeshua son of Kadmiel, and their associates, who stood opposite them to give praise and thanksgiving, one section responding to the other, as prescribed by David the man of God.<verse eid="NEH 12:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 12:25"/>Mattaniah, Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon and Akkub were gatekeepers who guarded the storerooms at the gates. <verse eid="NEH 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 12:26"/>They served in the days of Joiakim son of Joshua, the son of Jozadak, and in the days of Nehemiah the governor and of Ezra the priest, the teacher of the Law.<verse eid="NEH 12:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Dedication of the wall of Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 12:27"/>At the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem, the Levites were sought out from where they lived and were brought to Jerusalem to celebrate joyfully the dedication with songs of thanksgiving and with the music of cymbals, harps and lyres. <verse eid="NEH 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 12:28"/>The musicians also were brought together from the region around Jerusalem – from the villages of the Netophathites, <verse eid="NEH 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 12:29"/>from Beth Gilgal, and from the area of Geba and Azmaveth, for the musicians had built villages for themselves around Jerusalem. <verse eid="NEH 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 12:30"/>When the priests and Levites had purified themselves ceremonially, they purified the people, the gates and the wall.<verse eid="NEH 12:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 12:31"/>I had the leaders of Judah go up on top of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">go alongside</char></note> the wall. I also assigned two large choirs to give thanks. One was to proceed on top of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:31 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">proceed alongside</char></note> the wall to the right, towards the Dung Gate. <verse eid="NEH 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NEH 12:32"/>Hoshaiah and half the leaders of Judah followed them, <verse eid="NEH 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NEH 12:33"/>along with Azariah, Ezra, Meshullam, <verse eid="NEH 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NEH 12:34"/>Judah, Benjamin, Shemaiah, Jeremiah, <verse eid="NEH 12:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NEH 12:35"/>as well as some priests with trumpets, and also Zechariah son of Jonathan, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Micaiah, the son of Zakkur, the son of Asaph, <verse eid="NEH 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NEH 12:36"/>and his associates – Shemaiah, Azarel, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethanel, Judah and Hanani – with musical instruments prescribed by David the man of God. Ezra the teacher of the Law led the procession. <verse eid="NEH 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NEH 12:37"/>At the Fountain Gate they continued directly up the steps of the City of David on the ascent to the wall and passed above the site of David’s palace to the Water Gate on the east.<verse eid="NEH 12:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="NEH 12:38"/>The second choir proceeded in the opposite direction. I followed them on top of<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:38 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">them alongside</char></note> the wall, together with half the people – past the Tower of the Ovens to the Broad Wall, <verse eid="NEH 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NEH 12:39"/>over the Gate of Ephraim, the Jeshanah<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">12:39 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Or </char><char style="fqa" closed="false">Old</char></note> Gate, the Fish Gate, the Tower of Hananel and the Tower of the Hundred, as far as the Sheep Gate. At the Gate of the Guard they stopped.<verse eid="NEH 12:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="NEH 12:40"/>The two choirs that gave thanks then took their places in the house of God; so did I, together with half the officials, <verse eid="NEH 12:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NEH 12:41"/>as well as the priests – Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Micaiah, Elioenai, Zechariah and Hananiah with their trumpets – <verse eid="NEH 12:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="NEH 12:42"/>and also Maaseiah, Shemaiah, Eleazar, Uzzi, Jehohanan, Malkijah, Elam and Ezer. The choirs sang under the direction of Jezrahiah. <verse eid="NEH 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="NEH 12:43"/>And on that day they offered great sacrifices, rejoicing because God had given them great joy. The women and children also rejoiced. The sound of rejoicing in Jerusalem could be heard far away.<verse eid="NEH 12:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="NEH 12:44"/>At that time men were appointed to be in charge of the storerooms for the contributions, firstfruits and tithes. From the fields around the towns they were to bring into the storerooms the portions required by the Law for the priests and the Levites, for Judah was pleased with the ministering priests and Levites. <verse eid="NEH 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="NEH 12:45"/>They performed the service of their God and the service of purification, as did also the musicians and gatekeepers, according to the commands of David and his son Solomon. <verse eid="NEH 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="NEH 12:46"/>For long ago, in the days of David and Asaph, there had been directors for the musicians and for the songs of praise and thanksgiving to God. <verse eid="NEH 12:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="NEH 12:47"/>So in the days of Zerubbabel and of Nehemiah, all Israel contributed the daily portions for the musicians and the gatekeepers. They also set aside the portion for the other Levites, and the Levites set aside the portion for the descendants of Aaron.<verse eid="NEH 12:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="NEH 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Nehemiah’s final reforms</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NEH 13:1"/>On that day the Book of Moses was read aloud in the hearing of the people and there it was found written that no Ammonite or Moabite should ever be admitted into the assembly of God, <verse eid="NEH 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NEH 13:2"/>because they had not met the Israelites with food and water but had hired Balaam to call a curse down on them. (Our God, however, turned the curse into a blessing.) <verse eid="NEH 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NEH 13:3"/>When the people heard this law, they excluded from Israel all who were of foreign descent.<verse eid="NEH 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NEH 13:4"/>Before this, Eliashib the priest had been put in charge of the storerooms of the house of our God. He was closely associated with Tobiah, <verse eid="NEH 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NEH 13:5"/>and he had provided him with a large room formerly used to store the grain offerings and incense and temple articles, and also the tithes of grain, new wine and olive oil prescribed for the Levites, musicians and gatekeepers, as well as the contributions for the priests.<verse eid="NEH 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NEH 13:6"/>But while all this was going on, I was not in Jerusalem, for in the thirty-second year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon I had returned to the king. Some time later I asked his permission <verse eid="NEH 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NEH 13:7"/>and came back to Jerusalem. Here I learned about the evil thing Eliashib had done in providing Tobiah a room in the courts of the house of God. <verse eid="NEH 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NEH 13:8"/>I was greatly displeased and threw all Tobiah’s household goods out of the room. <verse eid="NEH 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NEH 13:9"/>I gave orders to purify the rooms, and then I put back into them the equipment of the house of God, with the grain offerings and the incense.<verse eid="NEH 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NEH 13:10"/>I also learned that the portions assigned to the Levites had not been given to them, and that all the Levites and musicians responsible for the service had gone back to their own fields. <verse eid="NEH 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NEH 13:11"/>So I rebuked the officials and asked them, ‘Why is the house of God neglected?’ Then I called them together and stationed them at their posts.<verse eid="NEH 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NEH 13:12"/>All Judah brought the tithes of grain, new wine and olive oil into the storerooms. <verse eid="NEH 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NEH 13:13"/>I put Shelemiah the priest, Zadok the scribe, and a Levite named Pedaiah in charge of the storerooms and made Hanan son of Zakkur, the son of Mattaniah, their assistant, because they were considered trustworthy. They were made responsible for distributing the supplies to their fellow Levites.<verse eid="NEH 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NEH 13:14"/>Remember me for this, my God, and do not blot out what I have so faithfully done for the house of my God and its services.<verse eid="NEH 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NEH 13:15"/>In those days I saw people in Judah treading winepresses on the Sabbath and bringing in grain and loading it on donkeys, together with wine, grapes, figs and all other kinds of loads. And they were bringing all this into Jerusalem on the Sabbath. Therefore I warned them against selling food on that day. <verse eid="NEH 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NEH 13:16"/>People from Tyre who lived in Jerusalem were bringing in fish and all kinds of merchandise and selling them in Jerusalem on the Sabbath to the people of Judah. <verse eid="NEH 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NEH 13:17"/>I rebuked the nobles of Judah and said to them, ‘What is this wicked thing you are doing – desecrating the Sabbath day? <verse eid="NEH 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NEH 13:18"/>Didn’t your ancestors do the same things, so that our God brought all this calamity on us and on this city? Now you are stirring up more wrath against Israel by desecrating the Sabbath.’<verse eid="NEH 13:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NEH 13:19"/>When evening shadows fell on the gates of Jerusalem before the Sabbath, I ordered the doors to be shut and not opened until the Sabbath was over. I stationed some of my own men at the gates so that no load could be brought in on the Sabbath day. <verse eid="NEH 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NEH 13:20"/>Once or twice the merchants and sellers of all kinds of goods spent the night outside Jerusalem. <verse eid="NEH 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NEH 13:21"/>But I warned them and said, ‘Why do you spend the night by the wall? If you do this again, I will arrest you.’ From that time on they no longer came on the Sabbath. <verse eid="NEH 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NEH 13:22"/>Then I commanded the Levites to purify themselves and go and guard the gates in order to keep the Sabbath day holy.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 13:22"/>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 13:22">Remember me for this also, my God, and show mercy to me according to your great love.<verse eid="NEH 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NEH 13:23"/>Moreover, in those days I saw men of Judah who had married women from Ashdod, Ammon and Moab. <verse eid="NEH 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NEH 13:24"/>Half of their children spoke the language of Ashdod or the language of one of the other peoples, and did not know how to speak the language of Judah. <verse eid="NEH 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NEH 13:25"/>I rebuked them and called curses down on them. I beat some of the men and pulled out their hair. I made them take an oath in God’s name and said: ‘You are not to give your daughters in marriage to their sons, nor are you to take their daughters in marriage for your sons or for yourselves. <verse eid="NEH 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NEH 13:26"/>Was it not because of marriages like these that Solomon king of Israel sinned? Among the many nations there was no king like him. He was loved by his God, and God made him king over all Israel, but even he was led into sin by foreign women. <verse eid="NEH 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NEH 13:27"/>Must we hear now that you too are doing all this terrible wickedness and are being unfaithful to our God by marrying foreign women?’<verse eid="NEH 13:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NEH 13:28"/>One of the sons of Joiada son of Eliashib the high priest was son-in-law to Sanballat the Horonite. And I drove him away from me.<verse eid="NEH 13:28"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NEH 13:29"/>Remember them, my God, because they defiled the priestly office and the covenant of the priesthood and of the Levites.<verse eid="NEH 13:29"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NEH 13:30"/>So I purified the priests and the Levites of everything foreign, and assigned them duties, each to his own task. <verse eid="NEH 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NEH 13:31"/>I also made provision for contributions of wood at designated times, and for the firstfruits.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NEH 13:31"/>
  <para style="p" vid="NEH 13:31">Remember me with favour, my God.<verse eid="NEH 13:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NEH 13"/>
</usx>
